Let's see if there's a new one.
It still says mono 0.1, wow.
That's alright.
If it was pre-mono 0.0, it would be 0.1.
What if you put an mp3 player, 40kb, 16 bits, stereo, 4 tones, something like that?
Well, we'll listen to it.
Andraž, what do you think, if it's bad, will you record it again?
Well, I listen to the same things in the car, if the sound is good, then I skip it.
I mean, really, if you listen to a podcast, and you just listen, and you don't have a video,
I think it's pretty important for my point of view, how good the audio is.
I mean, I don't know if it's going to be a debate, or if it's going to be interesting,
but we'll play it anyway.
It's a very good approach.
Have you found a way to get it up?
No, I thought, you can record 3-4 episodes, 3-4 files, and then upload it somewhere.
You can be agile.
You can be agile, you can go directly to the customer, you don't have to wait.
Release, then customer, then you look at the feedback.
I mean, you work, people ask for feedback, but you don't pick it up.
I'm really interested in Nenje, I don't know what he said to Jure Čuhalov on the debate.
He doesn't have time to listen to it.
How long did you work on it, and what did you come up with?
I don't know.
More than 16 centimeters, what's the problem?
No, I mean, the format, the format.
Roga has 3 hours.
That's too much.
I would say from 15 minutes to 20 minutes.
Then we'll see the feedback.
I would aim for half an hour.
I think that's just fine.
You can see that.
Half an hour is very meaningful if the discussion is very intelligent.
I expected that from Umizja, right?
Or from Kauč, or whatever you want to call it.
I don't know.
You know, we won't have two guests and two moderators in the morning,
so that's fine.
Do you want to do something on the level of those dialogues?
No, I think it would be good if you could see what's going on.
For example, you can see that Heroku has an outage,
which is an interesting topic.
You can see that someone is asking,
I don't know, one is on GCP,
and then my base is spinning,
and there's a debate,
and you can see that React hooks are fucked up.
It's an interesting topic.
And then someone comes and says,
listen, Darknet Diaries,
I could listen to that.
I won't listen to it alone.
I think it has a lot of impact.
In Slovenia?
I don't know about that.
If you want to do something local,
with better quality...
My question is,
do you want to do something like that,
when they are here in the dialogue,
and only in a different...
No, here in Selakovica,
it's more professional.
Well, I understand,
but I want to say,
the same concept,
where three or four get together
and go with their limited expertise and knowledge
to be smart,
smart,
or...
With more alcohol and more cigarettes.
Or what else?
And more scrappy.
Because scrappy is the best keyword.
Lean.
I can design this logo in Paint.
Four circles,
plus the color inside.
And that's it.
I don't think there's any episode left.
I couldn't do anything,
no page,
but when I had time,
FPSR,
then you can connect it,
and then you open the episode,
and then you can pull it out
and convert it yourself.
And you know,
this is cool.
Isn't it?
So you can stream more,
and then you can stream
something else.
What?
Hardcore listeners will listen to this one time.
One time.
Actually,
No, actually,
when you record in Wave,
then you record in MP3,
but then you convert it back
to record on a cassette,
and then you dispatch ten cassettes
as a limited edition,
and then you read it to people.
On TV.
No, that's cool.
You know what's cool?
Nowadays, people make vinyl records,
and those vinyl records come back,
because you have an audio player,
and they play vinyl records,
and then you make a cassette.
Yes.
You can be a bit more modern age.
Cassettes are still very popular today.
You can be modern age,
and start writing episodes
on 64 megabyte keys.
And throw them over the sea.
In a balloon.
In a balloon,
so that there will be more democracy.
We have a serious topic.
We have to have a serious topic.
We still have minus three minutes,
and then we have to get to work.
We have an easy topic for a start.
Kubernetes.
That's a joke.
I'm sure you don't care about Kubernetes.
You can start a topic like that.
What do you think about Kubernetes?
Can you read the trailer for the next one?
We'll talk about Kubernetes in the next one.
What do you think about Kubernetes?
That's how it all starts.
With Docker.
Have you ever looked up
what Kubernetes is on Google Docs?
They don't troll you now.
And what is it about?
It was a fight,
but that explains it.
Why did they decide to do it
in such a way?
It was an open puzzle.
Is that how it starts?
No, it was a fight
when they redid it.
But it looks good.
For someone who has never seen
or heard of it,
I think it's a success.
How long does it take?
Two parts.
Each part takes about 40 minutes.
That's good.
That's double binge-watching.
Was it always connected
to Docker?
No.
They only had their part.
Container, not Docker.
Container was replaced by Google.
Google was a container.
There was no Docker.
It's all open now.
It's a different hack.
What did you say?
Google worker.
You know what it is?
Open Vista or Virtuoso.
It's different.
Contemporary.
You could buy one,
but you couldn't buy the other.
How many servers did you need
for Kubernetes?
One.
One single node.
One Docker container.
Yes.
How easy is it to start
playing with Kubernetes?
One Docker container.
That's why you have
Kubernetes, K and Docker.
One Docker node.
How much WordPress site do you have?
You name it.
It depends on how much
WordPress site you want to scale.
your provider is.
Let's say the biggest
in Slovenia.
In every datacenter
you have a Kubernetes cluster
and then you scale it
through all your datacenters.
In Slovenia,
each location has
its own datacenter.
Each bigger city.
I answered you.
You have to market it as a city.
If you can deploy
Kubernetes in your
physical datacenter,
then yes.
Okay.
How about WordPress?
Can you deploy it?
No, you can't deploy it.
If you can deploy it,
you can deploy Kubernetes.
No, you can't deploy it.
Why?
Persistent databases
can be deployed in time.
Not for ultra-production
high-value data,
but it's better.
Nodes can't have
more than 10 milliseconds
in Slovenia.
Let me tell you,
everything is possible,
but sometimes
you don't know
where to start.
It's made for
a WordPress site
with an e-commerce
extension.
If you're the biggest
datacenter in Slovenia,
you need a Kubernetes cluster
to start meeting
and you have three nodes.
Kubernetes,
MySQL,
Postgres.
What else did you forget?
That you have to physically
buy those three nodes.
Why?
If you're going to complicate it,
you're going to have to
do this and that.
Do you have any management ideas
for Kubernetes in Slovenia?
The best.
It just works faster.
I like that.
You can even deploy it.
If you take a physical cluster,
you can only have
a classic virtualization,
because nodes can only have
110 pods.
That's the first limitation.
And then you need to have
something from the bottom,
a classic virtualization.
But if you give that node
a large share of CPU...
It doesn't matter,
as long as you have...
I mean, as long as you have
a real Raspberry Pi,
you're never going to exceed
110 pods on a physical hardware.
That's the first thing.
How can a large cluster
allow you to start playing
with Kubernetes
and see benefits?
Just one.
It doesn't have to be just one.
Why not?
You can't put everything in one.
I mean, I don't know why
you're mentioning that.
You're killing the pod.
Kubernetes is going to scale
and you're going to run it again.
You can't do that.
It's the same answer
as in all distributed systems.
You need at least three
to restart a node.
And then,
just one.
What distribution do you use
with Kubernetes?
I don't know.
You can think of
a Rancher with SOS.
I'd take that one.
It's not 3KS,
it's small,
but it's enough.
I don't know why
you'd put Kubernetes
on your hardware.
It's crazy.
It has no business value.
It's a micro-KS.
It doesn't make sense.
I'd go for
the development cluster.
You have the K3S
from Rancher.
That's really nice.
You can manage
it with
Google Cloud,
Azure,
others.
Open,
shift,
DigitalOcean,
Linode, Vultr.
Linode too?
If you're a normal
Slovenian company,
you can go to DigitalOcean,
Linode, Vultr.
If you're already
on one cloud provider,
you stay there.
If you choose
from three big ones,
you have Google.
K3S is
very complicated.
I don't know what's better.
A bit of a puzzle.
You need persistent storage.
If you're a provider,
that's why you don't deploy
per se in the cluster.
It's already deployed.
You need a distributed
storage
to install
and maintain.
How long will it take?
Good luck.
That's one person.
You buy appliance.
What's that Netgear?
I don't know.
When they give you a case
and you just open it.
I don't know if they have it.
I don't know.
You have to go from
Synology
to QNAP and so on.
But you don't know
how to do it.
They give you
iSCSI.
You look at
storage class,
iSCSI, blah, blah.
What's the name?
CIF.
That's above.
Now we have
Kubernetes cluster.
We have
our own
and we have
some of those offers.
We have
documented tasks.
What can we solve?
With WordPress.
With Svetlachar.
Now we have
Michael Cates.
Now we have to look at
developers.
It's amazing.
With FTP.
If you're a proper WordPress
deployer.
It's very complex.
What did I study?
If I had a team
of 10-20 engineers,
I would be forced to
manage Kubernetes.
This is the only thing.
I mean, you don't put it on yourself,
you put it on Google
or on Linux,
on Vultr,
DigitalOcean,
and then you have to manage
Argo, CD, or Flux.
So you get a UI
and you can make
GitOps.
You specify in the repository
what you want on the cluster.
Then the developers
interface,
configure in Kubernetes
so that they say
I don't know,
I don't know.
You put it in GitRip
so that if I want to run
this Docker container
with old replicas,
blah, blah, blah,
I can put it in
and have a nice UI
when you prepare it.
Because if you want to solve
Airbag,
it's very complex.
Let's go back.
If you want to copy files,
you have to do it this way.
If you want to deploy,
you have to copy the files.
Wait, really?
It's still very
debatable
for the use case.
Okay.
If you take
your engineering team
that is on the line
deploying FTP,
SPTP,
whatever,
what is it good for?
It's not good for you.
That's what worries me.
You can see it in the diagram.
In M2U with Kubernetes,
if you press
99%
you don't use it.
You use it if you have...
Yes, you use Kubernetes.
If you have...
If you have something
that is really
non-persistent,
you have to
scale it completely.
You have jobs that can be different,
but
they run or don't run.
Do you know why you use Kubernetes?
I don't know.
Kubernetes is used too much
because you want to use it
in production.
That's my main point.
And then
because you have
so few systems
that would make it easier for you.
You always have
a container in your hand
and it works.
It's a load balancer.
It's the only open source
thing that survived
the whole generation
that is Kubernetes based.
You had Rancher
that was Docker Compose based
and you had other providers
like Swarm.
That's why you said
you would use
Docker or Container based
with Swarm.
Yes.
So you don't have to worry
about everything.
No, Swarm is still used.
If you have Docker Compose
written,
I think there are
a few more signs
that you can put
in the Swarm cluster.
You have a black page
WordPress, whatever.
The first step is
to put it in a container.
The second step is
to start using
Docker Compose in production.
No, you don't want to
put it in a container.
Or Swarm.
If you have to use
Kubernetes,
if you have to use
Docker,
then you have to
put it in a container.
You can put it in a
Heroku
or you can look
at Swarm or Nomad.
Kubernetes is
very complex.
If you want to have
dynamic number of nodes,
you have to have
3 fixed nodes
at all times.
The load has to be
so low
that you can't
put it in a container.
If we talk about
nodes,
what does it mean?
How difficult is it
to put a node in a cluster?
I don't know.
I think it depends on
the distribution.
In the beginning,
you have to sign
on the master node
and that's it.
You copy the keys
You have to know
which nodes are which.
I think the master node
knows about
workers.
Nodes don't know
everything about themselves.
If you have a cluster
that is composed of nodes,
nodes are masters
or just workers,
then both can get
workloads.
That's the main process
that runs on a virtual
or hardware box.
Typically,
it's not a hardware box.
Each node can have
110 nodes because of
networking.
Typically,
you have 3 to 0
for production.
If you play,
you can have only one.
That's it.
I would like to interview
a DevOps engineer
for a DevOps position.
I can ask him
what is a good interview
to check
if someone will
manage it.
It depends on what is written
in the CV.
I typically check
if what is written is true.
How do you establish
a partner?
What would you do
if you didn't have
a DevOps engineer?
If you didn't know
what a partner is,
what would you do?
I think
if you really know
how to ask a question,
you have a path
that goes around
and around.
What would you look at?
Where would you debug
the problem?
It's not that
you want to see
the whole team
in a syntactic way,
but you need to understand
what to look at
from the description
to the service,
the situation,
what is logical,
and so on.
Do you ask him
what is a service
and what is a path?
Yes.
The question is
if you have an application
that is deployed on Kubernetes
and you refresh the page,
when do you get
500 EUR
and when do you get
200 EUR.
What do you think
could be done?
It depends on the level
of people you interview.
The good thing is
if you want
a person
to understand
the basics of Kubernetes,
yes,
you can learn a lot,
but if you want
a plug-and-play,
the understanding
has to be high enough
that it brings
the basic business knowledge.
The main problem
with Kubernetes
is that people
have to know a lot
and then you ask
if it makes sense
for a small organization
to use this technology
because in the end
you get very little from it.
Ok.
If we look at this,
these are complex questions,
but
how many
of these
new age
infrastructure stacks
and how many of these
stacks should be known
today?
Where are the responsibilities
of engineering
or developers
or developer league?
Do you think
to what extent
should developers
understand
Kubernetes
and containers
and where
should they prepare?
I don't think that's the case.
Do you think that developers really need to know this stuff?
I think that if they are developing it, and you already have the development,
I think that they need to include containers,
and if a developer puts it on his laptop, in his docker,
then to some extent he needs to know the containers, and he needs to know the docker.
Now it's just about overbuilding.
Do developers need to know what are the requests, requirements, and limits for their workflows?
No, I don't think that's the case.
The first thing, when it comes to organization,
the first thing you ask is what does DevOps mean for them.
In the beginning, in DevOps culture, developers don't need to understand
if there are nodes or not,
and you have the right to deploy them on the cluster or in the namespace.
In my opinion, in the next point, you need to know that
Helm nodes don't need to describe platform engineering or operations,
developers need to do it themselves,
and it's good to have someone who knows Kubernetes better through that guide.
And here's the next point again,
because people are used to deploying on some clusters,
and they have SSH, and they say,
oh, Ansible is a more structured framework for SSH,
and it's very useful,
but people don't like it when I say we'll adopt Kubernetes
because it's a completely different thing,
because it's much more complex,
and it's also much more specific to the application.
If you're an agency, you'll have a pattern,
and you'll be dancing in the application,
and if you're a customer, it's a bit more tricky.
Simon is shocked.
No, I'm messing with Celina.
Kubernetes will try to get through Celina.
These are really difficult topics for people.
They're not.
What, Kubernetes?
Yes.
I think it's a fully hype-driven technology,
everything that comes out of it.
And if you want to be in this business, you have to know it.
So the question is, if you're a person who wants to work on a platform,
or if you're in an engineering position,
then you have to learn it.
If you know the technology, the circumstances,
is it the most reasonable for our space?
I don't think so,
but if the whole caravan is in that direction,
then you have to go with that caravan,
as always.
Thank you.
How would you advise the management?
Look at the time.
Look at the Kubernetes.
Just don't do this.
Kubernetes is recording,
and it's pretty quickly closed.
You'll always need someone to...
Just a part of it won't be enough.
That's another problem.
If you're alone and you have some real products,
Kubernetes is doing things pretty quickly.
And then people say,
while we would have, I don't know,
canary releases,
then we would put 10% traffic on one release,
and 90% on the other,
and I would have my own deploy,
and then you need two,
and you're on 8-10 releases.
And with one release,
it all works.
Yes.
Right?
I mean...
Yes, it costs, but...
Yes, but it's very undervalued.
I mean, not 8 releases,
but 4 releases.
Yes, people are like that.
People will say,
we pay 2 euros for each release,
and that's very expensive.
And then you have to pay for 2 euros.
Yes, and now you have to pay for the frame.
It's a much better way.
It's that narrow-minded, you know,
that you're just looking at
one part of the price,
or one part of those accounts,
and then you have to pay a lot of money for it,
and in the superior part,
the human factor is the health factor.
Yes.
Well,
in my opinion,
if you're a full-time Slovenian,
and you're still looking at Swarm,
if you have a Docker Compose on 3 servers,
and you want unmanageable,
then look at Swarm.
Because it's still like Docker Inc,
and then it's a much smoother transition,
if there are alternatives,
and...
on the one hand,
you have to ask yourself,
do you really need it?
We've also touched on a lot of things.
Monitoring,
upgrading,
security,
a lot of things that still need to be done.
Well, that's not relevant for a Slovenian company.
Not relevant.
We're just upgrading.
Well, Kubernetes is a very complex airbag,
and the environment is very complex,
but you don't have to worry about it.
That's why these systems like Ergos, OCD, help you.
So you can say,
I want to have Google SSO,
and people who are in a Google group,
developers,
can do that.
Because otherwise,
you break down,
if you don't have that.
Monitoring,
if there's something easier,
or something better,
than anywhere else.
A good thing,
maybe,
is that when the services run in the Kubernetes cluster,
they're more easily auto-discoverable.
Because you have metadata,
and it's easier to re-distribute the data.
But if you're a Slovenian company,
it doesn't have that much of a connection.
What else was there?
What else did we forget?
Well, that's it.
Okay.
That's it.
Magically,
you don't cut your disaster recovery scenario.
You can still ask in Kubernetes,
what you're going to do,
when you have one.
For that,
for a specific disaster recovery,
if you want.
For a disaster recovery.
Yes.
Okay,
cost downtime,
if the disaster recovery,
I don't know,
was good.
No,
it's not cost downtime,
it's cost losing of data.
In Slovenia,
that has nothing to do with it.
If you're an international company,
then you know what to do.
We know.
You know,
even if you're a Slovenian company,
your business is online,
and you live from it,
and you've done it,
shot in the foot,
by complicating your life so much.
Can you calculate what that means?
I don't know.
That kind of downtime.
We know examples,
where they lost a lot of data in Slovenia,
and in the end,
no one got sick.
Everything is custom-made,
one e-mail,
and they don't feel it,
but they feel they're in another country.
But,
but,
you know,
that no one got sick,
it's so interesting,
if you put it into numbers,
and in some percentages,
no one knows you,
on your brand,
on the revenue,
that the company creates.
Right?
I don't know,
I came here for a consultant,
who creates a specific revenue,
in the Slovenian market,
and there,
you can calculate exactly
what that means,
one hour of downtime.
Right?
Right in the peaks,
when they were,
I don't know,
Valentinovo,
Božić,
or Novljet,
and so on.
Right?
So,
those managers,
or those leaders,
they know how to calculate.
Yes.
In general,
you calculate
how much
one hour of downtime is,
and you do a cost-benefit analysis,
and if you save one hour of downtime,
you don't get sick.
Yes.
That's different.
Yes,
in a nutshell,
let me put it this way,
probably,
that disaster recovery,
with that,
you know,
second best solution,
which can be totally static,
or even better,
when you restore,
or put back
the same complexity.
Yes,
disaster recovery
is a terrible,
expensive thing.
It requires you
to take a pen,
write an essay,
and look at basic tooling.
It doesn't cost much.
But,
what I want to say,
if Kubernetes,
if you think that
Kubernetes gives you resiliency,
you still have to
make a mental effort,
and write
what your disaster recovery
will look like,
and test it,
every now and then,
let's say,
once every five years,
if you're a Slovenian startup.
I just want to say,
that technology
won't autoresolve
certain problems.
We're fucked.
I know.
We've heard a hard topic.
I'm the first one.
You're like a machine.
Lp, bye-bye.
Yes.
When I listen to Jure,
I have to say,
that if I listen to him,
I'll send him an email,
or something,
I don't know.
No,
I'm not going to send him
an email.
That he listened to you.
He can write a message.
Yes.
If he does,
he'll write to me.
He'll write to me.
Or something.
Are we going to work?
We're going to work.
And then we'll try
Javascript,
or something.
Or something.
What are we going to try next?
Tell me,
so that Jure will see.
Something like ReactHook.
Or something.
What is it?
He can come back.
Frontend technology,
frontend technology.
And what is Javascript for?
If we went full backend,
maybe,
are we going
even lower in the backend?
Or are we going
to work in engineering?
A bit of engineering,
a bit of recruitment,
and something like that.
Or are we going
up the stack?
Let's say
we're a developer,
then we're going
to containers,
then applay,
then security,
then,
I don't know,
performance,
whatever.
Are we going
up the stack,
down the stack,
left the stack,
right the stack,
right the stack.
I think
I'm the only one
talking.
Can you give us
a more easy,
a more fun
Javascript framework?
A fun one?
Yes,
Javascript framework.
Not just fun,
Javascript is
something fun,
whenever
I'm in touch
with Javascript,
I always get
a call.
We're going
to link
the scripts,
we're going
to put them out,
to ask people
what they think
about the topic,
maybe we'll
talk about it
in games.
In games.
Have you ever
played a game
with children?
No,
but I watched
Spiderman,
the first
time I watched
Spiderman.
A movie?
A real movie
Spiderman.
The first,
but the last.
The one
with,
not the
Spiderman
adventure,
whatever,
the new generation,
the old generation,
who
plays
Green Goblin.
And?
And,
you know,
little kids
climb up,
climb up
those buildings
and sit
on Spiderman
and jump up.
I don't know,
did I tell you
to watch it?
I think you
watched it
in the process,
but...
There was no
Nobenga Joka.
No,
no, no,
there was Star
4,
yesterday
was Star 6,
and you
listened to it
and it was
great.
And you have
those two fingers
on the top,
you know,
close up,
Spiderman
on the top.
I liked that part
a lot,
I liked it a lot,
and
I thought
you were
old enough
to watch it,
so it was
cool.
Here.
Spiderman.
Here,
let's work.
Ok, let's work.
If I do it now...
We can't.
I didn't record,
right?
I just recorded.
I didn't record,
right?
I just recorded.