We can start with a fresh episode of Grodje, which we will dedicate today to a purely time-appropriate topic.
Today we will talk about trains, we will talk about infrastructure, we will talk about scaling, and we will try to focus on infrastructure as a whole.
Today's episode will be more technical than the previous ones, and today we are alone with Andraž Brodnik, and we will go deep into the Jarek.
Let's say hello to everyone first.
I was just thinking, what if I'm alone with you, and I can't do anything, and you can box me into the frame.
Hello everyone!
Now we will try to make two episodes, so that we can talk about it.
First, we will talk about the cloud, what is happening with it, why is it a cloud, and we will go deeper into IOC.
Now, around the cloud itself, the infrastructure, operators, orchestrators, etc., we can have more episodes.
So, have a little patience watching this.
But yeah, I was focusing on IOC today.
Andraž is nodding nicely.
And now, I was thinking, when I was preparing for this episode, if we are going to talk about this topic, it is very important that at the beginning we set up some credibility,
so that we can tell people why we came up with this topic, or where we came up with this story.
So, maybe one of the easier ways is to go back to the beginning, so that you can tell what you started at the beginning,
how did you start with the infrastructure, how did you start with Linux, how did you set up your first server,
so that we can make a parallel of how the world changed.
And maybe if we go back in time, we will be able to describe what was the situation at that time, what were the demands at that time, and what the world was like.
So, let's start there.
So, my first question regarding this topic is, where did you start with Deops, or system engineering?
Where is your beginning in this area, and we will try to talk about it later.
This is a very good question.
In the early 2000s, there was a wide spread of Internet in Slovenia, or it was available for the end user.
And at that time I decided that the router we had was not as good as it was, or I wanted to understand how networking works,
and that led to the fact that I bought, for 10,000 dollars, an old Dell Pentium 3 or 4, and an additional network card.
And then I followed the lead, I remember, from Choker, Forum, Nenjalnik, how to make a router out of an old case.
Something like that.
And then I copied the instructions in Dummy to Windows via SSH, and configured it.
But what about your server? Did you already download it from CD, or from floppy disk?
No, no, it was already in CD.
Oh, it was already in CD.
Yes, I remember, this case already had some CD notes, but I know that I could update it with floppy disk,
because there were some problems with adding those PCIe networks.
So my first home router was...
Something like 386, 486?
No, it was Pentium 3, Pentium 4.
Oh, that was already...
Yes, yes, I think there were 2 or 4.
I know that there was a bed, an old desktop machine, and on top of that I had a cathode monitor.
Ah, ok, that's why.
Because the LCDs were so...
Rare, right?
Yes, you could take a look at it, but it was so expensive that I didn't have a lot of money,
so now that we have them, you don't know where you're going to mount those two.
So, yes, that's how I started.
How did you start?
You set up a router, that's how you started.
Yes, yes, actually...
Yes, I don't know what exactly happened with IPTables.
But you didn't have the intention of setting up a web server or something?
No, no, I was actually most interested in...
Ok, I'm interested in how IPv4 works.
I mean, I was like, ok, that's pretty simple at first, and then you can play around with it a bit.
And then you realize that some concepts are so hard to understand.
To understand.
Because I still have to think about it a lot of times, I've done it a hundred times already, just like at the end of the month.
How to work on it, or, well, it's basically just a path, up and down, up and down, and...
I also had a fear of terminals, and that was a long time ago.
Even when I joined CyberPig.
When you're so black, and you can't write anything.
I mean, it's like...
But it's interesting that you said that you connected with WindowsBox,
on the machine you set up, or something.
Yes, I've already done that a bit.
So you didn't directly set it up?
I did, I did.
I mean, I used to be on these frozen boards, but it wasn't that convenient.
I'd go to an old recording studio and watch concerts.
And then, after a month or so, I think, I figured out that a path exists.
And it lasted like that, it was like that.
So I built an old router, which was this GL,
and I hacked it while everyone else was watching TV.
At the time, TV was still an analog satellite, and terrestrial,
so you didn't need the internet for that.
And then I hacked it again, because it didn't work.
And then I hacked it for so long that it didn't start working,
and it lasted like that for six weeks.
And you...
Now, for a beginner at that time,
and it's probably the same for us,
and especially in the Linux space,
do people connect with distributors?
Do you connect with distributors?
No, you just...
When you're a noob, you don't have strong feelings about things.
And what did you do when you, for example,
fucked up the system and went to format everything?
No, no, you couldn't destroy it like that.
Basically, all that happened was
that you hacked the firewall so much
that your whole configuration went to shit.
That you locked yourself out.
Yes, but that wasn't a problem.
I went under the table, but behind me was a domain
that I could destroy as much as possible.
You didn't see the firewall,
and some things didn't happen at the time
that would hide the system so much
that you wouldn't see it.
That was the beginning of the fax,
because I hacked it so much,
and then the news.
How did you start?
I prepared myself,
I went to investigate a little
when it was that I played with those things myself,
when I started playing with those things.
And that was also a step
before the break of 2000,
and around 2000,
and for illustration at that time
PHP 4.0 was used,
for example, it was at that time.
And that was also a breakthrough year,
and around that year
Apache 2.x came out.
I think these are the major versions
of those two softwares.
I played a lot with Linux Slackware,
and that was like,
okay, debugging packages,
that's already done,
what's more hardcore than that?
And then I played with Slackware.
And Slackware at that time,
I think this distribution still exists,
but it's like,
Linux kernel,
some basic bash,
tooling,
I think it's also a compiler,
I didn't talk about it,
getCB is healthy,
but this thing worked like this,
you pulled down from the Internet
Apache source code,
PHP source code,
then you could,
or even if you had less SQL,
you could pull down less SQL,
but that was the most popular combo.
Then you could first compile,
I think PHP,
and then you could compile Apache,
extension,
compiled everything.
And that was compiled in a couple of hours.
And if you forgot a flag,
you could compile it again,
and then you got those binaries.
I was much more into that,
before I realized,
oh, look,
debugging packages,
and RPM packages,
and all that.
Those were some of the experiments.
At some point,
I tried everything,
from Fedora,
to Red Hat Linux,
to SUSE Linux,
to the shorter Ubuntu,
I think there were a lot,
but mostly I tried all those
different distributions,
I pulled most of them down,
then I played,
and when I got bored,
I deleted them all together,
and I became lazy.
And I also tried those BSDs,
NetBSD, OpenBSD, FreeBSD,
so I played a lot with those systems.
I think I worked on a desktop,
and then,
when I knew a bit more about PHP,
I worked on a lot of split pages,
and when I learned about SlashDiag,
then I earned some cash
through the diag part,
and then,
after two years,
I bought my first server,
and it was a part of ESC,
I don't know what,
and I also got a playground
for experimentation,
and I worked on a page,
and then I hosted them,
or I hosted others,
and those were my beginnings
with infrastructure,
I realized then,
that if I wanted to work
on a page,
I had to live somewhere,
and if you know how to layer it,
it's easier to do it from the bottom.
I wasn't interested in
some nat-type of firewall,
and I never really struggled with that,
and I also hosted an FTP server,
and an IRT server,
and I played around with those.
Now, I'll give you a bit of context,
I went to look around a bit,
and when we talk about
2022,
in those areas,
maybe,
the internet
was around 300-350 million
users back then.
For example,
in the year 2022,
there were almost
5 billion users
of the internet,
and 62%
of the population
on Earth
has access to the internet.
So,
the world in which
we both started,
was such that
if a neighbor saw your page,
it was already big,
and people didn't really know
what to do with it,
plus those geographical challenges,
and now,
fast forward,
today,
there are more expectations,
more users,
and in a way,
there was a lot of luck
that there weren't so many users
and that you could play,
and there weren't any expectations
from the people who looked at the page,
that everything would snap together.
Yeah, I don't know,
when I look back,
there are three more things
that I remember very well.
I remember that traffic light
when you started MySQL
on Windows,
there was such a traffic light
that people thought
that you weren't working,
because they thought
that you were working,
and then when you set up
PHP, BBForum,
you were very happy
that you were working,
and then you thought,
okay, I'm the biggest
king in the world now.
That's a memory
that was very funny to me.
Then I remember
when I applied
and I was on duty,
I could get into
all those computers
very quickly,
because they were
in one code,
and they actually
booted from the LAN,
but at that time
it wasn't like that.
I mean, smartphones
came out very quickly,
and it was just
a different time.
People actually
didn't know that.
When you applied
for that particular job,
did you apply randomly
or did you intend to work?
Very randomly.
I just wanted to do something
that was connected
to technology,
and then,
because it was a factory,
the queue was already
very low at that time,
it was about two and a half.
And then,
I remember
that one question
was the best
question for the job ever.
There were predetermined
answers to almost
all the questions,
but one was just
for the job.
I mean, a game hadn't
come out yet,
and then you could
circle around it
for the job.
You could always install
a distribution at home
or at your neighbor's,
or something like that.
So,
one of the reasons
that I was more
comfortable with
building things
was because I had
been maintaining
a lot of things
for so many years.
This last memory
comes to mind
when I was at Krimp.
At that time,
if you had capital
or cash,
you went to the store
and bought short
Ethernet cables
to solder switches
to each other.
We probably didn't have
that much cash at the time.
I remember that
at Krimp I had
60 cables,
and you had to put them
into a connector.
You had to look at it
and solder it,
and I had a bloody hand
one day.
I remember that
because it seemed
really funny to me.
I hope you like it
when you play Krimp.
Well,
that was a trip down
the memory lane.
If I can go back
to the beginning,
why did I choose
this building?
I really liked it
because the systems
that worked
allowed people
to access the system,
the pages,
the media,
and people could see
what you were doing.
You could get tools
to help people.
I had this feeling
that I created a webpage
and people could work with it.
Unbelievable.
There was one guy
with a new gun
and a shotgun.
That was it.
Now,
you are a certified
Google Cloud Engineer,
right?
Yes,
Cloud Architect.
Now it's gone,
but I did
that certification.
Do you also work
for AWS?
I don't know how many
you have.
For AWS,
I could only write
and go.
I used to say
that
those certifications
are useless.
On the other hand,
when I started working,
I realized
that they are useful
because
you would never
go through
all those things
if you didn't have
a curriculum.
Some things are useless,
but a lot of them
are.
Before that,
I would do it
custom.
I like the fact
that all those things
are useful
when you study for it.
Do you want to save it
through a certification?
Do you want to go
and do it?
If you do
a certification
for Google Cloud
or AWS,
do you think
it's easier
to do it for others?
If you study for it.
I think
it's easier.
If you establish
the basics of
networking,
cloud,
deployment,
containers,
and then you study
for AWS.
On the one hand,
if you know Italian
and it's easier
to learn Spanish,
yes,
but you have to be careful
not to think about
words
if you really want
to know it well.
But I don't know
how...
Even if the things
are different,
you have a reference point.
If you say
that networking
in Google Cloud
is more loose,
if you study
for AWS,
you have that kind of
network.
I used it before,
but I didn't
think about it
that much.
On a very
professional level,
you think
that it's more
strict.
I don't know
how you separate
two projects
so that
in Google Cloud
and in AWS
it's different,
but if you know
how,
let's say,
Google does it
quite simply
and I think
it's good,
then in AWS
you can think
about it
more.
Will it be a
low-cost
AWS account?
Will there be
GitHub Organizations?
You can take
all the roles
as those
you use
because
things are
a bit different,
but it helps you
a lot
because you have
a reference point
where you can say
this is different
with this part.
It's always easier
because you don't
have any of that.
I think it's
quite fast.
I mean,
it's not ultra-trivial
to say
I did GCP
and in a month
I'll have AWS.
It's not like that,
but it's easier
for you.
For managers
who listen
or entrepreneurs
who have
programmers,
would you consider
sending your
system,
CDO,
or engineers
to these
tasks?
Do you think
if they know
more about
cloud
or if
they go
through
certification
or courses,
do you think
they will
use
those
cloud offerings
better?
Because of
less reinventing
and more
use of
those resources?
I think
it's
very important
that
if you're
at the beginning
of your career,
it's important
because you'll
learn a lot
because you
don't have
a lot of knowledge
and if you have
a guide
and a
curriculum,
it will
help you a lot.
In the end,
you'll get
everything you
need
from any
cloud provider.
It's not
that important.
If you're
employed
and you
have
a high
level
experience,
it's
important
that
you
have
a high
level
experience
and
you
have
a
smart
information
system
and
you
have
a
good
experience
and
you
have
a
high
level
experience
and
you
have
a
smart
information
system
and
you
have
a
high
level
experience
and
you
have
a
smart
information
system
and
you
have
a
high
level
experience
and
you
have
a
high
level
experience
and
you
have
a
smart
information
system
and
you
have
a
high
level
experience
and
you
have
a
smart
information
system
and
you
have
a
high
level
experience
and
you
have
a
smart
information
system
and
you
have
a
high
level
experience
and
you
have
a
smart
information
system
and
you
have
a
high
level
experience
and
you
have
a
smart
information
system
and
you
have
a
high
level
experience
and
you
have
a
smart
information
system
It's already quite robust, and this is a very important premise.
It's a very important word outside of technological affairs.
If you're in the commercial sector, and you want to have...
I mean, what is the set of people you need, it's harder without it.
Let's give this connection to people who may not know.
If we're talking about entry-level certification, engineering certification, courses,
does it cost, I don't know, 20,000 euros, 100,000 euros?
What is the price range of these certificates?
That's a good question.
Google has a deal with Coursera,
and for education you pay around 45 euros per month,
and they've allowed you to use Google's website for educational purposes.
They've found a good place for it.
Then, I think the certification was around 200 euros.
You need to write it in an exam center.
In Ljubljana, it's around 3 euros,
but you can also do it online,
but because of the coronavirus, it changes a bit.
In Ljubljana, you typically have to write it somewhere,
but here you have time.
For AWS, it's nothing special.
In Slovenia, there are offers for business training,
there are also mixed offers,
where you have to prepare for a certificate,
where they guide you through things.
It's also really good.
They tell you this, this, and this,
but it's also documentation that you need to go through.
Some things will be more interesting,
others will be less interesting,
but if you cover the same base,
and if you're really interested,
you also get a little extra money.
You don't do it because someone told you to.
Or, you know...
You have to look at it as an open documentation.
Yes, but when I pay for it myself,
it's a child's expense,
and you look at it differently.
In the end, the certificate doesn't matter.
It's more about me doing a better job.
It's more like I'm doing more business
on the software as a service,
rather than doing it on my own.
There are similar prices on AWS,
from 200 euros.
For someone who's a student,
it's relatively expensive,
but if you're in a business,
if someone wants to do it,
it's not that expensive.
At least, I don't think so.
In these conversations,
we'll call it biased,
but we also have Azure Cloud,
Oracle Cloud,
smaller offers,
cloud technology,
and also hosting.
I would say that there are similar problems.
I don't have exact information,
so it's a bit difficult to talk about it
in this episode,
but I think it's very similar.
You also get badges and certificates for Azure.
They also have very good courses,
and you can get everything.
I have one more question,
just to sum it up,
because I think it's interesting.
Who pays for the hosting
that you need to be able to play?
Who pays for the credit?
Where do you get the money
to be able to play half a day
on these clouds?
To do a lab?
That's a great question.
There are different strategies.
Google Cloud will make your account
in the first 12 months
with a 300-euro budget,
which you can spend,
and they will pay for it.
Most of the time,
for self-education,
the costs of daily infrastructure
are especially low.
So, I don't know,
everything I did,
I did it on my own credit,
and not at the end,
to make a lab.
There are a lot of people
who are educated,
who have specialized offers,
who have a contract
with cloud providers,
and in the end,
you get a lab.
It's a laboratory environment,
and it's on-demand.
You make a loan,
they give you a username and password,
and literally,
you get the environment,
and you click there,
and the lab also has a check
at the back,
if you clicked it correctly.
They give you a logo,
you click it,
and then they verify
if you did it correctly.
If the resources are there.
So, most of the time,
it's all included
in the education itself,
so you don't have to
pay extra for it.
Okay.
Phew, we're warmed up.
Are you comfortable?
It's warm.
Okay, let's talk
a little bit more
about
how we
actually came
to these clouds.
That's a good question.
Actually, I don't know,
20 years ago,
you had a server,
and it was your box,
and there was one box.
Why did we come to the cloud?
What's the path
that we are
full of clouds today?
Why do we need these clouds?
Give me a reason.
Why do you think
there's a need for
a host, for example?
I would say
it's a natural evolution.
Not all firms are
technology-first firms,
which means that if you want
to have a storage thing,
it doesn't make much sense,
if you're too small,
to have a server
in the middle of a desk
at your feet.
Let's say you're an average
middleman.
At some point,
in the mid-2000s,
I think everyone needed
a server, and then
you could have
some equipment, and of course,
there were offers.
They bought storage units,
gave them away, amortized them,
and offered it as
a monthly payment.
Most of the time, it looked like
you had to virtualize it.
You called a secret firm
on the phone or e-mail,
and you said,
we would transfer the virtual
with this and that spec,
this and that disk,
and then someone had
more or less than
one of us,
and a security guard,
and he calculated
that the amortization process
was going to take a while,
or maybe not.
And now,
people are calling,
sending e-mails,
it's fluid,
you simply have
split portals,
where you can click on it,
make an order,
send it back,
the most typical,
I don't know,
you want hosting,
localalpha.php,
ok, cool, you have that.
Then, at some point,
it started to happen that
above that,
what if people want
to access it
through APIs,
it means that
now everything is RESTful,
but at the time, it wasn't RESTful,
you had SOAP, or Remote Procedure Call,
in XML,
and everything was set by a server,
and that's how
it all started,
once you have an API
that can manage your infrastructure,
everything is done
through Cloud.
That's the
local version,
how we got into it.
In practice, I don't know,
AWS started with SQS,
which was very useful for them,
then they started to implement it as a storage,
and then they added
Compute Engine,
and Google started to...
Now we'll stop.
You went too fast.
It's all cool.
Let's go back a bit.
Why do you want to be a company
with your own hardware?
I mean, you can have it,
but it doesn't mean anything.
Why do you want to be a company
with your own hardware?
What are good reasons
to buy your own servers,
to set up your own
data center?
Good reasons are
if you really need
regulation,
I don't think you need
it because of regulation,
but if you really need
your own hardware,
that's one option.
Another option is
if you really need
a lot of data,
and you need
low latency,
if you're doing video editing,
and you need
a video production company,
then it's important
to have a server.
On the other hand,
I don't know,
we're almost there.
There are a lot of
special things.
If you have your own hardware.
Yes, or if you have
an infrastructure,
I mean, you're an industry,
and if someone has
a Java app,
you won't be able to cloud it.
It's like a box.
You have two identical boxes,
and you put them together.
These are industrial special things.
It's a waste of knowledge.
Or I don't know.
Yes, audio production is the same.
Low latency is very important.
Why is it a waste of knowledge?
It's because
you need to have
a good environment.
If you're a woman,
the environment is even better.
Then it's a bit hotter,
and you need air conditioning.
Then you need more hormones,
and you have an electricity problem.
Then you have to amortize everything.
You buy everything,
and you have everything.
You have to pay for the internet.
Yes, you have to pay for the internet.
Then you realize
that this equipment
is computer-amortized,
but at some point
you realize
that more electricity
gives you more compute power.
You have to think about
what you want to have.
In the future?
Typically, you will have a problem
that it is inefficient
before the future.
If you are extremely big,
if you are a very big company,
you will have to
listen to the public.
From the cloud,
the first thing you take down
are databases and data,
because you want to have them up.
You typically put computing up,
but there are
more advanced things.
You need to get
more of the classic things
that are everywhere.
They have flexibility,
you don't have to
have an additional server,
you don't have the problem
to call the provider
and say that your datacenter
has no more disk space,
no more RAM slots.
It might seem
bizarre to someone
who is already working
with Ethereum,
because it is unlimited.
Sometimes you call them
and they tell you
that they don't need more disk space.
What are you going to do next?
It is difficult.
The other bizarreness
is that you are
an e-commerce platform
and you have 100 pages
with 100 domains
on different providers,
you register them,
you decide that you are
very smart and you will
switch to DNS.
When registering,
for example, if you want to sell
sour milk,
they will write your IP address
where your DNS server is.
How are you going to switch
when you have 100 people
who are not technology experts
who have registered the domain
to be able to switch
the location of the server?
There are a lot of things.
I forgot one more thing.
If you have hardware,
you need people
who will physically
go to the hardware
and maybe change the disk,
upgrade it,
patch it.
Let's say in Slovenia
you get a disk on Friday
at 2 p.m.
When will you be able to buy a new disk?
It is said that at least on Tuesday.
Good luck.
I mean, you have to know
vendors and logists
in a special way
to be able to switch.
There are a lot of bizarreness
that I have encountered
and they are very fluid
to the point
that they are
even more fluid.
I think that
if we talk about compliance,
if you want to cut
data in Slovenia,
then you can do it
by yourself or by a Slovenian vendor.
Please, do it
with a Slovenian vendor
if you expect good support,
which will be better than
if you try to get it
from someone on the phone.
But
when a compliance
requires 24-hour
security for a person,
then you
can't afford it.
I hear a lot of times
that we can't have it
because there are some regulations.
It would be much easier
to give the risk to someone
and they will pay you
for
ISO 27000X
or SOC 2
or...
I don't know.
I know that there must be
a registry and some data.
It doesn't make much sense
to have it on paper
if you really want it,
but you can't afford it.
Did I forget anything else?
That's all I wanted to say.
I hear a lot of times
maybe a little less now,
but
reliability.
Reliability.
I mean...
How do I put it?
Even clouds are not silver bullets
and they are 100% reliable
and I don't know what else.
Local data centers
are not 100% reliable either.
None of those solutions
are 100%
silver bullets.
Even S3
is
endless, I don't know what else.
But it's not
100% reliable.
It has some 999
reliability.
I don't know.
Do you also have
a view of the world
where...
How should I put it?
Reliability is a very complex thing.
But the most basic way
is...
If you're in telecommunications
those 9 or energy
are very important because it's a critical infrastructure
for...
You can also buy a station
and your station
when you have it in the office
and the data center
can draw
and this event
can happen.
Now...
It depends on
your business model
if you want to cover it or not.
In both cases.
If you're a startup, even if you have everything in the cloud
or locally, in both cases
you won't have a backup.
If you're
a proper
company
it's more likely that you'll have it.
But you can have it in both cases.
Then you have
some special use cases
that are products that rely
heavily on infrastructure.
You'll look at these percentages
and calculate
how much theoretical output
there is.
You'll know the difference
between the 5th place
and the 7th.
I would say that
practically
the cloud
is more reliable.
It happened to me as well.
You get a daily event
and it's hard to find it.
It's gone.
It's not a problem
and it happened to me
once in my entire career.
I won't go
deeper into this
because we'll get
into it later.
Can you tell me
some types of
computations
inside
the cloud?
Can you tell me
the differences between the 3 models?
I'll give you the first one.
You tell me.
Let's start
with the computations.
Tell me what does
IAAS mean.
We can start
with the index.
IAC stands for
Infrastructure.
PA stands for
Platform.
SAS stands for
Service.
Infrastructure,
Platform
and Service.
Infrastructure is
a typical way
for small teams
to consume
in Slovenia's cloud.
You go to AWS
which has a large dashboard
and you click on
4 virtual machines
and so many disks.
You also get
implicit default networking.
You're very lucky
and it reminds you
of the times when you
only had VMWare
virtual machines.
These machines
are quite complex
but typically you can
think of disks,
networking
and virtual machines.
These are typical examples.
And when I have
4 boxes and I need
the 5th one, what do I do?
You click on it.
You have roughly
3 options.
You go to the dashboard,
click on it,
you get one.
Or you use a special tool
which will
if there are not 5 of them
it means there will be 5.
If there are 6,
there will be one less.
Platform as a service?
Platform as a service is like this.
You're a developer
and you know
you have PHP
and you need
a MySQL database
and then
you use a framework
let's say WordPress
and then you write a file
which is PHP
entry point
it depends on the implementation
or the language
how it's implemented.
It's called an index
it depends if it's conventional
or not.
And then it will say
that you need
a database
and you give it to yourself
you say deploy
and it magically happens.
It's the same with
Python
your provider
supports certain languages
and you tell
in which bucket
what your language is
and you get a dashboard
where the app is running
you have a logo
you can restart the app
and then it depends
it can also be a non-activity
if you don't have a package
it will be through an app
and typical examples are
Heroku
Google
Engine
Google App Engine
or Beanstalk
and it's great
if you're a beginner
and you just want to deploy something
you download it in Heroku
and then you write
Python or Flask app
and you deploy it
but as a programmer
as a user
you don't deal with
a virtual machine
you don't deal with networking
firewalls, breakups
you end up
with an IP
and because those things
are abstracted
from you
those providers can give you
certain cool bonuses
like if you want to revert
to another deploy
or if you want to have
two deploys
and 99% of the traffic
goes to the old one
and it helps you
with the new version
for example
in Canary
you have
part of the traffic
on a new one
and it turns out
if you want to do it on IEC
and you have virtual machines
it's not that easy
it's very complex
ok
and
let's talk about
service software
the third layer
of abstraction
what is it?
I think that
it's very
popular
more and more
I don't know if the basics
fall under that
you just say
I would click there
and I would have
a user
and now
I can put a base there
and I get back
that port
sorry, that IP
that's a username
and there's a base
and that's one thing
if you want to have
a mail server to send
instead of
saying
I need a mail server
open
The GIMP, SPF, all those things, certificates, so I don't go to spam, no, you just, there's an API, you call the API, and that's it.
You want to call a person on the phone, or you want to send an SMS, then you have an API there that you pay for every SMS,
then you receive it as a certificate, and then you send it to, I don't know, Postrequest, REST, or whatever else.
And then there's a huge, huge amount of that.
For old school, old school engineers who, for example, were, who went through, we just mentioned those shortcuts,
and if we go back to setting up your own servers in your own rack and stuff, if you go from that infrastructure, platforms, SaaS,
to ultimately LAMBDA, and so on, there's a lot of arguments here, that every level, when you go to vendor locking,
you always have less control over how you see it.
Because every level of abstraction is a question of whether you can achieve a lot inside, and you tune it, and, well, let's just say that.
Now that's the answer.
One time, a colleague told me that when you drive on public roads, or local roads, right,
I mean, for him, when he's driving, it looks like a bus that's pulling you from the center, or from the center.
You, in fact, have a project, and at that point you decide what you're going to choose, and then you go with it.
And that doesn't mean that you're entirely responsible for that vendor.
You're not an Apple user, or a Linux user, or a Windows user.
It's a little harder for me to replace that.
And then, if you look at it from a business perspective, you can also ask yourself, is this really such a problem?
And it's really funny to me that in our space, we think a lot about it,
because we work with very, very large companies that are not directly technological competitors to AWS.
All people work in risk analysis, right?
With the team that's responsible for that.
And legal, and everything.
They're just like that.
And, I don't know, we now have AWS.
The probability that AWS will disappear is very small.
And how we're going to fix it, how we're going to fix the engineers, that's their problem.
It's going to come from me.
And the benefits that we're going to get from them, because it's not like a business.
Is there a point where you say, shit, the components are becoming too expensive.
We're going to go back.
We're going to go a level lower.
How is this happening?
This used to happen in our space.
And a lot of times, people don't know how to calculate expenses.
Either equipment or people.
And then I think a lot of times...
For example, let's say we have two companies.
And it's very successful.
And each year they get 100,000 euros.
And then they get 4,000 euros.
And you say, wow, that's really a lot.
We're going to go back to...
I don't know.
We're going to hire engineers.
And then we're going to get a junior DevOps to fix it.
Because that's going to cost us a lot.
Because 4,000 euros is really a lot.
This might work for our bubble.
Because we're in some technology.
And you say, okay, I'm going to hire a junior.
I have to pay him 2,000 euros.
And then the amortization.
Let's say it pays off somehow.
But in the end, I think...
This is mainly happening because people don't know how to calculate expenses.
I pay a lot of attention to that.
You buy a new tractor, it costs 5 million.
Even if you don't deserve 5 million back.
This is also happening to us in IT.
I think we're not very good at it.
Or at calculating.
To be able to calculate it a little.
Now, if something is really obscure...
In the end, it's a cost-benefit.
If something is really obscure.
You say, aha, that's so expensive.
We're going to migrate to another one.
The price is different.
The price of migration is different.
Can we do it from the inside?
The risks we're going to have if we stay here are like this.
The risks of migration are like this.
The risk that a new vendor that is now more expensive will increase the price is like this.
I also pay attention to that.
People choose, let's say...
Slovenians make cloud offers based on price.
That's a very bad strategy.
At the time, Google was only one-fourth of the price of AWS.
That was their selling point.
When I started using Google Cloud, which is a good compute engine...
They were like, we're only 25% of the price of AWS.
Great, but...
Maybe in two months you won't be 25% of the price of AWS.
And Google is now the same price as AWS.
And they have more things to do.
Which is good in the end, if you have a smaller team.
But it's not the cheapest.
Maybe somewhere more expensive.
You have to think about it.
Never say never.
Maybe it will pay off.
But...
Do you really need your StriveX to wash a car once a year?
Or to go to the laundry to have someone else wash it for you?
If it makes you very happy to have your own StriveX...
And you pay people for it...
It's also fine.
Everything comes naturally.
Before I tell you...
Let's try to segment these providers.
Can we do it on a high level?
Or on a business level?
Or from the top?
Can we, for example...
Azure, AWS, and Google Cloud Platform.
Do you notice any differences?
How are these platforms designed?
How do they start to be used?
Is it possible to use it on a high level?
There are also big three.
I have a lot of experience with AWS and Google Cloud.
With Azure, less.
But...
I've seen companies I've worked for use it.
But I haven't worked with them directly.
Because they are big systems.
And I would say...
AWS...
Is...
More like...
StarCloud.
It's more like Dino.
And then you can see the legacy, how it's being used.
Things are well done.
Properly done.
But...
If you want to adapt...
Like Jason.
When you don't understand why it's there.
You need to gather your thoughts.
That's why it's not important...
Do you have access to something?
You can find a lot of things.
Can this service do this?
Can this user do this?
Can this virtual one do this?
Can this Lambda function do this?
What's the reason?
It's like an old XML.
It's edited.
And grounded.
Why is it there?
It's...
On the market...
There's a huge market share.
Google doesn't catch it.
Azure doesn't catch it.
If you learn one cloud...
And you want to be a professional...
On big companies...
AWS is the way to go.
And for a reason.
It's a complex machine.
And it's...
It's your career.
AWS is your career.
Google is...
In my opinion...
It's too shallow.
Hipsterish has certain advantages.
For example...
If you have more projects...
And more stages and production...
And two projects...
You can segment it in Google.
That's one thing.
I think...
Access is more loose.
Network is more loose.
It's not that strict.
If you want to talk outside your WPC...
You talk outside your WPC.
That's a problem.
It's reasonable.
You can create security.
Not that it's not security.
But it's not an extreme level.
There are certain things...
I think Google is still...
Ahead of everything else.
Data analysis.
They bought Looker.
It's a platform where you can look at data.
Their BigQuery is very powerful.
There are segments in the industry...
Where...
Google is ahead.
Almost everywhere else...
It's the same as AWS.
Or it lags behind.
I played with their Cloud Functions.
I think you played with their Cloud Functions too.
The same documentation.
It all makes sense.
But when you want to combine things...
Strange things happen.
If you want to have IPv6 in Google Cloud...
That's not possible.
Reload balancer is over.
If it's good, it doesn't matter.
If it's bad, it doesn't matter.
You can try it.
If it matters, try it.
It's not the best choice.
Azure...
It's really nice.
Because...
How do you...
Unlock and...
Make happy...
All the people on Microsoft stack.
It's very simple.
You start hacking...
Security releases...
On-premise security.
And you start pushing Azure.
And you say...
Active Directory...
You managed it yourself.
It's so hard.
We offer it to you as a student.
And it's all very easy.
And a bunch of candy.
Because it's such a hard thing.
It's a cost.
You already have Microsoft Teams.
Exactly.
And Cloud...
I think it's great.
Because I think...
If...
If you already have it.
And you need to do something.
It doesn't matter if you...
Go to AWS.
You're committed to it.
And I like it.
That's my...
Hypothesis.
I have a feeling that...
With Google...
The development of Cloud goes...
From the point of view that...
First of all...
They develop things for their needs.
Primarily.
And then those things they already use...
Then they go to some transformations.
And through those transformations...
They get to their...
Public Cloud or something.
Just like with Microsoft and Azure...
I have a feeling that...
Their main customers are...
Enterprises from the beginning.
And I have a feeling that...
With Azure...
They are much more...
And better connected.
I don't know what else to say.
I don't know.
You already suggested using Synapse.
I think they are much more...
Coherently connected.
With Google.
And...
One is coming from themselves.
Maybe I'm wrong.
My feeling was like that.
When I saw those tools.
Is that a hypothesis?
I know for a fact that...
Google definitely doesn't work like that.
Google doesn't use Cloud.
If you try engineering.
They force people to use their Cloud.
How do they use it?
I don't know.
They still use Borg.
They are not consumers.
Their concepts are different.
Maybe they use Bitcoin for their products.
Maybe.
But that's not the case.
They would probably eat...
What do you call it?
Eat your own dog food.
They would probably eat a briquette.
But...
You can see that...
Google Cloud has a lot of problems.
I think that their product...
Segment...
Project.
That's why...
First of all, they look around.
And then they try to implement it.
So they have a lot of cash.
But there are still things there.
You don't pay attention to that.
You really pay attention to that.
If you...
If you pay attention to that.
That's what I pay attention to.
If you use cutting edge.
Yes.
Ok.
Let's say...
I played with...
When I say I played, I mean I used it.
I didn't use it for my website.
I played with IBM's Cloud.
I also played with Oracle's Cloud.
Also those two...
I would say...
If we go through all the shortcuts...
That we had before.
When you say, I just want to have a computer.
That's it.
I just want to have 5 virtual machines.
And a disk, and I don't know what else.
There are no crazy differences.
You get the same boxes.
If you don't need them, you spend them.
There are no differences.
I think there are more differences.
Now I need Oracle's Autonomous Database.
I want it to manage itself.
Clean up, scale it up.
There are a lot of differences.
And when you go to even higher abstract levels.
When you go to Lambda.
When you go to those specifics.
There are a lot of differences.
And there are also...
I see differences.
Maybe you said it yourself.
Sometimes I see those boxes.
Or services that fill them.
They work great on their own.
Sometimes I see problems.
When you have to connect those boxes.
For example, with Google.
I noticed Google Cloud Run.
It's the Knative runner for containers.
It's fully managed.
It works with other services.
With VPC, with Caching,
with Redis and everything.
You connect that part.
It's one thing how you do it.
It's another thing what documentation.
But to be fair, it's relatively new.
It's still developing.
It'll be different tomorrow.
As it was a couple of months ago.
But I see those differences.
How things are combined.
And where you have right now
Hybrid or non-hybrid cloud.
Or you have some outdated
applications.
You have Knative.
If you're Slovenian
or someone who works in Slovenia.
Maybe it's more important
that if you already use
Google Workspaces.
You already have all the users inside.
Why not use Google Cloud?
And I think it's legit.
Reason for
using Google Cloud.
Don't go into
over-optimization.
It's not worth it.
I think people will think
oh my god, we've been there
and they'll get stuck.
We could go on
another topic.
Now,
let's talk about
the next big topic.
If we said
one server, then we had more servers.
Then you moved the phone
and said give me a new disk.
Let me configure it.
Then you sent mails.
Now,
where is
in all this
heat of some
technologies and tools.
Where is the space
for automation?
As engineers,
we need automation inside this space.
Maybe
that's the answer.
There are many
use cases.
One of the use cases
is that
all the dashboards are
relatively complex.
With time,
when you click the resources in the cloud,
it's problematic
because
you don't know
what exactly you clicked.
It would be more difficult
to have a sheet of paper
saying we need this
and we can have it in the cloud.
If you have
up to 20 dashboards
and you don't use many things,
you have more people
who know what resources
you clicked.
Otherwise,
it's complex.
Then there are things
where you need more dynamics.
A good example is
when you do surveys
for presidential elections
and you have
an image.
When you send people
an email
to do the survey,
in the first minutes,
a lot of people will click it.
Traditionally,
even if you click auto-scaling,
it will be too cold
and people
won't do it until
auto-scaling says
we have a lot of requests,
but you lost
track of the users
who opened the email.
It's a bit theoretical
but maybe
it's worth it
to warm up the system
so you hire 4 times more
surveyors and then send the email.
How would you do that?
You can do it with automation.
It's a useful thing.
You get
faster
and you can
react to needs.
You have better tooling
for automated
enlargement and
elasticity of your
infrastructure.
Cloud providers
often have auto-scaling stories
which will be watched
by users
using a reminder
or
a processor.
You can
enlarge it and
shorten it.
You also need webasto
when your car goes
in front of you.
You can work with that.
A good example is
we have 2 microservices
and traditionally
one click of the other
via HTTP
but if the other falls down,
the first one falls down too.
We are 4 but
if one falls down,
we all fall down.
And then we say
that we will create a queue
or a PubSub system
where we will log
the messages.
If one falls down,
it's great.
The problem is
when you have
a lot of microservices
and a lot of queues
and you have all those queues
in the cloud
and you can
say in your code
that this service is lagging on that queue
and then you have another process
or a program which looks at all those services
and where the queues
need to exist
and as a guarantee
confirms that they exist
on the cloud.
Ok, so let's
sort out 2 things.
The concept
goes to
the declarative
description
of what you have
or what you want to have
and instead of writing it
in a list, we write it
in some YAML
in some format, file, JSON, YAML
whatever
or
we use a programming language
to do it, but we describe
what we want to have
and then some tooling
will determine what is already done
and what is not done
and will determine
which changes need to be made
and will communicate with the cloud
or with some tooling
how to do it
and how to do it will be determined.
And in this I would say
infrastructure as code
or infrastructure
as a code
two A's.
There is also something
called configuration management
and these things
overlap a bit.
It's more about
I already have a server
and I have 5 pages
and there
in Nginx or Apache
I have virtual domains
or servers
where I say if a person
comes with a domain nom.c
I show him this page
and if he comes
with another domain
then
he goes somewhere else.
And now when I add
if I have 5 pages, then I add 6 pages
then I have to change this configuration
and so that I don't do it manually
you have more configuration
management systems.
These are systems that are more
specialized so that
for example
Ansible will function
so that you add
a new domain
it connects
via SSH to
the server, changes the file
so that Nginx
reloads or restarts
the details
and
that's it.
Ansible also has
a different module
that will tell you
if I still want
to install this
virtual domain and
it will also take care of that.
It's not necessarily more specialized
for configuration management
but infrastructure is code
that takes care of infrastructure
and that's also part of Ansible.
Before we get into the specific tooling
everyone who
might be listening to this
and I don't know
if SSH on the server is
done manually or if
scripts are written to do it
why would
you pay for this tooling
that we will talk about
to use this tooling versus
to just copy via FTP
or SSH and then do it manually
what's the advantage?
At some point it's hard to scale
that's the first thing
at another point
you can do it manually
and then decide
if you want to do it with or without script
and yeah
bash is also
a fun language
if you can call it that
that's also
from the time
when it was first
introduced
and
I think
it was
Error prone scripts are hard to maintain, and then you have to implement one more thing a lot of times with independence.
That means that when you call something, it already exists, it's okay, if it doesn't exist, you do it.
You can't go back to the fact that you want to do something and it still exists.
That means that you can call it many times and it will always be okay.
And that's why these tools are important.
One more interesting thing.
Do you want to be the same person who wrote the script that other people have to maintain?
It's no longer in the company.
That's a big question for me.
What is the correct way of writing this language?
How to maintain it is very tricky, because I think such a detail is difficult.
We don't all know this language so well.
It's a bit like JavaScript, but it's not so popular that everyone knows it so well.
Okay.
We have now described this basic concept.
Previsioning, configuration.
Previsioning means that you move servers, set up networking, load balancer.
Configuration means that you set up packages, make sure that the configuration is specific for the service, etc.
And then comes the deployment of a workload or data workload.
Which also needs to be configured or packed.
And then things start to flow.
Basically, we have two stages.
The first stage is the initial setup of the infrastructure, then the management of the infrastructure.
The second stage is the initialization of the app, and then the management of the app.
These are the two layers that we see in the whole space.
Now we will talk a little more about the other players that help inside.
We will talk a little about the boss, the puppet, and you will talk about Terraform.
Okay?
Okay.
Mixed salad.
If...
Let's sort them out a little bit.
What do these four things mean to you?
What does this tool mean to you, for example?
What does the boss mean to you, and what does the puppet mean to you?
I will ignore the fact that there are three of us, because it's easier.
I think that in recent years, things have converged a lot.
Puppet is not so popular, but...
Puppet and Ansible with the build-up were more...
What is it called?
With the configuration management tool.
For Puppet, I don't know if it can run on infrastructure.
When I used it last time, it didn't work.
The difference between the two was that...
Ansible will connect with SSH on servers.
Or at the end of the day, if it supports SSH.
I used it for Raspberry Pi.
And it will make some changes.
The good thing is that you don't need a client up there.
It doesn't have to be a SSH client, but most of the time it is.
And that's the model we call push.
Ansible pushes some things.
Puppet, for example, in Solstack, works the opposite.
You have a client called Puppet Master.
And then you have more things that connect up there.
And they say, what condition do I have to be in?
I'm this, she's that, what's my condition?
And then they pull it down.
And they change their configuration as they need to.
Why is that useful?
For example, we have KAL machines, which are smart.
Which are scattered all over Slovenia.
And they are behind some NAT.
And it's hard to penetrate them through networking.
They will simply contact you.
Or, for example, if you have a conference.
And you have 5 Raspberry Pi's that can show you sponsor slides.
It's easier for you.
You disassemble them until you write a note.
They are already there.
You can reboot one or the other.
They are registered back there.
I'm interested in the conference.
You mentioned autonomous vehicles.
Yes, I've already organized an autonomous vehicle conference.
But I don't have it yet.
It's a very practical thing.
We can use it on B-sites.
And then you lose a little bit of the existing infrastructure.
Because it doesn't make sense for the client to get some later infrastructure.
It was different before.
You have steps that start like this.
You create a virtual account on AWS or Node.
You wait for it to be done.
Then you connect it to SSH.
You put it on a Docker container.
And you start it.
It's a hybrid model.
In the first phase, you have the infrastructure.
In the second phase, you configure it.
Terraform?
You can do these things in Robo.
But it's not done to fully modify it.
Terraform is done.
In Terraform, you write a language.
It's very simple.
Very simple.
You have different providers.
A provider gives you an interface for a cloud.
For example, if you use AWS, you'll have AWS providers.
Then you put architecture on it.
If you want to have WPC,
networking,
you can have Kubernetes,
users, service accounts,
custom roles,
bindings of custom roles on users.
You write it there.
And when you run it,
the infrastructure is built there.
Terraform has a local representation
of what's on the cloud.
It's very declarative.
When you remove an object from the code,
it will look at its local state
and erase the resource.
That's how it works.
In Terraform,
what happens if someone from the team
clicks on something on the cloud
and it wasn't over Terraform?
That's a great question.
Nothing.
Terraform works like this.
Whenever someone does something,
they write it down locally
or in a shared state.
They write down the value.
They say, I'll manage it.
It's like a file.
It's a file with values.
It writes down, I'll manage it.
You add an object to the Terraform file
and it will generate it.
When you erase it,
and you don't need an object in Terraform,
how does it know it needs to erase something?
It creates a delta between states
and says, in my code,
it's gone.
Someone erased it.
It sees that the reference
to that object is no longer there.
I have it in the state,
but it's on the cloud.
My actions are to erase that object.
If I, as a regular cloud user,
create a virtual machine,
Terraform will erase it.
It's not in the state.
It's not in the code either.
That's it.
Why is it done this way?
Whenever you click on the cloud,
a cascade of resources
can be automatically created.
You can't call the cloud
and say, give me all the resources
that exist inside.
That doesn't exist.
It would be totally unbearable.
That's what I wanted to ask you.
What does Terraform plan do?
Terraform plan does the following.
It takes a local code,
compares it to the state,
and calculates the diff.
Do I need to create objects?
Is nothing going to change?
Or do I need to erase things?
Implicitly, what does it do?
It also calls the cloud
and updates those objects
that are in the state.
That is,
if I add a label,
it will say,
let's do it again,
takes the code,
looks at the objects
that are in the state,
goes to all the objects
that are in the state on the cloud,
pulls the last state,
and then just compares
if the local state
and the code are the same.
If you add an object to the code,
it will add an object.
If you remove an object from the code,
it will say,
I will erase one object.
If you accidentally add a label
to the cloud provider for some reason,
you didn't change anything.
It will also say,
this is different,
one label is different.
Why am I explaining this?
It has a lot of implications
from the point of view
if someone hacks you
because of security.
If you have something in IAC,
you can chronologically run the plan
and see if there was a change.
If you have a state in the cloud,
a state that is written for you,
if a delta occurs
on the objects that are in provision,
it's cool that there is a change.
The security team
will probably say,
no, that's...
Kubernetes has auto-upgraded,
that's why this version diff
or U, what the hell is this payload?
It will make a lot of code
and then I will have a lot of questions.
I hope that people
are still listening.
In December, a lot of people
will be listening.
Next question, tricky.
Hey, Andraž,
we already have everything
installed on AWS or Azure.
We have everything installed on Azure.
It works great.
This is our production environment.
Now we would have
another environment,
a staging environment.
What can I do with Terraform?
What do I have to do first?
That's a great question.
It's very practical.
A lot of these tools,
including Terraform,
support what is called
importing.
You import things
and it doesn't work automatically
as someone might imagine,
but basically
it does the following.
You say,
I would like to import
a unique identifier
for a virtual machine,
and from the source object
it will import it.
It's a specific ID object
in the cloud.
What Terraform does is
it looks at the cloud
and imports it into its state.
Then it says,
and when the next
plan arrives,
it will say,
I deleted this virtual machine
and I have it in my state.
What you do is
you put this part into the code
and that's how the import happens.
When you run it again,
everything is fine,
it's in the code,
it's in the state,
but how do you force it
to call the cloud app
and import it into its state?
So there is an import
for Terraform.
If you have a production environment
in Azure,
you take Azure Terraform Provider,
you support Terraform import,
you will get a state,
you will see an email,
and then you can
move forward with Terraform.
So this use case is
completely normal.
This is a real use case,
because
typically,
from an engineering manager perspective,
you have people to train,
and then you say,
from now on,
all the things we do
will be described in the IAC tool,
for example, in Terraform.
You run this for a while,
and then you say,
we would now formalize
the things that are in Terraform.
What does this give you?
It gives you a chance
to spin up complex new environments.
Let's say you have production
and staging,
and you see you have so many people
on the team,
that you need one more environment,
because so many people depend on staging,
and on the other hand,
so many people break it,
because they do things,
and then you say,
maybe we need to rethink
if we want to have a two-tier
environment setup,
we need something else.
These are some of the things.
You know what?
In the teams
that use IAC,
or maybe in the Terraform world,
because this question
is not so relevant,
could it be the responsibility
of the engineers
to write Terraform definitions?
Could it be
the responsibility of DevOps?
Can you give a tip?
Who do you think
would benefit from Terraform?
Who writes Terraform?
Do you think
as many engineers
as possible could use Terraform,
and DevOps could supervise it?
How could the organization
include Terraform in the stack?
This is not just
a personal answer,
it depends on how you have
the teams in the organization.
You can't just
let the engineer do it.
I know it's not DevOps,
it's the infrastructure.
People are different
than developers.
If you have a small team,
give it a look.
If it helps you,
give it a try.
I'll start like this.
If you're a junior in DevOps,
and you don't have a team,
give it a try.
You write Terraform
and you say Terraform deploy,
or something like that.
Then you go to Cosillo,
when your wallet hurts so much
that you don't have cash,
you just say destroy,
and you go to Cosillo.
When it's destroyed,
in 20 seconds,
you say deploy,
and it will be back in 1 minute
and 50 seconds.
You won't click on all of these things
because the system will
just deploy.
And then you have a bill.
I get a bill
that is on
63 pages.
The total value of the bill
is 3 euros,
and every order is 1 cent.
Most of these offers
have pay-as-you-go.
It's a minimal time frame,
but
most of them have bizarre
accounts.
It makes it possible for me
to have minecraft
in the server,
and I call Terraform
and I use an S3 bucket
with a state node, and then I destroy it.
And it takes
a bit of planning to go to the fridge,
but
there can definitely be failures.
I don't know, but that's how it works.
And you don't have to pay for it.
How do we get out of this?
You know what?
I hope that people
are still interested
and that they still know.
Thank you for that.
I wanted to ask you
if Terraform is better
for development alone,
or is it a practice
that it's a part of the CI pipeline?
Maybe you could also
tell us
where Terraform
comes from.
That's a great question.
When you're alone,
will you be able
to run Terraform
from your PC,
and will the situation be local?
In that situation,
there's also locking happening.
If I want something,
there's a global lock,
which means that no one
else can do it.
It costs two people,
you can put the state file
on something that's S3 compatible,
and then everything will happen.
You can't synchronize
the two parts,
and you can do it locally.
Locally, you can create
all the objects,
which means that
everything will work well.
But in the end,
it's pretty fluid.
Specifically for Terraform,
you have Terraform Cloud,
and you have
0.0.0.0.0.0.0.0.0.0.
Which
stores
the state,
and locks it,
and executes everything.
Which means that
I send the definition
to Terraform Cloud,
and it will do it by itself.
It's even sexier.
You have a repo,
and you make a pull request
with some Terraform changes
and Terraform Cloud will come
or 1.0.0.0.
And the bot will tell you
Hey Delta,
I'll make a virtual
server,
write apply
to apply,
and if you're satisfied
with that Delta,
that Delta is also local,
it won't change,
there are some nuances.
The first apply will happen,
and then it will say,
this is now applied,
and then you close it.
The rest of the team
can help you,
because you can make it so
everyone can make changes,
make pull requests,
but only certain people
can say, hey Delta,
I'm going to apply,
and then you close it.
It also means that all the tokens
are in front of the vendor,
and the vendors
are also like,
so compliant, blah, blah, blah,
and then you have it all done.
The good thing is that
1.0.0.0.
1.0.0.1.
I keep forgetting.
Out.0 and 1.0.
It also has a free tier,
so if you want to play,
it's for
all of our
vendors, so
you register there,
and you can download
and play with it.
Now I'm going to
take you out for dinner,
and then we're going to sleep.
We're going to go
a little bit further,
and I'd like you to explain
where inside
there are the columns.
Yes.
Can you explain that?
We've been talking a lot about Terraform.
Yes.
We were in 1.0, and now we're in 6.0.
Explain it to me.
The tools that are focused on infrastructure
as code, you have
the ones that are purely static, like CloudFormation,
where you just write some YAML,
and it's applied, you have some templates there,
you have some dynamics,
then you have Terraform,
you use the language that is HashiConfigurationLanguage,
it's a very simple language.
That's how it is.
Is it more secure than YAML?
Yes, it is.
I also think it's more secure,
you don't need a safe depository.
I didn't choose that,
so I hope not.
That's always my statement.
But that's what it's all about.
You have simple objects,
and you can make simple loops,
and the string manipulates it,
because it's important.
It's very simple to learn.
You say,
I need all the power in the world,
that's why I'm so smart,
and I want to make declarative descriptions
of the infrastructure
with general purpose language,
like JavaScript, Go, whatever.
Now,
I would also like to have
another provider, Terraform,
if you want,
and you say, I only trust you
that I will make a for loop
that will make 12 virtuals,
God forbid you get confused
when one is missing,
or there are too many of them,
and you can also do that.
So that means
that in the for loop
I write the word Zanko,
and I say, make 12 virtuals,
and in the for loop
I will then do what with the code.
Will it make some definitions
in the back,
from the same source,
or will it call for each type?
That's how it works,
you have a program file,
and the for loop
generates an object
that is a context,
and that object travels
through your code,
and then it is inserted
into the function,
and those functions
are virtual,
dot,
I don't know,
a new virtual,
and now it can go into the loop,
you change the same name
with each loop,
and it travels through the code,
and in the end
you return the context,
and in the meantime
it executes it specifically
for your language,
and in the end
you get the context object,
and then all the resources
are loaded,
and then it's the same game again,
it's the same state,
in this state you can't run away,
it's quite simple,
and the calculation
of the delta happens again,
what exactly happens,
it's the same in CAS,
in CAS it's a div,
or a preview,
that tells you what it's going to do,
so you can see the div,
and it's an app
that applies directly to the system.
And where does
it come from?
When you think people will listen to it for a long time.
No, no.
Look,
you know,
I'm also not an expert
on some bugs in some jams
from people who found them,
so I'm still watching the documentary.
Damn it,
I feel like we have to start
with...
I feel like we need to talk about it until the end.
Let's wrap it up.
There are more than 1000 questions.
Let's talk about CDKs, Cloud Development Kits.
Yes.
Can I make it possible?
Pulumi supports a lot of languages
and has the same system of providers
that can work with larger clouds.
Of course, you will also have AWS
and CDKs.
You can also write AWS
in JavaScript.
Without Pulumi.
Yes.
You can define it in code.
You can define AWS
because AWS is old.
Let's say that
CloudFormation is not enough for you.
You want more dynamics.
It is the last step
when you can solve it.
Do you need this dynamics?
For example,
if you have a platform
that generates
full shops
dynamically
and then you want to generate
configuration from some settings
and then you have to loop
and generate definitions
so you can apply them.
Is this QSK?
Do you do large-scale deployment?
For example, we have a custom e-commerce platform.
We developed it.
It is single-tenant.
This means that
the system was developed
for one customer,
but now we have a million of them.
A sales engineer
or a door call
has a split screen
that says,
great, we have a new customer.
He has a plan.
This is his domain.
Let's say it is a very popular thing.
Maybe he has his own store
or he is deploying.
One of the things
is that it has to be part
of the DNS record in CloudFlare.
If you want to have
another class that is his domain,
it has to match the IP.
When all this happens,
you either tell the sales engineer
what to do
or send a feedback.
You can do this.
Another example is
that we have a complex system
with 60 microservices.
All these microservices
talk to each other
via PubSub.
Then there are topics and subscriptions.
How will you ensure
that this complex matrix
of PubSub and subscription
is connected to Google Cloud?
It is difficult.
Then you say,
here is a file from a microservice
and you say that this microservice
depends on this microservice
and listens to this subscription
and sends messages to this topic.
Then you select this
and you know what to generate.
This can be part of your library
and you can work
with one microservice or 100.
This is also a use case.
In practice,
this is a very good tool
to learn Cloud.
If you ask me.
Because it is difficult
to traverse
through a complex database
and test something.
It takes a lot of time.
I would learn Cloud three times
slower
and test some features
from suppliers
if I didn't use these tools.
Then I say,
I'm interested in Linode
and I call Linode provider
and how to combine it with Cloudflare
and I have the same interface.
Maybe the name is a little different
because I'm looking for a different product.
But it's all the same.
I don't have to go back and forth
and click up and down.
And you know,
let's say you have Cloudflare
and 12 DNS connections.
Everything works,
but you won't delete them.
I click on them and say apply
and then I delete them
when I play something.
I have to say something
explicitly.
You are talking about
the providers you choose
for Pulumni and Terraform.
If there are
these recipes
that people
make themselves
or their companies make
and for example
if I wanted to
make coffee
with Terraform
or with Pulumni
or whatever.
You can take those recipes
and use them,
you don't have to do it yourself.
How stable
and official are those recipes?
The companies
support the providers
themselves for these tools.
Google or
AWS team
provides
the provider
plugin
that is completely up-to-date
and that is also automatically generated.
It's not a one-time thing.
That's why
they are interested in
giving you the interface
so you can make cash.
Terraform
and Pulumni have a catalog
of all these providers.
Some are official
and most are Pulumni
plus providers.
Some are unofficial
and some are
community-based.
That's huge.
The documentation is standardized
and I think
it's easier
to look at the provider's documentation
and sometimes
click through
the dashboards.
You can't see the dashboard.
You know what the problem is?
You create a VPC
and you click on VPC
or project and it stops
asynchronously.
I'm working on something else and I see
it's ready and it's been 5 minutes.
Now I have Kubernetes
and I click on Kubernetes cluster
and it stops.
If I use this tool
it's asynchronous.
That's my dependency.
It also calculates the tree
and that's it.
I have a scary thought
about these toolings.
You can publish everything.
I wanted to say
when you go with
CDK or Terraform
when you loop
through some resources
for example
if you don't fuck up a token
it does a transaction.
You can't say
let's go back in time.
You can say
sorry, maybe
I didn't have enough credit on my credit card
or whatever
and it will cut you off
and you lost access permission.
There are still
some tools like that.
You can't say
this is checkpoint in time
and now I will lock it.
That's definitely
when you get a plan
we will do those things
like when you worked
on 23 virtual machines
you got a quota
and you have to send them
an email to increase the quota
and then it resolves automatically
and sometimes it doesn't
when it increases.
These are just
technological problems.
You can't solve
everything.
One thing is
you have to be prepared
what will happen
when you make a mistake.
In the end
if you make a mistake
let's say in staging
if the infrastructure
blocks all
colleagues working on the front end
it has a quick
impact on velocity.
You have to be prepared.
It's definitely not
like we will try it on staging.
No, no.
You have to play at home.
If you want to save some
amount of GPU on E20
let's do it with Terraform.
No, I mean
when you connect the machines
there won't be more
and you will pay 50 cents for that.
Then you can go
play with the kids
and come back.
These are just use cases.
You need one more
tool.
So Terraform
not Atlantis?
Atlantis is
an open source version
of Terraform Cloud
and NVZero.
That means you can
on your server
enter the keys
and it will do the evaluations
and it's a GitHub bot.
These are the same things.
It looks at the repositories
when it sees who is doing Terraform changes
it takes the code
and divs it
and then in GitHub
it will tell you
what will be changed.
The good thing is
that it's self-hosted
and it works well.
Although
this Terraform-specific server
doesn't really
fit in the
pool of requests.
There is documentation
on this topic.
But
you need to research
and test.
Two more hours and you can go.
Here
we don't have
as much preparation as in the episode
but I will tell you more.
You said that.
One hour and ten minutes
and then we talked for another hour.
That's why you live
with these tasks.
I will
explain Tomi
and then we will
draw a picture
for the clouds.
What is crossplane?
You wrote it yourself at the end
but it's so sexy and sci-fi
that
you have to explain it.
Ok, but I will
explain it for a long time.
I really have to go.
No!
We were once
at IBM
mainframe.
Applications were deployed
in such a way that it was
very similar to
modern orchestrators like
Kubernetes. You said
this is an app, these are parameters of the app.
There was a dashboard, you wrote
a note to the staff and then the mainframe
said this is an app.
This is now deployed
and maybe it has high availability.
I don't know. I didn't work with it.
It was expensive.
It's not something you have at home.
I worked in research
and that's it.
How does Kubernetes work?
It works like this.
You have Kubernetes
which is not self-hosted, it's in the cloud.
It's managed.
When you
type
kubectl apply
you want to
have a container running.
Whatever happens
a JSON is sent
to the Kubernetes app.
Kubernetes saves
its store.
It looks
at the object.
It's just an object. It has a version
and a type of object and parameters
and then it calculates
how it will make it happen.
It will make a pod
that will run in a container
like an engineering slave.
Great.
And then
what people have done
is you can
have versions
and types in Kubernetes
like pod, service, deployment
stateful set, daemon set
These are built-in objects.
The schema is
built-in and
every Kubernetes has it.
What you can do is
custom
definition of these resources.
You can also
have an auto
version of one object
type
I don't know
podcast episode
For example, podcast episode.
When you put it in
Kubernetes doesn't know
what to do with it because
it doesn't have a
program
so it doesn't know
when it comes to Kubernetes
it will pick it up and do something.
If you want to, you can write
something called operator.
Operators listen
to changes in specific types
of objects
and you can write
auto operator and when you
put it in podcast, it will
pick it up and then
it will start to create
objects on Kubernetes
or it can do anything
it can order a pizza
depending on the conditions
of the operator.
What is a cross-plane?
You have a Kubernetes cluster
you install a cross-plane
operator
inside it
you want to have an
AVS provider, these are the keys
so the provider can work
and then you can
write in java
for example EC2
virtual code
Kubernetes apply
and the object goes to Kubernetes
because the cross-plane
operator
got the message
one object has changed
and it looks at you and says
oh yeah, someone
wants to have
EC2 virtual code
or some changes to
one of the
AVS services
and then as a program
it gets the secrets
that you put in the configuration
and
creates it in
this cluster
so you can with Kubernetes
provision
all the providers
in the cloud you have.
But maybe
it doesn't sound
like a far-fetched idea
but it's just
a slim layer of technology
that we described before.
But on a very similar
project if you run Kafka
you have this Kafka Streams
and it's a Kafka
operator for Kubernetes
and first you install this operator
then you say
Kubernetes wants to have a new Kafka topic
wants to have a new Kafka broker
and then this operator
inside Kubernetes will create
an object and if it works
for managing Kafka
or Cassandra or whatever
the same concept will work for managing
the cloud and that's the
overlap that Crossplane
provides. The selling point is
when you put a lot of cash
and depict a team in Kubernetes
because it's a very complex system
then it's logical
that it's also connected
so it can still work with it.
I think
it's a very interesting concept
I haven't
tested it
I watched a lot of demos
and I understand how it works
from scratch because in the end
it's just a slim layer
of existing tooling
but yeah, it's really sci-fi.
Andras, last thoughts.
Last thoughts.
Did you know that there's
AWS Snowmobile?
AWS sends disk drives
so you can upload data to S3
it's something like that
and there's also
AWS Ground Station
so you can hire a ground station
for your satellites
AWS has it
yeah, you have satellites
and robotics
you can look at the product. Very interesting.
These are really
your last thoughts.
What do you think about this last thought?
Thank you because you didn't go
too deep into technology
but you went very high.
Yeah, yeah.
That's good, that's good.
Let's try these things
everyone who's interested
in infrastructure
go and create an account
on Linode, Vultr
DigitalOcean
and play around
with Pulumi, Terraform
and real Baobab
and something new
and play around
with it
and definitely
it will help you
a lot
and maybe also for your project.
That's great.
Andras,
thank you so much
for taking the time
to talk to us.
Thank you.
I will be very happy
if you give us
feedback on this episode
if you tell us what we forgot to say
if you tell us
how we can
continue this work.
I assume there are a lot of topics
that are related
so if we didn't start today
every feedback is very welcome
share it with your colleagues and friends
and yeah
Thank you very much, Andras.
Thank you.