Hello, this is the 6th episode of the podcast in Grodje.
Today with me is Dr. Mateja Berlič-Brunčič,
that's him from the park, if I'm not mistaken.
Yes, thank you.
And today we are in a completely new space on the tour,
which is a bit different from our co-working in Ljubljana,
where we didn't have that before.
So, there will be some background noise,
so that you can hear me better.
Yes, that's it.
I wrote some notes,
and I would like to give you an opportunity to introduce yourself,
what you are doing at the moment,
and then we will go deeper.
Okay.
As you said, my name is Mateja.
For some time now,
for 15 years, I have been present at the Split as Sparkyca,
so since the times of Kornka,
the Slovenian version of Twitter,
and blogospheres and blogs and stuff like that.
Where do I start now?
I would like to change the world of engineering,
make it perhaps more modern, different,
even in our Slovenian space.
So, I am trying to talk and cooperate here,
and show, perhaps, how it can be done differently.
The topics that interest me are everything from engineering,
technology itself, to people, a lot of people,
leadership, management, you name it.
Yesterday was also the conclusion of the Maribor conference,
which is a fork of five hours,
which started in Ljubljana,
but then was prepared by a team from Maribor.
And yesterday was the conclusion of another successful season,
which ended with the transfer from the blockchain,
and with a change in the blockchain,
but it also worked nicely.
I would like to tell you a little bit about my experience with five hours.
I saw that you were very active in the discussions that you had,
and then you started some video streams.
I see that you were also very active there.
What is your experience with five hours?
I believe in satisfaction,
and satisfaction is something that fills me with energy,
and with that, five hours is magic.
It seems to me that I come home very hyped,
I don't know what else to do.
Now, to be honest, I have been preparing for a long time.
Today, when I was still thinking about sports,
because at that time I was still healthy,
and that respect is part of the team Iko Lajsa,
with whom I worked, and he was my student.
We are somehow connected,
and through them I followed and supported the return of knowledge to the community,
because we all know that the community matters,
we need to get to know each other, we need to help each other,
whether from a professional point of view or a personal point of view,
so that we can raise the level or quality of our professional work,
or if we change experiences, we drink a cocktail, and so on.
Now, in practice, I expressed a desire to participate in the Split Games,
because it is cool for me.
I am an introvert, of course, I learned how to be an extrovert,
because it is cool for me to meet people,
to get to know them, to spread the knowledge, experience,
and to connect people.
And there was a time when we needed a moderator,
because we were connected to Erne and others,
and we have been doing this for about a year now,
every season, and then the corona came,
and so there are always some challenges,
how to get people to come,
because everyone thinks that there is nothing to say,
until you invite them,
and then you see that they are very interesting,
they have a lot of things to say.
So, also from that perspective,
I think it's nice that I'm here,
I have a lot of connections,
and I know a lot of people in the IT sphere,
I can inspire a lot of people to come and share.
But with the corona, we said,
shit, we can't do this live,
what do we want to do?
And we decided to do a live stream.
Now, we have been recording for hours before,
but we were in a dilemma,
whether to stream it,
and support a lot of people,
so that they don't come live,
or, yes,
and the corona didn't give us a choice.
It just seems to me,
I don't know,
I was a viewer,
and I also participated in some of your discussions,
but I have a feeling that more people,
in some way,
could join because you started streaming.
For sure.
Maybe some other people,
if we didn't come,
they still participated.
It's definitely easier to come home as a guest,
I think it's even easier now,
in these years,
we have a family connection,
and there is a lot of logistics,
if you want to come from point A to point B,
to 7 and 5,
and then home.
I agree,
maybe it was our core value,
networking,
bonding live,
maybe that's why we didn't want to.
I agree,
we are definitely motivated today,
it's more convenient,
more natural for us.
Let's discuss
how to attract
a larger population
to meetups,
what are you doing?
I'm active,
I'm recruiting.
Recruiting for Split Nemurice,
and part of my job
was hiring or recruiting,
and through
getting to know people,
I attracted them to Split Nemurice,
even though we weren't perfect fit,
I liked that they knew
that something was going on in Maribor,
and I attracted them to Split Nemurice,
either as a teacher,
or to come and listen,
or to find out that something is going on.
I mean, it's nothing,
people themselves won't come.
When you make a product,
you talk to the devil.
With all these impulses,
it's hard to be
on top of things.
Yes,
I mean, in front of this stage...
You know.
I'm also interested
in quality production
in Split Nemurice Maribor,
I think that's something
that stands out from others.
Streaming on two platforms,
then CGP,
graphic design,
I think that's top-notch.
The story of Peljana Skozna
is really top-notch,
with CGP, top-notch production.
I would like to thank you,
because those who do it,
research it,
maybe you experienced it
as an experiment,
because you have to know
that we are professionals,
there's no money involved,
it's our money involved,
and then you look
where you can make
a lot of Split Nemurice,
so that it becomes,
not only Split Nemurice Maribor,
but also Split Nemurice Slovenska,
which is also in Ljubljana,
in Zajevac.
If we change it.
If we change it, definitely.
It will stand.
Well,
I can start the debate
in a different direction,
when you say that you meet
a lot of people at these events,
a lot of new people,
a lot of new topics,
new technologies.
Yesterday I met
three students,
two from Fria,
one from Tojini,
and I will try
to connect this topic,
and then there was a debate
about ending Fax.
And you are
a PhD student in computer science,
so I will give you
a piece of advice.
I will try to connect this topic,
and I will say that
those students yesterday
were like,
yes, you know,
I would like to work with theory,
and we are grinding here,
and we are not interested,
and it would be more interesting
to start working,
and someone would say,
oh, I will not finish summer school.
But you went all the way,
and I said,
ok, I will try from my perspective,
and I would like to know
what you would like to do.
I said that I went to study,
because I did not know what to do.
I mean,
my background is from high school,
and I am interested in Mars,
and it was at home,
here, as you can see,
it was like,
if you do not come to the end,
there is always a call.
And you will not have to work?
No, I did not bring a lot of work
to my family,
but it was like,
no, I want to be something.
I do not know yet what,
but I want something,
and then I went to high school
to get a little wider.
So I started at four years old,
I said, ok, I am interested in technology,
and then art.
And now what to do with it?
And then I got a little insight,
to see how it would be,
because at that time,
in my crazy head,
in high school,
I imagined that I would do advertising,
digital animation,
and I would combine technology and art,
and I do not know,
but there were a lot of theories,
and there was a lot of mathematics,
I also experienced physics,
which I like a little,
but not physics.
Yes, you have to grind,
and then you think,
why do I have six mathematics here,
and some curved integrals,
and all those eggs.
Now, when I look back,
I see,
FACS gave me
some tools,
and a way of thinking,
which I can now apply.
Not so much practical things,
at FACS you can not learn to program
production,
but you can learn
a little bit of science,
a little bit of scientific thinking,
you need to put some hypothesis,
how can you verify
this hypothesis,
or verify it.
And from that insight,
it seems to me,
it gave me
a way to find myself,
I would say.
But then,
at the end of that
post-graduate work,
I did not know what to do,
because at that time there were only two companies,
so I knew,
one was Hermes Softlab,
and the other was something else.
Anyway, I did not feel there,
and the opportunity came,
a young researcher,
and I said, yes, I can do it,
I will come back, I will be a researcher,
because it is cool.
But that experience was not so good.
It depends a lot on a young researcher,
on the laboratory
in which he joins,
on the mentor, how much time he has,
on the whole setup,
on the time,
maybe for me it was
not a very good time
to be a young researcher,
and then two years as an assistant.
But I got a lesson
that I am not for this world.
Although I managed to finish the thing,
if nothing else,
I did not finish it.
So from this point of view,
I think it is an accomplishment,
and this PhD is also a joker,
so usually
I do not give up,
but if someone
approaches me,
if someone treats me
as a douchebag,
and tries to put people
in some transition,
they will call me a joker.
But that's just my opinion,
I do not judge people
on paper, people are all different.
Now,
many times students ask me
what am I going to do in the master's,
why am I doing a PhD,
and I tell them,
go do it if you know why you are doing it.
Because yes, grinding is not good,
and if you see a hole at the end of the tunnel,
and you know it is there,
why is it there,
you will not have a problem.
If you want to get a paper
and you want to connect
with mentors,
because you have great mentors,
and great lectures,
just do it.
If you like the academic sphere,
which is a bit special,
just do it.
If you do not know why you are doing it,
then don't do it.
Let's go back a bit,
do you think
that you have,
when you see other
technical managers,
do you think that you have
some of those skills
that you acquired
through the academic world,
which maybe otherwise would not have?
Do you see that people
worked hard,
and maybe if you went through it again,
it would be easier?
What do you think,
what can you use as a manager,
a technical manager?
First of all, abstract thinking,
how to make something
out of some specific things,
then look at it more abstractly,
then draw something,
then think about it,
and maybe connect different areas,
because they are connected,
some patterns,
I definitely see it as a problem.
Then maybe when I went through
this research cycle,
in a way,
these cycles,
you look at what you have to do,
how to check it as soon as possible,
because everything we do
is individual,
even if something happens in production,
something goes wrong,
it is our own fault.
Such things,
such scientific principles,
solving problems,
breaking down problems,
writing documentation.
Come on!
Also, sketching,
the way you imagine people,
do you think it is easier?
Yes,
especially when you learn
to imagine things in a structured way,
maybe write it as an article,
because documentation is also
like an article,
to imagine a subject to someone else,
to imagine a problem,
because someone who is not in our field
probably does not know all the details,
but the problem you extract from it
is easy to put together.
When I was in Maribor,
honestly,
I am 6 years old,
when I was in Maribor,
we went to my grandmother,
I will record this podcast,
I think she had
a lot of discussions,
I talked to the doctor
about computers,
what would she ask,
if she is interested in computers,
and then at the end
we listened to Kingston
the whole time,
and we listened to Kingston,
and when I tried to turn it on,
we were 5 in the morning,
and I said,
you are crazy,
so from this field
I have some,
I expected to have
more intelligent questions,
but I will go back to
Codecats, because it seems
very interesting to me,
and then I will go to
Demi, tell me,
you put a lot of effort
into Codecats,
and you tried to
inspire young people
to go into
the technical waters,
how do you see this,
how do we attract
young people,
or how do we inspire them
to follow the path
in technology,
when you yourself
have a lot of work,
and it seems to you
that we have to let them
go their own way,
and they are lost,
and it seems to you
that it would be better
to introduce them
to the tech space,
to have different jobs,
to have developers,
to have project managers,
and it seems to you
that they could start
with Codecats.
Yes, that's a good start.
I know how it was for me
when I signed up for the
computer science course,
and I didn't have a good basis.
I said, ok, I will survive
the first year, and if I get
an A, I'm good.
The second year was ok,
if I repeat the first year,
I'm good.
It's not that hard,
and I'm doing great.
Maybe, I mean,
for girls, I know better,
all the girls are the same,
you need a bit more motivation,
it's ok, you can fail,
you don't have the power to just
realize what's going to happen.
We were getting questions,
why are you doing workshops
only for girls?
Codecats was created
and was created with the help
of Alja Isakovic,
she was driving it,
and we realized
that we need
a safe haven.
Girls like it,
maybe we just think
that someone is judging us,
judging us,
and you don't know anything.
And we showed
the proof in the end
that if girls are together,
they feel safer,
they experiment a bit,
they don't feel stupid.
And we inspired them
to come and try
something that was
totally out of comfort zone.
Even if they copied
some code,
it's not that bad.
There are some obstacles,
but it's possible.
And after the workshops,
people asked
what to do next,
and we said
let's do some
meetups,
we are both in technology,
let's do some work together,
learn to program,
and we chose Python,
which was easy, interesting.
And we got some time
on a weekly basis,
we had cohorts,
it's true that
all the ideas
are heard very well,
until you have to commit.
And today,
you need time, energy,
and you have to overcome
the first obstacles
when you have to solve
a bigger problem,
when you have to debug
something for 3 hours.
And then the girls
were like,
today I can't do this,
today I can't do that.
And then we had a group
and each group went to
a new Python installation.
We asked each other
to help us install Python
in each new group.
And in the last group,
we decided to do a project,
which started
in Code Week.
And we decided
to make an app
for
events
that will happen
in Code Week.
A real project.
No money involved.
Again,
I said that
it was a big responsibility
for the beginners.
For example,
Erika Pogorilac joined
and then Goran Blažič.
We were a bit more
experienced,
but others,
who were newbies,
were a bit behind.
But it was our successful project.
I don't know if it's still alive
or if it was replaced by others.
But we saw that
if you work with girls
in a different way,
and if they feel good...
You can help them,
you can make
a safe...
Safe for them, yes.
A safe
social environment
and give them your experience.
For me,
it's a stupid question.
If you ask me three times,
I'll answer you three times.
That's how we reduced
the barrier.
A few girls saw
that it's possible
to work with more technical companies.
I think Google
is a good scholarship.
For me,
if we converted one,
we did something.
I understand.
It's true that we
told the girls
that it's not about
learning how to program
and being a programmer.
Things are a bit more complex.
It takes time and effort
to become an engineer
or a developer.
Let me ask you.
The purpose
of the projects
you mentioned
was to teach programming
or to show people
what's going on
in the development of technical products.
I think
a lot of people
will try to program
and realize that
programming is not for them
and that project management
is more for them
and they'll find a way to do it.
Do you think this approach
will benefit the industry?
I'm sure it will.
There are a lot of stereotypes.
A developer sits in a room
with two monitors
and doesn't know what's going on.
No.
We've been to a lot of companies
and talked about it.
It's not a sole purpose.
Teaching someone
how to program
takes a lot of time.
I have to work from home
and share tutorials.
It's not a follow-up.
Life happens.
If you're not committed
and don't have a drive,
you can't do it.
On the other hand,
we've shown that
you don't have to
ask your colleagues
to understand
what they're talking about.
We had designers
and project managers in the group.
Maybe they found
a common language in the company.
OK.
I have another question.
How will the culture
of engineering
in Slovenia change?
How do you feel
as the Director of Engineering
at Databox?
Can we talk about that?
Of course.
We'll change it by one percent.
It's a topic
that I talk about
in various companies.
First of all,
it's not about the staff.
It's not about the staff.
Then you break it down
and you realize that
the staff is important.
Today, staff is
people.
People need
a good education.
They need to be comfortable,
they need to be educated,
they need to have a culture.
and a lot of things that triggered you to come to this company, for example.
And one of the things I see coming up again and again is that people say,
yes, this company has some good engineers, it has some interesting product,
but it doesn't have some technical management at the level that it could grow,
that it could have some breakthroughs, that it could have some talent again.
And I would like to hear from you how this is going to happen.
If I tell you how it's going to change, the easiest way is to hire all the people
who would like to change, because change comes from within.
You can change on LinkedIn, you can like as much as you want,
but if you don't apply to the company, it's futile.
We can do that, we can open to work, I don't know if my boss would be happy.
Otherwise, I think, as you said, it has to come from within.
People need to grow, they need to find ambassadors, allies,
and they also have to push back on their own in some way in management.
It's much easier if you live with a new company,
in such a way of thinking, to make sure that people are assets,
that you have to work with them, on them,
that you don't have to play chess with them,
and just pass them the ball as you like in the end.
It's important how they feel, how they feel used,
how much value they bring, how they feel heard,
and how much feedback they get, because we all get feedback,
we all have some nice PGs, sweet things, good things.
And, for example, what I saw on the database,
the meetings are weekly, one-on-one.
Well, if we take 15 minutes, it's not an operation,
but I talk to my engineers about what's cool in our relationship,
what's cool in the way we work, what's cool in working with others,
what's cool and not cool in communication with the inside team,
or with the outside team, and if you do that on a weekly basis,
something is accepted.
And then, when you group a team, they can move it forward,
or, in fact, when new people come in, they group them forward,
and that's how culture moves forward.
The other thing I talk about a lot is radical candor.
And I live for that, because you're, let's say,
nothing, nowhere is perfect,
and it's true that you can express,
that you're a dissenter, that you express a different opinion,
that that opinion is heard,
I don't have the brain to respect it,
I don't have the brain to look at the table,
and look at the different patterns, at the problem,
because I don't know the specific patterns.
If you have a company, let's say, a banal example,
if you have a company that is 99.9% male engineers,
you will describe everything in the documentation,
he does that, he does that,
where are we going, and so on.
And I say, I'm just a guy,
we're not just guys, let's say.
So that others can feel included,
so that they have everything in mind,
so that no one else exists.
Then, for example, one thing that I try to emphasize
is that we are all one company,
because there is a natural tendency to become a camp.
Oh, that's sales, that's marketing.
But each of us has his own piece of puzzle
that he has to contribute to the whole picture.
And if we draw some kind of empathy from other teams,
then we will understand that we have an image,
we need a name and an email that we get,
so that we understand that they have a slightly different payment,
and that they are not fools if they don't know how to speak our language,
because we don't know their language.
And let's say we don't use some patterns,
I wrote a lot about that,
because we are them, we are all us.
But I think we should do everything from the inside,
and then take management to a certain level for that.
The table is huge.
And it will be a bit similar,
because I practiced one-on-one for two weeks,
and one lesson.
But yes, it is mental effort.
But to sit with an engineer and debate not only
his current technical challenges,
but also how he will grow in his career,
how he will grow within the company,
how he can do some side projects
that will benefit his career and the company.
That's a lot of effort to put in,
but these are long-term investments.
You really hear about those one-on-ones,
everything from hatching to adopted cats.
But it all depends on them.
Yes, yes, it depends on them.
Adopted cats.
Yes, but that's part of life,
but also growth and death.
That's part of life.
I think it pays off,
because you have to put in some effort,
and if you work slowly,
then you don't need hours.
Sometimes you can solve things faster.
But yes, when things don't go smoothly,
and it happens that things don't go smoothly,
then there is some capital that you can invest in some way.
Absolutely.
And you get to know people,
you understand each other,
and it pays off.
That's what I recommend.
Can we go to a related topic now?
I think we started a bit, but okay.
Now you know that you have management of your peers,
which means that you manage people on your level,
and communicate with people on your level,
that is, with others, directors, managers.
Then you have downwards management,
that is, how you manage your subordinates.
Then you have upper management,
that is, how you communicate with your superiors.
I think we touched on the middle,
and I'm very interested in how you communicate on the top.
If you have a very good drawing,
then if the management doesn't see it for you,
but they know about it,
then it's not worth it.
I'm interested in your experience with upwards management.
It's great if the company supports
the increase of visibility of what the team is doing.
Specifically, we have weekly meetings on the database.
Who would have thought,
I don't know, an hour and a half.
That's a waste of time.
But it's not.
We recommend some key things within the team.
For example, an operation, progress of the project,
if there are any problems,
and also the human side,
who we might need now,
or how we relate to the team,
or we praise someone in the team.
So, for example,
upwards management gets visibility of what's going on,
and who has worked a little harder this week,
and who needs to be highly praised.
We've already had debates,
would you still have this meeting?
Would you still have it?
Because in the beginning,
you can do everything asynchronously.
When we post these things in Slack,
then you can check everything,
and we conclude.
If you can check everything,
you checked everything today.
That's one thing.
If you check everything today,
it works asynchronously.
But we found value in sitting together,
at the beginning,
for five minutes,
to discuss,
to fly over,
and then we debate questions.
And then we have such debates,
also at the leadership level.
That is,
how is the team now,
with which other team,
or where are some trainings,
or where do we need to help,
or what do we need to do as a team,
as some directors,
so that, I don't know,
we will be treated differently,
or what do we need to introduce,
or what do we need to support.
So, this kind of bonding,
at the weekly level,
is a part of the upper,
I mean,
management level.
Then we also have a weekly one-on-one,
for example,
with the founder,
or with the VP.
So,
it's not just an operative,
but today we also talk about,
for example,
if I have a challenge,
or I get feedback,
where my supervisor sees that I have a challenge,
or if it's just me,
then I remember that your team is working.
So, I get feedback,
that I need to support,
so that the visibility will be better.
Anyway,
this is how it works with us,
one-on-one,
up,
and actually down.
Then,
one of the things,
maybe we are a bit specific,
is that we are distributed.
So,
we have teams in America,
then we have teams,
if they can dance,
then we have a team here in Aptoide.
Now,
let's say that we are a bubble,
we don't care,
honey badger don't care,
we also have weekly meetings with them,
and it was like,
what did we talk about?
I mean,
what are the connections?
Yes.
And we noticed that,
even if we only see each other,
and at the beginning,
I don't know,
after 50 minutes,
we chat,
aha,
Bjeli will get a baby,
ah,
Tori,
and she went for a ride,
it also brings us a little closer,
and again,
we have some kind of growth,
to the mail,
to the task,
and it seems to me,
this is very important.
If we had been a scan slide for the first time,
we would have given it,
we could have talked even more.
And this,
this is not a waste of time,
you can't solve it with the mail,
and you can't solve it with a picture.
It would be much better anyway,
and I feel alive somehow,
but you have to maintain some kind of relationship,
for it to work.
Wow.
No,
good, good.
It's an effort,
yes,
no,
it's not the time yet,
but yes.
Yes,
so,
we established,
that you build culture from the inside,
we called ourselves,
Upward Upward Management.
Wait,
one more thing,
culture,
not that you build culture,
no,
we will now,
yes,
we will continue,
this is a topic,
we will try,
ah,
how do you see,
ok,
when you grow up,
you will need to increase,
manpower,
which you have at your disposal,
to expand the team,
everything can be increased,
which is some kind of a natural process,
how do you see,
how will you,
or how will you deal with it,
how will those patterns or culture,
which is happening,
this debate,
these relationships,
day-to-day activity,
and when you grow up,
when there will be more people,
because,
when the meeting would be one and a half hours,
if everyone came to it,
it would be a three-hour meeting,
how do you see this,
the scaling of these relationships,
and some cultures,
which come from it,
how do you deal with it,
how do you see it?
I don't know,
but I will be interested.
this is a challenge.
Will there be two meetings?
Yes,
it is,
it seems to me that these are some kind of natural processes,
bigger than all those,
yes,
bigger challenges.
Now,
you know,
when there are five people in the same room,
everything changes,
it is a natural state,
you don't have to work outside.
When you are older,
you can maybe
a little enforce
this communication,
these meetings,
these,
I don't know,
we have once a week,
all the teams together in the same room,
for example,
even a 15-minute sync.
Part of this magic of culture
is certainly lost,
because,
in my opinion,
I think,
as I saw,
like the previous company,
is that there may also be some subcultures,
we had a company where,
in general,
the company may not have had such a good culture,
but part of the team,
which was also location-oriented,
and when we were maybe
such people,
who were on the line,
and then we had some
negative feedback,
we built a subculture,
it is called
a subculture of respect,
challenging each other,
discovering each other,
one-on-one,
but it was not something
for the process,
prescribed by the company.
I have no answer.
For more,
it should be,
fuck,
this is a challenge.
I still have one
hypothesis,
a theory,
and with that I make
The Fork,
and I think that
in development,
in engineering,
you start,
let's say that
most people start
a student job,
or a junior developer,
a mid-developer,
a developer engineer,
and then a senior,
and then there is a moment
when you have to decide
whether you will be
a developer in the future,
or you will go
to a management position,
and I am surprised
that you were on
The Fork
at some point,
and then you decided
to go to management,
role management,
and that means
that now you are
more or less
only dealing with technology.
How do you see The Fork?
I am a manager
during the day,
and a developer at night.
I would not say
that I was on The Fork,
because I never felt
like a top-sheet
A-player developer.
I always had
this imposter syndrome.
But it seems to me
that my power
or my strength
is the bond of people.
Recognizing
some potential,
motivating,
challenging,
taking a lot,
it seems to me
that if I have
this empathy,
it can help me
on the management track.
And it seems to me
that I can contribute
even more.
So, really,
I never had
dilemmas
about where to go.
It is true that
in my life,
I said to myself
that I do not want
to be at the driver's seat,
I do not want to drive.
I have a certain ambition,
there are things
I would like to do,
and I know
that I can do it
only when I have
some decision power.
And I am very happy
to come to the point
where I can help
create everything,
some things,
because it seems to me
that what I am talking about
is important.
And I am happy
against those
who only look
at the numbers,
only at productivity,
and it seems to me
that I can balance
that human side
in engineering.
For example,
one such lesson
was given to me
by FACS.
When I got the feeling
that computers,
however they are called,
think for themselves.
A computer exists
because it exists,
because it is.
But if you look a little,
you step back a little,
you realize that a computer
is a support.
Today we support
all kinds of ideas.
We are the ones
who do it
because this idea
comes to life
and today it works.
We didn't do it
just for ourselves.
And that gave me
such a mindset
that in all companies
that we are,
even if it is an IT company,
it should be known
that we are the ones
who actually enable it.
We are not there
because we are different.
If there was an institution
that would deal with it
today,
to make a top sheet
of development,
for example,
we remained a support.
I would like to add
that today
you see IT
more as a
neighbor.
Yes, as a neighbor.
This is also
an interesting topic
because today
you see
that all companies
are tech companies
in a way.
Technology plays
an important role.
Some companies
openly support it,
acknowledge it,
focus on it,
facilitate awareness,
focus,
debate, etc.
Others don't.
And there you have
a lot of problems.
I mean,
today I imagine
that everything is
a tech company
where technology
is at the forefront
more than probably
some other companies.
But I think
I know what you mean.
Yes, no, hold on.
We are working
on the main level
of technology.
We want to do
stable things.
Of course,
we want to
work for a few years.
But we are not
satisfied.
Yes, we have
a top-notch
software,
but we don't
have a user.
Yes, I understand.
That's what I mean.
It means
that we need
to add
a user
in the account
who can
solve
any problem.
We are all
in business
to solve
a problem,
not just
to solve
a problem.
My own
institutions
where people
work
are good
because they
are easy
to research,
because they
develop
new solutions,
break through
walls.
There are
such companies,
but I
haven't worked
in such
companies.
I think
we need
to prevent
becoming
douchebags
and saying
yes, yes,
you are
a douchebag,
because
you are
a douchebag.
Let me
start
with another
topic.
I think
we have
changed
the comment
on LinkedIn
a lot,
but Dazabox
is
a company
that is
more than
10 years
old,
if I'm not
mistaken.
It holds.
It is
a company
that has
accumulated
technical
debt.
It is
a company
that has
accumulated
technical debt.
It is
a company
that has
accumulated
technical debt.
It is
a company
that has
accumulated
technical debt.
I'm
curious
how much
you invest
in your
job
with that.
How do
you solve
the problem
of technical
debt?
I can
answer.
Definitely
there is
technical
debt.
Now
maybe it's
not so
critical
that if we
don't
solve it
at this
moment,
the company
will close
permanently,
because
everyone
has a
house
and a
car.
We
are aware
of that.
Management
is aware
that
we have
engineers
that are
my sparring
partners and
I expect
from them
that when
they come
from the
product side
and say
hey guys
I'm working
on this
feature,
that they
stop
the over
my dead
body,
because
we need
to explain
that first
because
we are
working
on
that.
We
need to
evaluate
ourselves
when
it's
necessary
and
when
it's
not.
How
to say
no,
how
to say
yes,
or
no,
now
we
need to
solve
it.
I
think
we
have
backlogs.
We have
backlogs
and
I'm very
proud that
the
whole
management
supported
including
the
stability
year.
The
whole
year
all
the
engineering
teams
were
working
on
stability
projects.
That
means
if
you
cannot
go
to
a
project,
you
cannot
work
on your
own.
So
that
was
the
first
project
and
I
think
it was
one of
the
most
important
projects
of
the
year,
and
I
think
it was
one of
the
most
important
projects
of the
year.
So
that was
the
first
project
and
I
think
it was
one of
the most
important
projects
of the
year.
So
that was
the
first
project
and
I
think
it was
one of
the most
important
projects
of the
year.
So
that was
the
first
project
and
I
think
it was
one of
the most
important
projects
of the
year.
So
that was
the
first
project
and
I
think
it was
one of
the most
important
projects
of the
year.
So
that was
the
first
project
and
I
think
it was
one of
the most
important
projects
of the
year.
So
that was
one of
the most
important
projects
of the
year.
So
that was
the first
project
and
I
think
it was
one of
the most
important
projects
of the
year.
So
that was
the first
project
and
I
think
it was
one of
the
most
important
projects
of the
year.
So
that
was
the second
project
and
I
think
that
was
the
most
important
project
of the
year.
So
that
was
the
second
project
and
I
think
that
was
the
most
important
project
of the
year.
So
that
was
the
second
project
of the
year.
So
that
was
the
second
project
of the
year.
So
that was
the
second
project
of the
year.
They need to know that it's not just hype, cutting-edge technology and that there is still something behind it.
It's also a learning experience for them.
It's a moment for them, and it's a moment for both of them.
Together with this event, they have a better start.
That's how I see it.
Okay, now I'm done with the cards.
Now, if you want to say something to the audience, this is the moment.
Yes, I would say, be worthy of your name and profession,
work with your father and come to his podcast.
Thank you very much.
Thank you, Mateja, once again for your time and good luck with the launch of this technological park.
I would like to give the audience some feedback so that we can further improve this format and podcast.
Thank you.