We have a new SD card, which donated a lot to us today, so we have how much more?
46 hours, we can talk about Javascript today, in the broadest sense, to the most special sense,
we can debate back and front, we can get closer to the beginners, we can go to the executive decisions,
which invest millions in Javascript.
Today we have with us Clement Kugovšek and Andraž Brodnik, and today we will talk about Javascript.
Now, you will just try to introduce yourself, you will tell us what you are doing, so people can get the feeling.
I am Clement, I work for the company Kterinaj37, I work with everything that drives Javascript,
and all the environments where Javascript flows.
So, my decisions have changed a lot, so I am trying to support Javascript somewhere else.
So, you are not identifying as a front-end developer, or a back-end developer, you are identifying as a Javascript developer.
Yes, you could say that. Full stack can be a very problematic expression, because people start to assume that you work with hardware,
but you are also a developer, so you could say that.
Amazing.
I was also thinking about how to include the debate in some aspects of Javascript,
where everyone knows each other, everyone is happy with it.
I mean, today it is hard not to know what Javascript is, if you are doing anything, as I imagine it.
We will try to include this debate in some aspects, we will try to start with some basics,
then we will go a bit more front-end, a bit more back-end, we will jump a bit into the mix,
and then we will find some interesting topics for everyone.
I was thinking about what kind of questions we can ask, and my question is,
if Javascript was religion, what kind of religion would Javascript be for you?
For me, it would be Czechoslovak Zombie Church.
Czechoslovak Zombie Church.
And is it friendly?
No, Javascript is a bit more like C.
I mean, you have a pointer, right?
Most of the time it is a pointer.
I mean, that's how it is.
I mean, that's how it is friendly.
Well, at least there are some of them here.
I have a computer at home that programs Javascript,
and unlike other microcontrollers that I have used,
you can also upload code from any browser via Bluetooth.
So, unlike some AVRs, you don't need an SPI connector or an adapter or anything like that.
Let's go back to the question.
Let's go back.
How did you come to Javascript?
Why Javascript?
How? Why?
I think I started with something else.
I started with .NET, PHP and C.
And then Javascript was the thing that gave me the first cry.
Honestly.
But later I saw that it could be a very good tool,
with some advantages, including in a browser space,
and it was one of the rare ways to quickly transfer applications to users.
You didn't have to wait for thousands of computers to run it.
All you had to do was click on an update and upload the file to PHP,
and you had them in seconds.
Let's talk a little bit about the language itself.
If you identify yourself as a Javascript developer,
that would mean that you have some breadth.
Javascript doesn't look like a front-end developer.
You could say that it's like that in Europe.
Javascript can be classified as a general-purpose script language
with which you will implement some logic,
and the browser is just a VM,
or an environment where Javascript also flows.
I think that's why it was amazing in Ursnyc,
that's why it was the basis of Nared.
It seems to me that this thing has somehow grown.
Today we see that Javascript becomes a glue for everything.
I think that, in addition to Python,
it is probably the most advanced and the most advanced technology.
Yes, that's exactly what you said.
I really like this comparison with Python,
because I've been thinking about it for a long time,
and from this point of view,
I learned that Javascript is something
where you can integrate all languages very quickly,
and it has native APIs so that you can connect
with all the things you know quickly.
At the same time, it's not so hard to write all the appropriate logic
and then connect five other languages or products together.
You're struck by it.
Yes, it seems to me...
I would say that having a browser and Javascript as an interpreter
is very important,
but it's definitely not a big deal,
and I don't normally like it to be on the server side.
It's very strange to me that my first programming language was Javascript,
because when you go to Electrotechnica,
Javascript was syntactically very similar to C,
but in a for loop.
That's a C for loop.
It has nothing to do with Java.
In Javascript, 15 years ago, it looked like C.
Then they prepared you for what you would do in the second semester,
which is C for loop.
Why?
If you picked it up as a teacher,
you don't need a complex idea.
We opened Firefox,
and you ran through all the Javascript,
you sprinted,
you had all the repl,
and you could use it.
And then...
It's normal that they did it in the back-end,
and when you do it in the back-end,
Javascript has a good concurrency model,
which was a bigger problem with Python.
I'm interested in how this language grew,
what it did.
We also heard that there are very few things
that you can do in it.
We have dynamic types,
no compilers,
no tooling that you can find in other languages.
Which means that it was a very simple start.
It's very simple to see what's going on,
it's very easy to be productive with the system.
There's also shipping in all browsers.
It's very powerful,
and it certainly converged in the world
where we have Javascript on the browser,
and everyone learned through it.
Would you like to talk a bit about
the assumptions that Javascript is single-threaded,
and what are the limitations because of that.
It's a criticism that comes up
when you talk to people who hear about Javascript,
why would they use a single-threaded model
on the back-end,
or why does Javascript have only one thread
in the browser that renders things.
Can you explain that a bit?
Is it really such a problem that people could rely on it?
Yes, it's something that happens very quickly.
When you start with Node,
just like Andras said,
with concurrency and Python,
it's one of the biggest differences
if you want to write only Javascript.
Because all the operations that are shipped,
engines such as browser,
or notepad,
are all asynchronous by default.
You have to give a task
that will be called by someone else,
and then you get it back.
I'm right, let's move on.
Yes, and that's what all the other things do.
I've always looked at it from a positive point of view.
Because sometimes in one thread,
which is managed with all the logic,
with all the things that happen,
sometimes you never have any risk conditions
in that thread,
if you don't set them yourself.
But you always know that
if there's a class here that changes an object,
it will be in the same time,
and you can sometimes forget
about a lot of small things.
Because if it was in a language
where the main part of the thread is,
maybe it wouldn't be that bad.
So that people would better access
the browser experience,
if multi-threading was in Javascript,
in some first-level system,
would they have more difficulty because of that?
Yes, in my opinion.
Because it's all one thing.
And it's not something that all beginners do.
At the beginning, they talk about it.
And that you can forget about such a thing,
was very positive.
On the other hand,
I've seen examples where
it caused difficulties.
I've had some states,
some frameworks,
that found themselves in changes,
and people were working
as synchronously as possible.
And they didn't even know
what they were doing.
To make it sound better.
For example,
if you have Angular,
with JS,
which was the first
bigger framework that was used,
it had its own way
of following the changes.
Because you could
send all the changes
to Angular,
or give it a context
that Angular checked.
What I mean is that
when you changed an object
in the Angular function,
and when the function was completed,
Angular went through
the whole tree,
through all the states,
and made an update.
And in the meantime,
some components or modules
got the same values.
Later, in the same
flow, they fixed one more thing.
And again,
in the meantime,
instead of looking at a console,
if you wanted to debug,
you got different values.
Or you got something in the console,
which was just fine.
While you were looking at
what you were debugging,
you somehow lost it.
Shocking.
I don't know what you see,
but whenever I look at
a JavaScript framework,
I see all these candy bars
that they sell,
and the only thing I look at
is the lifecycle.
If you don't understand
what's going on,
or the lifecycle components,
or whatever,
you have a big problem.
I would...
Before we go to Java...
Framework Wars.
We'll go a bit more
into the back-end.
We'll talk a bit more in English,
and then we'll go to the Framework Wars.
We'll be able to talk
a bit more.
I'll ask you this.
You've been working
in JavaScript for a while now.
I think it's been 10 years or more.
Yes.
And you've been going through
a lot of changes.
As a language,
do you feel like
the language is changing faster?
Is it changing for the better?
I think that
today the language
is becoming more
feature-complete.
It's becoming more modern.
I think it's changing faster.
If it took years
for certain features to develop,
I think things are changing
due to the fact that
we have a small browser,
a Runtime Engine
for JavaScript.
What do you think about that?
Maybe we'll talk about that later.
In the 90s,
the biggest steps were
taken with ES6.
Back then,
I don't know how many...
6-8 years ago,
I think a huge leap
was made in the community
when the community
got together
and formed
a committee
with the ECMAScript standard.
Since then,
every year
there's a new release
where you get new features
and they draw inspiration
or ideas
from a huge variety of languages.
The feeling I have
is that they pick
the best out of everything.
There's also a lot of criticism
about what the language is
if it's everything.
Is it still...
Won't it be too much
and will it just float
and not be used?
But I think
it's developing in the right direction.
One of the good things is that
everything is backward-compatible.
The browser is working,
the language is stable.
It's like running
a very old code
on the current manager
and it will work.
That was one of the things
that contributed to the popularity
because you didn't need it
all of a sudden.
Now we have a new spec language
and we will migrate
or use it on the last manager.
It's also easier
for the beginners
because the tutorials
are still old
and they work.
You don't have to
change the basics
of the language
to make it work.
That's why it's easier
for the beginners.
A follow-up question
is
since so many things
have changed
I'm back in JavaScript
and then I put it on a CV
and then I delete it.
If you don't
change the basics
of the language
you change how you program
in it.
My question would be
a bit strange
but is JavaScript
like strict mode 2
where you say
we don't iterate
through arrays anymore
and now we have
strict mode 2
and if you add
youstrictmode2
you will get warnings
or a direct error
if you use it.
My question is
does strict mode 2
work in a limited
type script
that is already in the browser
or what will happen?
Yes.
Now
this thing with backward compatibility
somehow
is not a breaker
but maybe a progression
where maybe
weaker parts of the language
and parts that
enable the engine to be faster.
So if that means
that you won't be able to make global changes
without initializing them
or declaring them
that's the thing that will happen.
I think the style
is something that
the team or the company decides
based on the control they have.
I think it's still easy
to publish JavaScript in CV.
Do you think so?
I don't think so.
I don't know
I have to look at the language
every couple of years
to see
if it doesn't create
some kind of loop.
But I think
the concept of looping
and iterating
is still
working
and creating new ways.
I think it's a language
that is completely forgotten.
Maybe because
the language itself
is better than everything else
that has been said here.
When the browser part comes
I don't know
things have changed a lot.
We won't open up
a conversation on the framework
but the first app
that I wrote in React
was in 2014
when React 1 came out.
When I look at React Hook
I'm like
why is this a good idea?
I don't understand
that it's a powerful concept
because my knowledge
has nothing to do with it.
I know JSX
and I know Lifecycle
but I don't know
if I would have written
what you saw.
I think the basic concepts
are still the same.
Maybe you write something
differently and then cut it
but the mental models
that you put together
about the language
are still the same.
The functions
can still be changed.
Wait, async call is still
just promise?
Yes, async and promise
are the same thing.
From callbacks
to async
it was a huge thing.
From promise to async
because they managed
to solve the problem
with promise
and from callbacks
it stayed the same
just different writing
and async changed
how you can
form it differently.
It's more visible.
Can you ask me
if there is
such a spread
of knowledge and
old technology
how do you recognize
junior JS developers
and where
do you put
this is really good?
Does it mean that you look
at the style of code
or API knowledge
or language?
There are a lot of questions
that I ask.
It shows
what they are used to
and what they are afraid of.
In the future
they will be more careful.
I would say
that getting to know
the current status of the language
is more important
than the language itself.
It is interesting what you do.
Most of the people
who wrote
what you said
stayed in that space
because it is still interesting.
If they wouldn't be interested
they would probably start something else.
So that's it.
But it is also interesting
in interviews with beginners
or juniors
you can see the influence
of their industry
and the teams where they worked.
Most of the styles of writing
come from the teams
where they were.
And then one thing
that I often do in an interview
if we have a code exercise
then someone writes
something that could be treated
as a request
or a request
from someone on the other side.
Maybe looking at the documentation
I would say that I would solve it
with that function
or I can try to solve it
using Google.
Because one thing that I think
is very important in interviews
is that you don't prevent people
from using Google.
Because if you use it
every day
it can be more valuable
than some current knowledge.
So then you can see
if someone knows how to convert
the documentation
and make something out of it
how quickly you can form
a model that they will use.
One such thing
that I find interesting with JavaScript
is that if we compare it
with some other languages
it has a very
small or very simple
or very shallow
standard
library, standard set
of functions that come
from the language itself.
Let's talk about languages.
If we look at Python, it has a very large
standard library. Ruby has a very large standard library.
JavaScript doesn't have that.
And I think that because of that
we have seen in the past
a very large library
that has been supplemented
by a standard set.
How do you see that?
Is it good for the language itself?
Is it bad?
I would say that it was good.
Basically,
why it's good that the standard is small
is that
because of that
it can flow in many different environments
and then the new environment
doesn't need to be
covered by a large part
of the standard library
If you look at the small part
and then look at me,
what kind of environment can you add?
For example, if I had in the standard
all the things that the browser adds
it would mean that
the language on the backend
would look a little different
or work differently
for people.
It would be very difficult to ship, for example.
Then that's the right explanation.
Because they wanted to make the core
very portable,
so they didn't need a large standard library.
Did I get that right?
Maybe, yes.
I would say that
the beginning
I mean, JavaScript is a language
that has a standard
and then you implement it
and then it seems to me that
the idea is different
because Python is a language
that defines its implementation
so it's a problem
to write any other interpreter
other than Python
and then go back
to choose the implementation
and try to make sense of it.
And then you have
all the other trade-offs.
In my opinion, this is a very good
reason if you want to have
more independent interpreters
and then you want to have
a language that is
well defined, which JavaScript is.
Some things are very strange
in the definition,
various comparisons,
some are bigger, some are smaller.
It's deterministic, so if you implemented the whole language or the standard subset, you could do it quite simply.
It's the same when we see people sharing or reading.
You read together, string plus nothing, false plus true.
You see a lot of puzzles, snippets that people want to...
Mind blowers.
Mind blowers, yeah.
How would I argue that?
Why do we see that?
I mean, people share it and make examples because they want to show that the language is shit.
It's a comical aspect.
I'm sorry, what do you think?
I have this...
It seems to me that...
It's a kind of trial and error.
It seems to me that you see this in production codes.
Because I don't have a feeling that...
That's how it is, unfortunately.
In my opinion, you see it in production codes.
If a person is very new to the language.
And on the other hand, it exists and gives you a lot of other advantages.
For example, you can give an object and it will know if it's null or undefined.
Or if it's a true value.
And now, if you look at any other language.
Or most of them.
Again, you don't compare strings and numbers.
Or you get a compiler error.
Here instead of a compiler error, you get...
A very black-and-white deterministic state.
Maybe you don't know everything.
Or it's not that obvious.
Do you think that the cases we see...
Are they meant to be corrected?
I mean, that's the language.
That's how it's always been.
That's the aspect.
The aspect is very precisely determined.
What happens if you compare different...
Quotes.
Types.
You compare them.
In fact, it doesn't say...
If you have an empty object.
Is it bigger than us?
It doesn't say that in the standard.
It's always determined.
Now, for me...
I have a lot of problems with that.
When I write code.
If you accidentally get a different type than you think.
The thing doesn't explode.
And you can have some weird things.
Or you go to another case.
And you see people checking.
Additional guards.
Additional checks.
That's a different thing.
You have a lot of that.
You have a lot of helpers.
They help you.
When they tell you.
That's not it.
And then you have...
In one of their cases.
If you want to see if something...
Maybe in another language.
It's a conditional.
In Javascript you can have more.
To hide what you really want.
And if you're using a language.
As a person.
I'm not 100% in Javascript.
It's harder for me.
On projects.
I'll need.
A month or two.
I know that the risk exists.
And I'll handle it easier.
But still.
I'll always say.
The frustration people have.
If you ask.
Is it a language problem.
Or is it.
We have.
One language.
That is.
Half.
We are on the same page.
Can I ask you something about TypeScript.
Or not yet.
Is there.
TypeScript that will help.
To improve.
I.
Not yet.
For now.
Yes.
Because in my code.
You have hardcoded data.
You can follow the type.
And it will tell you.
You did something strange.
And you can.
Watch it.
On the other hand.
As it is.
Javascript is used.
Data comes from somewhere.
There are a number of types.
And.
If you protect this part.
Very well.
Then you make various conversions.
Then you parse it properly.
Then you can.
Solve most of these problems.
But.
When we first talked.
You said you were not.
Directing in Javascript.
Do you use TypeScript.
Does that mean.
Not so much.
But my result is always.
Javascript.
Then you know it.
This is very important.
TypeScript is more full typing.
A lot of people will use it.
You are already warned.
On annotations in TypeScript.
But.
You don't have decoders.
In some other languages.
When you.
In runtime would say.
In TypeScript.
You don't have.
Automatic validators.
For types that are defined.
There are some projects.
I've seen them a little.
It's not a standard.
A lot of people still use it.
You have some.
Cultures.
Where you can.
Generate types.
Plus all.
These guard mechanisms.
If I have this object.
It came to me.
I will send it through this thing.
It will come back.
There will be an error.
We'll just say.
At the end of the link.
In the description.
Let's be friends.
To the beginners.
What is TypeScript.
We will all be on the same page.
TypeScript.
Is now a project.
It's been a few years.
To be presented.
In a broader community.
With Angular 2.
The idea of ​​TypeScript.
It helps you write.
More carefully JavaScript code.
With the addition of types.
Add static.
Checking.
Where you can.
Today predict.
For these types.
Work.
I think the result.
TypeScript is still a constant script.
What is missing.
Are all the signs for types.
Will.
Is there an additional performance penalty.
If I use TypeScript.
Performance.
In the runtime.
No.
It is additional.
It may take some time.
You can save time.
If you do not want to look.
For some strange bugs.
It's just a TypeScript project.
Almost everything.
I do not have a developer.
To check it.
As we have auto refresh.
Automatic check.
This problem.
On large projects.
Has come so much.
To appear.
Competitors.
If you take TypeScript.
Specification.
Then in another language.
Write in static checking.
Then you replace the tool.
If you still write TypeScript.
Use another tool.
To check everything.
Type checker.
But it is still.
TypeScript compliant.
Do not add.
Do not try to add your own types.
Just try to optimize.
Do you think.
That this.
Definition.
Type checking.
Which TypeScript does.
As its own project.
We will ever get.
Strict mode.
That part of JavaScript.
Some annotation.
Function.
Can be zero.
Do you think we'll ever get there?
There is currently a proposal.
Which is now stage 1.
In addition to the fact that someone wrote it.
They really talk to each other.
They have.
Authors from different companies.
Microsoft.
Bloomberg.
Another company that I do not remember.
But their idea.
Here was.
Let's not take TypeScript.
And say it will now be in the browser.
Then we will optimize everything for that.
But let's let developers.
Let them choose for themselves.
We will then add a standard.
Some annotation.
Some grammar.
Which will enable typing.
Which will always.
In the end, maybe you can remember.
Your own type language.
If it's JavaScript.
In practice.
That means.
You can follow it.
An example of this.
When they set it up.
Maybe for beginners.
Is.
That you can use TypeScript.
And now.
When I learn JavaScript.
TypeScript will take it.
Try to run it in the browser.
And then in the node.
Then you would get an error.
That you have a syntactic error here.
This is because.
JavaScript engine.
Still does not understand.
Types.
How to break.
Rules.
How the language is written.
And now that they have decided.
We will give you some syntax here.
Which corresponds to the comments.
Which we will ignore.
And we will choose.
And we will not go to the side.
You will.
If you want to make your own type system.
You will follow the standard.
If you want it to run.
Without any compiling.
You have to create your own.
Because all the rules.
They have a compiler.
Which will solve it for you.
With what they have proposed.
It will allow you to write.
In any language.
Which is compliant with it.
And you will always have.
In all the engines.
That will implement this standard.
All.
Beginners who do not know.
TypeScript.
It is very complicated.
And you have to learn it.
What do you think about it?
Learning JavaScript first.
And then TypeScript.
Learning TypeScript.
Or trying.
Angular tutorial.
Where do you see.
Do you know what this question is?
In my opinion.
This is a very complex question.
Also very dependent.
From how.
But how do you see it together.
Now my opinion.
This is.
As for the job market.
A lot of companies use TypeScript.
From the heart.
It is practical to learn.
Kreative.
TypeScript.
It is implemented.
In all those major.
Editors.
And you will.
You will get a lot of benefits from it.
Already the day before.
You need to write a type.
Every book.
When I write my type.
You will have an auto-complete.
Notebook.
Browser.
You have all these things already written.
For self-study.
It seems to me.
Presented.
More effort.
You think about the type.
And you write them.
I think it would be great.
To be able to use it.
TypeScript is still.
A great network.
I know that.
If I write TypeScript.
Only JavaScript will do it.
You will probably get.
With the default configuration.
Some errors.
You do not have this.
You can change it.
But still.
If you have a TypeScript file.
If you have a good configuration.
You can write JavaScript.
Maybe.
For a beginner.
It's one thing.
Yes.
Definitely.
TypeScript also has.
Strictness.
Something you can define.
You can continue.
You can start with.
Very loosely defined.
Types.
And then.
If I'm more experienced.
I can.
Strengthen.
But you can.
More strictly.
You can also.
Hint people.
You can start.
With the existing knowledge.
At this point.
One question.
If we are juniors.
At the executive level.
TypeScript.
Is it worth it?
To invest.
In modernization.
Of their existing.
JavaScript stack.
With TypeScript.
Yes.
Executive decision.
Very.
On the one hand.
You can stop development.
So that everyone.
Adapts.
On the other hand.
As in many projects.
You can start.
One team.
Or just in new files.
Something to add.
Now we will assign everything.
To something new.
You can incrementally.
Introduce.
If you look.
From an executive point of view.
You can move it.
Are people more satisfied now?
Do they complain more?
Have they noticed.
That maybe they are faster.
Or that you have less bugs.
When it comes back to development.
How to prepare.
What will this change mean?
You can say.
That if the company.
Will continue to work on TypeScript.
That it would be because of that.
Less bugs.
You can say that.
Or just developer experience.
Better.
I wouldn't say that.
Because.
It all depends.
On the team that adapts it.
But I think that.
Developer experience can be very correct.
I always try.
On such projects.
To look first.
On a core part.
And a user-led part.
Where you have some.
Implementation business rules.
And now.
Even if you do this core part.
Very well.
And you do it with TypeScript.
I think it will be a very good developer experience.
You still don't need.
On every type of code.
That will be repeated only once.
And used only once in one example.
Go to the end with TypeScript.
I wanted to say.
At this point.
That TypeScript.
Type system.
Turing complete.
And then I wanted.
With this new knowledge.
Plasma.
But constantly.
Flying on this wall.
With Andraž.
You can imagine.
That would be Jason Turing complete.
And Folkiger would write Jason.
Like a cave.
I think that.
I really.
I really like that.
Often as developers.
We think that we are gods.
And that we need a tool.
That knows how to do it.
If not Turing complete.
Then it doesn't matter.
I don't know.
I'm the kind of person.
I really like to invent.
Because I build them.
Because your project grows.
And you have more and more developers.
And you tell them.
Can I please.
Not have a compile time.
We don't write that template.
I don't know.
But.
I mean.
Maybe I wanted to mention.
That it's extremely powerful.
If it was at the beginning.
TypeScript or type system.
Basically basic.
Now it's very.
Very powerful.
I think that's what Turner did.
Do you think.
That it's more.
Some features that would.
Worldwide.
Library developers.
Can you explain that a little bit.
First I met.
With Turing complete.
Only in TypeScript.
When I saw that someone wrote.
Bubble sort.
Then someone wrote.
Base in TypeScript.
In fact.
In just type checking.
You can add elements.
Choose from them.
At the end I saw the implementation.
When someone implemented TypeScript.
In TypeScript.
Because it's such a good fun fact.
Something you might ask.
Millionaire.
In practice.
There are examples.
From the library.
Which is very popular.
Million developers.
Around the world.
It may be good to invest some time.
To do it.
I'm a developer.
This is also something.
At the moment.
Make or break a library.
I'm the same developer experience.
Because of TypeScript.
Because of the lack of TypeScript.
TypeScript also has some macro.
Notations.
I'm not.
One hundred percent sure.
Because I did not go.
A lot of work with TypeScript.
I saw a lot of things.
But at some point it will become.
Also very complex.
If you use it.
In some normal projects.
And do a lot of things.
For generics.
This code will work great.
Code.
For some consumer.
If you want to fix something inside.
And you will change the types.
You can do it.
If you have a brain.
And add.
Now types.
Then you can change something.
But especially.
I do not know.
Do you think frameworks like React.
Become more accessible.
Because of TypeScript.
It's easier to navigate.
In general.
Framework and codebase.
If you use TypeScript.
If you know something.
What property.
You have to write.
If they are magic strings.
If you have a name.
It's much easier.
Because the editors know.
Choose and use.
OK.
Now I think it's time.
To make a snack.
Let's talk about frameworks.
What are you waiting for?
I'm waiting for the BackboneJS debate.
BackboneJS?
I heard.
One of the most popular.
Framework.
Or library in the world.
Is jQuery.
You need it more and more.
But still.
97% of the web pages.
Still have it.
Also in combination with modern frameworks.
But why do we need it?
If we have everything else.
I would say.
That we don't need it.
But there are answers.
There are a lot of answers.
On StackOverflow.
How to use jQuery.
Because developers.
Copy code.
I don't ask.
What is jQuery.
I've seen it many times.
From the dollar.
People are crazy.
Dollar.
I'm a pure beginner.
What is jQuery?
jQuery.
Is a library in JavaScript.
For a long time.
Helped.
To change.
A lot of things.
From JavaScript.
Browser.
API.
Supported everything.
From Strang.
Toggle.
And a lot of other things.
Together with Ajax.
There is jQuery.
That solved all the problems.
That people had.
And then.
Browsers realized.
That maybe their API.
Has a lot of work.
And they can add it.
And because they added.
Everything in the browser.
I think.
jQuery is still developing.
New versions are coming.
A few months ago.
I played with it.
And.
It is still changing.
The truth is.
Not so much code for.
Backwards compatibility.
If you count.
Older browsers.
Then you count on it.
But it is still developing.
I think it is a valid tech.
But.
Those APIs.
That were on a new basis.
They are still working.
jQuery is still working.
In the same way.
Backwards compatibility.
When I started the project.
I always.
The first library.
When I added the project.
LowDash.
Some functions.
Functional helpers.
It is now.
Is it still added to the project?
Yes.
I haven't seen it yet.
In almost every project.
LowDash.
Is a special library.
Made to make it easier.
To work with.
You can add.
A lot of functions.
That you can use.
For example.
How do you glue together.
Two objects.
Merge.
Concatenate.
All the things.
I could do it myself.
LowDash.
Underscore.
That is.
Browsers.
And.
Optimal code.
To make it faster.
You have more.
It becomes very important.
How do you iterate.
Circumstances.
It doesn't matter anymore.
At some point.
I had.
A huge set.
Some strange privileges.
While.
Is much better.
For.
How to optimize.
Javascript.
And now.
A lot of things.
That were used.
They were presented.
In Javascript.
Language.
Filter.
Array method.
Still.
But.
It's a lot of people.
They have been using it for a long time, they know the functions and they are...
When we talk about jQuery and Loadech, I feel like I'm getting old.
Because I remember, we started using jQuery some time before,
some time before Loadech, and then you try it yourself in different browsers,
and you see that different browsers react differently.
But yes, they were prepared.
Those projects that we took from them were prepared,
and then they continued the web development,
and because of that, they expanded a lot.
I'm proud of that project, absolutely.
Okay, what was the next framework?
My question is, when they were removing the screens,
and I think they used Backbone.js and Mariuni.js,
what are the most established frameworks now,
and what are the super new expectations for ESN?
The most established right now, if we look at the industry,
are React, Vue, and Angular,
where they support their three big corporations.
I think the new...
Let's start.
Okay.
If we now go to the executive level,
if we have an engineering company,
and what are we going to do?
Spotify for folk music.
Spotify for folk music in the Balkan region.
So we have money, and everyone listens to music.
Okay.
And we have to decide which framework we want.
They chose Vue.js, React, and Angular.
How would you approach it?
What would you do?
That's a very good question.
A very demanding question.
I would say ESN.
What do you think?
ESN has some consequences,
but it also has some things that you can type in one or the other.
One of the key things I think is good to have,
when you already have a team,
someone who knows a framework.
If you have someone who is an expert in Angular,
then you will go to React.
Seniors, every expert has their own framework.
You don't have three engineers.
That's a bad advice for executives.
You don't have three engineers who know three different frameworks.
I can say that I prefer React,
but all the other examples are the same.
It's my cosmetic preference.
Do you think there could be a distinction
between working on a web page or a single page web app?
Do you think that could be an important factor?
If I'm working on a page,
then I probably have a different perspective.
If you were working on a web page,
you would be more focused on Vue.js or React.
But not because of the framework itself,
but because of the support you have from the community
and the platform that exists to support you.
Especially the use case of landing pages
and commercial pages.
There is also server-side rendering,
pre-rendering,
how the customers affect it,
what you can bring to the table,
and how fast you can build a website with a framework.
I was careful with Vue.js.
You can say that about React,
because I've never used it that much.
I have a feeling that Vue.js is trying to be
a spiritual successor of jQuery.
When you put it in,
you start to include a few types,
and then you start to use it more and more
in more complex parts,
like building a whole page.
I've heard that from a lot of people,
but I'm not sure where it came from.
Because if you look at it,
I can compare it with React,
but also in React,
you have a lot of previews.
You can say,
mount my application on this element,
Maybe the advantage of Vue.js
was that you didn't need
any transpiling or compiling in the beginning,
because if you used JavaScript,
you had a template in the strings,
and then everything was done in runtime.
That's why you didn't need anything else.
You could just drag it in,
open a JS file, and start writing.
Now I've changed that,
because Vue.js already had Vue.js files,
which were combined with CSS,
a template, and JavaScript.
It wasn't that useful anymore.
You couldn't make a Vue.js file in a project
and then mount it.
If you added a transpiler,
or a webpack, or whatever,
it would be the same as Vue.js,
but in a different way.
Angular added a couple of years ago
an application on the element,
but it wasn't there in the beginning.
Let's stay on that level of comparison.
Can you explain to me
the Angular framework,
React, and the library?
Does it still work,
or can you explain the difference?
I'd say it's still working,
because Angular was there
from the very beginning.
It gave you a way to render,
it gave you a way to fetch data,
it gave you a way to run routes,
it gave you a way to use state management.
React didn't define any of that.
It gave you a rendering engine
at the very beginning,
with a minimal local state,
and a way to transfer data
on the tree.
React added state management
a couple of years ago,
and it's much more serious.
It gives you a way to do everything,
but the state management
has to be done from the ground up.
The whole state management
and the way you use it
is up to you,
but the main difference
between the framework and the library
is that you get everything from the ground up.
No, it's a library,
and currently there are only two
that are being used.
You can write your own,
but you don't have a router.
If you need access to a specific URL,
you don't really need a router.
I'd like to answer this question.
The difference between
the framework and the library
is the way they communicate
between the components.
How do they communicate?
It seems to me that
when you open a tutorial in React,
it's all about the components.
It's a bit isolated,
but it's functional.
It's not about visual images
or interactions,
but the components have to communicate.
Can you explain that to us?
I don't know how to deal
with the difference,
but in React you have...
I don't think it's the same,
but you can send data
or you can send a function
and then you can call that function
and it will change it
and you can update it.
It's a bit difficult to explain
what Angular 2 is.
I've never written anything about it,
but when I had...
They called it a service,
and then there was Factory
where there was a singleton
where you could write data.
In the local state,
Angular made sure
that when you made a change
in their environment or context,
it was ready and checked
if anything had changed.
React was probably smarter
from the beginning,
because it was always a tree
in a tree,
and whenever you made a change,
you could put it in that tree.
You could put it on top of the tree
and everything would be written.
There could be a change
or something similar,
but they added a bit more magic.
You write a normal JavaScript,
but in the back,
all your data changes,
it goes through the tree,
proxies are created,
changes are made,
and they often tell you
to focus on Angular 1.
Angular 2 is different.
It's a different framework,
it doesn't stay the same.
I think React is more similar,
and in Angular you have
ngNRX, which is a state,
and through that,
changes are made.
What else can you tell us
about those classic guys?
One thing about state management,
which is interesting,
is that most of it happens
outside of the framework.
In React, the difference is
that all those things
that are in a script,
or in a state,
like Redux or something else,
are things where you have
a main logic change
written outside of React
and an adapter to React.
A lot of frameworks can be
written in Vue or Angular,
because the core idea
is the same.
I have a question.
In all those frameworks,
server-side rendering,
is it something
that you can use now,
or is it a new standard?
Is it something that you
can use in a lot of apps?
Who and why is it a problem?
Server-side rendering is
something that's been around
for a long time.
PHP was a good example of that.
Everyone went to the client
because they couldn't do it
in the browser.
You need some time to load it,
then you load the data,
then you can show it.
In e-commerce,
I think they started
returning to server-side rendering.
You lose a certain percentage
of users every millisecond.
You reduce your profits,
so you have to wait 1-2 seconds.
I think that's now
under 200 milliseconds.
Server-side rendering
is not something
that means
that everything is server-side rendered,
but it's just your first frame.
When you log in,
you already have a picture,
a text, a scene.
At the same time,
you have to wait 1-2 seconds
for your brain to process it,
to show it,
to load the framework,
and to add all the interactivity.
If you have time to first frame,
then you pay an extra step
and invest in server-side rendering.
Or you can take a step forward
and do pre-rendering.
Instead of rendering
an application or a screen
when the user requires it,
you prepare all possible screens
that you can save
so you can serve it statically.
You don't have to process anything
and then go back to the framework.
You can do that for SEO as well.
For SEO, it might make a difference
in terms of timing.
The result is the same
when you render it.
So server-side rendering
is a bit more complicated.
It complicates the setup
and the pipeline.
It's a big investment
to set it up,
prepare it,
and do it in such a way
that you can do it all.
All the major frameworks
are doing a great job
of optimizing it.
For example,
Vercel did a great example
when they did Next for React.
They started with a container
and then did Next,
which was great for static pages.
Then they set up the infrastructure
so you can write a website
with React in a great way.
They made sure
that it goes to CDN
and that they have edge nodes
that know how to server-side render
and you don't have to deal
with the fact
that these are the data you fetch.
I see that there's a trend
for cloudflare JavaScript
on edge nodes.
Where does it live?
I don't want to go too far,
but it starts with you
having a server
and your computer
serving it to the world.
The server gives you the data
and sends it back to you.
They made sure
that if you have users
from all over the world
and there's a lot of traffic
and the data is fast,
you can put a server
that has the same files
and you have more local access.
Then CDN started preparing
to put more smaller servers,
one in Ljubljana, one in Maribor
and one in Koper
so no one has to wait
for packages from Koper to Ljubljana.
They saw that it's great
and it's faster
and you can solve caching normally.
That's why they used
the servers we already have
to process it faster.
So CDNs are no longer
servers that serve statically,
but they can also perform
some kind of logic.
If you have a lot of processing
it doesn't matter.
They also have some subsets.
It doesn't mean
that you have to put
the whole server on the edge node.
In 200 milliseconds
when you go to the base
and back and process something,
it won't be as fast.
If you have a smaller operation
it can be much faster.
We can go to the server now
but we'll leave the debate for later.
Let's go back to the framework.
We built our single page app
in React, Angular and Vue.
We decided to do that.
Maybe you can tell us
what is Shadow DOM?
I think it's a question
that people don't know about.
Why did you choose it?
There are two expressions
for Shadow DOM and Virtual DOM.
Shadow DOM comes from web components.
One of the attempts was
not to need a framework like React.
Browsers would support it on their own.
You need a component
that would have new elements
inside it.
In HTML there will always be
one component and Shadow DOM
produces everything that
that component produces.
Virtual DOM was a solution
that everyone remembered
in React.
You build a HTML representation
that is applied to the HTML
that is in your browser.
It's like a diff algorithm.
Yes.
Browsers were very slow
to replace it.
Now you have all new elements
and you can apply the new state.
With Virtual DOM you can do that
in React.
It's not smart to know
that you can't lose the state
on the input.
Can I ask about serverless?
I'd like to talk about
more exotic frameworks.
I'd like to talk about backends.
Just a little bit.
If I wrote React.frontend
and replaced my backend
with Javascript.
I'd like to talk about
Microframework.express
and Blockatons.
Is there a framework
with admin page and models?
What is used on the backend?
Express is still very popular.
It was the first one
with a tutorial about it.
It's still not supported
by Async.Write.
If you write Async.Write
you need to know how Express works
and how it handles
its request and response.
There are similar frameworks
or similar apps.
At the moment
the most popular choice
is Festify.
It's similar to Express
but it adds a global context
where you can handle
DB connections.
It's not a tab-based thing
but you have adapters
and they add validation
so you can validate data
with JSON schema
when it goes in
or out.
You can pass JSON schema forward
and they can take it.
It's very smart.
They start parsing data
and they can half-hardcode
how JSON is generated
or parsed.
If I'm parsed or stringify
they do it in a smarter way
in the stream
because they speed it up
from 10x to 100x.
It's still an Express-like framework
or a Django-like framework
where you have Django admin
and a CRUD interface.
It's still an Express-like framework.
I know that you have
a lot of expectations
about this technology
and that it's only available
in certain countries.
I think you should try it.
I think Nest exists
where you can get more
than a candy bar.
Sometimes they give you
some constraints.
I don't know if there's
a Django-like framework
where you can use it.
That's it.
Do you expect to have some other tools with which you can manage these servers?
And how will you manage servers if they are expensive?
This is also one of the things that is becoming more and more popular lately.
Ok, we went through building our own CMSs, like Evolution,
we built a framework that helps you steal operations.
We also learned that moderation of systems is not so trivial.
We realized that this premise is expensive, and these servers are getting old,
and we are now moving to the next generation of Evolution.
We see Cloud and Serverless.
These are two areas where I see Javascript as a go-to glue to glue these things together.
How do you see these things?
What is the role of Javascript?
The role of Javascript is that it is often available to people in the backend.
Everyone can write a backend and deploy it.
And when things start scaling, everyone knows it by heart.
Because you can quickly write something that was not fast enough,
or had different difficulties, and then deploy it somewhere.
Then you can auto-scale it a bit, and if it is missing resources on the server,
you can add more.
A lot of teams would focus on delivering features,
but there is a lot of technical depth in the infrastructure itself.
And maybe there is no access to people who know all this,
but there are people who know how to connect to the base and get something out of it.
I think Netflix was one of the first to come up with the concept of functions for service,
and now we have serverless.
And they wrote their own platform on AWS.
The idea is that maybe functions for service has grown a bit.
You could be a service handler.
The idea is that you write your own business logic,
and it is not about how it fits into a huge codebase,
or how many layers you need,
but that it fits into a database,
and you write your own function,
and now one thing is behind it, and it will fit.
We got closer to the idea that serverless developers,
or developers who work with this technology,
deal more with logic and data,
than with business logic.
Everything else is done by the serverless technology and the cloud.
A lot of impacts are taken to the side.
There are a lot of things that could be done by the cloud,
but it is still not explored.
But if I give you an executive question,
with this Lambda function, the serverless platform,
they are not underrated.
Do you think they are expensive, are they underrated,
is there less moderation, less ops?
If a server is killed by one person a day,
Lambda, or serverless functions, are practically behind.
It starts to show up when you have a constant,
huge pressure on the server.
Maybe that makes it a little more expensive,
to use a daily server, or a container.
For a very unpredictable load,
where you have a lot of time to do nothing,
you can save a lot of Lambda,
plus you don't have to worry about how you will scale it.
For example, on On-premise, there is a limit
so that the server does not burn.
If you don't set a price limit,
when will you be able to solve the problem,
because you won't be able to pay the bill.
If you go to different conferences,
where they are big guys from Raven,
or conferences are being sold,
Lambda is being sold,
and I won't go into details.
But I think that there is an Asterix from Raven,
which should be mentioned here.
Lambda functions and architecture
are not all very good.
They have some limitations.
How are they limited?
You are limited to the fact that it doesn't really matter
how the data comes in.
You are limited to the infrastructure
that the cloud offers.
They are like adapters.
You say, I have a function here,
and this function can be called,
and it can come from a web socket,
or the trigger function from the database.
You don't have access to it,
if you have a server on your Linux,
where you can connect in,
and you take the runtime,
when they offer it to you,
and maybe you have a delay
for some latest releases.
But is it meant for stateful?
No.
The idea is that it is stateless,
although it is a lie,
because the thing is still stateful.
And if you take it as stateless,
we had an example where we connected to a database,
and every time it created its own connection,
closed it,
and at some point we stopped
as much as we could,
the connection was open.
But I think that it is just working
to be stateless.
How do you fix this problem?
In a global context,
you connect to a database,
and you use the same database,
and Lambda doesn't live that long,
so when the connection is closed...
Does Lambda have a limit
on how much time
it has to process a reply?
Yes, you set it up yourself,
and you call it.
Another thing that can be problematic
is cold start.
It means that whenever
this thing is set up,
when the server comes in,
it means that every time
a new Lambda will be created,
because it doesn't have
every request,
you will need half a second
for the engine to start.
This is now solved in different ways.
You don't need a compiled language,
where you can just run it.
You don't need to process
JavaScript.
If we're talking about
JavaScript,
it's not necessary
for Lambda functions to be implemented
in JavaScript.
Python,
Scala, Java,
.NET,
it depends on the provider.
Every provider decides
what they will support.
Anytick allows you to set
your own Docker image,
and you can say,
this is my Docker image.
Do you have a question?
My question is,
if we build
with Lambda architectures
and serverless functions
our new
product system,
how are these functions
transferable if we
integrate them to GCP
as a full
vendor specific?
How are they made?
As you know,
you will need them
on your cloud,
you can create
some layers.
It can be a layer for data
file storage or block storage.
It can be a layer for some
buses.
It can also be a layer for handlers.
Maybe everyone has
their own function,
but maybe
everyone writes
different parameters
and expects different output.
Do you have a framework?
For example,
a popular one for a long time
was serverless framework,
which allowed
to make it easier,
but not as easy
as you would imagine.
Do you
want to
work with serverless?
Yes, I do.
If serverless is fully adopted,
will you be able to do it?
Yes, I hope so.
Then I will be able to write
only frontend,
and my heart will beat.
Although I don't know
if I will be able to do it.
What do you think
about Firebase?
It's SaaS.
SaaS also has
serverless.
Yes, it's one of the features.
Firebase is just a nice
mask over GCP
for their console.
With SaaS,
when you open the cloud console,
it's hard to see.
It's a little visible.
AVS is even worse.
I don't know
what you think about it.
Firebase as a base
is just a product
that Google provides.
It's a base for
authentication.
It's easy to write
and you don't need a schema
to keep everything.
They provide real-time,
client libraries,
or some
syncs.
I don't know.
We experimented with Firebase.
I see it as
a next step
in the evolution
of technology.
Developers and engineers
are dealing with
business logic.
They don't just
offload
their chosen cloud provider.
You can see that with this technology.
They give you a bunch of
things that are possible
from the beginning.
Whether it's an offline
or online app,
how to change
authentication.
It becomes very interesting
for developers
because time-to-market
is very fast.
When I talk to people
about this,
they often ask
whether vendor locking
is really that important.
From all the technical
questions that you
deal with as a decision-maker,
it's just one
of the challenges.
In reality, we see
a lot of cloud providers
maneuvering.
That's a question for C-Level.
Firebase was very interesting
because you have
a client library
for mobile
and desktop apps.
At the beginning,
Firebase in the browser
was a collection.
Imagine that you have an array
and you give it elements
and Firebase syncs them
with your request.
If you need more advanced
backend processing,
you can switch to
a Lambda function
or a pipeline.
In the first part,
you can do it very quickly.
That's the advantage
of today's
proof-of-concept
and MVP.
People can start using it
on the same day.
If you saved half a year
of development,
you can say
that you saved a lot.
You can start with users
and what not.
You can also use it
with a model.
You get this part
and you get full constraints.
Besides being easy,
it's very hard
to do analytics
inside Firebase.
What people do
is dumping.
You don't have
advanced queries there.
You mean,
you have to do it
on your own
or on triggers.
Or you dump
Firebase
in a real database
and process it.
As engineers,
we work with trade-offs.
We go from one direction
to another.
It's not a silver bullet.
You have to know that.
Pricing.
What's the fastest
you can write in Rust?
What else?
I'm glad
I don't have to answer that.
We have a weird question.
Maybe
shameless plug.
On Amazon,
on AWS,
on Firebase,
they call it
AppSync.
Unlike their standard,
which Firebase has,
and ClientLibrary,
they have GraphQL.
That means
you come to this UI.
We have this table
with these types.
They generate DynamoDB
tables,
and at the end
you write
GraphQL schema,
which is translatable
in all languages.
You get subscripts,
analytic queries,
and you have a defined
database.
If you know
your data structure,
you have a back-end
made in URI,
which will scale more
when you write.
Maybe that's an interesting option.
We wanted
to talk about
going back
to the front-end,
and maybe
we could talk
about
the future
of the front-end.
If you could tell us
about jQuery,
React, Angular, and Vue,
what are the new players
that are coming,
what is the cutting edge
where we see new patterns,
new libraries,
or frameworks that you see
that are coming,
what is the future like?
One thing
we've been hoping for
is that web components
are usable
so that you can
use them quickly.
You can start writing a project
with React,
so you don't have to
break standards,
but you can start writing stories.
I haven't had
a chance to google
a framework
that already solves this.
Not Polymer,
but Lit.
Is that the successor
of Polymer that Google
started to write?
No.
Another way to optimize
is,
I won't mention names,
but the idea is
to take the framework
out of the final build.
When you write React,
you can take it out of the compiler,
remove runtime from React,
and only use
the code
that you've written.
This is a great way
to implement it.
A lot of people are
stuck with syntax.
What are we talking about
in the technologies that
won't be based on Javascript anymore?
They won't be based on
the fact that you remove your runtime,
because React, Angular,
their core, when it comes to the browser,
the core will be removed
while building.
It will be like writing
fully optimal Javascript code.
It will know what to write
and talk to each other about components.
It will do it
by itself.
Do you think this is a more real future
than full adaptation
of WebAssembly?
WebAssembly?
Yes, technology of WebAssembly.
No, I think
that there are two
different things
that will change.
Do you think that
WebAssembly will be written
in any language?
Do you think that
we will still be stuck in Web technologies?
I think
that we will still have this.
WebAssembly is being used
a lot for
processing.
For example, if you want to
do image manipulation
or to change
more complex algorithms.
A faster canvas.
Because you are working
and calculating everything
in a binary language.
WebAssembly is still
a very small subset of Javascript.
You have a few methods,
but almost every language
can be compiled into it.
This part
is being optimized in engine
so that it works
almost as fast as native.
Can we play Doom in browser?
Yes, you can.
I am already working on it.
I always recommend it.
With WebAssembly
one of the examples
that a lot of developers
and front-end developers know is Figma.
They were preparing
to have full performance
with
their own
home and front-end
HTML element.
Then they
changed it.
Some players
ported their desktop apps
and used all the logic
they had.
Then they compiled it in WebAssembly
and wrote it in JS.
Then they
changed most of it.
In a sub-interface
we will have it in WebAssembly.
You can use it with your
computer.
You can compile it in Bascos.
You just need to write a remote procedure
in Javascript.
You have Photoshop and Solidworks
which have their own web version.
I think they made a mistake
in Photoshop.
Solidworks is just a viewer
but you can still watch 3D models.
But we will see
if Figma
will use WebAssembly
to make a better canvas.
All the other
UI elements
are still classic HTML.
It's good
because they are
accessible.
You don't need a new zoom
to make it accessible
for a person with a camera.
With sight and hearing.
I think it's advanced stuff.
It's like
if we were biologists
we would talk about
micrology and so on.
I think it's crazy.
You can still
watch Javascript in WebAssembly.
Damn it.
You can drink a beer
and then lie.
Now
let's
pack it.
What do you mean?
Now
maybe you can tell us
where you are
or where do you play
with such technologies.
Which company are you
and where do you do it?
So people will take it
credibly and understand.
Where do you play?
I work
in a company called 37interesat.
We are
consultants
for a company.
We work on different projects.
For example
we don't have a solo market.
We have teams
who are
managed by a company
or by individuals.
Our market
is Scandinavian.
We also base
our company in Sweden.
Our companies
are based in Sweden.
We have
the biggest
company in Sweden.
They work in a bakery.
Yes, they can work in a bakery.
They can work on a Volvo
or a Polestar.
We work
with a music player
Klarno.
We have a lot
of bigger companies.
We also have Tetra Pak.
So if you drink
milk or something
from Tetra Pak
and you get sick, maybe it's our fault.
Maybe not.
Tetra Pak.
I hope so.
I would
suggest to all listeners
to check the links
in the description.
If you have a Twitter
follow
Klem
because he has a constant stream
on GitHub.
He is very active.
I would suggest that.
Do you have anything else to say?
It was very cool.
Thank you.
Stay cool.
I hope that the
Swedish JavaScript Meetup
will be in your territory.
I hope that
everyone who is interested in JavaScript
will come to the Swedish JavaScript Meetup.
Go to those meetups
if people are already organizing them.
Go there.
Drink beer.
People are also shy
so they won't
invite you.
They are
on guard.
I would like to thank
the listeners for
their attention, time
and feedback.
We will be very happy
if Klem and André
follow GitHub.