Hello and welcome to a new episode of Ogrodje. Today we are here at the microphone with Alis Justin and with me is also Andra탑 Sraka.
Today we will talk about Java, about JVM, about Java as a language, about Java as a religion, about how Java has changed over time,
we will talk about Quarkus, we will talk about everything that is included in this ecosystem.
It is a great honor for me to have Alis Justin with us today, who is a Senior Principal Engineer at Red Hat and a living legend.
I forgot something in that intro, Andra탑, would you like to add something?
I don't know, I don't even know you, how long have we known each other?
This is the beginning of my work at Red Hat, this is 2006.
It was funny, I don't know how we met, but I contacted Justin because he had a Red Hat server that needed to be fixed.
And then I met him in Vrhni Kopelu, in Mercator, right at the top, where you rent a table in a dark room.
And there he was sitting and said, look, this is the server, it needs to be fixed.
I don't remember if he was mad that they hacked it, or if something needed to be done.
It was something like that.
In my opinion, it wasn't a Jboss server, but a server, because I was the only software guy.
And I think Tomas Cerar gave me your contact.
He also met you at those events, but I don't know, he recommended you.
I bought a server because I wanted to have my own tasks, even though there was no cloud.
But I wanted to have my own builds, and I didn't have them on my computer.
Because the computers weren't able to delegate my testing and everything to that server.
I set it up nicely.
I also hosted some friends, but I didn't have everyone at home.
Yes, it was very interesting for me.
Did you do it for free, or was it an unpaid bill?
I think it was for beer.
We all were very friendly at the time.
My costumes were made of butter, which is on pizza and beer.
It was interesting for me.
When someone works on Red Hat, and I worked with Linux a lot,
I met Red Hat from a different point of view.
And you, as someone who has already been on Red Hat,
you were a part of J-Boss.
Red Hat already took J-Boss under its wings.
How did you find yourself on Red Hat?
Was it a dream job, or was it an opportunity?
You were on Solveria, right?
Yes, on Solveria Linux.
It was interesting.
When I was in high school, I used to go to Red Hat clubs.
I used to say, this is really good.
Melon was green.
Yes, it was green.
I also have a story about that.
On Solveria, we had an interesting part on the farm.
An energy software writer wrote about it.
Of course, we weren't many.
There was a J-Boss application server,
and we thought, this is something we need.
But even at the beginning of open source,
it wasn't that popular.
We used a lot of libraries, from J-Boss to Hibernate,
to Spring.
We started with Spring,
then Tomcat, and then J-Boss.
I thought, J-Boss is beautiful,
and this is even better than that.
But I had the code written in Spring,
with the same Spring bins,
and I didn't want to finish it.
So I rewrote it, and wrote an integration,
J-Boss application server for Spring,
with Spring bins.
So we moved on,
and I was like, J-Boss, J-Boss, beautiful.
And as a reward, I was sent to America.
Did you write it in open source?
No, I had it in Persep.
The company sent it to you?
No, the company sent it to me,
not as a reward,
but because I wrote it.
So I went to Java,
and talked to Bill Burke,
who was in charge of J-Boss application server,
and he explained it to me,
and said, yes, you can integrate it.
For example, we have Spring Deployer,
and I was like, wow,
how did I write that?
I hadn't seen it,
so how did I write it?
So we had laptops,
and I went home,
and I found Spring Deployer,
but I couldn't find it.
So I was like, ok,
I wrote to Zafor,
I listened to your talk,
I looked for Spring Deployer,
but I couldn't find it.
So I wrote my own,
and I was like, what is this?
And he answered me,
and I was like, oh no,
I said it in theory,
because Spring was popular.
So I was like,
it works,
you can show it to me.
So there was no GitHub,
and we also had private,
no, Microsoft,
and VSS,
so we had a lot of help.
A lot of help.
So you took a contract
for everything else,
and you couldn't do anything else.
So I asked everyone in the service,
can I use it?
And they said, yes,
but there was already
a contract,
and I gave it to Sourceforge,
if I remember correctly.
And when I saw it,
I was like,
that's exactly what I wanted.
I wanted to contribute to it.
And then I, yeah,
I re-wrote that there was
a Jboss package,
I gave them some documents,
an info queue,
documentation,
and it wasn't a special
download for a long time.
There weren't a lot of downloads.
And then,
when they said,
and I fixed it,
I patched Hibernate,
Jboss portal,
Jboss,
and then Jboss World,
and they invited me
to Jboss World,
and I was a bit confused,
because they were really busy.
They were talking about
Jboss Spring Deployer.
I was getting ready,
and then Flurry,
who was the owner,
and Scott Stark,
who was the Chief of Technology,
and Chief Scientist,
Adrian Brock,
and Gavin King,
came to me,
and Flurry was like,
thank you,
can we talk?
And I was like,
why are you doing this for us,
8 hours a day?
And that was it.
I was a bit crazy,
but that's it.
Dejansko was a science service
at the time.
I think it still is today.
Yes, it still is.
I mean,
only a small percentage of people
live from open source directly.
Yes, but a lot of people
have more opportunities
in the field of
open source engineering.
I mean, an engineer working with open source
at the time, definitely.
I came home that time,
I don't know, two brothers,
and I walked around the office,
and I didn't know anyone.
They told me,
you work from home,
we can move you to Switzerland,
we can move you to Atlanta,
you know where,
and I was like, no,
I'll just work from home.
And how can I move you?
And they didn't know
that there was still Slovenia,
at one point it was called Solvenia,
and so on.
And how can I pay you?
How can I pay you?
But we changed.
So,
that's how it started.
And then, I don't know,
from home.
You don't have to know
what you have to do.
If you're at home,
you can take off your pajamas.
But you don't have to know anything,
because you can find
the job yourself.
So, once a week,
we heard each other
through some phone calls,
which I had all over the country,
and you could call for free,
because there were no video calls yet.
And through the forum,
Djira was already there,
we were in Djira,
and a lot of people on the forum
were writing to each other,
because we were in different
passes, so there was no chat.
And you were part of
the J-Boss team.
Yes, exactly.
But J-Boss wasn't under Red Hat yet,
when you were there.
When I was there,
I wasn't there yet,
because that's how they called me.
Red Hat was there,
when they called me,
and we could wait a bit.
I was in the office,
so I could answer and wait.
And they said,
let's wait until we
merge with Red Hat,
and then we can onboard.
At this point,
can I ask you
for our listeners,
who don't know much about JVM
and the Java ecosystem,
what is J-Boss,
and why do you need it?
J-Boss, in the beginning,
when it was a company,
when it grew around
the J-Boss application server,
you are
the main specification,
and in a certain way
you can
put your application
in the application server,
and it helps you
in various aspects,
like web storage,
how transactions work,
security,
connection pooling,
and so on.
You don't need it all by yourself,
but after specifications
and using standard apps,
you can write
and use your application.
Plus,
this application is portable
among different application servers.
J-Boss was
one of the first
open source,
free application servers.
You had it,
AVI had its own
web server,
BA had WebLogic,
Oracle had
its own
application server.
Oracle application server?
Yes.
J-Boss was the first
open source.
Tomcat differs from J-Boss.
J-Boss is bigger than Tomcat?
Yes.
Tomcat was part of J-Boss.
Tomcat is only web storage.
There was a connection pool
hidden inside,
which helped you
use it.
Tomcat was
designed to be
embedded in J-Boss application server.
Let's
talk about this a bit more.
Back in the day,
you bought
a bare metal server,
you installed Linux on it,
which was a distribution,
if you were a real company,
it was a distribution with
support,
SUSE, Red Hat,
CentOS.
CentOS, OK.
Then you installed
Java directly on
the Linux,
and the application server.
Then people developed
applications on their
machines, they packed them
in VARs,
and then you grouped them
in the application server.
Yes,
a particular director
gave you this job.
There was a scanner
that looked through
to see if anything had changed inside.
Then you got to know the structure.
When you wrote this,
there were thousands of possibilities.
J-Boss was not only open source,
it was also
very expandable.
The other
servers
had
minimal packages,
monolithic,
you couldn't do much.
Probably not enough vendor lock-in.
You were limited.
When you wrote for one,
you had limited features.
Yes, limited features.
Let me ask you this.
For the listeners
who use
or grew up
with containers,
what was the advantage?
Why did you do it this way?
Why did you need an application server?
Why didn't you write Java applications?
Java applications are directly exposed
on the Internet.
You wanted...
What was the big advantage?
J-Boss could
have abstracted
it to look like a Docker.
You wrote
your own application
and put it in J-Boss.
I could have done that, yes.
The advantage was
what I created.
You had transactions,
you had a web where you stored it,
you had security,
and so on.
You didn't need to write that.
It was a kind of standard.
As Andra탑 said,
it could have gone beyond
the standard specifications.
Sometimes you could,
so you could have added something.
But as I said,
you weren't an expert
for transactions.
You wanted to use transactions,
so you wrote it yourself.
It's OK if you do it
the right way.
But then you get confused.
There are rollbacks, commits,
and you let people
who are really good at transactions
come to J-Boss
and buy a firm
which is...
The transaction engine
was a man from the academic world
who studied
these transaction systems
for 20 years.
From the very old ones
you could write
transaction engine.
But you wouldn't trust him
to do it properly.
You got used to it.
It was worth it.
You didn't have to write it yourself.
My experience
with J-Boss
was when I worked for Telco.
You used to boot
this part.
Before you went to the mall,
you could use this part.
The startup time
of these application servers
is legendary.
People installed
not just one,
but all three of them.
It was a well-known problem.
I used three versions.
I used four,
five, six, seven versions.
Four was like this.
You could scan everything,
look at everything
you had inside,
delete everything
in the descriptor,
configure them,
instance them,
and so on.
If there was a bigger application,
it would be worse.
With TPoE, it was even better.
We didn't work for one side.
We worked for a group of people.
It took a couple of minutes.
The fifth mission
was a bit more manageable,
but we didn't do much with the deployment.
We only had six.
The seventh was
done on purpose.
The seventh was Wildfly?
Yes, the seventh was Wildfly.
Was Wildfly a rewrite?
Yes, it was practically
from scratch.
We didn't implement
the transactions,
but the kernel,
the core,
was written from scratch.
As we saw,
I was one of the authors
of the microcontainer kernel,
kernel five and six.
We wanted too much.
We were crazy about
the attack stuff.
The application server
wasn't a monolith.
You could have
one or two M-bins,
and those M-bins
were stored in the kernel.
It was a big kernel,
with 100-200 M-bins.
It was like Jamex,
where you had to write
a lot of stuff.
We said, okay,
let's make five carapaces
and one M-bin.
Then we said,
now we have to
support the services
in the kernel.
We wrote a super abstract kernel,
which supports all possible
services.
Let me interrupt you.
You came up with
the features,
and it was good.
Did you get the community
or the commercial part
of Red Hat,
and why did you support it?
You could see
where the world was going.
Spring was very popular.
Spring had a lot of
ordinary M-bins,
which made the application
much easier for you.
People came to us,
and we had pages
that weren't that good.
Spring had a lot of M-bins,
but they had a lot of MXs.
We also had OSGi,
which was very popular.
Everyone was running OSGi.
We also had OSGi services.
We wanted to try it out.
I don't know,
we remembered the features.
Today we said,
let's combine it all.
We did,
but we didn't have a problem.
We never stopped working.
Then we tried all possible ways
to make it faster.
But it didn't work.
We didn't just do a rewrite,
and then we said,
let's do M-bins.
But Wildfly was in the marketing
that it was the fastest product.
Yes, it was.
Before,
there was a lot of one-click,
one-reflection,
and everything was dynamic.
With Wildfly,
we said,
let's go back to the hands.
You touched it a bit.
When you have a service,
you have to touch it
as if it were a hand.
If you touch it more than once,
the service will be faster.
You won't touch it with one-reflection.
It really helped.
What I changed,
not only the bins,
we also had a class-loading model,
which could support the old one.
It was super-hierarchical,
with four pockets.
Then the new one,
which could also support
different dependencies.
We also supported
the OSGIO class-loading model.
We had a class-loading layer,
and thousands of things worked.
In Wildfly,
there were strictly modules.
Modules could be specified,
one by one.
Mapping, and then
it looked at what was specified,
and put it together.
It wasn't like
they wanted to be smarter,
like we wanted to be smart.
We wanted to be smart,
and the user could enter
whatever he wanted.
Excuse me,
I can ask you this.
Who defines
the roadmap,
the specifications,
how do you think
which features will go
into Wildfly?
Who dictates it?
Do you dictate it,
together with the parties?
Is it a myth?
How does the roadmap look like?
It's interesting
how it changed over time.
Let's start here,
when we were at JBoss.
There was a party,
and they didn't dictate
any features.
We were the project lead,
so there were very few
who decided
to make a roadmap,
and then you had
some parties,
big parties,
who wanted to have a feature,
or something that wasn't
on the list,
or something they saw
and they paid for it,
so that they moved
a bit higher,
or something was added,
and so on.
Now, later on,
it's very product-driven.
You can see
what needs we have,
because we are so much bigger,
and we collect all the
demands of the big parties,
it's a bit filtered,
and then the projects
move towards
the satisfaction
of the needs.
If I understand correctly,
you were at the
product, which was
JBoss Enterprise,
and then you have
the JBoss Community,
what is the metaphor?
Did the JBoss Enterprise
become a community,
or did the JBoss Community
grow and then become an enterprise?
A long time ago,
the enterprise,
it didn't start
after a couple of years,
when Red Hat bought it.
It was a community, JBoss,
nicely tested, packed,
downloaded,
supported,
you can pay for support,
but it was all done
on that community,
there was only one version.
Then came
EAP,
EAP is nothing else
than a community,
but everything,
all the jars, all the packages
are tested, verified,
marked,
signed,
and that's it.
Is it easier to sell the enterprise?
It's an enterprise standard that requires it.
I don't know if it's a standard, maybe...
You know, this is a provocative question.
Java, let's start with version 1.0, and maybe 1.2, which was a big difference.
Look at how we are all here.
This has become an enterprise language.
In enterprise software, Java has become a de facto language.
What is it that makes this language, Java, dominate?
Why would Java dominate?
I don't know.
I've been programming since I was a kid.
When I was a kid, I used to do some serious stuff.
I'm talking about C++, when I was a kid.
I used to work only with Java.
But now I see that when I work with Java,
I'm not really impressed by the fact that
when I needed a book for something,
it was already there.
When you remember, it was already there,
so you could buy something from it.
But in very rare cases...
At the beginning, when I was still working as a soloist,
we bought a few things from smaller bookstores.
Later on, when I'm still playing,
it's not a book that wouldn't be open source,
that I wouldn't be able to get.
That's why it was fascinating to me.
In Gojo, there's also...
I don't know where else,
but in Gojo, there's also a store.
I don't know if I've seen it,
but I haven't really worked there.
But I don't think there's such a quantity,
and such a quality.
If you think about it, you could get Jboss for $100,
and it would be really good.
It was really good,
and there were a lot of other bookstores.
There were a lot of big ones,
Kafka, Hadoop, I don't know what else.
It's crazy what quality you could get for $100.
That's it, I think.
That's it for me.
Andra탑 wanted to say,
that he wrote Java 1.2 in the last episode.
I'm sorry.
When I started with Java,
it was 1.0 at the time.
And then there was the jump to 1.2,
where everything was different.
1.1 was a disaster.
1.2 was the first one,
and 1.4 was without...
1.4 got generics.
No, my generics were 1.5.
1.5.
Yes, 1.5 were the generics.
But 1.4 was already...
Things were already working well.
Before, it was a bit difficult to keep up.
But with 1.4...
We went from 1.4 to 1.4 for a long time,
and with 1.5, generics helped a lot.
Is it true that most of the world
is running on Java 8?
On Java 8?
Yes.
It's been a while.
I saw it for the first time,
when I was writing our projects,
on Java 8,
because you promised to support it,
but you couldn't go any further.
Thank you, Dio.
I think that on 1.1, it was a quick jump.
On 1.1, you could go,
but you didn't ruin much.
I think that on 1.1,
there were modules,
but not yet.
As someone who has been working
on Java for a long time,
do you think that Java is moving fast?
Do you think it could develop faster?
Do you think it's slowing down?
How do you see it?
Can you comment on how the language
changes and develops over time?
OK.
1.4, 1.5,
I don't remember how fast,
but I think that 1.5 was quite slow.
For a long time,
there was nothing smart.
A lot of languages appeared there.
They were all famous,
because they had a lot of books.
I remember Google's head of books,
I don't know what they were called,
but there were a lot of books,
and streams,
because you could see it in other languages.
But not here.
Then new languages appeared,
like CEL, Kotlin, Pascal,
and it was nice that the price changed,
because we made a mistake.
Then Java 8 appeared,
but I didn't make a lot of mistakes,
because I added it to the stream,
and I made the function for the lamp.
I didn't make a lot of mistakes.
Then they made a commitment
to make the versions faster,
like 9, 10, 11,
and it was fine,
but there were a lot of mistakes.
With Java 8,
I didn't make a lot of mistakes.
Before, I was like,
I have to work on my collection,
I don't know,
I don't have to call those functions.
I think the recommended version
for a new project is 17.
Yes, I have 17.
I've been playing with 19 for a long time,
so I know Project LUM,
to see how it works,
but yes, 17.
LUM will have a new trading model,
can you tell us more about it?
Yes, when you look at the whole problem,
because of trading,
like it is now,
the price of one thread
is high.
If you have an application
that needs a lot of...
I don't know,
if you want to have
one thread for every request,
it won't work.
Then there's React,
which is a connection pool,
and you can request your tasks
as soon as possible,
so they don't take too long,
but you can share
a lot of short tasks
with a small number of threads.
But now the threads are different,
they were made natively,
and now they will be...
I didn't show them all,
I hope I didn't say too much.
It will be a bit confusing,
but they will be natively made,
and that's how the virtual threads
will be made.
What are they called? Green threads?
Yes, virtual threads.
So they will help you with execution
and the last schedule?
Yes, something like that.
You're just nodding.
Some things just happened.
You didn't fall asleep,
you just moved on.
Let's break it down a bit,
and move on to other things.
For example, people who do
high-frequency threading,
or ultra-performance threads,
and they talk about
C++, C...
It's not about scale.
Aka!
I just wanted to hear
that Java, in your opinion,
is a real player for
high-performance threads,
for latency-critical threads,
and everything moves in that direction,
there's always more optimization
going in that direction,
and it's a language you can use
for high-performance threads,
and it will help you, I know,
to work on modern applications.
Do you see the problem inside,
or would you say,
sorry, garbage collection will
take care of the problem?
Interesting question.
I worked on a project,
instead of Red Hat,
and the problem was
that it had to be very fast,
and it was possible.
In our case, it wasn't
that critical,
it was just important
that it was fast.
As I said, if it's fast,
it's very important,
but it's also possible
to use different types of JVMs.
You can use different types of JVMs,
I haven't thought about that,
but you can use IBM JVMs,
or Oracle,
or academic JVMs,
which are all based on OpenJDK,
but they're all written,
so you don't know
how to use them.
There are different types of garbage collectors,
you can choose one,
and you can use the whole garbage collection
algorithm or mechanism.
What we did,
there's an interesting paper,
Disruptor,
which mentions
a few trends,
it's very fast,
and we added there,
to expand the problem,
there was Kafka,
and with Kafka you can scale
horizontally as you want.
If we needed more,
we would have more Kafka instances,
and more Kafka brokers,
and we would be able to handle
a crazy amount of messages.
You're talking about millions of messages
in a very short time.
Do you think that Java
is a good language
for any problem?
If you go to a special W,
I think it's good.
If you're an experienced developer,
you don't have to do anything,
because it's a garbage collector.
If you have a memory of your own,
it's probably better,
because you have something for women,
which you don't have any influence on.
You can make it very short,
and you don't need a lot of memory.
If we're talking about cloud,
we might have a bigger corpus,
and maybe the connection is
the part we see on GraalVM,
and the ahead-of-time compilation.
When we talk about cloud,
we're talking about different architectures,
where we talk about small services
that process data,
and when you don't need them,
you kill them and downscale them.
Cloud, especially for software,
has different requirements
than what we talked about in JBoss.
I wonder if you can see
what the requirements of the cloud are,
and how JVM and Epic
work together.
I was here in Del,
when OpenShift came out,
we already had Red Hat,
and then we bought a farm,
where we were working
like some containers,
and it quickly turned out
that there were no containers,
but there were some processes,
and they were running there.
Then OpenShift 1 came out,
I think it was too fast,
and then OpenShift 2,
which was already on containers.
We didn't have any other smart software
to offer,
so we offered JBoss in the cloud,
and then Infinispam,
and other projects like Drool.
It quickly turned out
that this is not good.
People already said
that they will buy OpenShift 2
and run JVM applications on them
in JBoss or in EAP.
Before they wanted Cluster,
and we could run JVM for everyone,
and in JBoss,
and it was a resource
like eating candy.
The color of the JVM application
was quite nicely pasted.
Today's OpenShift 2
was more like Kubernetes,
a very poor man's Kubernetes.
When Google came to us,
I still didn't know about Kubernetes,
but the day before,
I learned about it.
We were just on the other side,
and then Kubernetes.
Everyone knew
that you couldn't do anything smart
with JBoss and OpenShift 2.
You couldn't make a lot of changes.
JBoss wasn't an example,
because it was a resource
that could be used for everyone.
It was JVM,
so everyone knew about it.
Everyone quickly started using it.
Microapps, SpringBoot
were a big hit at the time.
SpringBoot wasn't exactly what you wanted.
It was a bit of a nuisance
that you only needed it at the time,
that you didn't want to crash
an application server.
You could crash JBoss,
if you knew about it,
but you were on the other side
and it didn't work.
SpringBoot was designed to be minimal,
but it was always too big.
Then there was GraalVM.
GraalVM was beautiful,
you could compile it on the net,
but everything didn't go as planned.
You couldn't compile a lot of things,
because there were substitutes
and you had to ignore things.
But you could do a lot
if you didn't do it alone,
because you didn't know
what you could do.
Then there was the need for Quarkus.
Quarkus has more...
Let's go back to Quarkus.
It's great that we have a deep debate,
that's why we're here,
but I still have to say a few words
for those who don't work,
because we talk about God every day.
GraalVM...
GraalVM is a new version
of Virtual Machine,
which doesn't use Java binary anymore,
but it uses a native binary
that GraalVM uses.
Java is a classic
chest-in-time compilation,
versus Graal, which allows
you to do a lot of things.
Can you explain the difference?
You're asking me first.
If I imagine GraalVM,
and I don't watch it anymore,
because I built it a bit,
I'm a bit older,
and I'm not much younger
than I could be.
It's a nice app,
and if you work with Graal
and Unicompiler,
you can do it in the class
and in the native.
When you get the binary in the native,
you get your application packed,
plus GraalVM hidden inside.
The point of GraalVM
is that you can use it
as a regular virtual machine,
but you can also use it
to build a native binary.
That's my logical question.
When you write in Java,
you can put it in GraalVM.
You can compile it from Java C,
get the classes,
call the native image from GraalVM,
and it will show up in the binary.
The binary has a VM inside,
and all the code you have,
and that's the binary.
It's because the compilation
has to know the path to the frame,
and you have to give it additional information
so the native image can show up.
The point of these images is
that they have a smaller memory footprint,
so they are smaller,
and they move faster.
You don't have a reflection, for example.
But you have to do the compiling,
so you probably have a smaller architecture.
You have to compile it.
If you build for different architectures,
you have docker images
for building specific platforms.
I think you can't build on Mac.
There are old Mac images.
I don't know if you asked me.
I know I can't build an image for Linux,
or a binary for Linux,
because I put the binary
in my Linux image.
And the native you get
can be compiled in docker.
I can build a native for OS X,
and then I can build it directly
for my wife.
You can connect it,
but then you have to do it properly.
I didn't do that.
I built it for OS X,
and I said,
oops, that's it.
I think it supports
all different architectures.
Not only Java,
but you can use Ruby,
JavaScript, Python,
but you can also
compile different languages
for native images.
Oracle's idea with GraalVM
is that you can put GraalVM
inside Oracle,
and then you can put SQL inside Oracle.
It's a very interesting project
that Oracle is developing.
It's meant to unlock
Quarkus,
and to bring Java closer
to the cloud.
Before we go further,
how do you feel
about Red Hat,
the transformation of Red Hat?
Where was Red Hat
when you joined?
What did you do together?
How much has Red Hat changed?
I had the opportunity
to talk to someone from Red Hat,
who said that Red Hat fell asleep.
That Red Hat is a software company,
and that it's just a cloud train.
The only thing they have to show
is OpenShift.
All the other projects
like OpenStack and similar
are just clouds.
Red Hat has never been
a service.
How did you like it?
You have to make a sandwich.
First you answer that,
then we'll talk about Quarkus.
I don't have to answer you well.
Not that I don't want to,
or that I shouldn't,
but that's just my opinion.
Red Hat was very special for us.
We had a software middleware part,
a Linux part,
and an OpenShift cloud part.
We had a stand
of JBoss,
and then a middleware division.
There are some people
who mix it up,
and you can probably
answer that well.
I don't really practice with them
from Linux.
Benga, Stemi, Cloud, OpenShift, and a few others.
I'm not saying I'm not ready, but I know that when you hear it and see it,
there's a lot of commitment in OpenShift.
There's a lot of teams, and we had some really good people,
a few of them left, and Clayton went to Google.
But it's good to be able to replace someone like that.
It's good that they stayed there, and I bought them.
I know that we have one storage company, then another,
then a third, and you really need that.
If they were doing well, I wouldn't buy them.
We're all determined, and later, when IBM bought us,
it's interesting how determined they are,
because they have two determined cultures.
IBM has its own culture, Red Hat has its own.
I think that IBM is letting Red Hat's autonomy go,
that it's still Red Hat.
Yes, they are determined.
I know them, but I won't say where.
I think I know where the problem is.
But, as I said, they've let go of everything that's developing.
They're all getting together.
I see more of them going to IBM, to Kinio,
to Red Hat, and bringing people to Red Hat.
They're also going in a different direction,
but I'm paying less attention to that.
In fact, the consequences of IBM, WebSphere, and similar things in China...
Well, you can't really say that in China.
Yes.
It's just one more leg, and you're behind,
and with my support, you can...
But I see that with us, too.
For example, the e-app is very popular,
and every year we release a new version,
after a long time.
But you can't do that.
They don't have a WebSphere,
but they have a WebSphere Lite, and so on.
So we don't have to go to E-app,
and then go crazy.
You can't fall asleep.
I don't know.
It's interesting,
I don't know if I'm exaggerating,
but if it wasn't for Quarkus,
I could really say that we fell asleep.
Because Wildfly was there,
and they have good projects,
like Drools, which is at a very high level,
it has something similar,
and Hybrid, which is still developing,
they have such fine details,
and some other projects,
I don't know.
But that was it.
But when Quarkus came,
we fell asleep,
just like with application servers,
just like with game-changers.
SpringBoot is on the case,
but ours took a step forward,
and we have to deal with it later.
We don't want to...
No, no, no.
You can see it.
We said, why Oracle invested in it,
and why Quarkus,
these are the giants in the cloud,
all the technologies we will talk about.
But is the company still developing software?
Or is the company in a transition
to start developing as a server?
All the giants have focused
on being in the service.
But someone has to write software.
If you don't write it,
someone else will.
No, but here I understood
a sad story with RedHat,
that we wrote OpenStack
and similar applications,
but now it's used by others,
and someone else serves as a service.
We are just the ones
who write software and provide
professional support.
Nothing but excitement.
Yes, yes.
To go into services,
that's it, you don't just write software.
But the first service
that we would repeat
within our cloud,
is the Kafka service.
And it turned out to be very, very difficult.
Yes, and I think it answers
why it's not.
It's very difficult.
A couple of hundred people
turned to this to do it.
And they did it,
with such an optimistic plan.
And it turned out
that it's very difficult.
And because of that...
Are you talking about Streamzy?
Yes, Streamzy is used within it.
Streamzy was written,
and then another software was written,
to orchestrate it,
so that you can offer it
as a service in the cloud.
So if Andra탑 comes,
who has to install Kafka,
he can go to RedHat or IBM
IBM has its own cloud.
It still has it.
It's a cloud in Serbia.
No, no, no.
I know, I know.
IBM used RedHat,
and RedHat replenished their cloud.
I think that IBM
is no longer a player in the cloud world.
That's a powerful statement.
But there are players.
Amazon, Google, Microsoft.
Alibaba.
Now we know who will sponsor this podcast.
Thank you, Andra탑.
Thank you.
I wanted to tell the boss
that you're getting stickers.
Okay, look, IBM will be the cloud,
that's something else.
That's what I told you.
Messaging was one of the things
that was abolished,
and people who worked on it
were moved to RedHat or Streamzy.
I was there, I replaced them,
and we got 3-4 of them.
A few of them we already changed,
and we started talking about
synergy and integration,
so we wouldn't split up.
I saw a few of them go to another company.
A few of them joined us,
so I think that's the end of the project.
Because you could see that
everything was similar.
When you looked at Streamzy and their work,
it was clear that it couldn't be any different.
Streamzy was a bit newer,
a bit more ready.
For listeners who listen to podcasts,
Streamzy is an orchestrator for Kafka,
for Kubernetes.
You install it through Helm,
and Kafka will move it
to your Kubernetes cluster.
But you still need to have your own Kubernetes cluster.
Yes, you need a Kubernetes cluster,
but today you manage Kafka in a Kubernetes cluster.
It's very elegant and on a high level.
You run Kafka yourself,
and Kubernetes is...
I won't do it for you.
No, I won't do it for you.
Can I talk about Quarkus now?
People are really hyped about it.
It's true.
I fell into a bubble again,
when Ale큄 called me
to the Mekit conference,
and also to the Java conference.
Quarkus is the way to go.
It's a new web project,
and Quarkus is the way to go.
Maybe I'm biased again,
but if Spring or Spring Boot dominates...
How long will it take you to not say
that it's the way to go?
If you want to use Java,
where modern web frameworks are,
where you can use modern approaches,
Quarkus dominates somehow.
Maybe I'm biased,
but I see it as a part of...
It's a part of the solution.
I did the assumption,
and maybe my listeners will stream it
and correct me.
If it's great,
give me other suggestions.
Now we'll talk about Quarkus,
because you work with it the most.
I've seen the page,
but I've never used it.
It seems that Quarkus and Graal.vm
go hand in hand,
or that it's a combo you recommend.
I know the main features,
why I would use it.
What are those 3-4 features,
and why Quarkus is the best
web framework for the modern world?
As we mentioned before,
you had Spring Boot,
which reduced everything for you,
but it was still huge.
Quarkus...
Spring Boot,
all the frameworks we've seen,
all had that problem,
and they had to scan a bit.
Then came the annotations,
and you had to scan the configuration files.
But it was always scanned.
The bigger the problem,
the longer it lasted.
A lot of defense,
Quarkus...
You don't need Graal.vm,
you just need Graal.vm,
and it will build as best as it can,
and most of the time,
if you don't use it,
it will build native.
You can deploy it mechanically.
Then there's the speed,
that you don't need to scan anything.
When you get used to the app,
you don't need to scan anything.
You already know what to do,
and Quarkus does it for you.
In build time,
when it scans the whole app,
you can see what you're using.
If you're using a reflection,
you can say this is a reflection,
and it won't delete it.
But it also knows
what you're using.
For example,
if you have a huge entity,
a big table,
it will prepare everything,
and it will build a model
in build time,
and it will store it in REST,
in CDI,
Bean Injection,
it will know all of that,
and it will do it in a modern way.
Quarkus uses it internally.
Quarkus is a small kernel,
and then it has extensions.
Those extensions have two parts,
build time and run time.
In build time,
you can store all of that information.
In Quarkus,
it's called eat your own dog food.
With that kernel,
you can use those extensions,
and in build time,
you can simply add your own extension,
and another piece of information
from another store in build time.
When the application starts,
all of the binary code is there,
and it just calls.
Invocations are crazy fast,
because it's not scanned.
If you did something wrong,
the web application,
REST, a couple of Beans,
and maybe some entity,
it takes less than 100 milliseconds.
It's incomprehensible.
If you think about it,
when we started the application service,
it was a wild fly that took a few seconds,
and it was already wild.
It's not just a Hello World application.
It's a daily application that takes
a REST endpoint,
a Bean injects it,
and that entity writes it to your database.
For reference,
if the web page has more than 200 milliseconds
of rendering time,
then people will pay attention.
100 milliseconds is very important
for serverless models.
What do you do with it?
You run it, turn it off,
the application is as it should be.
If we go back to Aquarcus,
it's good to have extensions.
It's a bit low-level,
but you pay attention to it.
You don't need a lot of knowledge
to use it.
With extensions,
all the main tasks we do
receive all possible support.
Plus, Aquarcus has a quirky version
where the community contributes.
When we talked about it before,
why is Aquarcus so good?
When you think about it,
you can easily find support for a book.
Recently, I played and needed
support for S3 storage.
I added a dependency
and I had S3 storage.
It's very interesting.
The principle of Aquarcus
is similar to Dev Services.
You just need to add
a certain dependency
and if you still need
a service,
for example a database,
you need a database
and then go to Dev Service
and Aquarcus will take care of it
from the back.
It's like a developer container.
Yes, it's like a container
that will be taken care of
and then turned off.
Or for Kafka, for Base,
for S3, there's a mini-Io
Dev Service.
I realized that I don't need
to write Dev Services.
It's great that in the community
there are already written
Dev Services.
How is it verified
and how do you know
that the project is good?
Do you check it?
Do you have a signing?
Do you go through a revision?
Aquarcus ecosystem.
Yes, Aquarcus ecosystem.
You would include something
and you would include something
that you don't need to maintain
so you know that it's a quality code.
That flag is working for the bank.
For some security mechanism
when you go through
some things are unprogrammed
and you're affected.
Good question.
You have Aquarcus
and Aquarcus is an extension.
I don't know how we decide
what goes directly to Aquarcus
and what goes to Quarkiverse.
Maybe from Quarkiverse
you go to Aquarcus.
What's inside Aquarcus
is quite strict.
You go through GitHub,
pull requests and reviews.
It's not like at the beginning
when we had a lot of people
and we had a lot of tests
and we had a lot of work.
My boss said
if it's not tested, it doesn't work.
Don't tell me it's bad.
Half of the things were written
and half of the things were tested.
When you go to Aquarcus
everything has to have a test.
As many different tests as possible.
Then you go through a review
and you have a ping-pong game
on GitHub.
It's quite strict.
I don't know.
You go through tests
and they're great.
Even when you make a lot of requests
a lot of things happen
because of the number of tests.
If you make a request
you have to look at it.
you have to look at it
because of the effects.
If you make a request
it works.
It's probably a bit slow
but it works.
You also have reviews
but the main thing is
the incubator.
For example,
if I make a request
I can change it
but it's the same thing.
It's interesting to be known.
Andra탑, what is Istio?
What is Istio?
You want to make a full mesh
from inside your containers.
Explain to me like I'm five.
Where does Istio work?
The idea is inside Kubernetes
between individual services
to create a communication
that you can control.
How do you terminate TLS connections etc.
It's a kind of end point
where you make a policy
which application or service
you can communicate with.
You can't automatically add
network, low-level level
load balancing, failover,
tracing, metrics etc.
But you can add it to this level.
And if you give priority to Istio
in your stack
you don't have to implement it
in the application code.
For example,
I work for Devo.
You pay for it.
Without Istio I can't
and I can quickly
program what I need.
And I need a lot of time
to write a test
which will help me
to include Istio nicely
in the test.
So you have the whole test suite
of Istio.
I don't want to spoil anything
so I have to add Istio
in a few other tests.
I don't want to add Istio
in a thousand places
and I want to add Istio
with Istio and without Istio.
I would like to go back a little bit.
In Quarkus it says
that it combines
an imperative and reactive
way of development
or implementation.
Can you explain
what reactive software means
in Quarkus?
What does it mean
to be reactive in Quarkus?
We already mentioned that.
But let's talk about Quarkus.
As we said,
trading is expensive
in applications.
If you need
all your stack
or all your application
if you don't want to use
a lot of thread,
every part of the application
has to be reactive.
The web has to be reactive
to use the initial thread
and then forward it
and receive a callback.
When it's done,
you can send a response.
If it's not reactive,
you can finish it.
But if you have a little bit more...
Rest, Endpoint, a base, a message to send and so on,
so that it can be combined.
It can be Web Endpoint, Reactive, a base.
There is a need for a hybrid Reactive,
so that it doesn't block the base.
We have messaging, Kafka, and so on.
In Quark, every component that can be rewritten,
that has a Reactive note, is written in this way.
It is written in both ways.
I don't know if it's a good thing to say,
but it's good in an imperative way.
For example, when a request comes in,
it doesn't go through your thread completely.
If you have a bug somewhere,
you can do a stack trace,
and then you can follow what's happening.
In Reactive, it can be worse.
You put it in a context of execution in different pools,
and if something falls out,
it will fall in the middle.
In this context, if something happened on the base,
and it fell out,
you won't know where it came from,
what was inside, and so on.
And also for debugging.
A debugger would go through the code,
and if something fell out,
it would fall out in the context,
and you wouldn't know where it came from.
In the context, you would go,
oh, here I am in the end point,
these were the parameters that made me
a null pointer exception, or whatever.
So, there are pros and cons.
The whole point of Reactive is that
the less things you work on,
and that things happen when you need them,
and that you have enough information and context
to execute an operation.
And the work starts where the user is,
the user is in the interaction,
and the lower you can go through the stack,
the faster and more responsive the work is.
There are also complications.
It's like a trade-off.
Yes, absolutely.
If you have a lot of requests,
or a lot of messages to process,
for example, to get the experience inside,
and then give it to someone,
or a lot of requests from the web,
you will be able to do it differently.
You can go and make an extension
for a certain instance.
With a small set,
let's say a few hundred threads,
you can do a lot of things.
Because you will be giving information,
you will be smartly programming,
you will be able to do it.
If you wanted to do it with an imperative model,
it wouldn't work.
Of course, there you will see
if something goes wrong, or not.
And that's why various tasks
were included in the project.
Practically without any tracing,
without any metrics,
without a tight context,
you can't do it.
And then there was a problem,
because we reduce the use of threads,
but we also bloat the context.
Because everyone is a bit more balanced.
And how to do it in a smarter way?
That's a $1 million question.
The amount of context
doesn't affect what you want to achieve.
In the same context,
it says that Quarkus is very good
for event-driven architecture.
Can you comment on that?
What do you think about it?
It's almost like Reactive.
Reactive is a method,
and an event is...
Every request, every message
can be assigned to an event,
and then you pass it
through the Reactive implementation.
It doesn't depend on...
It's already asynchronized,
you can split it,
go to two,
join it, and so on.
Quarkus, as a tool,
is a very good thing
that I've noticed,
and I'm very proud of it.
It's a tool called Funky.
I hope I pronounced it correctly.
It's a support for FAS models,
Function as a System,
or Function as an Infrastructure.
It's a Lambda architecture,
where your app is just one function.
You build it, deploy it,
and then you put it in a managed service.
I've heard about Funky,
but I haven't heard about it.
I think it's the basis
for our K-Native,
Serverless.
Yes, it's called serverless
for functions.
I've also noticed that
there are annotations
that allow you to
use only one function
from your microservice.
It's a trend in Quarkus.
It's the basis for our K-Native.
You have the specification,
and so on.
I don't know.
I have to be careful
when I'm working
that I don't destroy
the K-Native descriptors
that are generated.
I've only heard about Funky.
I haven't heard about it.
No, Quarkus is something
that we have from the inside.
We're a bit different from Quarkus.
We work not only on
each of our devices,
but we also combine
our devices in a functional
and smart way.
I'm working on React,
which I'm working on
with Grpc and Kafka.
Funky, as you've described it,
is our K-Native.
I think that
K-Native
is one thing,
but there are
some specifications
that you can annotate.
Your application is portable.
I have a question, Dra탑o.
Did you say what K-Native is?
I said K-Native.
You'll see that later.
That's because you said it.
I'm like that.
I don't even know
what K-Native is.
I don't know what K-Native is.
K-Native would be
an abstraction
that helps you
if you have a Kubernetes,
to deploy your app
and run it
in the Kubernetes environment.
If you have a bigger app
and you want to say
now we have this version,
now I would like a new version
of the same app, a newer version.
I would like only a part of the traffic
to the new version.
That's something you solve
with Istio, right?
Yes, it's cool in this
related space.
Maybe you're competitors in this,
but it's an abstraction
that can deploy and manage
versions.
If you don't have that,
then you can add
routing,
different ways of versioning
and
this layer.
If you're using
a Google Cloud Platform,
you have Google Cloud Run,
which is fully managed in Kubernetes
and they give you K-Native above that.
That's their Google Cloud Run
offering.
You just transfer it,
build an app, build a container,
tell it to go up and K-Native
and these layers will manage
everything else.
Maybe
Istio is probably in the same space.
I mean,
part of it
you can probably solve
in a different way.
It's also true that Kubernetes
and the whole space is still
very fast.
Maybe in the time
this debate will end.
It worries me a lot
that we're still
complicating the ecosystem.
But I think we're consolidating everything.
You can be surprised that Kubernetes
is more stable.
It's not about being stable.
The problem is that it's too complex.
I mean,
if there were
some projects that were
glued together
and then banished,
now there is
maybe K-Native will win,
it will dominate.
I didn't have any feeling
that Kubernetes was so unstable.
No, it's not unstable,
but it's too complex.
I mean,
it's highly complex.
You don't know
which project you will
run on Kubernetes.
In the beginning it was simple,
then they added features,
now it's even better
when you write a book.
I think that
I've talked a lot about Kubernetes.
I hope I'll be able to talk about it.
I hope you'll listen to it.
I wish you good health.
Luka wrote a book about Kubernetes
and Action, if I'm right.
Now I'm correcting myself.
I think he said that the first book
was about 300 pages.
This is the new edition,
which is almost 900 pages long.
But look,
this is just the content in Kubernetes.
The question is
if there will be anything else.
The environment is so complicated
that
you need to know
why you need this environment
and what kind of problem you're solving.
It's not like
Kubernetes is
the solution
for your problem.
Additionally,
you need to know
where to start.
It's a big pain.
That's true,
but I also think
that a lot of things
that are out of the box
if you don't know they exist,
if you don't know they work,
you'll spend a lot of time
writing it in your app layer.
Or when we talked about
service,
you need to know this part
and not everything else.
That's part of it.
How to design
a good architecture.
That's what you need to know.
How to make a good architecture
in this world.
I'm left-handed.
I remember
four years ago
if I'm not mistaken,
five years ago,
four times two,
I remember
when we installed
Netflix stack.
They wrote it
in all possible languages.
All the main tasks
like load balancing, failover,
tracing,
and all the tasks
supported by Istio.
They were working on it
and they could
write it in all possible languages.
Jager would be fine,
open tracing would be fine,
telemetry would be fine,
and so on.
Load balancing
wasn't right
and it was clear
that they won't be able
to write it anymore.
The app was nice,
you can always get stuck
in bytecode manipulation
and you hack the byte
and it goes inside.
Some things were nicely written
and there were always some interceptors.
Interceptors on web,
interceptors on Bin,
interceptors on Kafka.
A lot of things went nicely inside
and where it didn't,
there was a byte agent.
It went inside
and appeared in Istio
and we decided
that we don't need it anymore.
We'll forget about the booklets
and we'll give everything to Istio.
Four years later
and I practically
don't see it anywhere.
I hope we'll be able
to convince them.
I don't work with Istio,
I talk to them
but I hope
they'll tell me
what's Istio and what's that.
All these problems
bring you a trade-off
for which
you have to decide.
And then it's
do you want
additional complexity
and will it solve
your problem
or will you shoot yourself in the leg?
And it's easy
to add complexity.
It's full of complexity.
Maybe in this context
since we're talking
about Quarkus,
I don't know,
you can also split Quarkus
into JBoss.
All the projects
you've worked on
are huge projects.
These are really
big projects.
JBoss is huge.
Not only are they huge projects,
these are projects
that are massively used.
Massively used and really huge.
Can you give
an example
to the world
of people who
are connected
to bigger projects
or who
want to contribute
to bigger projects
or have a challenge
to go to bigger projects.
How do you navigate
such huge codebases?
How do you load them?
How do you build a mental model
of where things are?
How do things work?
Do you manually
select all 10,000 files?
How do you build a picture
of those projects
so you can manage them?
Can you build on them?
If you start from scratch,
it's easier.
If you start with a project,
it doesn't grow overnight
to a million layers.
It takes some time.
For example,
if it's so big
that I have to
write my IntelliJ part
with memory
to make it work normally,
you need an orange laptop.
If you start from scratch,
it's easier.
You prepare step by step.
Sometimes you get lost
because you have your part
and they have theirs.
I haven't been a fan,
but I've never had time
to look at it.
If you start later,
it's harder.
You have to find a way
to look at it
from the beginning,
the basics,
the things you wouldn't do.
For us,
a lot of people
have one thing
that they know how to do.
I came from
a lot of those
kernel systems,
class loading,
so I was familiar
with Quarkus.
Then I worked
with GRPC and Kafka
and then I focused on that.
I didn't come
from the beginning of Quarkus,
but I got used to it
and I used it all the time.
I used it all the time,
I was interested in it,
and I think I did a good job.
You shouldn't give up.
If you see something
and you quickly solve it,
I don't give up
and I try to do it in a nice way.
I remember one time
when I was sitting down
and I was a bit confused
about Quarkus.
I wasn't satisfied,
so I downloaded the second
and the third version
and then I started coding.
In the beginning,
when we were alone,
we found those books
in the library,
and then we were alone
and I was building sources
and linking them
and connecting them
to the IDE.
Now you have Maven
and Maven pulls you down
and you learn how to debug
and how to jump.
I hope you didn't skip React.
And you jump,
and you jump from the beginning
of the application
when you go through Quarkus
from the start to the end
and you look at what's in the stack,
in the stack trace,
and you look at what's going on
behind it.
You have to be persistent.
Thank you.
It's such a big problem
that I didn't even look at it.
It was a simple web application.
It's a complex application
and when something is called,
Lambda is connected
but Lambda also hides problems.
You know what?
I want to ask you this.
When you have people
who are juniors
at the beginning of their journey,
even you,
when you first started Quarkus Codebase,
it was also scary for you.
I'd like to hear
if it's normal
that it's such a huge project
and it's normal
that at the beginning
you don't understand it,
but then you start using it
and you start getting to know it
more and more.
Even when you try
to understand it.
I've been doing things like this
for 16 years,
big projects like this.
When I first started
a year ago,
I didn't understand anything.
I didn't know anything.
And then I started.
To contribute,
when we all started,
I had a bug,
you didn't work
and now you look
and it's not your problem
that it's not your code
and your configuration.
You try a little
and you fix it.
You look at it.
You'll know from that trace
even if it's a deep reaction
to you.
Sometimes there will be a bug
and it will be very difficult
to find it.
I don't know.
You have to take steps.
Even if at the beginning
you seem very dangerous,
yes, you are on one side,
but nobody knows everything.
Even here.
For us at JBoss
there were a few people
like Scott Stark
and Adrian Brooks.
They were crazy.
They probably knew everything.
The rest didn't.
Quarkus is a bigger problem.
Quarkus,
as I said in the beginning,
the core of Quarkus
and how it starts
is not so big
because
it's big because
it has a few hundred extensions.
That's what makes it look like that.
So when you go down to the application
and you use an extension
and they use another problem
and so on, you can get lost quickly.
Here's a question.
As a hardcore developer
on such large projects,
what are the tools
you use
that you can't live with anymore?
They can be commercial,
open source.
In your environment,
in your work,
what are the tools
you can't imagine
You have to have two bikes.
Oh, I see.
A road bike and a mountain bike.
It's like
when you go out on a bike
and then come back in two hours.
That's a smart question.
How many kilometers will you do this year?
Maybe that, and then you'll go up.
What else?
I have a feeling that
I'm having a little fun,
but because you ride a lot,
you probably have a lot of time to think.
Yes, that's true.
You give yourself a little time
to think,
because sometimes
time just passes by
and then you can't do anything
and you just ride a bike.
The other thing is that
you don't go to bed for a long time
and then you get up
in the middle of the night
and you go back to it.
You have time
when you can't do anything
and then you breathe a little
and then you go a little like that.
But yes, this tool is so interesting.
First of all,
you don't need a lot of things.
What do I have in the terminal?
I still have an old school.
If I have any tools
from the terminal,
I have a default
soft terminal.
I don't download anything special.
I wrote a few shortcuts
so that I don't have to type a lot.
A good IDE,
IntelliJ.
Now you have a free version
for a lot of things
that you don't need
in any enterprise.
A pen-like laptop
to have a little more memory
because you need it
in such a part.
Because everyone wants
to always have a mini cube
and that's it.
It's so interesting
that I would need a lot of things.
All those profilers
that are up and down
I would need a lot of things
but very rarely.
I also have other teams
that are performance teams
and they deal with it.
The only similar profiler
that was
and they are fast
and want to have a paid one.
But you need
through Jstack
and it dumps the part
or in the IDE
you have to
look at those snapshots
and that's it.
IntelliJ is enough for you.
Yes, a lot more.
Great.
Ok.
Nothing more.
We will talk about this part
until the end
and then we will see
where we are going.
We are almost at the destination
of Slovenia.
Open source
doesn't work without community.
It's somehow connected.
between people, and it doesn't work without people who contribute, who push for the development.
In Slovenia, there is a community OpenBlend, which is currently the largest Java, JVM, meetup, or community in Slovenia.
The only one.
The only one, yes.
Where do you decide what OpenBlend is, how long have you been doing it, where do you decide?
I will tell you about it in my forum, Levanski.
There goes another spongebob.
Yeah, yeah, we forgot about him.
He will drink the beer himself.
No, with all the things we talked about...
But was it decided in advance?
I mean, was it decided in the beginning?
I don't think so.
What is OpenBlend?
So, OpenBlend is...
I think we are at the end of 2007.
I joined RedHat in 2006.
I was already an open source,
mostly everything I worked on was open source.
And I joined RedHat with those guys from Parsec,
who later joined me and RedHat.
We were already thinking,
that it would be a problem for us to get employees.
The best way to do that is
to prepare a meeting,
a conference,
to get to know each other,
on a monthly basis.
When we started,
every conference was a bit the same,
if we talk about development.
We were not OpenBlend,
we were Vest and Parsec.
We organized a meeting
in Ljubljana.
It was a great event.
And surprisingly,
there were 150 of us.
We were there the whole time.
You knew Java 1.2,
and you went to the meeting?
No, it was just for listening.
It was for everything.
It was hardcore.
The idea was,
that the conference would be
as we would like it to be.
No bullshit PR,
no marketing,
just hardcore in Java.
To get programmers
who do it,
and you can teach them.
Good food,
good company,
good beer,
and so on.
At every moment,
you can find a hardcore developer,
and you can get him
even if he is not as good as you.
We got such people,
that it was hard to get them
from the sky,
when they were talking about their projects.
When we did that,
we were like,
let's get some people.
I went there,
and I got a few people.
I don't know who is drinking,
who is crying,
what is it about?
You are a one man band,
and we are an open blend.
We want to distance ourselves
from individuals like us.
We want to make a society,
and a society for everyone.
A society of protocols,
We got together,
and we said,
that it would be better
if we could get some sponsorship.
Not to get a lot of money,
but to give something.
People gave us money,
and we were like,
okay, cool.
We got so many people,
that we could do monthly events,
like Caf챕 Babe,
and conferences.
We were spreading from one track
to two tracks,
from two tracks to three tracks,
and back and forth.
But we were spreading.
At one point,
Oracle bought Sun,
and I bought Java.
Sjok,
the Slovenian Oracle user group,
was also involved,
so they were helping a bit.
And we were already
splitting up,
because they were
Oracle's partners,
and we were the rest.
But we got together
as a group,
and they were
normal people,
not like Oracle,
Fama, Gart,
etc.
They changed a lot,
and in the last few years,
we've been doing
2.8, 2.9,
and from 2.10 to 2.15,
we've been an open band.
We've been together as an open band
and Sjok,
and we're still singing history.
Before Corona,
it was phenomenal,
I've never seen so many people.
In the beginning,
we went from Ljubljana to Jable,
from Jable to the beach,
and from the beach we went,
I think,
once or twice,
to the beach,
because it wasn't fancy.
Then we went to Portoro탑je,
and Portoro탑je is a winner.
Before Corona,
there were 400 people,
it was crazy.
Corona slowed us down a bit.
But we're good with that.
We always played in October,
and now we went in June,
and it was even better,
it was warm,
and people come to work.
We try to keep the concept alive.
We, as an open band,
keep the concept alive,
and when things get better,
we go to the beach,
and that's how it all started.
All the big companies
started to show up,
like Evangelists,
and when you want to get someone,
you try to contact Evangelists,
and you have to ask
to get a cover.
I know them personally,
but I can't ask them all.
I don't know all of them,
and I can't ask them
to sing for me.
But the concept is still
quite similar,
I would say.
Developers, Evangelists,
a lot of things,
and you know who to turn to.
Good food,
and a good evening.
I would also like
to thank Sky Union
for the Make It conference.
The speakers were very good,
and the engineers were very good.
There were some people
who came to sell
fake tickets,
which is fine,
but I don't know,
there were people from Oracle Labs
from the Danube,
who have a PhD,
and they program Oracle,
VM, whatever,
and everyone talked,
because they were very approachable.
It was very good,
I would say.
I recommend
that people go to these events.
Honestly,
I notice that
the older population
goes to these events.
I would like to see more students,
younger population,
but here.
Be approachable
at these conferences.
JVM is not that sexy.
No, no.
Maybe
we should commit to the conference.
What else will you do?
You had a meet-up,
I saw that a few years ago
on Kimber Peep's archive,
there were 12 recordings
of you talking about J-Boss.
All of them.
Yes, all of them.
What else
are you preparing for this month?
We finally slept a bit,
during the summer,
as always,
and every time
we have some free time,
from Kimber Peep to Polygon,
when we have nowhere to go,
we lack a bit of motivation,
but
in Ljubljana,
there are some places
suitable for that.
So, on November 24th,
which is
almost...
We will see when we will go out.
November 24th,
you will be here
in Ljubljana Tech,
in BTC,
Oto will give us the link.
We will give all the links.
We will start the season
with OpenBlend.
We will have a place
in Aquarcus,
but with some slides
and some technical details.
We will show some codes.
And Oto will be here.
Yes, Oto will be here.
It's interesting,
this Ljubljana Tech
is such an interesting place.
They worked hard
and it's worth a visit.
Then you decide
if that's it or
you are still struggling.
I would like to add
that
in the community,
you have meetups
and conferences.
But the point
is not only in those.
The point is in the community
to meet other people
who work in these ecosystems,
who work in these technologies,
to solve problems and questions.
I would like to add
that you are a very open
community.
As far as I know you
you are a Red Hat guy.
Well, beer is healthy.
And it's expensive.
Yes, but with milk
it will be even better.
Only with milk
it will be difficult.
I was a bit surprised
when we had
all those events
and when we
organized everything.
My co-workers
were not programmers
but they were former programmers
and then they had a community guy
and they innovated a bit.
Dimitri Senket
had a very good lecture
on how to become an open source contributor.
And then there was
a party and that's it.
We didn't have a good day.
More people didn't
come.
There were five of us
and then four of us
went to do something else.
Various people
came.
We didn't...
Well,
when we met
we didn't really talk
but they told us that
we came from a community.
We met on some other lines
and then we debated.
They found me
and I told them that I'm a fan
and that I'm a good guy.
Lazo came to me
and he convinced me
and we started to work together.
I helped him a bit
and he's still happy.
If he was here
we could do it.
You contribute a bit
you see yourself.
You contribute more and more
and then you need it
when you need
to be together.
Now the question is
what is
the current state
in which the world is
in terms of hiring etc.
Please,
this will be the last question.
Well,
many years ago
we had some advantages
because we were almost single
and it was a remote culture.
We were encouraged
to work remotely
very easily.
It wasn't like now
when there was corona
and everyone could work from home.
The majority of people
who work at Middleware
are at home.
We don't have many
developers
in the world.
They are at home
and it was very
attractive.
In recent decades
the world has changed
and now I imagine
that we are not as sexy
as we used to be.
It doesn't surprise me
that people don't call me
because
only a few people
can get a job
for half a year
or even more money.
At that time
you could move
through Lusatia
or somewhere else
where you already had
big spaces
or you were at home
in your own environment
and that was it.
It didn't surprise me
that much.
In 2013-2014
we were at Vi큄ko
and I remember
that it was a very popular
and well-known project
in the world
and for us.
Luk큄a helped me
to work.
We were like hipsters
but outside
it was ok
Join OpenBlend
if you are interested
in Java and JVM
like everyone else.
Come to these events
because they are very open.
Ali큄 will greet you
and tell you how he talked.
Come!
Last question.
What did you ask him?
You said that you forgot
the last question.
No,
roadmap.
What is on the roadmap?
What is interesting?
What is waiting for us
in the next few years?
Maybe Red Hat
or
projects that you are working on?
Red Hat
is asking
that
we should not talk
we are not
we are not like
Google
First of all,
there are problems
but
for us
it is
Qarkus 3
that will have
two problems
one is Jakarta specification
that is micro problems
like
Java Enterprise
so that we can
Jakarta Qarkus
when it gets hot.
The other is
Project LUM
that is
because
the whole Qarkus
has a lot of written problems
like Reactive
Neti, above Neti is Vertex
and that is what enables
Reactivity.
Now we are losing these problems
and we need
to see
if Qarkus 4
or Qarkus 5
will be Qarkus
or Lumus
or something like that.
That is an interesting question
for us.
Because it will be for sure.
Those fundamental
changes will be lower
in terms of opportunities.
Yes, that is the future
If the trading model
will be replaced
so that you will not need
to work with virtual trading
imperatively
then everything will fall off.
Ok.
Exciting.
I will give you one last thought
and then we will finish.
One last thought.
What would I say to the world?
Yes.
Let's go for a beer.
No, no.
No,
I mean
Open Source
gave me a lot
and then you can live with it.
It is not just a service anymore
but it is a way of life
for me.
I never wanted
to choose something else
but I had some offers
from big companies.
Living at home
or living in a car
has its advantages
but if you see the world
it is also more stressful.
I organized my time
so that I can live
outside of work
with high quality.
Open Source
gave me a lot
and I got to know
a lot of interesting people
who are passionate
about their work.
You can see
why they are
so talented
and well made.
When you get to know
people like Gavin King
it is very interesting.
There are also
a lot of people
who I have already mentioned
a few times
who taught me a lot
Adrian Brock
you took me
under your wing
and I grew a lot with them
and you are also
a very fascinating person
who you never know
but you know about Gavin King
and you meet him
in the middle of the road.
Don't be afraid
to adjust to Open Source
because one or two bugs
will join you.
We are not the only ones
we are the biggest
Open Source in the world
but we are not
the only ones.
Ale큄 Justin
thank you for your time
and your contribution
to Open Source
and thank you
for your time.
If you liked this episode
please share it with your friends
give us some feedback
and see you
next time.
Good luck
and goodbye.