Welcome to a new episode of Grodje. Today we will try a little more unscripted
again and very organically talk a little more about our podcast. We will try
to talk a little about the feedback we get, we will try to talk about the future of this podcast.
We will discuss the production, we will discuss how we see this part, what could go forward.
We can also talk about some of the experiences we have gained, we can talk about the mistakes we made.
Let's make a break today. Knowledge is also one dollar today.
I write in the comments that you are a sound wizard, but I think I could call it a multimedia wizard,
because you don't just work with sound and you are at home in the whole production industry.
You also knew Andraža, Andraž Brodnik, Brodol and Andraž Sraka.
Everyone, welcome and ...
I hope you are quiet.
With this intro, I asked myself all kinds of questions.
It's hard to talk when there are four of us, because I can't hear a single word.
It was hard when you said that intro. It's not scripted, but you put it that way.
A cover or a device that we don't like.
Today there will be a lot of debate. Today there will be only debate.
Today there will be only debate.
Unscripted, against everything else, very structured.
Turn off your notes.
So, maybe ...
Let's start from the beginning.
What's on your mind?
People complain that we have such good sound quality,
that when they drive on the road, they hear our alarms and sirens in the background.
That's a real problem.
It's almost as if I would let go of those comments.
But I really try to hear them as little as possible.
But you can't cut everything out.
Today we have a lot of people here with a hot microphone.
And we got ...
Jan drove from Maribor.
And he's actually right in the back, so you can hear us so well.
It would be really interesting ...
I think we could make an episode about that,
so it would be a role play for those who are interested.
I can make an interlude here,
and then I'll edit it.
I know I edited it.
And then I'll put it back together.
I think that's the easiest way.
So you can see how much work is needed
and you get a pretty good result that is audible.
It's really interesting to me,
because everyone praises the sound quality,
and I know that I could do a lot more
to hear myself a little better.
It's always free for everyone,
so I think it's something new we're studying.
So yeah, now we're at 60% of what you'd like.
60% of what we're doing with this setup in this environment.
Yes.
And then ...
Do you want to say that we can get another 40% from this microphone?
Yes.
We're taking a little more space here,
so it would be possible to do a lot more,
but editing would be a little more complicated.
Considering that we switched from mono to stereo,
I don't know if I can correct that.
But it's still known,
because the one on the left or the one on the right
can cover a lot of space.
It goes a little further than me.
If you look at professional podcasters,
they have 4 or 5 microphones,
and some networks,
would you dramatically improve that?
Would you go further?
Definitely, there would be less sounds
from the road or something like that,
because you have a microphone for every speaker,
almost in front of your mouth,
which doesn't pick up and practically does nothing.
But we would be able to do that.
You'll see how everything dies.
Yes, we'll see how everything dies.
I mean, we have the opportunity.
Something is still dying.
I mean, technically,
yes, a lot of different things.
In my opinion,
whatever we switch, it will be more like it is.
It's also nice that we can set it up quickly
and that you always have the easier work.
I care about the infrastructure in the information system.
I appreciate it when people
and the product of their work,
if it's written in a good way,
so that I don't have to work.
So that I understand your pain,
and I think I spent 10 years in CyberPip
taking care of the sound and recording on cassettes.
I didn't edit it,
but I heard that I worked the hardest
so that there were no microphones.
And I also understand the life of technology
and I know how underappreciated it is.
That's why this will be a typical journalist's question
where do you go to primary school?
No, I won't answer that.
I think you are probably the best
in multimedia and journalism,
and in the way you work.
I think we are all better.
I think Draž will probably answer that.
More theoretically,
I tried a lot of things in this field.
In every episode I try to learn something,
to be better.
And I realized that this microphone
is not as scary for our guests
as if I gave it to someone
on a t-shirt,
or if I told them to hold it in their hands
or to throw it in front of them.
Or maybe I gave them headphones.
Yes, like a studio.
And probably this is also related
to our format where we try to simplify it
so that the guests are simplified
and we also try to be organic.
Maybe it sounds a bit weaker
so that we don't have 60%
or 100% or maybe 65%
so that we have only organic guests.
Because it seems to me that in the beginning
people make mistakes in the first few minutes,
in the first 10 minutes,
then they will forgive themselves.
And then when you go,
you try to make the sound
between the conversations
so that people don't fall.
People will wonder what kind of microphone is this.
Look, now I can take a picture
and they will see what it looks like.
We will put it somewhere.
No, I don't think it's strong enough.
Let's go back first.
How did you find each other?
How did the idea come about
that we are now in the second or third episode
and that we don't have to do the production ourselves
and we need a person who will assist us here?
Let's solve that first.
That's a good question.
The part where we are together,
we will talk about it later.
We didn't know that we had
the same part together.
We recorded it.
In the beginning it was like a joke,
now I see it as a start-up
or as a business story.
When I see something working,
people reacting well,
then I evaluate it.
It pays off a lot of time, energy,
knowledge, money and so on.
If you do things like that,
you want to have a good team
and you want to lay a good foundation.
That's the point,
to lay a good foundation.
We need a good personality,
how we will attract people,
how we will discuss things.
These are things we need to fulfill.
On the other hand,
you want a well-equipped infrastructure,
well-founded foundations,
on which we can build.
If the microphone has some capabilities
and we don't use them to the maximum,
then it's not an opportunity for me.
Jan is in charge of sound,
but in the back he is also in charge
of multimedia and multimedia production,
which means that in the next phase,
when that phase is over,
when the time is right,
we will also go into video,
streaming and so on.
If we do that,
I think Jan also has a lot of experience
in this area.
You can't do it alone,
you have to cooperate
and look for people
you can cooperate with.
It's a common theme.
You sound like an overseller
from Brazil.
A lot of people still haven't answered
how you found Jan.
I met him in the back.
This podcast wouldn't have been possible
if I hadn't met him in the back.
The people I met in the back
are people I have cooperated with
before or still cooperate with,
similar to other projects.
In this case,
he connected me to Jarnej Gračner.
He is a multimedia master
for 15 hours in Maribor.
Jarnej, if you can hear me,
I greet you nicely.
He says that if I need
an artistic work
for a Slovenian developer,
I ask him,
if I need other graphic elements,
etc.
Jarnej is the one
I turn to.
He also has the best experience
with streaming.
He made me a title
for the podcast
and he contacted me.
That's how we came together.
The rest is history.
Then you offered him
a recording
and he said,
this is not it.
I gave him a cover
for 5000 euros
and I said,
let's do an episode.
Each episode costs
5000 euros minus.
So, if you can hear me,
let's make a deal.
That would be great.
I pay more as a developer.
No, I mean,
I don't think
we have a deal yet.
I mean,
he contacted me.
In the first episode,
we started adding
ideas
on how to
continue recording.
I think that's
getting better.
Now we have
optimized
the setup,
the microphone,
and so on.
But post-production,
when you get the recording,
you have a lot of work to do.
Yes.
You can write
what was...
What is it like
for the listeners?
What must be done
in post-production?
You can start
by yourself.
What to do with the sound
in post-production?
What are the possibilities?
What can be done?
What can't be fixed?
The main thing is the volume.
It has to be loud enough,
but it can't be too loud.
When you can
reduce the volume,
then everything is
loud.
You have to reduce it
and set the limits
so that it's loud enough.
That's how it works.
In addition,
the noise is removed.
It's not all
complicated.
You have to go through
the recording,
listen to it,
and so on.
You can see
the recorded sound.
You can see it in the graph
if someone speaks too quietly.
Then you can
raise the volume
or reduce it
if it's too loud.
It's usually when you laugh
or when someone speaks too loudly.
That's when the noise
starts and you have to
reduce it.
You can automate it,
but I don't do it
at the moment
because I'm listening to it
directly from the podcast.
That's
the most basic thing.
It's a suitable software.
How do you work with it?
What's the hardware
software that
makes it the easiest for you?
I've been
using the standard
Adobe programs
for a few years now.
When it comes to
DaVinci Resolve,
which is Blackmagic,
we do everything
with DaVinci.
It's a great software.
I can do anything with it.
I'm using it now.
Is it something
that you would call
industry standard?
What do most people
use?
It depends on
the industry.
If we look at
big media sites,
like RTV,
they definitely use
software that's
more for their industry standard.
What I'm using
is
from freelance
to
the beginning of Hollywood,
because DaVinci became
very strong in the film industry.
It started with color grading,
but they added
a lot more.
There are some
shortcomings,
but you can do
practically anything.
I wouldn't say
that it's beyond
any standard.
Maybe it's on a
professional level,
because
CDs,
I don't know,
it's a music production.
You don't record music.
But it's a tool that you use
not only for sound editing,
but also for video.
Everything works with it.
It's primarily a video program.
I had it at the beginning
on colors,
but the whole editor
and the section
where you have
effects,
various visual effects.
It's kind of like Unreal.
At first,
it was something,
but now it's...
I don't know if DaVinci
is one program,
but it's a suite of problems
that you can solve
or work on.
Color grading,
pictures,
3D animation.
That's what I like
most about DaVinci.
Every program is special.
You have Premiere for
editing,
After Effects for effects,
Audition for sound.
Everything is special,
and you can re-open it.
DaVinci has a section
where you put
everything from the project.
It's easier to work
with a team,
because everything is packed.
They also
developed a cloud
collab,
where you get a version
of a NAS system,
but everything is
connected.
I still have to try
that,
or get to know someone
who got it,
because everything is
automated.
You keep the main files
in DaVinci.
Everything is generated
in proxy.
Everything is done
at the same time,
on the same project.
It's not that complex.
I still don't get it.
Let's talk about
audio reproduction.
Files are huge.
Our 2 hours
is about 2 GB.
It's just sound.
Do you have any problems
with the volume?
It depends
how long the recordings are,
and the quality.
For sound,
for podcasts,
I try to keep
the best quality possible.
Now we have
a 20-bit WAV file.
It's a 2 GB file,
but it's not
that big.
If I compare it
to a video,
it would probably be
more than enough.
When I record
pro-res formats,
with less compression,
these are huge files.
If I wanted
to put a camera here,
and record 2 hours
with more sound and video,
would it be 1 TB file?
No.
Probably
for such a long recording
you don't need
such quality files.
You record
as much as you can
in some mp4 format.
In the end,
I would definitely
record a podcast video
on my phone,
because it's enough.
For someone to record
a podcast for 2 hours,
and watch it from the side,
and then want
an extra-nice 6K picture,
I don't know.
I believe that only the sound
plays here.
The better the sound,
the better the quality.
I have a question.
Can you record 1 hour
of video on your phone?
It's not about the power.
The question is,
I can check that.
I've seen so much
in other video games,
that I don't know about the phone.
It's probably more
about the app.
If it was a basic app,
like mine,
DSLRs and mirrorless cameras
are limited to half an hour.
If you would record
longer than half an hour,
there wouldn't be more cameras.
There's also
trade agreements.
All of them are limited
to 29 minutes.
It's a bad video.
You can record it,
but you have more power.
Speaking of sound quality,
we're recording in stereo.
The recorder has two microphones,
so we're recording in stereo.
You mentioned the noise.
What does it have to do
with the stereo?
Can you
check the noise
with the two microphones?
It's not a glitch.
I made the left and right channels
smaller.
We're in the middle,
and both microphones
are relatively the same.
Andraža and Ota
are on their own side.
If one of them speaks,
the other channel basically
does the talking.
In the beginning,
I make both channels
as my own mono recordings.
So, the noise
on these two channels
is drastically reduced
and the environment
and the sound.
That's the first step
we took
with the stereo.
Everything is known.
I'll ask Andraža.
When you said
you chose the recorder,
we were in Maribor
and he asked me to bring
the recorder to look at it.
And I said,
we have this,
what can we do with it?
You know,
when you see a person
who is really into his industry,
when he holds it in his hand,
it's like click, click, click.
It's a completely different setting.
We do it differently.
When someone says,
oh, you have a recorder,
I look at it and say,
no, don't touch it.
That was just because
you didn't want to bring it.
No, it was because
it took so long.
You know what else I learned?
People won't know,
but there was an episode
where I thought
I had recorded it for an hour
and then I realized
it had been recorded for 10 minutes.
And then I apologized to the guest.
We didn't film for 40 minutes, I'm an amateur and I don't know how to continue, and it took up a lot of space for us.
So, if you can do something wrong in the roster, fix it, and then try again, it's practically a waste of time to try again.
The guest says it for an hour, then he goes back, and then once again, the whole debate, me and you, it's fucked up.
If I remember correctly, the guest said that he would say it even better.
Yeah, he said it even better. On the other hand, we had a hard time, because we didn't know if we had already discussed certain things,
or not, and it was already a bit... It was especially hard.
The main thing is, when you work on a production, you can edit some things, you can clean some things,
but when it comes to personality, you can't fix mistakes, and that's why it's good to have someone who knows the industry.
And Brian Vodilte doesn't make automatic mistakes.
No, no, no. He just starts something. On the other hand, Brian Vodilte tells you how you should look at it,
how much space you still have, and what you should fix.
That's true.
Yeah, yeah.
But, a bit on his side, I don't know. When it comes to formats and similar things, it's not in Vodilte.
I mean, he shows you how to fix it, but...
Oh, I made a mistake there.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
I think, in the end, it's important, if you're doing a podcast, to do it in stereo,
and if I don't have any problems with the production, which we didn't have, in the end, it was all the same to us.
Then, how to do a trade-off between the important resolution and the frequency of the sound.
What do I know? I know, as an electrician, when they told me,
Hey, you have a TV signal here, send it to me.
As someone who listens to it, or someone who studies it professionally, what is it now,
do we need to have a very high frequency, or more beats?
You never know.
Yeah, I mean, both for the video, and for the sound, and for everything.
In fact, the more quality the file you record,
the more quality it is, the more friendly the format is, the bigger the files are,
but they are so big, because you need so much information,
with which you can work in post-production.
So, that's just a trade-off.
Because, for example, those first recordings, I think they were shot in MP4,
for example, there, the noise, it was hard to erase the noise.
Because there is no program, there is no data, there is no beat.
So, wow, the format is raw, not lost, right?
Well, no, I wouldn't say it's raw.
So, 24 beats, we record...
Stereo.
Stereo, and how many frequencies do we have?
48,000.
48,000, OK. So, I can't have a very high 5.
I mean, you can try, and then...
But you won't hear it.
But wouldn't it have the same standard as a CD?
No.
CD has half.
Phew, now you got me.
Beats have less.
Yeah, beats have less.
The other one has...
I mean, 48 kHz, but how much is on a dance floor, then...
CD quality is definitely compressed.
When you ask like that, if an album on a CD is 45 minutes,
then it goes to 700 megabytes,
and we wait for an hour, it goes to 2 gigabytes.
I mean, really, it's...
Right?
So...
If you...
Yeah, you could look at how fast the dance floor is,
and you would hear it quickly.
With videos, I'm more consistent with those numbers,
than with audio.
I have a very basic question.
Like, okay,
at first, you didn't do it like that,
for a videographer, and everyone taught you that,
but where did you learn all that stuff?
That's a very good question.
That's an error?
Yeah, I would say so.
I've always been a geek with some technology,
whatever it was.
I've been with computers for many years,
and then I just kept doing it.
And, yeah, I mean, it changes.
I always say that everything is in the menu,
it's all written for you,
what's there, click and type.
So, yeah, I follow that logic.
I look at what's written,
and if it's useful, I type it.
But yeah, okay, in the back,
I know a little, theoretically,
what needs to be done, but...
Did you go to school?
Oh, yeah, yeah, okay.
I don't know.
So, you went to school,
and then you did podcasts.
No, no, because you asked me
where I learned all that stuff.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
You didn't go to school,
where you learned all that stuff.
I mean, you studied multimedia, right?
No, I studied media communication.
Oh, sorry.
We didn't, okay,
we didn't just work technically
in the media and production,
and everything,
but also from other perspectives,
why and how, and stuff like that.
But that other geek talk,
which I really like,
media criticism,
and stuff like that.
Media criticism?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Now we have a debate here,
and we can do some media criticism.
I did a podcast, which is just
positivism, without criticism.
I got that feeling.
Criticism is so positive.
Yeah, that's true.
But anyway,
through the media studies,
I was absolutely lucky
with a slightly higher level
of production equipment,
which is different.
That's the best compliment I've ever heard.
I mean, okay,
I'm not as lucky as I am,
because I did something else
when I went to lectures.
But yeah,
more than anything else,
I fell into the details.
Yeah,
we'll stop there.
Okay.
I made a mistake
when we were talking
to Jan last time,
and we started asking him,
well, okay,
who will do it?
Who has to do it?
I have to do it,
you have to do it.
And he said,
that's a great question.
I can send you an example
of what an agenda looks like
for social media,
communication,
plan, division.
I said, we could make more clips.
But it's still yours.
It's still your job.
Now,
I would like you
to tell us
if you get,
if you have a real budget,
or if,
whatever it is,
it doesn't matter,
and you have to put together
a media plan,
an agenda,
how will you release it,
where will you put it?
Okay.
Do you have an idea
of what this podcast
could look like?
No, I would like to see
and listen to
what this preparation
or agenda looks like
that you have to prepare
for some other
production team.
Let Tomáš decide.
Okay,
I'll try to simplify it a bit.
Because,
first of all,
you have to decide
what kind of market
you're entering,
what you're doing,
and then,
depending on the market
and what you start with,
you'll see
what you can cover.
And now,
the podcast probably won't
go to social media,
but in the magazine,
on the other hand,
it's a standard to do marketing
through social media,
because you don't get paid
for anything else,
especially not for something
that is absolutely
digitally distributed.
So, you stay digital.
What are the social media
that are
interesting enough
for...
Boomer questions.
We only left one on Twitter.
So, what's next?
Now, maybe a better question
is where not to go.
Okay, fair enough.
So,
if you remember
everyone you want to meet,
I mean, you want to be present,
even if it's just
a re-share of your other
profiles.
Now, for the podcast,
again, who will listen to
the podcast?
Is it for the younger audience
or for the older ones,
or is it for everyone?
If it's only for the older ones,
don't put it on TikTok.
I don't know
what's going on
on Snapchat.
I don't think
everyone is for something like that.
So, I would say
everything is covered.
Now, TikTok has to be covered
even if you're doing, I don't know what.
It's funny to meet
people who clean the table,
I don't know, the facade,
the windows, and so on.
They are completely involved
in TikTok.
It's a huge conversion.
I mean, who...
Yeah, we're old.
Young entrepreneurs also have TikTok.
I think that
you have to ask yourself
why you would do it.
The question is
why someone
who cleans the windows
on TikTok
doesn't do it to sell on TikTok?
Yeah, or maybe not.
What's the endgame?
I don't know, but
if you look at a brand awareness
and you're present
and you see it,
that's why someone
is selling something.
I would say
let's say you're not on TikTok.
You can go to Facebook or Instagram
or maybe Twitter.
If you're on Facebook or Instagram
you will definitely post stories
and announce something.
Why wouldn't you post them on TikTok?
Yeah, if you're doing it.
I mean, the first problem
is to create content
and if you have content
it's almost nothing
because you're announcing everything.
I say almost because...
But you know what?
You said
media communication in the media.
But I think these channels have
everything specific.
If I put this person
on LinkedIn, there are people
who are more professional
and more...
industrial?
Everyone is on LinkedIn.
LinkedIn is special.
On TikTok we can't...
You have a non-professional relationship
that everyone knows.
I mean,
does it hurt you
if you post something
that's relevant
and those people who don't see it
don't care.
What if you post it on Parler?
But can we generally
look at these media
as a one-way TV channel?
Do we have to look at them
as a two-way channel?
I mean, if you want to have an engagement
and then look for an engagement
you have to look.
Look at the experience.
If you put this person
anywhere in the media
if there's no engagement
then it goes nicely
among other people.
When you think of content
you won't put a podcast
on TikTok, right?
But what to post?
I think
social media is a huge
pain when it comes to
presence, to promote
the main content.
These are absolutely
supportive channels
for what you do.
I've been saying
for a long time
that it doesn't matter
if you promote a community
or a person
to be heard
but you work for the algorithm
because if you don't
persuade the algorithm
to push you forward
you can have the best content ever.
The algorithm wants quantity.
But the question is
do you want this war with the algorithm?
What's that?
Endgame.
It's like this.
We're hobby chablis
and we always have 12 girls
and we don't know
if we'll have 20 km per year
or 5 km per year.
If you're a professional chablis
then yes.
That's the debate
we had before we started
recording.
How are you going to pack it?
You're saying that
we should focus on good content
and how to hype it
well
and sell it well
or fight with the algorithm
to push the algorithm
but the content
won't be the best.
But I'll make sure
that I'll be seen
in the audience.
In the minds of people
or followers
you'll see that
there's a team
that starts
from the bottom
but the question is
are they that relevant
or do they have good content
or did they just destroy
the SEO against the algorithm
to get there?
A good example of this
is
a bad example of this
is content farming
or the YouTube
version of
tasty videos
or do-it-yourself hacks
or some
trash content
with billions of views
that does
exactly what you said.
They just push the algorithm.
No quality,
no business,
but it saves them
because that's their business model
to be seen.
If we look at this podcast
I believe that
it's set up well
and there are good guests
that's why I don't want to
fight with the algorithm.
Now
if you want to
distribute
and promote this good content
you need
to have this game.
But only because
your main content
will be seen
because if you post
once a week
with a podcast
the algorithm won't push
because you didn't have
other posts.
Even if you post
a meme every day
the algorithm doesn't recognize
what kind of question it is.
Consistent frequency.
Yes.
That's it.
You don't need to
study all the hacks
because
it doesn't pay off
because you start working
on Facebook,
you can hack the algorithm
as much as you want
if you don't give them
everything.
Maybe we'll see
I don't know.
I have some experiences
from another project
where
it turned out
that
there is
such a specific person
that it turned out
that this specific targeted audience
exists on Twitter
and then they tried
to do the same on Facebook,
Instagram and so on
and they quickly realized
that they can't do it.
That's because
it's a very specific topic
and it's a step
of quite a lot
of influencers
that we know
that pushed
the fight
against the algorithm.
I can imagine
that it's hard
if you have
a very specific task
and then it's easy
to push it out.
I remember
that you participated
in some festivals
and now you're talking
about meetups
and events.
Yes, specifically
for B-sides and so on.
Your success
of one event
depends on
how many people
you attract.
I think that
for this use case
Facebook is
a place where you can
attract money.
You can't build
such a big audience in such a short time.
Facebook also told you
a funny story.
Yes, probably it's
a hole in the fence
and you have to pay
a lot of money
to get there.
It's an ongoing game.
That's how it is with Facebook.
First you upload some content
and after some time
you get a post
pay 5 euros to reach
1000 of your followers
and when you
say it
you pay
5 euros
and then
21 euros
and at the end
you say
it's just a platform
where we will passively reference
content or events
on that platform
and we will not
look at it.
Do you think that
fighting against this algorithm
is not the same as
creating a good
base of followers
who consider
content as
a valuable
sharing?
And
this kind of base
starts to be shared.
You have more people
who try to share
the same content
and when you
share it
because
they see
here I learned something
and here I learned something.
It's worth hearing.
This is
an organic growth.
You have to get there.
And now
with this podcast
I think that
it's fully connected
and you can see
that it gets reach
I don't know
why it would be limited
only to this.
Maybe you don't fight
directly with the algorithm
but you prepare
one post a day
for a few months
whatever it is.
And that's it.
You just keep going.
Just to get there.
The problem is that it's not.
Because now someone
will go to the grave
and google it
and maybe they'll come to Anchor
and they'll want to see more
but now there are no profiles.
You said that the biggest problem
is that it's not on YouTube.
You have to search on YouTube.
Let's talk about
two things
that we can talk about.
One is the audience
and the other is the feedback.
Those things are very important.
Let's talk about that
and maybe we'll get more specific.
I think that the first audience
is still
the first degree network
meaning the people you know
the people you work with
that's the first network
you have around you.
We try to
lean on them
so they'll listen
and give us feedback.
You know that they're biased
because they know us
and the topic is very close
and maybe they live in that industry
but I don't know if it's because of us.
You're not old enough to listen to them.
My dad listened to that episode
I wrote him
and he was like
how much do you charge?
I think he listened to it with Janko.
My dad is
a real entrepreneur
and a manager
but yeah
he's an old school entrepreneur
and he's not close to the audience
so I can't say he's a target audience
and it would be pointless
for that audience.
But you get good feedback.
We get a lot.
I think that episode wasn't interesting
but there are other episodes
and other sections.
If you listen to Janko's speech
in a previous episode
in his own language
and he says
OK, that can't be interesting.
If you listen to the episode
with Rod Petrovic
when he talks about Slovenia
and the Serbian economy
it's interesting.
If you listen to the episode
where Saro talks about recruitment
and technology
it's possible
to expand
the population
but
Brodoj said something really good
about the core audience.
Do you agree with that?
How big should your audience be?
What?
Do you remember when you said
seven years?
Yeah, yeah.
That really resonates with me.
An engineer would think
what is a minimal viable product
but we think
what is a minimal viable audience.
For us
what is a minimal viable audience
is also a question.
What
do you expect from this podcast?
You need to know
OK, you have
four well-dressed people
who
sit here with a microphone
every one of us
worked on commercial projects
and deserve
a part of their apartment.
So
you need to ask yourself
how many people
cover you
no matter what it means.
And people are different.
I am a community of
a lot of people.
in the last 15 years
a lot of my life
and maybe a bit too much
and let's say
for me personally, this podcast
it turns out
to be very challenging
and has less words
than if I recorded an episode
from a textbook
yes, ok, we don't have
those... we don't have to
embrace ourselves as programmers
but
sometimes it's not a problem
or maybe
we'll say something later
maybe we'll combine it with
a physical event
on the other hand
I'm also thinking
about this anecdote about pornography
because I use it a lot
we've been waiting for this
we've been waiting for this, yes
I mean, people can watch
highly produced pornography
good actors, good cameramen
good actors, good screenwriters
make-up scene and so on
yes, yes
but in the end
this amateur porn
has its own passion
because it's not
highly produced
and now
it's hard to compete
with
a highly produced
American
content
we can start doing it in English
but in the end we'll get lost
in the sea
of this content
and that's the second
anecdote about pornography
you can have a girl
who speaks English like a stock
or a woman, we won't be chauvinists here
but maybe
a girl or a woman
who speaks Hungarian like a stock
I don't know
I mean, yes, ok
you still have to understand Slovenian
I want to know where
this will lead to
but I want to say
that maybe you'll find
a minimal viable audience
and that it's cool
and that you're happy with yourself
and you'll be able to
make money
because you're producing
or you're just filling it up with energy
and you're working for reference
or I don't know
Fame and glory
Jesus Christ
I don't know about that
I already understood that
this fame and glory
will be able to monetize
I mean, if we don't pour
pure wine
I was
active in CyberPipa
and we were fighting for sponsors
so that the space could exist
and when I went
to the company
it was like
ok, your content
is not for our pages
marketing, sales funnel
technological page
that I went to
to support
they said, if we're the first to sign up
these are not our pages
and now
they're listening to us
these are not even our pages
no matter how much time we spend on it
maybe
God will give
a good word
and he'll say
I think these people here
are really cool
in the community
maybe they'd just hire him
for 60€ per hour
to fix the Kubernetes cluster
you have to think
no
we'll do this
as a community
what is the minimal viable audience
and how
do you increase
or decrease it if you're in Slovenia
or do you want more
podcasts that are more comprehensive
that more people understand
if you have podcasts like Blissar
or Rodon
that are more approachable
but on the other hand
you lose the Hungarian
Janko
or at least me
that I'm coding in Kubernetes
I don't know
I think
I see it
as a community based
everyone
has a professional
career
and starts doing things
that
if I use
the words
of my father
we remember
but we remember
with a bit of passion
with a vision
that is based
on our professional
career or
something that we've already experienced
it can be anecdotes
it can be war stories
it can be events
we have our
social network of people
that are interesting
that we introduce them here
and their views
and experiences
and I
perceive it as
a return to the community
or
an awareness
that is happening here
my philosophy is very similar
my philosophy is
that
if
at some point in your career
I think at this point
in your life
you get the opportunity
to give back to the community
it's your duty
if you had a good mentor
to become a good mentor
and in a way
you try to give back
and
this podcast
meetups
Slovenian budget
and also
Slovenian development
and open source
if you give back
you improve the ecosystem
if the ecosystem is healthy
if the ecosystem is good
if people learn from these things
if they become better
and if they are better
if we have better projects
it's a blessing
for everything
and
if we build good
relationships
good
we exchange experiences
then we get
not partners, but co-workers
like a cat
a cat
it's all very healthy
the Hungarian industry is more English
I don't know
I just
as I would say
I look at it from a different perspective
when we got together
when he explained
the concept
who are the guests
and all that
and
his vision
and also
the access
to all these guests
and
I don't know
I see the potential
that this podcast will survive
because I think
it's not a
hard struggle
to get a guest
and with that also personal
the fact that it's
so niche is
an absolute plus
because if you cover a niche
even if it's in Slovenia
at first I don't accept
Slovenian guests
of course
but
they have their own value
absolutely
I don't know
because I'm not a developer
I just know this community
directly through
their forums
and it's obvious
that the engagement
that people are interested in
I don't know
if it's a need
maybe
I don't know
Do you think it's a need
if we turn it off in the morning
people will write
no, no
it would be nice to hear
I mean
probably if it comes to the routine
that people will watch it on Monday
in the morning
and then it will come
I don't know
Feedback is very interesting
because
we don't know
I mean we don't know
it will depend on what you most
agree with
that engagement
because of your engagement
that you started through social
is it really
interesting
because of the content
and they wanted
to give something back
I don't know
I think that
I would like to hear these things
I want these stories
that we make
to share
I want the stories
like Rodo's
Janko's
all the stories before
I think they are so powerful
inspiring stories
for young engineers
for experienced engineers
that it's possible
you are not crazy
if you do these things
people do these things
full of these stories
like you said
for a long time in the industry
you heard some horrible
and interesting stories
I think it's interesting
to share them
on the other hand
infrastructure
code, javascript
some niches
it's interesting
if we go now
to the feedback
maybe I mentioned
a lot of answers
maybe go to English
then you will have a bigger audience
maybe you will see
what kind of a guest he is
maybe here
I think that
in our podcasts
there were Turks
and Slovenes
who still live in Tuin
so we have a kind of Turks
let's speak English
we all work
for the English market
for 10 years
English is not a problem
for us as a host
even for our guests
the question is
how our audience
will react
will our audience accept it
or not
and then you start
to put it in the box
in some Tuin podcast
really?
I think to some extent
because the topic
when it comes to javascript
it's something
on a global level
it's not just about
Slovenian economy
the question is
will you
as an Englishman
I mean in English
say that you will target
the audience
maybe it will be interesting
but they will not be able
to change anything
if you target Slovenia
and some Slovenian listeners
who would be interested
this is the problem
they can engage
will we have Dr. Pedrama
security expert
in Slovenia?
in Slovenian?
yes or no?
I'm looking forward to meeting
a Slovenian woman
everything is possible
I would say
that
I think it's a unnecessary question
to work in Slovenian
or in English
one or the other
podcast
as such
the topic is
now
if the episodes are
more local
with local themes
they are absolutely
necessary in Slovenian
because no one in English
has listened to what is happening here in Ljubljana
on the other hand
why not
invite a Tuin guest
who will speak English
because then you will get
his audience
but also his local audience
you will get
who will know
the city because of where he came from
I don't know
I see it
as an added value
I think
it sounds very new
but here is the filmmaker
look how beautiful he is
look at him
he is right here
I think that
Slovenian people are
the basic filmmaker
and Ljubljana is
a bit more pro-filmmaker
the people
who are present here
will be a bit more relaxed
if they are human
if we work every day
we speak more English
than in Slovenian
I think that
I will not speak English
with Goran
I think
that is
one of the things
that adds simplicity
we are
we talked a bit
in the past
you have this framework
cool
about the framework
we can also
create sub-booklets
sub-things
and
all these episodes
go from
casually reading things
to almost meta-interviews
to
last time with Mark
we were more prepared
than we know
and the question is
do we need only
this platform
under this platform we can
create sub-titles
that serve
a different audience
or from a different point of view
you work for the audience
but this platform can
serve our creators
if I want to read
explicit content
be salty on
PHP
drink it
if I want to
it still has to be
a production need
coherent
it can also be classic
interviews where we have
more
more approach
this is the domain of interviews
no, no, no
I think
you said better
what you said
I definitely agree
it's an award
that can have its own path
do you think so?
absolutely
I think
bigger podcasts
have bonus episodes
or a special section
it's not a problem of diversification
the question is
we all know
I have a fantasy view
I have a feeling
what do you expect from this podcast
if you don't know
but what is it
it's a platform
that you can
experiment
but it's not
for real
to be able
to find
something for our
commercial product
and also
nobody dictates
how it goes
how not
I mean
here
he said it without agenda
the thing was
this section needs
a name
let's write a few names
and then
where did you get it
I hid it
internal dictatorship
is easy
it's cool
because
in a way it's a vision
not a direction
the worst thing
was that
you draw a plan
you stick to it
and then you realize
that it doesn't work
and you are stressed out
and I don't know
if there would be
feedback
do you have any questions
for these guests
and then additional questions
if it's real
if we go
back to feedback
when you sign up
for
YC Combinator
it's one of the best
professional accelerators
in the world
in San Francisco
Dropbox and similar companies
because it's a crime
to do a crime
and on a public image
from YCI
the question is
which things
does your startup start
in this phase
that is escalating today
which things are you doing now
or which things
do you start
that gave you
a look
at the beginning
and maybe later when
the corporation is in you
you don't have to
but at the beginning
they help you grow
and
a few things
that I see
and I will ask you
I see that it won't escalate
but now they are
extremely valuable
now
we have stickers
so if you meet someone
and stickers
it's escalating
but I think
I go to a lot of events
meetups
lectures and so on
and
I imagine
that there are people
who do this for you
and if I see a colleague
who is a system engineer
we haven't seen each other for a while
and I ask him what he does
and I ask him
if he knows this thing
if he discovered it
and if he didn't
it's very valuable
information
and I'm interested
if he listens
to any person
does he even know
that this thing exists
why doesn't he know
if I listen to the channels
we talked about
I won't mention him
and what do I say
we put a sticker
what is the point
and most people
who are interested
at that moment they pull out their phone
and try to look for this thing
or go to their studio
and what happens
what I've seen
is that people open YouTube
and start looking for it
on YouTube
and that's a good feedback
that you get
if you go to your audience
and talk to them
and discover
I just don't know
if you're going to invest
in TikTok or YouTube
yes
but it's a good feedback
if I just sit here
and just
put it in this clip
it's a very good feeling
if I put it on this channel
and if I don't announce it
it goes to waste
and
this initial audience
builds up
and people ask what do they expect
what do they see
have they listened
and I see that those
who are on-board
I say
listen and tell me if it's for you
and a lot of people write
yes I listened, it's very good
and I see that
in some way you listen and build
if I just jump in
you mentioned
that you go to meetups
and events
I see
that
why couldn't
a garden go to an event
why couldn't it be
like a
I don't know, a message
but why couldn't
a meetup get a guest
and an episode from that
you can respect that
as a journalist
I don't know
I mean
I
with people
I think we have
100 episodes
it's not a problem
all that feedback
that people write
that they would come
and say something
and sell
but
if we go back
what is the point
what is the purpose
I don't know
if we are going to
directly try to sell
or
that's not the point
I want to be global
and with such a person
maybe there will be people
I don't want to exclude
but if they can tell me
details, if they can speak passionately
about their technologies
all the market secrets
yes
I want to be able to tell
how to do it
I can sell myself
but I'm really interested
I don't know how many
meetups we had
because I have no idea
what it looks like
it's interesting
because we talked
about it
because I think
it's worth it
it's definitely good
to have a podcast
like this
and in the end
we have a lot of
unprofitable
please explain it
in Slovenia it's like this
in Tuin
unprofitable means
that you get paid
but you don't make a profit
NGO looks different
for example
CyberPIP
for a while
was under the name
K4 through 6
then suddenly
it became zero
at some point
you as a member
of the community
have the capital
to live and serve
the community
and you have
some kind of community work
you're happy
if you do zero
because there is no space
and no cold law
because of electricity
but your volunteers
or people who organized it
don't have any compensation
It's just that they have expenses.
What we normally get from the school,
I don't know if it's the same now,
it's completely different.
That's what I'm talking about.
I think it's not a problem for me to come to an event
because I know that those people anyway,
I won't say,
well, I can say that,
but I'll say that they're hiding something.
Now, when you're a student, you have more time,
you can compensate with work,
when you're a little older,
you'll be ready to pay more.
But maybe this event can also help
the community,
from the point of view,
aha, you're a part of this event,
I was there,
there was this event,
and then when you're looking for sponsors
to cover expenses next year,
you can finally offer this podcast,
where you say, hey,
this podcast is great,
there are some synergies that can be made.
On the other hand,
I don't know,
if someone comes
who doesn't sell themselves,
and is ready to say something technical,
it's definitely interesting for our audience.
Or I also think that
in this flow of
general knowledge,
or general content,
I think,
maybe someone is ready
between
OTA,
or me, or Naio, or Nestri,
or whoever,
to ask this flow of questions.
Because you can have, I don't know,
a conference
about digital cities,
and then you have a bunch of people there,
maybe
someone is interested
to be a little technical,
out of people, in a conference,
to bring out some technical things.
I think that we have
a good
beer for that.
Because we know how to ask questions.
If we always know enough,
we know how to ask questions.
Yes, absolutely.
Andraž, do you want to add something?
No, no, no.
Well, yes.
The bottom line
with this feedback is
that it's huge,
that I really want to hear it,
that I really appreciate it,
that it's not only art
that people will give feedback,
but also
objective feedback is
extremely hard to get.
If you learn that,
if I ask you directly,
do you like it?
It's very likely
that people
find it harder
to give negative feedback
than to give
positive feedback.
You also got a few
negative feedbacks.
The most negative feedback
I got was from you.
Sorry, sorry.
But that's why
it's so huge.
I wanted to be in a balance
between constructive
and constructive criticism.
Yes, absolutely.
You have to circle
in a way with experts
who give a wide range
and both.
If we all nod,
yes, yes, yes, great, great,
we won't improve.
If at the beginning
we were given
great sounds,
if we were invited
to improve it,
we wouldn't even try.
It's the same with YouTube.
If we don't
stop it,
it's better
to finish it.
For example, TikTok,
if I go back to it,
we're not on TikTok
to transform quickly,
to get rid of it.
According to my research
it's a media
that is
trying to be
as we are.
You can't fake it,
you can back it.
If we were on TikTok,
yes, it's big,
maybe we would have
another audience,
but maybe we would
go with a partnership
or a co-host
or someone who lives
on YouTube.
Your daughter
starts using TikTok all the time.
Why would you do that?
I don't know.
We've talked about it before.
Maybe.
I see people
with this presence
on all social media
that go to YouTube
and can't find a home.
At the beginning,
you can't fill
every profile,
but you're there
so you don't make
any mistakes.
Yes.
Maybe one more feedback.
We haven't talked
about it on record yet,
but in the last three episodes
I'll put a link
to the Discord.
It's for
older listeners
IRC,
and for younger listeners
Slack.
I try to encourage
people to join the Discord.
There are
more than 100 people there.
The debates
are starting,
people are trying to discuss,
they are full-engaged,
but I try
to get people
from all platforms,
LinkedIn, Facebook, etc.
to join the Discord
and have a channel
where we can talk
to listeners
to get feedback
and ideas for the future.
There have been
a lot of suggestions
for topics.
I don't know why,
but people would like
to talk about
full devices.
I'm always interested
in private keys,
asymmetric cryptography,
cryptography.
There are topics
that people suggest
because they would like to hear
about them.
We have to listen to them.
There will be a balance
between them.
Do you want
to meet them?
In a way, yes.
Do you feel like you have to
meet them?
No, but they get feedback.
I was wondering
what do you think
is the quality content
that is missing?
I mean,
maybe you get
a good feedback
and then you filter it.
You don't understand anything.
Something really good.
For example,
Rod gave a great idea
and then he wrote
that it would be good
if there was some preparation
so that all the guests
could get to know each other.
It's a bit contradictory
with the NoScripted concept.
For Marko,
when we filmed him
it was a difficult topic.
It was a very broad topic
and we prepared a lot
and then the whole debate
flowed more organically.
We went into those things
that are really core
debates, that are interesting
and that we wanted to talk about.
We didn't stick
to the script,
but it was a reward
for the debates.
I really like
that in the end
the garden is like
a pop-up restaurant.
It's still an experiment.
We couldn't do it without preparation
because we're not game developers.
Maybe Jan is closer
to this topic than we are.
To go back a bit,
I think the feedback is great.
Definitely.
You look at the listeners
and get that feedback.
If I'm a person
who's here
and I try to speed up
things a bit,
it's probably a grown-up thing.
Because I've spent
so much time
in the community
and I've grown a lot from it.
If it wasn't for CyberPip,
if it wasn't for organizing
10 events,
if it wasn't for the financial
and life risks
and all that stuff,
for me it's the most important
that you're okay.
I know it's a weird thing,
but now that we're organizing
events and I protect the volunteers
who are the operators and I run them,
they have to feel good,
they have to be hydrated,
they have to have something to eat.
That's the first thing.
And for all those
expectations,
we're still at the beginning.
The world is globalized
and the quality of the content
is automatically higher.
If someone does a static
move to the side,
it's not enough.
We can
very quickly
set expectations
very high
and then implicitly
the team feels
obliged to keep them.
That's my opinion.
Are we all okay?
Are we comfortable?
When we
adopt a new standard,
it's like in the First World War.
You have an endless
line of soldiers.
It's not enough
to keep
that line of soldiers
because it requires
logistics,
you have to be in that trench
to get to the enemy base.
It's not that trivial.
I don't know if that analogy fits.
Yes, it does.
It's the same in the business world.
We can talk about
infrastructure as code,
how great it is,
the whole infrastructure.
But if you don't have a single test
written for your application,
is it really meaningful?
We can put a camera here,
record it,
record what's happening with that camera
that's shaking,
and then we'll flatten it from the front,
from the back,
up and down.
That standard is already set.
The next standard is live stream.
We won't have YouTube videos anymore.
We've all learned that
from CyberPip.
The main catch is
if you want to spend most of your
creative time
making content
you need a session.
I'm not saying
that we'll forever
edit audio content,
because we won't.
It's drastically improved
from episode zero.
We didn't even know
that episode zero would be released.
It's a brilliant idea.
The analogy would be
if we go to a video,
we won't be able to just
go back to the audio.
It would also affect you.
Especially you.
When I talk to people
before a video,
I get a lot of feedback
like, yeah, give us a video,
but how can you get
better guests than you?
AI will generate
the characters,
and you'll just
have a voice-over.
The first thing you see
is that you're still drawing.
Imagine being able to
publish that drawing.
That's a lot of work.
That's another criticism.
We don't know what the guests
look like.
You know how it looks
on a PHP form.
We don't know what the guests
look like.
That's interesting.
Now again, who wants
to know?
Programmers really want to
press the button when they see you on the street.
I think it makes more sense
to link everything
that has a guest.
If it's aligned,
if the pictures are there,
then it's OK.
I don't know.
I'm a little biased
when it comes to pictures,
but on the other hand,
I'm really into GDPR.
Jan, maybe we should link TikTok?
Do you have TikTok?
I do, but I'm not active yet.
That's the same thing.
I know how
poorly I play social games.
I don't know.
100 episodes will be different.
Now I'll share 100 episodes.
It's a lot easier
to link a website
that I haven't done in two years.
No pressure.
I'm talking to
Kovačevo Kobilo.
He's the boss.
We all have nice websites.
I talked to someone, I hope he's a guest.
He has a website.
I wrote him that I wanted to see
if he would be interested.
He wrote,
I'm a virtuoso,
but I'm not a guest.
I said, OK,
I'll promote you as a virtuoso.
He said OK.
Kovačevo Kobilo.
I don't know.
You have to have a presence.
Other people just don't know
that you exist.
OK.
We talked to the audience,
we got to know each other.
When you publish
the podcast,
how does it look for you?
Do you have a website?
No, he has 10 apps.
How does it look?
Now we'll press
the square
where the recording will be.
It's nice if we record
10-15 seconds at the end.
Then I upload
to Google Cloud Storage
or Dropbox
and send the link to Jan.
Jan has time
to edit it.
When I come back,
I'll talk
to the co-host
or guest about the topic.
The topic I publish
is sometimes different
than the topic
we talk about daily.
Then I try to
create a title.
Most of the
big podcasts in Tuin
and here
have this format
where the guest
takes the title.
I try to extend
the topic.
The topic is more important
than the guest
because we don't want an interview.
We create the topic
and then I listen twice
to the raw recording
and try to come up
with a copy.
Then I use the
OpenAI tool
for generating
a picture.
Then I tell him
some key words
and he generates a picture
and I write the sentence.
Then I use
a platform called
Encore FM
for podcast distribution.
You upload
the recording
and they have
RSS.
You upload
the RSS to the podcast platform
and then the podcast platform
takes the RSS.
No, you give them the RSS
and then they download it.
Encore FM
is when you upload
the recording
and you can also add the voice.
In the beginning,
you can record the podcast directly
on the platform.
You can also add the intro, outro
and teaser.
Then, when it's published,
we release it
via the platform
and schedule it.
Then I wait
24 hours
after the recording is uploaded
to the podcast platform
before I start the social push.
The delay
of 24 hours
is to see
how many people
our core audience
has
before we publish it.
To see
the organic growth.
After 24 hours,
I publish it
on all social channels
and I ask
the guests
to publish it on their channels
and to publish it
among their companies
so that they can hear it.
I also ask the guests
to tell me
that this content
will be interesting
for their companies
for recruitment or whatever.
So that they can try it
and publish it themselves.
How many hours
does it take?
Have you ever thought about it?
When I set it
for 9
hours, let's say 2
to publish it.
I've heard a few comments
asking if I need it.
I don't think so.
I don't get it.
The hardest thing
is when I listen to it
for example
when Ro sends it to me
I don't listen to it before
but when he sends it back
I listen to it
and I'm like fuck
I need to wait a week
before I publish it.
That's a sweet problem.
It's much more than
how many hours
it takes to prepare it.
You need to give feedback.
People do it
but I try to stick to a schedule.
You recently said
that we have a higher
frequency of publishing.
It's a good topic.
Have you ever thought
about a buffer?
To make it longer?
When I talked to
more professional Slovenian
podcasters, journalists
and experienced media people
and so on
they did it.
It's not possible.
I can't do it.
You can't?
No, because
I think it has to be
organic.
When we lack
a few people
and we start recording
5-minute podcasts
with an algorithm
I think it's bad.
I think you go back
to those standard
recording sessions.
No, no.
Feedback is like that.
You have people
who don't listen to podcasts
and they find it interesting
and start listening.
They are not media people.
They are introducers.
When I talk to people
who listen to us regularly
I save the last episode
for when I go to Copera
or Maribor
and I'll have time to listen to it.
Then you have feedback like
this podcast
is so important
for my industry
so I save time
and actively listen to it.
Some people use it
as background noise.
Let's jump a bit.
I think
it's my version
of using
podcasts in general.
I need more time
to listen to it
once a week
or 14 days more.
You can't listen
to 10 podcasts
all the time.
I think
it's better
to have a break.
Not every two days.
In Apple podcasts
you can choose
the frequencies.
I think I put
every two weeks
something like that.
Every two weeks
I don't work
too much
on what I have to do.
Now
Vaja's vlog
as a co-host
has nothing
to do with it.
It's a ping-pong.
For Vaja
you come
for 4 weeks
and for 5 weeks.
So for Vaja it's even less.
I don't know how
it will sound.
I don't know.
It's an experiment.
The frequency is very important.
How long
do you use it?
I don't know.
I can't imagine.
To get a cover
with 5000 views.
It's a whole day.
The first episodes
that you sent me
were rough,
mp4 format.
You didn't have a chance
to create a lot
because
you can't.
There's no information.
There's no filters,
no compressors.
At that time
it was like
if you could
repeat the episode
you have to study
where to cut.
Maybe I have more work
with when to start the episode
because you start
talking
and I listen
the first 15 minutes
just randomly.
Then I cut it.
Now that I have a stereo
I take more time.
I don't know.
One and a half length
of podcast.
For sure.
Highly focused.
You can be too old.
The problem is
that you can listen
what you're doing.
If I put one channel
or whatever
in the last episode
it was a few seconds
of pure silence
or someone drank water
etc.
You cut it.
You can listen later.
It requires work.
If I wanted
to cut
every episode
I would say
in the same way
If I wanted to cut
it would be three times
the length.
Maybe it's a bit
exaggerated but
I think it's three times
that it's meaningful
to go back and forth.
And you, when you finish a track, do you listen to it one more time to get used to it?
Not entirely, not at this point, no.
Because at the moment, I'm more concerned with the technical aspects,
I don't have any personal preferences.
But no, more like that, to check that the things you've created are there,
that they're there, that they're not there.
You do it the opposite way.
Even if you imagine, I mean, 100 cuts is like that,
or 100 keyframes there, it's fast.
I think now you can do everything by yourself, and it's fast.
But it's probably the same for you, that you have a visualisation,
that you see, I don't know, various...
I see some dots, in the waveform.
Various dots, and those highlights that you need to cut, and things like that.
You find a section that you want to divide, you listen to it,
then you divide it, and then you listen to it,
if it fits, and you get used to it, and that's it.
I could say that, in a way, when I scroll through the waveforms,
I have to listen to some parts, to see what it is,
I try some equalisers, and so on,
so that I can get a hint of the colour of the recording.
And in the end, I add some intro sound and outro sound,
to a meaningful place.
And that's what I do, as I said,
that the basics are based on the sound,
and that's how it's done in the right way.
I still have a job, or I'm hiring someone, so...
You still know how to talk.
Like the two of us, right?
Yes.
For all those stories, it's like this,
you have those active hours,
when you can't do anything else,
and then, how does it fit into your day,
I don't know if I'm saying it right.
So, what I do is,
I collect all those correspondence with guests,
or people on the topic,
I go through those emails twice,
and then I think about it for about four hours,
and then I quickly write it down on a piece of paper,
so that I can remember some questions,
that seemed meaningful to me.
And optionally, I do some background research on the guest,
even though I don't know him that well.
So, the active time before the podcast,
it takes me about half an hour,
but in reality, it's some kind of background,
because I try to ask myself about those topics,
what would be interesting for the guest.
So, yes, it's not exactly half an hour,
but it would be hard if that day was, I don't know,
because it's some kind of work,
and you go from the inside of your day,
it's not a problem, but if it's out of the ordinary,
or if I'm stressed,
then you can't think about it that day.
So, that's it.
I don't know if the listeners noticed,
but when we have debates,
I try to be less of an active member.
So, if you have three people,
and it's a guest,
I try to be the secondary,
or the moderator.
You want to overstate this.
No, no, no.
I try to listen.
I try to listen a lot,
and I have interesting questions,
or to change the topic,
or to get out of the technical depths,
and it gives me success.
For example, when we were recording with Janko,
when you go to Rebol,
what am I supposed to do?
You need to have self-defense for dancing,
so you can jump high.
It's not necessarily bad.
It doesn't mean that I want to do it synthetically,
but I try to ask myself,
okay,
do we need to ask a question
to make it easier for the beginners?
Because we've known each other for so long,
Oto, Andraž, and me,
and Andraž,
and we breathe technology in some way.
Sorry, yes.
I've known you for 15 years,
and I was only 18.
You're going to answer,
or can I ask you a last question?
No, no.
I can ask half a question,
but I like that,
because I know what it's like
when you're flying,
and you bring someone on a project
and they do something similar.
I like that I don't have these tasks,
so I look at myself
and see how I suffer,
but I see that this is the suffering
that brings you joy and pleasure,
and I know that's why you're doing it.
As far as my effort is concerned,
I'm very similar to Andraž here.
I try to fit in
what I need in my schedule.
I try not to go back
to the scripted task,
what I need to do,
what I don't need to do,
what I would like to ask,
what I would like to talk about,
what I would like to see.
I try to be not too scripted,
and not too much research.
We had guests
that I was able to pick up
from the side,
because I came
into the flow,
but I try to pick up
as much nature as possible.
One last question.
What will we conclude
the first season with?
I don't know.
I've heard that here in the house
you'll be doing a live stream.
I'll be doing a live stream.
People will enjoy it.
Hostess, go-go girls, everything.
Hostess and hostess, both.
What's the male form of hostess?
Hostess.
I think it would be pretty cool.
Let's do it.
It's not a surprise.
I'm serious.
It's a work in progress.
I'm talking about the house.
Andraž, Andraž, Jan,
thank you very much
for today's interview.
Thank you for inviting us
Thank you for giving us feedback.
Thank you for giving us the energy
to work on it further.
Share it with your guests.
And have a nice evening.
Bye.