How did you come up with the idea of creating a game developer and a gamer?
We both thought about game developers and gamers,
and we came up with this mind map,
and we will try to follow this conversation.
As I said, we are web developers with a web background,
with Ops, Infra, and similar tasks.
However, we came up with this idea to talk about game development.
We would like to find out what it means to make a real game today,
what are the challenges, what technologies do we use when developing games.
We are interested in what we don't know yet,
and what we need to know in order to make a proper game.
Welcome to our podcast in Grodno.
Today, we have Andraž, Marko Grgurović,
well, it's hard to say where we are right now.
Welcome, and could you please say hello to our listeners?
Thank you, thank you for the invitation and introduction.
I'm really looking forward to the debate.
Could you briefly tell us who you are,
and how did you come to this industry?
Why a game? Why not a computer system in DOS?
And why did you drop to level 60?
Let's start with today.
At the moment, I'm the director and founder of Triterion.
To be honest, I write too many codes.
I wouldn't dare, but that's the way it is.
It all started in 2014,
when I was just playing Mordhau.
Before that, I'll go back even further.
I didn't work a lot in that scene.
I was just playing.
My connection with game development started in...
Let's say around 2000-2003,
when I was playing a really old MMORPG, Ultima Online.
But I was playing it on private servers,
because I had my own emulator.
It was really well written,
and there were a lot more codes than official ones.
So you could fully customize the emulator,
and then buy new mechanics and stuff.
It was completely different back then,
a completely new style, new mechanics.
I've been playing Ultima Online for 10 years now.
On and off.
Sometimes I worked on it and wrote stuff,
but that was it.
Are we talking about modding?
Almost, yes.
If I understand correctly,
you had a client, and then you had a server site,
and then the community reverse-engineered
the protocol and made their own server site,
and then you could modify it.
Yes, and the client was completely dumb.
You couldn't push the client,
because we didn't have that.
But the server had control over everything,
so you could almost start everything that way.
Yes, and you were the first with the multiplayer.
It wasn't that detailed,
everything was in 2D.
I remember that.
But Ultima was a milestone in the gaming industry.
I recently heard that.
People were crazy about hacking,
and it was one of the most important features.
Yes, I hear that.
Hacker podcasts,
where people went in the dark direction of hacking,
everyone said that they hacked Ultima,
stole some coins, etc.
Games were crazy about mechanics.
You could sit in a bomb shelter,
pick up a Nugget,
find the hacker, kill him,
steal the whole bomb shelter,
and sell it.
It was crazy.
It was so free,
you could do whatever you wanted.
It's not like that anymore.
It's a nightmare.
As far as the community is concerned,
it's crazy how you manage it.
People let it play,
and there were safer options,
like World of Warcraft,
where you couldn't build a bomb shelter.
You said that you played it,
and that you hacked the server,
which you had access to.
I would like to know,
what were the game masters doing there?
All the private servers were there.
You opened a note,
worked on it,
wrote some code,
it was C Sharp,
I think the emulator was called RunWall.
How did you discover it?
How did you discover those things?
I wanted to play Ultima Online
many years before that.
I didn't have internet.
I went to the store,
took a box,
and told my mom to buy it for me.
She asked me if I had a mod,
and I said no.
I was really sad.
I waited until I got the DSL.
Then I downloaded it.
It was in Chinese.
I don't know.
There was a torrent.
I downloaded it,
and it was in Chinese.
I couldn't understand it.
Then my colleagues and I
found out what it meant.
I don't know Chinese.
It's like going to a modern washing machine,
looking at a symbol,
and then you find out
what it means.
That's right.
We started off well.
You still have your PhD from computer science.
I don't have it yet.
No?
That's another story.
It's all about waiting.
OK, thank you.
But there's a way
from hacking Ultima servers
to getting a PhD.
You went everywhere.
A few things went differently.
I started doing this
as a hobby.
Then I started studying
for my PhD.
I was really interested
in algorithms and such things.
I continued that
with the goal of starting
design, algorithms,
analysis,
and science.
Then I decided
that maybe...
It was quite late
when I started my PhD
and I had a scholarship.
I decided
that maybe
that's not where I should start.
The academic sphere
doesn't work the way
you want it to.
You need to work on projects.
I decided
that maybe I should try
and do it myself.
I've seen people do it.
In Unity,
they have a 3D game,
but it's not that hard.
I know how to program,
so I'm going to try it.
That's how it started.
On January 1st, 2014.
You said you studied for many years.
I remember,
but I know it was January 1st.
I created a project.
That's when people
were eating sour soup
with cat food.
That's weird.
Maybe I don't remember January 1st.
You don't remember January 1st.
That's a bit suspicious.
You started with Unity.
I mean,
I have this feeling
that proper game development
used to be
Windows,
API,
C++.
You click and write.
You write a text,
and it starts.
I used to play a bit
long time ago.
I think it was Object Pascal.
I don't know why.
It was a bizarre language.
We had it in middle school.
Someone forced it.
I said, let's try it.
But yeah,
most of the development
was done by yourself.
You created your own engine.
DirectX, OpenGL,
3D, 2D,
whatever.
Without any libraries.
Minimal.
But now it's changed a lot.
Especially because
the level
of what you need
to include in the game
is much higher than it used to be.
Expectations are higher.
In the past,
you could create
a simple 3D model
and play a simple 3D animation.
But now it's not enough.
You need to have blending
between animations.
You need to have
inverse kinematics,
so you can support
a visual style
other than 3D graphics.
Post-processing,
and rendering
is much more complex
than it used to be.
Let's move on to
the core,
where you started.
When we talked
about gaming,
and people helped us
prepare the agenda,
Goran said that
he sees gaming
as the most complex
form of entertainment
we know today.
Or art, in a way.
Because
even movies
are a lie
compared to gaming.
What do you think?
How do you see it?
Yes, definitely.
The idea itself,
and how you base it,
is that you are a gamer,
and a gamer can destroy everything.
And a gamer wants to destroy everything.
So you do it
under pressure
so that
they will always need you.
It's not like a movie.
You shoot a movie,
watch it, and it will be like that.
Maybe you have a different TV,
but it will be like that.
A game that is made
has a million libraries.
Today it works better,
but still,
if he comes, he will decide
how he wants to play,
he will have these controls,
he will have those controls.
That's the problem,
and then the game itself.
It's not like you imagined it,
but in a different way.
It can be a better way,
but we have the same problem.
How do they interact?
It's like a meta-game.
A meta-game.
I think that people
take it for granted
that if you play hockey,
everyone has fingers,
and then they shoot a goal.
Because people see it as a game,
and nobody pulls out a gun.
If you talk about hockey,
you are also young.
You are already close.
I understand.
You have to be technically
very capable
to make your vision of the game
so that people don't take it for granted.
Yes, it's very dangerous.
I think that's what's great
about AAA games.
They are very careful
that you can't do too much
as a player,
that you are limited,
that they have their vision,
and that vision is the same.
But here you also lose
the indie scene,
which is very popular now.
Demo-meta and sandbox.
Players can destroy everything,
destroy everything,
break everything,
but they let it go.
Players like it a lot
because you can make stories.
For example Minecraft.
You can do whatever you want.
It's like Sol is creating
a world,
which is part of the game.
Sol is creating it.
I have a lot of questions
about Mordhau,
and then we will
get out of it
somehow,
if you know.
Let's start first.
Can you introduce
the game in your own way
so that I don't get nervous?
Mordhau is a multiplayer
fighting game.
I mean,
you actually fight
very close to each other.
I think they described it
in Joker.
We were in the last issue.
So yeah,
it's about
64 players
at the same time
on the same server.
One is bigger,
the other is smaller.
There are two team players,
and you fight 32 against 32
in all possible ways,
it's very bloody.
So yeah,
it's mostly
because
it's hard to describe
only the hit.
You have to create a feeling
when you hit someone.
It's not that realistic.
In the real world,
when you have a match,
you don't have to beat the knight
with a shield.
You just fight back.
But without that,
it would be very flat.
You wouldn't have that juicy feeling
when you hit someone.
It's one of the main features
We spent a lot of time
on all those
parts,
and sound.
For example,
in the movie,
you set up a scene
and the knight will go down
and you build up the sound
before the match even starts.
That's very important.
In the game, you don't know
that the knight will hit him
until he does.
But in the real world,
you don't have to do that.
In the movie,
it's easier to do that.
You have a juicy feeling
and a good sound,
but in the game,
it's more complicated.
I don't know if it happened,
but it's already known
if you want some kind of anticipation.
We spent a lot of time
on sound, animations,
what happens when you
hit someone.
It's a first-person game,
so there's a third-person
view.
But the main thing
is first-person, of course.
We spent a lot of time on that.
Then there's networking,
so it looks like it should.
Then there's the effects,
what happens when you hit someone.
It's hidden in that location,
so the reaction
is exactly as it should be.
It's not necessary that it's an animation,
because in animations,
you have to understand
that animations are recorded
and they always play the same.
You can do some tricks,
but if you have a code
that drives that truck,
it's quite something.
We spent a lot of time
on that.
It's a competitive game.
You're a player against a player.
It's not a co-op game.
You're not fighting against each other.
It's like you're in two teams.
It's competitive.
You probably won't attack
your opponent.
You'd be surprised.
We also have a co-op game
against AI.
Together,
you defend
a bot,
and you get
waves.
That's interesting.
That's my style of play.
You protect the table.
I think it's quite competitive.
When you're playing with friends,
you can't really decide
who's going to attack who.
But if you attack AI,
it's easier to defend the bot.
I wanted to ask if it's easier
to make a game where
people are fighting each other
versus AI,
but it's probably
a different set of problems.
Yes, it's a different way.
It's a different challenge.
Yes,
when it comes to game design,
when it comes to mechanics,
if you have a player versus a player,
you want both of them
to be happy with each other.
So you don't want
to overdo it.
For example, if one player
attacks the other,
those who will attack him
will feel bad.
Those who manage to attack him
If you have AI,
it doesn't care what you do to it.
You can mistreat it,
smash it, cut its head off,
let it bleed.
The player isn't there,
so it's free.
You can give the player
really good mechanics
to make it feel like a total badass.
On the other hand, it's not a human.
It's completely different with PvP.
So when you're playing
a player versus a player,
it's not too brutal
for the one who lost.
Yes, it's just a challenge.
You can't overdo it.
That's really interesting.
It reminds me of when you're a kid
and someone older than you
is playing chess.
You have to let go of the game,
so that the game is still meaningful.
You don't ask questions,
you do a table flip.
This is the recorder.
If you're a game designer,
it's even more complicated.
You don't have the time
to let someone else win.
You can, of course,
but you only have the time
that everyone else has.
It's not just about winning.
It's also about the feeling.
Some mechanics feel great
for the player,
but not for the other player.
It's uncomfortable because
you have to wait.
It's a catastrophe for the feeling.
I read a book
called Deep Thinking
by Garry Kasparov,
a chess master
who played against
Deep Blue from IBM.
He was the first
professional chess player
to be beaten by an AI.
He talked about
the development of chess algorithms
and how
brute force was
the first method
and how they developed
more intelligent algorithms
for preparing
for the ideal position
that the chess program
exceeds.
A big chapter in the book
is dedicated to
the fact that they were prepared
to make a full AI
that would beat
a lot of people,
and it was too good.
It had to be smart enough
to still be interesting
for people
who were inexperienced
or beginners.
It had to be useful
for learning and fun.
Do you have a similar experience?
With first-person shooters,
the AI can always start
at 100 km.
It's a bit harder,
but not as hard as we made it.
We could beat it,
but then we did
things differently.
In the beginning,
it could not defend itself
at the last moment.
That's not a good feeling.
We had it,
but then we somehow
reduced it
so that it didn't have a good reaction.
But I think
we could do it differently.
We wouldn't look at it that way.
I don't know how much.
In our example,
when we were making a PvP game,
the AI was added
so that we could test it
more than anyone else.
So they use the same
methods as players.
Everything is the same.
They don't have anything different.
Usually, in games,
it's changed a bit,
so they are more organized.
They have the same interface as players,
but we are moving the mouse.
Do you have a problem
that players
golf in such a way
that they write their own?
Not only that.
When we talked about Ultima,
the gameplay was simpler.
It's a 2D game.
Here we talk about 3D,
moving, space, etc.
People are cheating.
Yes.
There are a few things
where cheating happens.
We physically
work on the server.
But we left certain things
to the client
because
it's too difficult
or impossible
to make it smooth
for everyone.
These corrections
can be really bad.
So we left some things
to the client.
We said that maybe
someone will exploit them
and we will fix them.
We left some of them.
At the beginning,
it's hard to read.
They are full obvious.
Those that are not so obvious
have some details.
The problem is that
when you turn it around,
you control the attack.
That's the main feature.
It's not as easy to read
as in a shooter.
Here it's not.
It's a very
difficult
concept.
You have a parry.
It's a block.
When you activate it,
it lasts 0.3 seconds.
Then it goes down
and you can't do anything.
It's an easy task.
When the attack starts,
it lasts 0.4 milliseconds.
When you just activate it
to see it.
Then 0.4 milliseconds
or 0.5
when it moves through the game.
But when it moves,
you can't move it.
You catch the attack with the block
and it moves away.
It's not as easy
to read.
I understand.
It's another detail
how they move the attacks.
It depends on the hitbox,
how the player looks,
what the animation is.
It's the exact last moment
when you get hit.
I don't want to dwell on this topic, I'm interested in what's going on with the active search for cheaters.
No, we don't have that many problems.
The problem is probably with those competitive players who play on private servers and then go around cheating.
For us, it's not a priority.
The community is always happy, it's not the cheaters.
Yes, there are very few cheaters.
When we find them, it's obvious that we ban them.
Let's move on to the next question.
Why Mordhaud? Why knights? Why swords? Why the medieval theme? Why not in Vesolje?
We started because we wanted to make a melee game.
You have to be close to each other and fight each other.
That was the starting point.
From that, we could go in any direction.
The reason for the medieval theme was...
There were 9 of us.
9 people in the world?
Yes, and we were all divided around the world.
We wanted to keep the organization, so we had to do it in a way that you just can't.
In the beginning, it would be possible, but we couldn't be more than that.
We didn't have a team that would only deal with management or production.
We all worked on something specific.
So I tried to overshadow them, or put things in a way that would work.
The easy way to put together a 3D art is to focus on the medieval theme,
because then you have the old pictures, manuscripts, references,
and they all fit together.
If you were working on a space game, and you told different artists to make their own,
they wouldn't fit together.
Concept art is a lie.
You don't need it at all. We didn't even have it.
You just look at the books.
Everything fits, everything is meaningful.
The other thing is that it's still a style of play, because we know that medieval works,
but we haven't seen anything else like medieval.
So from the market point of view, it would be too risky.
For us, medieval was cool.
It's cool, you have this, you have Kry, you have decapitations, and all that stuff.
It's cool.
I'm wondering if we have to look at this podcast for ourselves,
for explicit content.
We have to, right?
I don't think so.
We don't have anyone, so it's okay.
Let's talk about the main thing.
Also, the standards for explicit are globalized, of course.
Yes.
I mean, the market is absolutely clear for immersive personal games,
which are an action.
People are hyped up about different games.
I mean, when I was researching this topic,
you found a niche in games.
If I understand correctly, there were some other games,
I don't know, you knew a lot about them,
that had a market, but hadn't been on the market for a long time.
Yes, Chivalry was in 2012.
Or do you have more conferences today?
Yes, Chivalry is now in development.
The market is definitely small.
It's not as big as Shooter is.
Everything is known, if there are two games on the market.
Everything is known.
I think that the market has also burst out of that bubble.
I think it was at some point,
not just for a certain aspect of the player,
but I think people were like,
okay, I'm going to play this game with a colleague,
even though I'm not a big fan.
The launch was huge.
I think we were the third on Twitch a couple of days ago.
We were on top 7 on Steam for three weeks.
I think it was number one.
It was huge.
All the streamers came up and played.
In general, it's also impressive how many people
got to know it and played it.
It's not as big as it was three years ago,
but it's a lot of people.
I think Post Malone played at some point.
He's the Mountain of Game of Thrones streamer.
What do you do to keep the player base?
How does it work?
Our player base goes down over time.
It's hard to keep it.
Especially here in the TV,
the game becomes harder over time.
People, because it's a PvP multiplayer,
get some strategies,
learn different animations,
more specific ones,
learn from other players,
and change the way they play.
Over time, it becomes harder and harder.
What does it mean?
That it's for beginners?
It's completely different.
Now we're trying to add some special strategies
for beginners,
but it's not a good solution for that problem.
It happens with every game.
It's always happened so far.
In the beginning,
everyone came up and saw the Twitch streamer,
everyone was running,
no one knew what he was doing.
It's a different feeling.
You're waving at someone,
they're laughing,
they want to defend themselves,
you hit them,
they're defending themselves.
You don't have to do anything,
he's defending you,
you need a lot of time to hit him.
It's not the same feeling.
It's a bad position.
Do you play a lot with on-boarding,
or with the first experience,
when I install a game,
I start playing it,
the first feedback is probably very important.
People try to play it,
and if they have a bad experience,
what happens next?
It's a refund.
It's a daily refund.
I think they have two hours,
and then it's a refund.
We've all dealt with it,
but it's very difficult
to solve it in post.
When you have a lot of players,
you have a community,
which is active,
but it's hard to grow again.
Especially for PvP games,
it's hard,
for co-op it's easier,
because you add new content,
and players come back and play.
We don't base it on
how long it will last,
I don't know for how long,
but I think it's important
to pivot to new projects.
We don't have a goal
to keep it at this level,
we will keep it,
but only for a while.
You said before
that you tweaked
the servers,
and it somehow
forced you into the game.
In this game,
there's a lot of weapons,
and character building
is extremely important
for the player.
Tell us more about it.
I think we have
a thousand different
hair accessories.
It's huge.
We overdid it a lot
with the customization,
you have the face sculpting,
to make your own face,
I don't know why you do it in PvP,
but we added it.
For example, you can play
like a madman, I don't know why.
Then we added
a lot of hair accessories,
you have gloves,
a hat, a frame,
a hat on the chest,
a hat on the head,
a hat on the neck.
Is it based on reality?
Yes, there are hats,
some of them are made up,
but you can change them
independently.
You can paint it,
and it's like a Barbie
simulator.
The players have to do it,
and a lot of it is...
Some people come to the game
to do the loadouts.
So there's a lot of it.
And then they buy...
We have
an in-game gold system,
you get it when you play.
We didn't have a DLC
until late,
and we started giving it
to raise the revenue.
But most of it
is a game,
with time in the game.
You get gold.
Those DLCs are a way
for the community to support you
in the future, right?
To get more DLCs
for everyone who played
Tetris recently.
It's actually
a new feature.
A new feature
for which you have to have
a basic game,
but it gives you
a new hat,
and you get a hat
and a sword for 5 euros.
You can't get anything else.
Some time ago,
World of Warcraft was
known for
building a character
from a level
and then selling it.
Do you also sell
folk characters?
No.
No, we don't.
In World of Warcraft,
it was a bit different.
You made the character,
and it became more powerful.
We don't do that.
All the things you remove
are just cosmetic.
You have a different hat,
and you have 3 types of armor,
actually 4.
Depending on the type,
light, medium, heavy,
it has certain
effects,
but it's fixed.
Then you have a different
cosmetic look.
It would be a nightmare
if you wanted to replace it.
It's too much.
We have
4 different types of armor.
The eyes are only on the head,
chest, and legs.
Legs,
chest, and head
have different bonuses.
Weapons have different bonuses.
It's too much.
When you talk about bonuses,
is it
an insight
as a developer,
or is it something
that people know?
I mean...
They know...
They've been playing for a long time.
They know,
because you have a tab
where you can see all the weapons.
We went deep.
I like it.
There are things
I would never have thought about.
Why this topic?
Is it because you have
a concept art?
Do you buy the sounds,
or do you record them yourself?
At the beginning,
before the release,
I started working on the sounds.
They were bought,
then replaced, cut,
as they had to be.
It was...
I don't do it anymore,
thank God,
but I'm still involved.
Before that,
I mean,
we didn't record the sounds.
Except for the voices.
You can choose the voices in the game.
We got
people who came
via e-mail and said
they would record something.
I said OK.
I'm an amateur.
They recorded it and it was cool.
But it was so...
We didn't have
a good pipeline for it.
Someone could call
or get to know someone
so we could do it.
Then I cut it a bit,
then they cut it a bit,
and then I did it in the game.
Now it's done differently.
We go through agencies,
they find people,
so we can do it.
How old were you? 9?
8? 9.
That's impressive.
You have your core team,
you make a game
which is a top
worldwide game.
What does it look like?
It's like
you go to an island with a palm tree
and take three things with you.
At first there were
more people.
How did you come up with it?
At first
it was more or less like
everyone lived at home.
In 2017 we had
a Kickstarter
and we got 300,000.
But it didn't go far
considering
that we could
reserve it for servers.
Our team
consisted of
two programmers.
From artists
there were
four, I think,
and then
two designers.
One of them
was a level designer,
which means that
the things the artists did
were set in levels.
I don't know
who else was there.
And the Kickstarter...
One of the things
I really liked
was the community.
Especially indie games
have a big community.
When they were preparing
to make a game
they already had a community.
And those developers
that you mentioned,
did they also come from the community?
Yes, from the community
of Chivalry.
Because we played there
and I met them there.
So they came
from the team chat.
I haven't seen them
since then.
I mean, I saw them later,
but until then I didn't know them.
Some of them...
Chivalry also had
what is happening now
that they are sponsoring a modding contest.
And they have a prize,
which means that
the best one is given in the game.
And it's a content
for the player,
and it's a cash or recognition.
And some of our guys
participated in it.
So we picked them up from there.
Some of them are with us.
A few of them are with Diablo.
When we posted
there was a lot of filtering
to find the right person.
Because working with a team
that is not paid,
is a completely different thing.
We had the luck to be nominated
by the team in all 4, 3 years
we worked with them.
People could eat.
Yes, but they were more or less...
When you pick up these people,
you have to be careful
that they are people
who will live at home,
and they are young enough
and they won't cause problems.
And that's it.
That's a very simple description.
Every startup...
Only for beginners,
if you want to play.
And of course,
the programmer has to be alone.
Because it's very hard for the programmer.
He will always get a job.
And those 3D artists,
they are tired of it.
No.
So,
to make it better,
this project was
totally crazy,
totally passionate,
a lot of work,
a lot of tape,
space and water,
cables.
So the medieval theme
was not only in Art Direction,
but also at home.
I wanted to ask you
how is it to start
today in the gaming industry,
so that you can see
what you want to do.
I think you offered
a lot of answers
through the fact that
modding is a very nice
opportunity to start
doing something.
If you want to work
in an indie scene,
those who will be programmers
will definitely have everything in their hands.
Because it's really hard
to get programmers.
Even now, if you pay them,
it's hard to get them.
Everything else can be found
or solved.
You can do it
and show it.
For us it was
that when we started,
I already had something.
Something to show
what you can do.
So the easiest way
in the indie industry
is to be a programmer,
like everyone else.
That means
that you are a master of language
and a master of some kind
of environment.
Yes, you learn
how to do things
and don't worry
about 3D animation
or some kind of sound.
Because people
who would only do that
won't get it.
You will have, for example,
three people in a team.
One of them is a 3D artist,
a programmer.
It's not a space for someone
who would deal with production
or management.
What does your compass
and your travel card mean?
No,
I wanted to add one more thing.
I think that
young people
who play games
and maybe are interested
in how games work
and want to enter
the industry,
that community exists.
Indie game community.
It's hard to say
because I think
it's an obstacle for young people
because they don't know that.
But maybe they do.
What do you think about
young people who want to
enter the industry?
Is there a community
where they can learn things
and people will help them
to gain knowledge?
If you are a young person
in a certain area,
you probably won't be able
to talk to game developers
every day.
What I would suggest
is that if you count
in the industry,
there is only one thing
you need.
Everything you need.
Today it's a lie.
If you download
Unreal or Unity,
you don't need anything else.
If that's not enough for you,
then you are in the industry.
It's very competitive
and it's hard to succeed.
You have to be better than
everyone else.
You will see it when you
look for answers,
but don't be that guy.
You have to invest
some time in it.
Today it's a roadblock,
but you persevere
and break through the wall.
The filter is there
for those who don't persevere.
That's it.
Engines are available.
Everything is practically
available.
You don't have to pay anything.
Unreal, for example,
is free, but you pay
5% or something.
Then you have Unity,
which is free.
Let me add something.
Games,
as you said,
have extremely high
expectations.
If you are a programmer
and you start thinking
about what you can do
for a game,
it can be overwhelming
and it will distract people.
My question is
how can
Hello World
or Simple Game
or...
How in the world
would you offer someone
to make their own game
that will be simple
and additionally
give it to someone to play?
It's a tricky question.
As you said,
if you think about
what you will do
when you see that
it's 4 years, 5 years,
I don't know how long I will work.
Then you can't do it automatically.
It doesn't work that way.
You have to be
naive,
but you can't be
too naive.
If I take my example,
I think that every year
from 2014 we will release
the same game.
Absolutely no chance.
If I knew I could do it
in 5 years,
I would say no,
thank you.
But I was naive enough
to think that the game
has changed.
If you think about it,
it's still one year.
But because of that
I persisted.
You have to be naive
a little bit.
If you are too naive,
you have other extremes.
For example,
I will make an MMO,
World of Warcraft 2,
we are 3 and that's it.
It doesn't help you at all.
You conclude that Facebook
doesn't exist.
We have 3 people in 2 years.
You have to be
naive, but not too naive.
Is that naivety?
I don't know.
I don't know which one.
At some point you learn
that you were naive,
and then you grow up.
If I draw a parallel
to
web development,
web development is
so successful
because if I want
a different experience,
I upload a new file
and the experience for all users is new.
If I make a mobile app,
which I can upload to
iStore,
there will be a review process,
and it will take 5 hours.
With gaming,
things have to be more
polished,
more stable.
You can also
look for
perfectionism.
Do you have to be a perfectionist?
Can't you be one?
Yes.
It's related to
the question
that was asked
before,
that games are complicated
and it's hard to succeed.
The market exists for all types of games,
even for those
that are not so sophisticated.
They are also among those who are very successful.
They are simple, 2D.
The only difference is how many people create them.
Because they are easier, and people are much easier to catch up with.
Subsequently, there are more games like that, and it's harder to succeed.
The more you complicate a thing, the more you complete it, the more you finish it, the more time you need,
the fewer people who succeed in it.
This means that there are fewer other developers, which means that you are more likely to succeed.
So in the end, you also have a mistake on those that are really AAA,
but then you use so much cash for it that it's a bit pointless.
There is a sweet spot, where there is not a lot of noise in the store itself, in the products that come out,
but at the same time they don't use too many people, or too few.
So it depends a lot on where you are going with it.
But there are a lot of very simple games, and even if it's a great game,
you can simply lose some noise and not sell anything.
But probably if you are a beginner, all this experience,
look, this game you made for me, it's on the market, I went through the whole process once.
Sure, no, this is now...
You should try to find people who are interested in this topic, right?
No, it's for sure, but don't make simple games.
Because if you want to make them, you're right,
but with that you won't get any useful knowledge,
look at how 3D animations work, how do I put it together, what is the workflow for that.
Completely different techniques are used.
I mean, there are basics that you can use, of course,
you know how the engine works, you know how to put it on a store,
what is a store integration, or something like that,
or simple things, but it's a completely, completely, completely different thing.
The details that you have to deal with, and also the changes,
the very architecture of the game, how it's based,
what you have to deal with, and so on.
I've learned that you often do difficult things,
so let's go back to the doctorate.
What is your doctorate?
It's in theoretical computing, algorithmic graph theory.
In fact, they are the fastest algorithms for...
especially for the best graphs.
It's a classic problem,
I've tried to run faster times in theory,
and sometimes also in practice.
Okay, nice.
I recently talked to a guy who worked for Neo4j,
he worked in the company Neo4j, for Neo4j,
it's the most popular commercial offering for a graph base,
and we quickly agreed that even he who works in Neo4j
actually doesn't work in X-graphs,
that they are fully...
in our part of the industry, they are known as taxilor bullets,
but everyone wanted to work with graphs,
but in reality, those traditional bases are still
quite optimized and good enough
that most of the use cases are covered by those intermediate graphs.
Is that related to Moorhound?
No, it's completely unrelated,
it's purely an academic thing,
nothing to do with the industry,
very little practical.
Now, we're going to try this podcast,
even more technically now,
and this technical core is probably,
if I'm right,
the core of your game engine.
I'm going to try to ask you a question now.
So if you could just explain to us,
did you first start making your own game engine?
No.
We're in Unity.
So you started with Unity,
and then you went to Unreal Engine,
if I'm right, you now have Unreal Engine 4.
Yes, and we're working on it again.
Can you now explain
what your game engine is,
and what is the core of that game engine,
and what's inside it, for example?
Yes, it's different,
but at the beginning,
the expectation is that your game engine
is something that all games would need.
So you don't need to mess with it.
If you have an operating system,
you can't write it,
you can only write applications.
So ideally, we would work on games,
and not mess with banal things
that are not really important.
Things like, let's say,
mind tooling,
like, for example,
sound support,
so you don't have to mess with it.
So your rendering works,
so the renderer is set up,
so you can import models, animations,
and then solve them.
But those are very simple things.
Nowadays, engines are much more advanced than that,
and they also enable you
to have a sound system
that is more complete,
so you can, for example,
edit and paste together
various sounds into larger constructs,
so you can import animations,
and the code and the handling
is quite open,
so you can work on your own features in the engine.
In fact,
networking is also possible.
Now, different engines
offer different things.
Some,
maybe not as much as some others,
are competing with each other.
The main two are for
anything
bigger than 2D,
Unreal and Unity.
However,
Unity is...
I don't have
the best opinion about Unity
nowadays.
It's really cute as an engine.
I don't know if I'm going too far.
No, we're going even deeper.
Unity is a very nice tool.
It's very nice to work with it,
unless you're doing something serious.
Then you realize
that it's a disaster.
It's a disaster
because
the problem is Unity,
what they do and what they focus on.
The engine has a lot of features
that are so outdated
that they're completely useless.
People do their own networking
inside the engine,
which is unacceptable.
I mean, you can do it,
but why?
Then there are various optimizations
for rendering,
which have a lot of plugins.
People trust the plugin
and use it,
but it's very dangerous.
You're dependent on a plugin
that some guy
made at home,
and now he decides
to go to the office
and get a job there.
It's not supported anymore,
but you're based on it.
You're going to ship it.
I don't think so.
I don't know
what code he used.
We were very worried about that
and we had a lot of problems
in Unity because there were
a lot of things to do.
We had our own networking,
but in reality
there are very few things done.
But Unity was the only option in 2014.
Unreal was easy
when it came in the preview,
and then it was released,
but you don't want to
do something new.
Don't touch it.
Don't touch it for another year
because it's not good.
They say it's good,
but it's not.
Unreal was a god
when it started.
There was no Marketplace
and I worked alone,
so I chose the Marketplace
from Unity.
Now Unreal is also there.
Did you start with Unity
when you said it wouldn't work?
Yes, a year and a half ago.
You started a year and a half ago
with a new engine.
Did you move assets?
What did you do?
We moved some things,
but very few.
Maybe Unity
is easier to start with
and then when you do
more complex things
or risk management
when you manage some risks.
Unity is a very nice start.
I mean, I enjoyed
when I worked a lot
and then you do something
and everything works
and it was cool.
It doesn't have many features,
but it also forces you
to do your own thing,
which is also OK.
The problem is that it offers
very little when it comes
to architecture,
which allows you to do
whatever you want.
Nothing will force you,
everything is OK,
but nothing is really
well supported.
I like it so much
that you can program
so vertically.
I only hear React vs.
Angular.
For example,
Flask is very popular
and when you click
Hello World,
it works.
I have a favorite framework
where you can write
one .ini file,
then the same thing,
then the third thing,
and then when you go
to a commercial product
in a year and a half,
you say,
now I understand
why you need to
do a lot of things.
When I have eight people
in three years,
I understand
that these things
are still meaningful.
Unreal Engine 4,
you said,
is this part
open source?
This is a very important thing
in Unity.
Unity is closed source,
and usually with those
that are open source,
you don't want to see the source.
That's terrible.
Crytek leaked,
CryEngine leaked
some time ago,
and it's incredible what's there.
You close it, and bye.
No chance.
You can't find anything there.
On the other hand,
Unreal is open source,
and it's very important
because in Unity,
you don't know what you're doing.
If I'm interested,
if I have a specific game
that requires me to know
how much input latency there is,
where the input is,
does the input change at the beginning
of the frame,
does it change at the end of the frame?
A game renders each frame individually,
and it lasts 16 milliseconds.
Input latency can be 16 milliseconds,
it can be 30 milliseconds,
but it's very important,
and it's a black box.
That's a big problem in Unity.
You can't even,
for example,
it's important that you have
access to low-level C++ stuff.
Unity is written in C++,
but you work in C sharp.
And it's all known.
I mean, you don't have to
work on the whole game in C++,
but I'd like to have
things like that, maybe.
Unlike that,
Unreal is a pure open source,
and it's a lab source.
Everyone chooses it,
everyone edits it.
Of course, then Epic decides
if they're going to put something in there.
But it's also huge.
Unreal is huge.
Unity is a fly against Unreal.
Unreal has so many things
that you don't even know
what's going on after five years.
And it's very strict
on a lot of things.
There's a specific framework
that you have to follow.
If you want to go beyond that,
it won't work.
I mean, you can do it,
but why? Go to Unity and work there.
When I went to Unreal,
I had a lot of good practices,
and I went to work in Unity
on similar things.
And I realized,
why do I work in Unity
if they have it done
and you can see
that it's much easier to do it.
But if the framework is so big,
doesn't it happen to you
that you might start
reinventing something
because you don't know
what's going on?
It happens a lot,
and it's a lot of work.
You can't allow that.
Even in our programmers,
if I see that they do something
on their own,
I have to go to GitHub
and take a source file every day.
Because the documentation in Unity
is the only documentation.
Everything else is outdated.
You have to take the source,
you have to go through
how it works,
but you can see everything.
You can see exactly how the networking
works, exactly how the input works.
There's no debate.
That's the only documentation
that really exists.
The difference is that
Epic, which makes Unreal,
ships games with it.
Unity didn't ship anything.
There are very few games
in Unity at that level.
Usually 2D or mobile games
are huge there,
but at that level
there are very few releases.
In some sources,
Unreal was an option the day before.
But Unreal,
Fortnite, all those things,
all the good practices
that they did there,
they did in Unreal Engine.
Especially with more
gameplay-oriented things.
For example, the framework of the game itself.
What's the difference between
when you're not a player?
Are you a player now?
Is it just your character,
or is it another controller
that controls that character?
Unity doesn't have any of those concepts.
Unreal has already defined it all.
It's just that
it's a real demo of the engine.
It's more of a philosophy.
They have
this beautiful practice
where
for every engine,
for 4 and 5,
they make a reference project.
That project has its own team.
They update that project
for every engine update.
They update it.
If a new system is updated,
they update it.
They show you all the good practices
for the whole project.
Are those games also open-sourced?
Yes, they're all open-sourced.
They promote
that a good way to start
is to start with your template
and then build on it.
You wouldn't choose
a goat and drag it out of the thing.
I have three questions for you.
Is it more like open-source?
Come on.
You're not a believer
in open-source.
I'm not asking you to
take it and recompile it.
That's a different question.
We're not going to
guest-stroll it.
SDK is available.
It's not open-source.
It's just visual scripting.
Unreal Engine, Epic Games,
and Team Sweeney.
Can you explain
the philosophy
of Epic Games?
Why is Unreal Engine open-source?
What's the vision
of Epic Games?
Epic Games
is one of those
technology companies
that has been preparing for
what Facebook started calling
Metaverse.
Immersive experiences
and so on.
Facebook, Google, and similar
players started talking about it.
Epic Games is a technology company
that has been investing
in technology for 30 years.
They didn't know
they were doing it.
How did Epic Games
get involved?
They started with Unreal Tournament.
They were like Quake.
They were arena shooters.
They brought that engine
and somehow
they were the only ones left.
Why is it open-source?
Everything is open-source.
Every engine is open-source.
To be honest,
you don't get
anything
if it's closed-source.
Only if it's unbreakable.
Most examples are.
Nothing helps if it's open-source.
It can have a third party behind it.
Everything has an Epic.
If it doesn't, it's not open-source.
I don't know why
others hide open-source.
I don't think it's on their level.
Epic Games doesn't have
any problems with it.
They take away 5%
from the release.
It's OK for them
because huge studios use it.
For example, CD Projekt
that has Witcher and so on.
They switched to Unreal.
It's full of that.
They can live
in Fortnite.
I'm a cash printer.
Is the ecosystem
Fortnite,
Engine, Store,
Launcher,
and Publishers
in general?
Publishers
aren't at the top.
Everyone can publish now.
It's not about that anymore.
But
in the beginning
they started with Unreal
until Fortnite came out.
They always worked against each other.
They had an engine team
and teams that worked on games.
Those teams
talked to the engine team
and the engine was updated.
They had
some kind of a flop.
They released Paragon
which was a mobile game.
Fortnite was
a survival game
that could
be a flop.
Then they changed it
to a real game
and there was a lot of cash.
What happened next?
Unreal was already
5% free.
It had nothing to do with that.
Then they started
with the Fortnite cash store.
With that store
they tried to compete
against Steam.
There were less players
and less sales.
But they financed them
by buying the games
for some time.
If I understand correctly
the royalty you pay
is lower, right?
Yes, the royalty is lower.
It has nothing to do with that, right?
It does, but
the sales are so low...
Wait, did Epic Games
have
a dispute with Apple Store
because of some...
If I understand correctly
why
did they go there?
Yes...
I think it's important for the industry.
Yes, they go there
to try to pay
those 30%.
But that's half of it.
It's a big problem because
Steam has those 30%.
They don't do anything anymore.
They are a cash printer.
That's it.
You can't
go beyond that.
They try from Epic Store
and lower everything.
It's so ingrained
that you can't get inside
if they make everything accessible.
Why go to mobile?
Because you have no options.
It's terrible to force yourself
to pay 30%.
On the other hand
you have a lot of games.
They don't want 30%.
They want 30% of the things
you buy inside the game.
If I make a store in a store
they will get 30%,
I will get 30% and they won't get anything.
I don't know where you're going.
The difference, in my opinion,
why
would I focus so much
on that if I was
in their position?
If you want to have a game
that is more like a metaverse,
that you can
have a note in yourself
made by a player.
The only way to make a good note
is if they are paid for it.
And if players buy it.
But if you have that
and the store gets the percentage
and you get the percentage
and they get their share
it can't work.
Until you destroy the store
then anyone can survive
It's very difficult.
Facebook succeeded
on the quest.
The same store dominates.
The numbers are
abnormal compared to Steam.
So yeah,
that's the main problem for them.
It's even better
if they don't have to pay.
But
if they don't...
I understand, thank you for telling us
but I will go back
to the engine.
If Unreal Engine
didn't exist
then Unity
would be the only option
to write
the specs for the engine.
No, it depends on what.
For some 3D stuff.
Unity, I mean CryEngine
still exists but
I don't know, it's a tricky situation.
Nobody uses it.
The only ones that use it
are Crytek.
Very few people use it.
I haven't
looked into it.
What would be the other option
if it wasn't for Unreal, Unity
or CryEngine?
I've heard about an engine called Godot.
Yeah, I haven't heard about it.
It's a new open source engine.
I've seen that people
are crazy about it.
I think it's more for beginners.
I don't know if you know about it.
No, I don't.
I've heard about it.
I know that it exists.
I've never worked with it.
Those are the best.
Unreal...
That's your league.
I know.
All the tooling
from YouTube,
all 7 products,
IntelliJ,
IDEA,
EMUVIA,
those are the only tools
that you see.
It's so complex.
If a new player comes,
it's a multigenerational effort
to catch him.
There are studios
that left their in-house.
You can't do more.
There are so many things
that need to be noticed.
Out of all the animations,
we always go more, more, more
complex.
Animation design.
How do you put those animations together?
Those are just clips.
You need to make it smooth,
so everything works.
It's important
because designers
are more empowered
to make the code themselves.
Next generation.
It's a bit of a problem.
They really
made something
from scratch.
The power of code.
It's terrible.
It's not nice.
But it's interesting
that an ideal engine
has 3 languages.
One is low-level,
like C++.
Unreal C++, by the way,
is really nice to use.
It's not like C++,
it has its own things.
and it's also a reflection
the second one is a scripting language
it can be C sharp, it can also be a scripting language
it can also be Python
or some words that are written nicely
and the last one is visual
and you have to have that for a designer
so you think in blocks?
yes, or in node-based
so you have these three things and you cover everything
if you don't have any of those, it's a problem
C++ is too low-level
I mean, you can work with it
but it's clear that a block would be better
with something more compact
but Aril has C++ and node-based
while Unity has, I don't know
node-based you can make it
if you have some plugins
the other one has C sharp, but it's not low-level
if you don't have low-level, you don't have performance
if you don't have a scripting language
you deal with C++
and with node-based
you deal with spaghetti
I mean, it's crazy
so the organization of the code
you want to have in the text
so these three things are perfect
but there are none
and Aril is planning to add a scripting language
one question is
ok, you have Aril
you have Aril
and then you have
of course, you have to build
specific pipelines for a lot of things
asset pipelines
I'm also interested
have you been able to develop
some internal tooling
or did it just go to the side?
no, we didn't have anything like that
Aril has it nicely
so you can extend the editor
Open Source is also an editor
so you can do something there
some automation
you can do with the editor
that's cool
but other than that, nothing
have you been able to buy
some third-party tools
you have a lot of tooling
that specializes in sound
I don't know
for sound, you have
Wyser
and FMOD
we didn't, because Aril
has it nicely done
in Unity, that's a problem
you need it there
so Aril is basically
self-sufficient
the only thing I missed
was the backend
we have PlayFab
but you have to integrate it
Aril also started
to work there
now we started with the backend
game engine is there
you have it
store, ok, we have it
you use the backend
from the store, from Steam
then came Epic, then came consoles
now it's not ok anymore
you have to have cross-platform
and backend is in PlayFab
what do you think about the backend
do you think it's
a server side of the game
or what do you think
not from the game
but where your profile is stored
where your items are stored
items, what you unlocked
in the store
do you develop it yourself
no, we have PlayFab
those are general things
you can do
but I don't think
game mechanic, netcode
is a thing
netcode is a part of the backend
that's Unreal, it's a game server
we still have servers
we currently have
machines
if someone doesn't want to, we can add
a server
which is the same code as
the game, but it's stripped
that's all Unreal
it strips the graphics
so it's a command line
let me understand
if I'm saying the same thing
you make one codebase
one game, and then
you generate servers
you get server side code
client side code
and then you run server side code
that's right
what about communication
server client, I assume
it's optimised
do you talk about it
daily?
what is netcode?
the basics are
traffic
in all engines
it's always
high, fast paced
it's always UDP
you always have your own reliable
functionality
and you have to handle it
on your own protocol
for Unreal
it has that
and it's nicely written
with some difficulties
if you have a lot of players
but you handle it nicely
because
it's not just sending
the designer decides
this is what all players would like
it has to be a framework
how it will work
and it's nicely put together
to send it to you
of course, here
netcode is a gameplay
you do it on your own
netcode is a slippery
definition of things
but
with netcode, you have to be careful
that you don't know
what kind of things will come
you have to understand
in Unreal
what comes together
what doesn't
what does this mean
and you have to be careful
that you don't know
what will happen
you have to be careful
that's the first thing
the second thing
is how do you
make it
synced
how do you make it look
that's
time wizard
because you have to ask yourself
when are you
in this moment
because time is relative
for everything connected to the server
for example, you press a button
one option is
what happens
you press it
and you get a response from the server
it always goes forward
because if you wait, it will crash
it will be a disaster
that means that you are
in the future
the server is not there yet
the server will be there when it gets the input
and if it needs it, let's say it will
you are in the future
it's the same if you
if you
if you look at another player
the server sent him the information
but he sent you where he is
at the moment
and where he was before
and you only know where he is now
you have to interpolate that
and maybe you will need more time
because you don't know where he will go
so he is in the past
for the server, he is in the present
and where does it get complicated
let's say you start an attack
you start an attack that starts like this
so it's in the future
and you find a guy
who is in the past, but in the server
he is in the present
but you are in the future
and that's why the server sent you
and now you are in the past
and you get the registration back
how you do that is
by interpolating things
in different ways
if you start an attack
what you can do is
that the animation of the attack
is slower than your ping
so the server will send you
you sent him first
he started the attack
when he sends you the answer
back
the second part of the ping
and that means that the whole ping
will go back
and you are synced
because your attack was delayed
and now it's cool
I get it, it's like FPGA
when you have three cycles
but there is one more problem
so this is
what we do
in a controlled way
we inject lag
but in a very controlled way
which means
we show you where you were
not where you are
but we extrapolate a little
to where you are
so you have a feeling that it's easy
but it's not
how do you simulate this?
in the beginning
you simulate
it's easy, it's not a problem
and that's it
now you test it
how do you know that it's a code
which works
how do you solve it?
you go through the code
you go through it
until you know
that it's for sure
if it's something
you go through it
and if it's formal
you look at it
you can introduce a lag
so you get it earlier
around two players
who pressed something
and then you sit down
and play the game
these calculations
run on
both client and server
yes, you have a different code
every code
as I said in the beginning
you take it out of the server
it's the same code
not that it's expensive
but it's the same code
and in the code you have
if you are a server
else if you are a client
why is that?
it's impossible to write it differently
you can't do it like that
you choose it
you see two contexts
it's different
there's no better way
to write it
the client does what the server does
but it does it
so it can predict in advance
it's not a dumb client
it's a complete interweaving
it would be a complete duplication
and then you have
the third option
where the player
plays it
the second option
is not the same as
with time
when the player starts
the player will react
to the animation he sees
but that's in the past
and he's in the future
because he sent it
but when you say
future, past
how much time
depends on lag
depends on ping
60-100 ms
that's a lot
in this example
he reacts to things
that happened in the past
it's a well-known reaction
so in this example
you switch his animation
where it was
so you help the player
to make the prediction
but then you have to be careful
because if you do that
the hit won't be synced
he'll go over
and you have to be careful
from the calculations
you have to make
and then we come to the idea
of 64 players
that you have on the server
no, we come to that idea
because in our example
the server takes all the physics
and all the calculations
and all the animations
so if you shoot
he'll say
ok, you shot, cool
and if the server confirms
he can't check the animations
in this example it's ok
it's ok between the ones
that defend and the ones that attack
in the shooter it's not that important
that's why we work on the server
and we couldn't optimize
to have more than 64
we came to 80
but you need
mega hardware for that
and very specific machines
they are very specific machines
but it's true
that if you have more players
you can do less things
if you have
one or two players
you won't get
as many machines
to be able to shoot
for 64 it's better
but yeah
it's mainly for optimization
it's very important
to be able to shoot on the server
you need profiling
and everything
and then look
what takes you so long
the line is spinning
every frame
why
you give a side
and a simple one
or you miss something
that was in the visual scripting
that is heavy
or I don't know
they have it in physics
but they are far enough
that they don't need it
one thing we have is
level of detail
it's not just a code
if it's to the side
the tick changes
every code is based on frame time
as much as it is
what you can do
if you hit a note on the right place
you give it more tick time
and you tick it less
and that way you balance it
so the refresh rate
is lower
which is closer
and more important
for everything else
connected to the code
when I listen to it
I'm so proud of it
globally
where do you think
the state of art is located
in the industry
I feel like
you are top of the top
on team size
we are almost done
for the feel
of the impact
it's top
it went through
really well
the games that came out
don't have that sync
half of the people laugh
and say they did it better
there are other things
that could be better
but we haven't seen
anything better
so much freedom
do you think
I will
will we see
games that cost
more than 60 players
maybe play karate
or
will we be able to change
paradigms, hardware
will we get better hardware
on the server side
what will we do
it usually goes
to one point
but then you have to think
that you have more followers
this brings
some problems
what if you are on the border
and you see the other side
this can be solved
with design
but then you are back
on your own
so if you have a seamless world
you have to use boundaries
but how do you get there
there are tools for multiplayer
frameworks
that handle this
and are easily integrated
in Unreal
but in those tools
as soon as you change a low-level thing
it breaks for updates
they have all the features
to mirror you through boundaries
to see that it is seamless
it becomes very complicated
that's why we have this podcast
that's what we said before
I made them
a few years ago
it was that advanced
and then came game development
pure technology madness
recently I was
looking for
Epic Games
to see
that Unreal Engine
will eat
movie production
yes, yes
I don't know so much about it
but I know they work a lot
and they use it a lot in real-time
the difference is that movies
have been made fully offline
which means that those things
are set up, you press a button
and a server machine
that cost you a lot
drives it
and they worked
and drew one frame
and that was it
and then the next day
you draw another frame
Unreal is real-time
different techniques are used
especially now
when we have ray tracing
we are moving in that direction
I mean, ray tracing is a totally different thing
it's not that
but they are moving in that direction
and at some point
it will be possible to start
with those machines
that are not used so much now
so they are forcing
real-time movie making
and it's much more valuable
it's easier to change
maybe you don't make
the same quality
but you can change
in the scene
in the movie itself
how you do it
to make a better result
and that's a lot
it can be connected
to Unreal 5
we saw that Lani
I think he came
Lani or before Lani
Unreal 5
I saw that demo
for Unreal 5
when the lady walks
and dances
and it was like
and you were so impressed
that you had a headache
they marketed it
very well
Unreal 5
it's a version bump
but
we are on Unreal 4
.27
and that was Unreal 5
but
let's say that it's Unreal 4
.30
not such a difference
in programming terms
it's still the same engine
the same engine
let's talk about marketing
it's the same engine
there are new features
huge features
you can open
Unreal 4.27 project
in Unreal 5
and it will work
you don't need to do anything
the difference is
that they added
node called Nenite
for virtualized geometry
so you don't need
to deal with performance
and they added a lot of other things
that they added
just because they added that
you need real-time lighting
or illumination
illumination
and then different
shadow casting
that shadow casting
that is more dynamic
because traditionally
that shadow casting
is different
and if you have that Nenite node
it doesn't work anymore
and you need a different
shadow casting
but the code is the same
in the end
all those new features
it's unstable
you don't need to use it
even Epic said
don't ship anything
we don't know where it went
it's a full heavy performance hit
when you add that Nenite
you think, ok cool
now I can perform much better
but the problem is
we need global illumination
and now we need to cast those shadows
in every 10ms frame
so for once
we don't know
how much of that will be used
especially for a game like MatTV
that happens a lot
multiplayer and all
is it even more known
than single person
or some easier mechanic
it's most known for
big open world games
like you are
which we aren't
in this game it's known
we had a lot of characters
and those characters
don't get anything
because Nenite is only
for static geometry
so this is still classic
but it goes in that direction
that
their goal
is not to make things look better
but to make it easier
at the moment
we make a level
one model
then we need to generate
level of detail models
which are always wrong
and then you need a system
that handles that
then you go to the side
and you need to optimize
that character
and put less material
and less texture
and when you're done
it lasts
I don't know
half an hour
it means that you need to
calculate the light
for every option
where the light is
and you can see that
for every map
you can build this
and that
let me explain
for every level
I need to calculate
for every option
where the light is
and then I need to bake it
is that right?
you calculate the light
for the player
it doesn't matter
because they move
for static objects
you calculate that
plus you calculate the essence
and you bake it
and you put it in the binary
and that's very confusing
and there's one more thing
and that's not the only thing
there's one more thing
for one model
you have the level of detail
but you don't have it all
and now you need to put
a hierarchical level of detail
specific for that level
and combine it
in one model
and we call that H-LOD
and you need to build that too
and it lasts
50 minutes, 40 minutes, 30 minutes
and then it crashes
and then you do CI
isn't that a beefy machine
where you say calculate
and it lasts for 3 days
now we use
team city
to coordinate things
we have a beefy machine
and
it builds
it plays by itself
everyone has their own part
where they live
but in the past
someone had one at home
another programmer
for that
highlight
Goran told us
that there's so much
change
for engine and game
builders
tooling for artists
who have to
work on assets
characters
that tooling
wasn't mature
for that complex
besides that
there's ray tracing
because
now
when an artist works on a model
he has to simplify things
there can't be too much detail
that's why we bake details
into a normal map
that shows you the details
in a hacky way
if you want to have a reflection
then you have a material
and you write in a texture
the right things
but that's all
full of
layers
and
it's all
in a
that you have to add and save for them, and I don't know what.
If you have such a system, then you don't have to
hack it, because it handles it, when you import it,
the engine handles it, and it streams it in such a way
that you get exactly what you need, and nothing more, nothing less,
and you don't have to mess with it. If you have ray tracing,
for example, you don't have to mess with various reflections,
which you hack in some way, and stuff like that.
In fact, game development is full of hacks.
And if you want to have a scene, if you want to have a view,
you make a camera that captures the whole world,
and then you capture it as a texture.
I've heard that it's true.
It's more because of the design.
Because of the design, yes.
Yes, and your job is to make a matrix
on a very weak hardware,
so people think it's like that.
And if someone doesn't watch it, it's not like that.
Our animations disappear
if you don't watch them.
We had a problem that people didn't hear
if someone was following them. Of course not.
If they were walking, right?
I still have this question.
I think we touched on how you handle
spike games.
You mentioned that you have
a suicide code.
Probably after you went to the Steam store,
you were on the first chart,
and then the Kickstarter.
Yes, everyone cursed at me.
The game is successful.
Purely on hard.
I didn't have a back-end,
but my colleague who had it said
that he made it,
everything worked,
but when you play it so much,
it doesn't work at all.
I think that in two days
we changed the back-end on Steam.
Besides that, a lot of other things
didn't work.
The servers had a docker
that made the server perform
in a terrible way.
I fixed it a bit,
but I don't remember now.
Is that from the perspective
of SRE?
You also sold a lot of
Gatling and KSX for load testing.
Is that because you didn't test
the load of your system?
You didn't expect that?
Honestly, I don't know
how much we tested,
how much time we had for that.
He was doing all the testing.
That's how it should be.
At the last moment,
there was nothing bad.
In the end, we fixed everything
until the first week,
because there's always a peak on Sunday
and everything works until Friday.
Is there an email prepared
for SRE?
If a vendor calls,
which one does it depend on?
It's all about the scenarios.
If you show people
all of their information,
if you show them all of your equipment,
leveling, progress,
it's all about the map.
That's how I see it.
I know what you're saying.
You're a technical person.
I'm just trying to see
if you have an email.
Let's talk a little bit
about engineering.
A few weeks ago,
Microsoft CEO said
that they're having a hard time
with C and C++.
They're putting a lot of emphasis
on Rust as a language of the future
for low-level system programming.
I have a question for you.
Will C++ always dominate
this industry and this market?
Do you think that Rust
is a language of the future
for low-level systems?
I don't know.
Rust is very specific.
What we're doing with C++
in Unreal is a subset
defined by them.
It's a little bit like sellotape.
You see the macro,
put it up, and it works.
It's a little bit scary.
At the beginning,
we didn't have any problems
because C++ is so nicely handled.
It has its own containers
and garbage collection.
For real-time gaming,
it's really tricky.
You can't have a spike frame.
In simple games,
if you have 120 frames per second,
you have a spike of 5 milliseconds.
It's important that they handle it.
We've never had any problems.
Do you use C++ as a compiler?
Is it Unity or Visual Studio?
No, it's Visual Studio.
You have to know Visual Studio.
You don't have other options.
It's very portable.
If you're making an Unreal Engine,
you can repack it for different platforms.
We've been talking about it
for a year now with Porting
so it's not exactly the same.
You have to have store integration.
At the beginning,
you had PlayStation, VR,
Xbox and Nintendo.
It all works.
If you're going to Nintendo,
do you have to have someone
who's an expert for Nintendo?
Do you think you can trust the technology?
No, you don't have to be an expert.
I mean, you have a lot of
macros for Blender.
Yes, of course.
There are a lot of details.
If you have a machine,
it's better.
Shaders don't work anymore.
You have to lower it a bit.
Unreal Engine does it well.
It's a multi-platform game
and you can set the settings
and play the same game.
It's very well supported.
Are you going to have crossplay?
I don't think so.
PC player base is too skilled.
Do you have it on Steam?
No, we have it on Steam.
Our backend is on PlayFab.
Backend is a multi-platform game.
PlayFab connects to everything
and it's very helpful.
Epic Online Services
is very free.
It's a very good backend.
What do they get out of it?
Epic account.
Is it included in the 5% royalty?
Yes, it is.
I don't know if it can be used for Unity.
I think it can.
They want you to have an Epic account
and you log in,
and you get friends and players.
I understand.
I forgot to ask.
2 out of 9 in Unreal Engine
are interesting.
One is MetaHuman.
Is it interesting for you and your characters?
We worked on a pre-production
and I don't think we'll use it.
Maybe we will.
It looks really good.
What is MetaHuman?
MetaHuman is a system
created by Epic.
It's a system for creating
fully realistic people.
Human characters.
It has rigged and animation ready.
You can pose it,
add facial hair,
and it's generated on the sliders.
If you have a realistic game,
it's a go-to.
It's 3D scanned.
It's high resolution.
It scans people?
No, you can't get close to it.
The problem is that it's so good
that you can't compare it
to any other game you have.
I see you added Megascans to the game.
Megascans are like MetaHuman,
but for other objects.
They are fixed in the library.
You can't add them.
You can't do everything with Megascans.
The problem is,
what do you do when you have to add
something new that doesn't exist?
Like Megascans.
If you have everything with Megascans,
and you add something that doesn't exist,
you make a mistake.
And then you have to fix it.
With Megascans, for example,
if you have a stone,
usually it's 3D scanned,
and you see what's shooting out.
But we turn the stones around
and put them here and there.
Megascans are cool,
but they look exactly the same.
I remember two more things.
You mentioned VR.
More how to VR.
How many people ask you that?
Not that many.
It's an interesting idea.
We're working on a new project,
and all the projects we're working on
are 3-4 years long.
So we're only focusing on that.
But VR is interesting because it's growing.
There's adoption on Quest.
Quest is huge.
It's being sold like Xbox Series
and PlayStation 5 consoles.
It's huge.
Before, it wasn't feasible.
You released a VR game,
but it's still a compact experience.
You don't need 3 years.
In a year or two,
with a team of 5 people,
you can make a VR game.
We're still looking for people.
We need 30 people for our main game.
There are 22 of us,
so maybe 5 more people.
We have 6 Oculus girls
in the office.
We're thinking about that.
Facebook is also interested.
Maybe.
We don't know yet.
Are you going to release the games
in pre-production?
In pre-production,
most of the people are still at Mordhau.
It's just the beginning.
Maybe next year,
we'll be in full production.
I have a community question.
It's an interesting time now.
You can work from home.
If you want to work at home,
you can work on games.
You can do everything by yourself.
In the office.
It's too big.
You need a bit more space.
I was thinking about working at home.
That's why you need a house.
Or a small office.
A quarter of the size.
We had a catapult.
It can't be 90 kg.
But it's something.
People can learn everything.
It's a strange golden age of knowledge.
We used to go to libraries
and take C++ books.
Then you had a CD.
Then you worked on Windows.
Now you can do it all at home.
I wonder how you and your team
are connected.
Are you connected to Slovenia?
Are you connected to our region?
It's not that important.
Are you connected to male enthusiasts?
I understand.
I agree with what you said.
If you want to be a legit
spokesperson
in certain industries
you have to come to the game.
You can't just show
what you have.
You have to be credible.
But you have to come to a point
where you want to convince people.
When it comes to work
we were the opposite.
We were remote in the beginning.
Until Lani we were 100% remote.
Then we moved to Ljubljana
and now we have 22 people
who are physically in Slovenia.
Do you have a lot of people in Slovenia?
No, they are mostly here.
One of them is from the original team.
The other ones went to do their own things.
They have been here for 8 years.
We have a Slovenian team.
We are still looking for people.
It's a different feeling
when you are in the office.
It's definitely easier to work
when you don't have to focus on the media.
You can coordinate things
and that's a huge plus.
Andras wanted to ask
about the European game.
How did the indie festival come about?
We were a bit unlucky
with the timing.
We released 2.19
and then Corona hit.
We were at Gamescom
and connected with the developers.
We also had the SGC conference.
Then it kind of stopped
and now it's starting again.
I hope it will continue.
Today's episode is a bit longer
than usual, but...
I just wanted to say that
Lulat is our...
No, I didn't mean that.
I just wanted to say that
I don't know, I think it's possible.
Marko, what would you like to conclude?
I would like to ask
that there is so much knowledge,
energy, optimization,
details...
Now it's going to be explicit.
There is a lot of shit in this game.
And when I listen to it,
I think that 30 euros for a game like this
is way too much.
A lot of engineering knowledge,
passion and knowledge.
I think it's...
Congratulations for a successful release.
Congratulations for overcoming
all those technical challenges.
I think it's possible to play this game.
I don't have any questions,
but I think the price is too low.
I don't know about that,
but I understand what the market is like.
It's not easy to help you.
You have to balance a few things
with the price.
It depends on how many players you have.
If you give a high price,
you can sell the same amount
but with fewer players.
That's why it's free to play.
By the way, today, Thursday,
I don't know when it goes up.
On Monday.
We have a free weekend.
Today we have a free weekend.
Today we have a free weekend at home.
Let's talk about social media.
We can write about it,
we can talk about it,
we can promote it
and listen to the content.
We can do whatever we need to do.
Damage is probably the top.
Now you're a director.
You're not a technical director.
You're a technical director.
I'm also a technical director.
How do you balance that?
Tell me more about that.
I've heard from you that those challenges
with milliseconds and shaders
are more interesting than
what you're doing now.
No, that's for sure.
I've taken on some other responsibilities.
Then I put them aside.
So everything is balanced in time.
There's always something new.
It's not about managing people.
That's not my goal.
Yes, in time.
We find someone else to manage it.
You delegate.
Marko Grgurovic,
thank you for sharing your knowledge
and experience with us today.
We wish you all the best
in the future.
I wish you all the best.
Do you want to add anything?
No, thank you for the invitation.
I don't know.
If you're making games,
send us an email.
If you're interested in working in the industry,
We're open to suggestions.
We're here.
We have a few more industries in Slovenia.
Not only mobile,
but we also have a studio.
Thank you.
I'd like to thank
Goran Kudruno, Janko Tometelko
and Andrei Skoto
for helping us prepare this episode.
Thanks to Andraž Brodnik for co-hosting.
Thank you.
If you liked this episode,
please share it.
Leave a comment and play some games.
So, get up in the morning and go to bed.