10 seconds have elapsed. We can start with a special episode of the garden, with the first experimental episode that we added today, the first video and we have gathered here
that today we will try to upgrade our garden and finish the first season and add lights, microphones, videos and set up an experimental platform for the future.
And today we have a special guest here, we have Tom치코 Zaman, and with me is Mr. Sraka.
And today we have gathered here to talk a little bit about greenhouses, to talk a little bit about gardening, to talk a little bit about why it is such a great start.
Now here we have a bunch of cameras, light, cyberpunk theme we have chosen and we have done all this so that we could talk about Type 3 and PHP.
Today we have invited Zaman and Skobilja.
This is all being edited, right?
I don't know, because we have spent a lot of money on cameras and gear, so I don't know if we have a lot of money for post-production.
My intro to the guests is disastrous, so I have to ask you first if you can introduce yourself and tell us who you are and where do you start.
Ok, I am Tom치코 Zaman, not Zaman, from Skobilja, not Skobilj. Skobilja is a vast village on the Slovenian side, which is in Hungary.
What do I do for a living? Well, at the moment, as you mentioned, I work in a printing house, or I want to create a name in the printing house business.
But my career in the printing house business lasts a year or two at most. Before that, I was the founder of a company in Denmark called Codable, and this company will be celebrating its 10th anniversary in January 2023.
I decided that it was time to take on a new challenge. I fell in love with the company, and I fell in love with the printing house.
It was a challenge for me to be attracted to it. I mean, I didn't enjoy it, but I have to thank God that I am lucky enough to be able to decide and change things around me,
to get a job, to go into the future of happiness, because I think that today there is too little emphasis on that. From the very beginning, we raise kids, they go to school, they get a job, and then they die.
I see that I am happy, that the people around me are happy, and maybe the kids grow up in that direction.
Very interesting. We have known each other for a long time, and we have had the opportunity to meet. You and your wife fly into my Twitter stream. Thank you for that.
Yes.
So you are starting something, right? You are now taking over the influence. I don't know, because I clicked on one of your YouTube videos by accident, you are now a YouTuber.
Yes, a 14-day career. Actually, I want to make a name for myself, even at home, maybe, because I used to, well, I don't think of it as a compliment, just a compliment, but I made a name for myself in the WordPress world,
because we somehow found it in my previous business, and we went around the world at various conferences, and I reached a level where people knew who I was.
We are a Slovenian band, because we practically didn't have a website in Slovenia, which is such a small market for these things that we are not interested in advertising or anything like that.
We are quite well-known around the world, I would say maybe among the top 10-20 companies in terms of knowledge or some reputation. So it was very outside-focused all together.
Now, with Tipkovnica, I would say that you would like to start in Slovenia as a sort of playground. The market is so small that even if everyone knows that you are doing something great, there are still very few people who know that you are doing something great.
If you look at a wider audience globally, you can see that you are growing very quickly, and I'm a bit of a fan of these things, especially the promotion of Tipkovnica.
This is your hobby, right? Those lights, right? And all that gear, right? That's probably what attracts you. If you go there, you still experiment in those waters, right?
Yes, that's true. That's the other side of the coin. I don't know why I have so many lights. I have so many lights at home, and the postman brings a new one, and the woman holds her head, because I have so many lights.
And then I said, OK, but we have to use them in something, because there are not enough people, because if you have them, you have them, and that's it. And then I said, well, I'm going to put a YouTube studio at home, and I'm going to light it up nicely.
For my taste, it's a pretty good job, but other colleagues and friends can see how you light it up, and then the debate starts, so I can say that I'm making a hobby out of this.
I wrote to you in the intro that you would like to draw from you today love for technology, passion, persistence, extreme focus.
What did I want to draw from this question, to ask you, why do you want to do something? I think that a lot of your projects you do for yourself, for your fun, you have to have some kind of passion for these things.
I think that if you find that passion, then you are 100% committed and brutally focused. And what if it's not like that?
I've never been to a proper diagnosis, but I always, I don't know if it's an excuse or not, but I often say that I have a little ADHD, a little bit of obsessive-compulsive disorder.
One extreme is that when someone accepts me for a reason that I don't know, and then they hold me, and at the moment they are lights, and I buy lights, and I choose lights, and why they are the way they are, and how they work, and color spectrums, and I'm looking for a lot of things.
I don't have a business need for these things, I'm just interested, and then I draw as long as it takes, and it takes a long time.
Do you go to the end, or do you try?
I'll put it this way, it depends on what the end is. Sometimes I get to a level where my brain says, okay, that's good enough, let's move on.
Sometimes I draw them, for example, against the walls, specifically, because I thought, okay, let's do one again, and it will be good enough. But no, let's do one for every other countryman, and let's do half of them.
But on the other hand, there are things that don't attract me, don't interest me, and I won't do them. I mean, it's like paying the bill. And we didn't make a deal here.
Here, the deal is just that I have to log into a joint bank, I mean, I have to open a bank, and then I have to show my picture on my phone to be identified, and they give me a bill, and then I have to put it in my computer, and then I go to the next step.
In the next step, I get another bill, and then I have to put it in my phone again, and then I have to enter the numbers in there, and I get sick of it. But you haven't made a deal there yet, and then when you pay, you have to send the bill to the accountant. It's a pain.
How did you optimize this part of your life? Because everything that is in this composition, let's say, you have four children.
Yes, yes, yes.
This work-life balance, how do you manage it now? When you start from scratch, and you're healthy now, and at the same time you still have to take care of your family, and then there are other things to do, because you also have to pay bills.
Yes, look, my recipe was that I learned, and then you just have to, because a woman comes with advantages and advantages, and also with a stick in her hands, I'm not kidding.
My wife is a great woman, and she also strengthens this balance for me at times, because she has to, because sometimes I fall so much into something that I ignore life.
It's like, I don't know, you have to drive your children to training, and it's already 6.30 in the morning, and I'm already in one thing until 8 in the morning, and instead of going to eat something, a few cigarettes that don't hurt, and then back to action.
Now I take it so much that I walk the dog a little in the garden to get some fresh air, but I fall so much into it that sometimes a woman comes and says, Tomas, you know you have four children, and I don't.
I'm not kidding, but she's the one who pulls me out of that hardcore focus. But on the other hand, she's also my biggest fan, which is also amazing.
That she always supports me in all my stupidities, I don't know, I told myself I'd be a YouTuber. Most people are like, hahaha, what's wrong with you? And my wife is like, go for it.
Everything is like that. We set up the last farm from scratch, and if my wife hadn't stood by my side, because we had four small children, credited, without cash, it really was a low point.
And she actually brought me the rhythm, if I may say so, that we succeeded. Without her, there is no chance. That I can write four small rhythms, write a healthy code, sign agreements, promote, I mean, no go.
You have to let go of something. And for us, it was a woman, my luck, and in the final phase, it's both women in the court of that relationship.
I don't get it, how do you do it?
What do you mean?
You have a kid, and ten companies, how many do you have?
Well, it's just ten women at a time.
Ten women, or what?
Or one that's worth ten, right?
No, here's the thing, in the issues you mentioned, like passion, you also include children, right?
Do children say such things, that you've started to combine something, so that the children are already...
No! No! Children want to play football!
And that's so... No, I support them, they won't help, but...
I have to admit, I'm totally anti-football.
I think the whole team is here, but okay.
I wouldn't say that, but anti-sport. I only deal with sports because of my health.
I'm not like someone who watches sports on TV, whatever.
It doesn't stimulate me, so I don't really care about that.
I do want the kids to be a bit...
Look, my first child, I'd coach football, cool, right?
You're a football coach, and you take your two kids, I mean, your oldest and youngest,
and you take them to football, and they're good, and they go to competitions, and so on.
Whatever comes to mind.
But yeah, you want to be a programmer, but...
They're in those years when they're so in love with football, and that's it.
It's a bit too early for that.
We'll see. But I do want to be able to help.
I mean, look, financially you have to, because they're your kids,
but I want to be able to do more than just financially.
But we have more times, let's say, if I apply to what we said before,
I want to tell them that it doesn't matter where they start, as long as they're happy.
That's the most important thing to me.
Don't look at it as a challenge.
I think that today, as a society, it's like, what do you do?
And it's not like you're going to...
It's like you're going to deceive a person.
His value changes depending on where he starts.
I do that to all my kids.
You have to work hard.
You can't do without it.
You're not someone who's going to make you happy,
because then you're going to win in life.
If you're happy, I think that's number one.
You know, when you listen to these inspirational speeches,
and all together...
If you look back at your youth,
and when you were just looking,
you probably didn't expect to work with technology,
with computers.
You probably could've looked for it yourself.
You probably could've put a lot of effort into researching it.
Or you were like, I'm going to program it now.
I'm not that, probably.
But it's a passion, right?
Yeah.
Actually, in IT, I fell...
I fell for it.
Actually, it was like this.
I worked in the Biotechnical Faculty,
in the Department of Forestry.
After graduation, I was almost a forestry engineer,
because I didn't graduate.
I practically did everything.
I was a full-time gamer until FACS.
I'm still a full-time gamer.
I'm not ashamed to admit it.
Even today, when we come home,
we'll be with our colleagues, we've changed...
What are you doing today?
Tea, tea, tea.
My colleagues have their readings this week and next week,
so even at midnight, if I come, we'll be gaming.
What are you playing today?
Escape from Tarkov.
We'll be shooting each other in the head.
But...
Wait, no, no, no.
That's really bad.
What?
If you come home late today,
who will you be playing games with?
With my colleagues.
For example, I have a colleague from Germany.
You'll be sleeping with your wife and kids, right?
Yes, that's right.
But have you changed?
Yes, yes, yes.
I ping them on Discord.
Action, let's go.
Online.
Are they older or younger?
Both.
And younger teams.
We've been living happily ever after,
because we've been playing together for a few years.
We're 200 old, 40 give or take,
and 200 old, 25 give or take.
And we've been happy.
We went to the seaside together for a few days.
Retreat.
We're a proper team when we're gaming together.
You know.
So, yeah.
And in my third year at Fax,
I somehow had a hard time.
There wasn't a single moment
where I was really drawn to the game.
And that's why I said to myself,
OK, I'll program the website a bit,
to see what it looks like up and down.
And I actually pirated
some online courses for PHP.
Woo!
Yes, but I have to admit,
that I pirated them for a few years.
But then, when we started using Scodable,
when we started using Dnar,
I signed up for the same website I had pirated.
And for a long time, I was paying the membership,
for as long as I was using pirated copies.
Just because it was fair to give it back,
because it was what Jaro did in the end.
You realized that you had to...
Yes, that's right.
Sometimes you realize that
the more effort you put into it,
the more you start looking at it differently.
Especially if you can translate it.
And I've now turned to this page,
the first page of my notes.
And on this page...
Do you need help?
No.
And on this page, I've now written Codable.
OK.
Not PHP, I think it's PHP.
It's all connected.
Just wait for us to get to you.
Because in the past,
when we were just starting,
some engineering and language examples,
there was a lot of feedback.
When will there be PHP?
Yeah, shit, yeah.
And in the last comment,
there was a comment that there will be PHP in the kitchen.
What are we going to do?
Yeah, I mean, we had...
Well, yeah, a lot of people...
A lot of people...
I won't say it again.
A lot of people are using PHP.
PHP is still an extremely popular language.
Why?
You're going to tell us now.
And our audience is growing,
and somehow it represents
a large segment of our web development audience.
And logically,
people want to hear more about PHP.
Now...
Let's do this...
Take on...
PHP,
and try to connect it to Codable.
Tell us why...
Why did you make Codable,
and where does it connect?
We need to know that.
And let's move on to...
What was it, 10 years ago?
2013.
It says 2012.
Yeah, okay, 2012.
Yeah, well, all the beginnings were before.
On a business day,
or when we established the firm in 2013,
we were already working on it before.
PHP
has
one good feature,
and one bad feature.
What do you mean?
He wants to finish.
And that's it.
The main thing...
Okay, yeah.
Both, really.
I mean,
the good thing is the early...
No, not early.
Low barrier to entry.
That's because you can load it very quickly,
the documentation is huge,
the examples are huge,
the tutorials are huge.
He has his
embedded
story,
which he really cares about,
and...
Personally,
when I see Codable,
it has these tags in it,
in HTML,
and whatnot.
The bad thing,
for example,
is that a lot of people
stopped there.
It's so fast
in some tasks,
which is a plus,
that people stop
and wonder why it's so fast,
or why
they don't get bored.
With these basic constructs
that language offers,
I think a lot can be done,
and a lot of people,
especially in my freelancing career,
which was before Codable,
corrected some basic constructs
that someone who didn't know
the language enough,
but knew how to sell online,
made on some freelancing portals,
and then hired me
to debug and correct it.
He wrote his own function,
and you have a built-in function
that does the same thing
for one type,
and doesn't need 30 types.
I'm just kidding,
but...
You can say the same thing
about JavaScript,
or other languages in that space.
You can also write Ruby.
Yes, really.
But PHP is the most...
It's a culture that comes from Raven.
I think it's more...
For example,
with my people,
the mindset of people
who are...
I don't want to offend anyone,
I don't mean to offend anyone,
but the average mindset of people
in PHP, in my experience,
is much more satisfied
with the result
than the mindset of people
who write Ruby, for example,
or JavaScript,
who started writing
more difficult languages.
It's subjective,
but since I'm a guest,
I have the right to say
that Ruby is more demanding
than PHP.
I think people go deeper
into the language,
and devote themselves
to education.
It's the same in PHP,
but in my experience,
PHP is more like a community.
It's about doing something good
together.
While...
No, no, I'm talking about PHP.
PHP communities are more like
a kumbaya scene.
You know?
That's my experience.
I have a lot of friends.
I don't mean to derogate them.
They're really good people.
I've been to their conferences.
I still go to them.
I don't go to work anymore,
but I still go to meet them.
It's the law of the community.
On the other hand,
you have RubyFolk.
I've been to a few of their conferences.
I'm a developer,
but I don't bother them.
I go to the other end.
I go there to write
a fucking rocket for Mars
in Ruby.
Maybe it's because you said
that the entry barrier
is so low in PHP.
I don't know.
I would say
that a common application
or something to do again
is to edit a file in PHP
and upload it.
If the problem is solved in Ruby,
if it needs to be fixed,
and connect the server
so that the problem
can be fixed.
It could be that.
In PHP,
as you said,
you can use FTP,
which is ancient,
and allow you to bypass
a lot of best practices,
which are very good in the long run.
As long as Ruby doesn't let you do that.
I mean, both have their place.
I don't want to say
that Ruby is better
or PHP is better.
I know at least a few of them, because thank God all my jobs are so beautiful,
that when I came to Ruby, I could already hire a person who knows a lot more about the topic than I do,
and I could also hire someone for PHP, so I'm interested in a really good programmer,
and I know how to solve a problem pretty well, so to speak.
Let me say, when you moved to Slovenia, you moved because people imagined our cuckoo,
up there is a cuckoo's eye, and you live inside it, in bigger streams, they say it's the end of the world,
and then you fall down there.
And Codable also comes from a problem you somehow discovered when you positioned yourself in that space,
so give me a little beginning, where is that place, where does Codable come from, and why did you make it?
Which problem are you solving?
When my wife moved from Lithuania, where she was born with twins,
we lived there in Lithuania with a very small, modest population, and it was simply too small for four people,
for two it was ok, and at that point her older sister, Dinka, moved in,
and we decided to live in Prekmurje, so she gave us an apartment,
and at first it was like, fuck no, Prekmurje, no!
But later, when we started to think rationally, and started to write some pros and cons on paper,
it was still like, we don't have any horses, ok, Delcje, but that's the only horse,
you know, I have a gigabyte of optics at home in the house, so you don't have to worry about everything,
so, yeah, and, ok, I don't have it at the moment, but there is some project,
or the project has really grown somehow, and we said, ok, let's go,
and we moved up, and that's how I got into web development, and I worked with the TYPO3 system,
and I'm a certified TYPO3 integrator, even though it's version 4.7,
if you don't know the version, how nice it is.
And it's still alive?
Yes, yes, yes, yes, it's a corporate site, like Germany, they still have it,
but I don't know about us, but in Slovenia there was a whole gov scene on it.
I think it's like that for undecided listeners or viewers,
I worked with TYPO3, I don't know, two years ago I showed him how to set up a blog,
that kind of thing, it's very simple and complicated, but,
TYPO3 came about when people started to recognize TYPO3, or PHP, as a language,
as a platform that could be an alternative to Java at the same time, and so on,
and that's when the open source started, and, I don't know how to say it, Kasper,
who made the enterprise CMS for TYPO3.
And for a long time it was like a supervisor for the enterprise,
from Lufthansa to, I don't know who else.
It's a well-known place, where you need to go to school to understand it,
that's the precondition for enterprise software, and, no matter the high price,
without any other support, you can't buy it.
He also had a very good, very small, he had this system of extensions,
you can imagine it as some kind of package management,
which we have in those, I don't know...
Plugin management.
Plugin, and that, and an extension called T3news, which was very powerful,
in fact, as if he had a Wordpress game inside.
Yeah.
You see, I'm impressed.
I know, I know.
Look, I'll tell you this.
Early days, TYPO3 was a very good circle for me,
because I was attracted to it.
Actually, if I go back in time, before I die, it was on a fax,
I went there because, I like to be attracted to things that interest me.
We've already discussed that.
Yeah, and when I started web development, I knew I needed a project.
Because I'm very opinionated.
For example, when younger developers ask me where to start,
don't start anywhere.
Start with the idea you have in mind, or the problem you have,
which you will solve.
I'm very, how do you say it, I mean,
a supporter of learning with a known goal.
I mean, not that I'm going to learn Force, Anche, Wile, whatever,
but find a problem.
I don't have one.
And then it's very difficult to learn.
Find yourself a problem, or find a colleague in a problem.
Ask him, I don't know what he's doing at home,
on the computer, whatever.
Have a problem.
And then go against the problem.
But if you chose TYPO3, you made more problems in the beginning.
That's true.
But I didn't choose it myself.
I went to the fax directly to my computer science professor,
who had a joint venture with Lesar,
which is a truly catastrophic site.
There are also static HTMLs in Driftweaver.
Remember the days.
In Driftweaver, they edited it,
and then copied it to FTP by hand from the fax.
And I said, let's go.
I just found a CMS, which had such a cute logo.
I didn't know anything about it,
and I didn't even know PHP,
if it was really basics,
and I was so overconfident,
so self-assured to the professor.
I would make a joint venture for you.
He was delighted with the idea,
but he was a loser.
TYPO3.
So I said, okay.
Look, it lasted half a year.
At home, I didn't sleep,
and I failed exams,
and I was in a hurry, but I made a site.
I hired a designer,
who was one of the very good designers,
still is, actually.
And he made me an interface.
But let me brag.
He said, how are we going to pay for it?
I said, I'll make a site,
and you'll pay for it,
because I had a scholarship,
and I lived at home,
so the money wasn't a motivator,
because I was too young to have a good feeling about it.
I said, you bought me a 16-inch MacBook Pro,
fully specced out.
And I made a site, TYPO3,
and they bought me a fully specced out MacBook Pro,
and I still have it on the shelf.
It doesn't work anymore,
because the screen cracked,
but it was a high-quality machine for 10 years.
And that's how we started,
and that's how I ended up in TYPO3.
Now, if I go back to what you asked me before,
how it was across the sea.
Across the sea,
I broke ties with the company
behind which I worked here in Ljubljana,
with which we cooperated,
because they wanted to put me on a site.
So I went on a site in Ljubljana,
and we...
And I applied for a job on the internet.
And I found an e-lance site,
and I worked on it for two years,
and in May I decided to get a certificate.
And at the time, there wasn't as much as today,
when you get an online certificate.
I could get in the car,
and drive to the store in the Danube,
and pay 200 euros,
because I was...
I don't know how to call it,
a non-educated...
Certification.
Yes, a certification.
Thank you.
And I paid there,
and then I signed it,
and it was so...
It was hard,
it wasn't like...
No, no,
it was half a year of training.
But the positive result of that
was that I became
much more competitive on those sites.
Because I...
And I could overnight,
and I'm not lying,
overnight I doubled my hourly rate,
and I started having better projects.
That's why I...
Also in Coda,
later on I had my own thing,
for example, I was invited to international conferences,
to teach about not being a price raiser.
Let's...
I wrote that on my own,
I'll burn it all down.
Okay, let's go to the end now.
Yes, that's what I meant.
Well, and...
Because on that portal,
certain functionalities,
approaches,
mentality, founder, whatever,
I was so confused,
that I wanted to be a competitor
to the portal that fucked me up,
because it wasn't like I wanted it to be.
Yeah, I hope you'll go to the bank one day.
Okay, sorry.
Anyway, well, and then I...
I got to know,
while working on that portal,
someone who was on my side,
actually.
The gentleman's name is Per Esbensen,
because he's Danish.
And he was a businessman.
I mean, he sold my computers,
in Danish,
and we got along well.
And we became friends.
I'll tell you my story later.
So...
And then I got to a point where I said,
Per, listen.
I don't...
Marketing,
and banking,
and accounting,
I mean, those aspects...
Accounting.
...accounting,
I'm not...
I'm not used to dealing with that.
I said, let's two competitors
build this portal ourselves,
I'll take a programmer,
I'll program the interface,
everything,
and you'll have all the rest.
And he liked the idea so much,
that he was so tired,
a few days before I told him,
and he called me while he was tired,
when we went to a party,
and he said, Tomas,
this is so good.
I said, do you really know this?
I said, I'll learn,
and we'll do it.
Well, and...
Yeah.
Here's the thing.
I don't know if we got it.
I mean,
this is a site,
or rather,
a site that solves this problem,
that connects some freelancers,
who have their own sites,
developer sites.
Right, right.
So you have a market
for developers,
and for companies
looking for someone
to implement things.
Yeah, yeah.
And back then,
but everyone knew,
everyone knew,
that we two couldn't
compete with someone
like eLens,
who got millions
of risky capital,
couldn't compete with two
NHL players from Prekmurje,
and...
But you didn't know
on the internet.
Yeah, that's true.
Anyway,
and that's why
I decided on WordPress,
especially because
it's a niche,
but a pretty big niche.
I'll be honest,
back then,
I had no idea
about WordPress.
To the point
when we established
a WordPress company,
I hadn't seen
WordPress from...
How did you do
that research?
I don't get it,
I don't get it.
How did you do that research,
that now WordPress
is almost the same?
We knew, for example,
that there has to be
some programming,
because I was a programmer,
but...
WordPress,
after a year,
was selling a lot,
and WordPress was the most...
That was it.
By the numbers.
But developers
were mostly
in WordPress.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
I mean,
you probably
stopped it
so that
a percentage
of the business
goes to you,
or what,
and how does
the market work,
so that it's a bit
more decisive.
Yeah,
let me first tell you
what problems
we had.
When Per
announced his job
at eLens,
150 developers
applied,
of which
from third-degree
countries,
and me.
Me,
when I applied
for some projects,
it didn't matter
if they were from Per
or someone else,
I had to compete
with 149
offers from
third-degree countries,
no,
less-degree countries,
you know what I mean.
Anyway,
the problem was
that
the mentality
of those people
is usually
more of a
fast learner,
someone who can
learn fast,
and that's it.
No quality,
no hard understanding,
just that
fast turnaround,
and they're
so serious,
not all of them,
but most of them
are so serious,
you know,
they have some
written goals
and they just
apply for everything,
and what happens,
happens.
And I said,
I don't like this,
let's create
a portal,
I mean,
what would I solve,
when I introduced
my company
to a
pre-screened
developer,
and I still
face
the biggest challenge
in this company,
which is to keep
the supply
and demand
level.
I mean,
for us,
a developer
is a kind of
expectation
for a system
to be ready
within a few months,
and when we
found it
ourselves,
it's a very
rigorous process,
and it's
optimized time-to-time,
so that,
so that when
you have too many
parties,
and too few
developers,
you will be in
competition,
and if you have
too many developers,
you will be in
competition with
developers,
because they
don't have enough
work.
I mean,
you always want
this,
and this is
always this
balancing act,
never-ending,
which you always
look for,
I mean,
how many
developers,
parties,
right?
I mean,
we had tutorials,
we wrote articles,
we had an e-learning
system,
which was
intended for them,
I mean,
the price,
and if the price
is less than
60 euros per hour,
it's a conversation
with us,
with our customer
support,
why are you
paying so much,
right?
Is it really
that
low-effort
project,
but
then we also
dribbled them,
you know,
price your time,
right?
I don't know what
you did,
then,
for example,
I didn't go,
sorry,
because I couldn't
at the time,
but I was
attracted to
an Indian message,
for example,
because he said,
come,
because of you,
I mean,
because of
what you
enable me,
I will
order,
you know,
and you hear
such a story,
or
our developer
came to me,
so to speak,
so that
this problem
we wanted to
solve in
WordPress.
Do you think
that,
I mean,
if WordPress
is a
garden,
and
if you know
what a garden
is,
then you
can,
for example,
if you're a
good developer,
you really
know what
a garden
is,
and then
you can
technically,
theoretically,
probably choose
a WordPress
site and
do it,
I mean,
you don't
need any
extra
planning
in those
projects,
or what,
if you
probably
wanted to
work,
I don't
know,
with Java
or some
C-Sharp,
the response
of the
project is
completely
different,
then
complications,
then,
you know,
you can't
replicate
it in
any other
site,
no,
you can't
replicate it,
I think
it's because
of WordPress,
because,
look,
I mean,
in most cases,
not all,
but basic
functionality is
that it's
some sort of
split visit,
meaning that
they are more
representative,
less interactive
pages,
of course,
there are
plugins that
you can
use,
but basically
it's a
publishing
platform,
and you
publish content,
now in
what form it
is,
or,
I don't
know,
the principle
of publishing
content is
always the
same,
meaning,
if you
have a
blog,
or you
have,
I don't
know,
a landing
page
or something
like that,
so I
think it
would be
very difficult
to replicate
on some
other
systems.
Well,
probably
so,
Type-O-Tree,
Drupal,
etc.
are
still
in the
same
corner
as
WordPress,
right?
Yes,
they are
still,
conceptually,
they are
still
in the
same
corner
as
Type-O-Tree,
but
they are
still
in the
same
corner
as
Drupal,
and
Type-O-Tree
are
still
in the
same
corner
as
Type-O-Tree,
and
Drupal is
still
in the
same
corner
as
Drupal,
and
Type-O-Tree
are
still
in the
same
corner
as
Drupal,
and
Type-O-Tree
are
still
in the
same
corner
as
Drupal,
and
Drupal
is
still
in the
same
corner
as
Type-O-Tree,
and
Drupal
is
still
in the
same
corner
as
Drupal,
and
Type-O-Tree
are
still
in the
same
corner
as
Drupal,
and
Drupal
is
still
in the
same
corner
as
Type-O-Tree,
and
Type-O-Tree
is
still
in the
same
corner
as
Type-O-Tree,
and
Drupal
is
still
in the
same
corner
as
Type-O-Tree,
and
Type-O-Tree
is
still
in the
same
corner
as
Drupal,
and
Drupal
is
in
the
same
corner
as
Drupal,
and
Drupal
is
in
the
same
corner
as
Type-O-Tree.
We
really
say
that
Raptors
lead
themselves
as
people
in
the
same
corner
as
Type-O-Tree.
We
really
say
that
Raptors
lead
themselves
as
people
in
the
same
corner
as
Type-O-Tree.
We
really
say
that
Raptors
lead
themselves
as
people
in
the
same
corner
as
Type-O-Tree.
We
really
say
that
Raptors
lead
themselves
as
people
in
the
same
corner
as
Type-O-Tree.
We
really
say
that
Raptors
lead
themselves
as
people
in
the
same
corner
as
Type-O-Tree.
We
really
say
that
Raptors
lead
themselves
as
people
in
the
same
corner
as
Type-O-Tree.
We
really
say
that
Raptors
lead
themselves
as
people
in
the
same
corner
as
Type-O-Tree.
We
really
say
that
Raptors
lead
themselves
as
people
in
the
same
corner
as
Type-O-Tree.
We
really
say
that
Raptors
lead
themselves
as
people
in
the
same
corner
as
Type-O-Tree.
We
really
say
that
Raptors
lead
themselves
as
people
in
the
same
corner
as
Type-O-Tree.
We
really
say
that
Raptors
lead
themselves
as
people
in
the
same
corner
as
Type-O-Tree.
We
really
say
that
Raptors
lead
themselves
as
people
in
the
same
corner
as
Type-O-Tree.
We
really
say
that
Raptors
lead
themselves
as
people
in
the
same
corner
as
Type-O-Tree.
We
really
say
that
Raptors
lead
themselves
as
people
in
the
same
corner
as
Type-O-Tree.
We
really
say
that
Raptors
lead
themselves
as
people
in
the
same
corner
as
Type-O-Tree.
We
really
say
that
Raptors
lead
themselves
as
people
in
the
same
corner
as
Type-O-Tree.
We
really
say
that
Raptors
lead
themselves
as
people
in
the
same
corner
as
Type-O-Tree.
We
really
say that
Raptors
lead
themselves
as
people
in
the
same
corner
as
Type-O-Tree.
We
really
say
that
Raptors
lead
themselves
as
people
in
the
same
corner
as
Type-O-Tree.
We
really
say
that
Raptors
lead
themselves
as
people
in
the
same
corner
as
Type-O-Tree.
We
really
say
that
Raptors
lead
themselves
as
people
in
the
same
corner
as
Type-O-Tree.
We
really
say
that
Raptors
lead
themselves
as
people
in
the
same
corner
as
who told me that I'm a permanent codable developer.
And that took a long time.
We even made a poster for it.
We signed it with Per,
Certified Codable Developer.
And that was it.
When he came to the conference, he mentioned it to me.
And that was a great pleasure for me.
So, Certified Codable was based on the satisfaction of the website?
That's right.
And not on the fact that you would go and review whatever was done.
We only went through the vetting process,
to see if he had a technical task.
Otherwise, we didn't go to look at anything.
When he was vetting,
he had 10, 15, 20 projects in mind for those three months.
And then we saw that the average score was 4.7,
which is very good.
And most of them had very high scores,
which we had already cut off.
If there was one, everyone would do it.
But when I got five for the first time,
then something went wrong.
And then they flew out of the system.
Did something happen?
Or is there a situation where the other side with a developer
is doing very well,
and says,
hey, let's go down from the platform,
and we'll do it without you.
That happened a lot.
But the developers started,
let's call it a start in the business.
The start was a lot from the point of view of the side.
But we were so focused on the happiness of our developers,
that they returned us with loyalty.
And we knew, for example,
he came and said,
listen, we want to start.
Then we clicked on the side, local account.
Look, we won't work anymore.
I mean, we can work well on the account.
That's how it is.
There must be some rules,
written or not.
And a lot happened.
Let's say we saw that the developer was working like this.
It all happened in half a year.
For the same side.
And listen, we talked to the side.
And maybe Mika would work exclusively for them,
to hire me.
And then we switched sides,
and we had a meeting live on Skype.
So we're talking now.
Okay, we're live now.
And the side said,
yes, we would hire him, up and down.
Okay, if we do this,
then no problem in the future.
We're not total pussies.
I mean, if he's working through,
you can't look down on him.
It's not fair in the end.
We put him on his feet.
We gave him a lot.
We also had a lot of contrast from them.
Okay, because of that,
a correct attitude.
And it also happened that a developer
came in two years ago.
He said, we don't have the end of the project.
Or the company went bankrupt.
Whatever, we took him back.
Wait, if I understand you correctly,
the developers were actually employed for a long time.
No.
They are still freelancers.
You are still that platform
that provides
the bidding
for projects and that's it.
Yes.
I have a question here.
Now...
Okay, people who are listening.
They're watching.
People who are listening,
probably have a question.
If you're going to work in a tech company
or an agency,
it's a technical interview.
And you have to check
some technical skills
of the candidates.
You could also change your career path.
Yes.
Tell me, maybe...
We haven't established
how many different companies
you worked for before you came to Codeable.
Okay.
I guess you went...
To get to know the process
of a classic company.
You come in and talk.
How different was that process
compared to the technical recruitment
in Codeable?
Was it close?
Was it top secret?
No, it wasn't top secret.
I wasn't involved.
In the beginning,
the first X was
a gut feeling.
To see what V is talking about.
And there was
brute force.
The parties are happy, good enough.
The parties aren't happy.
In that funnel,
you get people in,
and through the video rating,
you give them an opportunity to try.
Yes.
The first freelancers
I got because I published
a fake project on the competition.
I got them, and then I
tied them up.
The competition probably returned you
with the same attitudes.
I have no idea.
They weren't you.
They weren't successful.
It was really high.
We did have
a technical process,
but at that point,
it was 4-5 years in.
I wasn't involved
in that process anymore.
We had employees
who dealt with it,
especially on customer support,
when they were hired for it.
Now I have
two dots here.
I love customer support.
That's what I wrote.
I wrote it with all my heart.
You probably have a passion
for customer support.
It's the same thing as PHP.
Or worse.
I know a conversation
where they wrote
that if you have so much
customer support,
you went on rotation,
learned about parties,
problems.
Did you learn anything from it?
This might be a topic
that he won't want to talk about.
Wait.
I want to be...
Political correctness.
Look.
I love customer support.
Of course, I'm crazy
about customer support
until someone else does it.
I mean,
the drama
that human nature
brings
isn't close to my heart
if I'm politically correct enough.
I'll tell you this.
When you wake up in the morning
and someone writes
that you're great as a company,
that you're doing great.
Dear listeners of this podcast,
let me draw you
a picture of typical support
of the environment.
People who are satisfied
with their work
don't do it.
In short, what
you have left on customer support
are people who are dissatisfied.
And sometimes
they're not satisfied
at all,
and sometimes they're total assholes.
With a big P and other
lines, they call you
and draw a line.
And no matter what you give them,
they're not satisfied.
And this is, for example,
if you're more
empathetic,
then it
exhausts you.
You talk to one person for three minutes
and you're totally
lost that day.
So,
customer support is not for me.
But luckily,
what's cool,
Americans are fantastic
at it. Then I hired
an American,
and we hired
a guy named David.
And David was like
everything is awesome.
American
principle, yes.
And he was followed by speech forks.
They were shameless.
And he was like, yeah, cool, we'll solve it.
And I was like, how
do you have to do that?
And he was like, yeah,
smile.
Do you think it's
really solving problems,
or do you also get some insight
how to develop a product in the final phase
of the company, or is it
a myth?
The fact is,
you established a company
that is Danish,
but you worked globally.
Sometimes the pages are remote,
sometimes the clients are remote.
How do you develop a product
in such an environment
when you don't see the pages?
Is it all gut feeling or
metrics?
You get feedback.
Before I got to Carriker,
not all pages
are that hardcore.
You have a page that is told
and some don't like it.
And that's huge.
So you get
a story,
an idea,
where the company could move.
We got feedback
from our developers.
We got feedback from everywhere.
We met at conferences,
we had a dedicated forum
where we talked with them.
We had a Discord chat.
So there was a lot of feedback
from the developers.
The pages also told
what they were missing
or what would be different.
Based on that,
we decided
where we would go.
It's like that,
squeaky wheel gets the grease.
The pages were louder,
you remember them more
and there's an additional weight
on the features that would solve
their problem.
I would like to
ask you two more questions
and then we'll move on.
Go ahead.
Automatic,
is a company
that has a name
WordPress.com,
WordPress Cloud.
They are the biggest
commercial offer
of WordPress products in the world.
They are affiliated with
the WordPress label.
Yes.
Atomic
also invested in Codable.
Automatic.
Automatic also invested in Codable.
Yes.
Tell us how did it happen?
Why did it happen?
How did it help you?
It was like that.
They didn't invest in itself,
but they bought a company
that was a co-owner of Codable.
That means
when we started with Codable,
we didn't have
anything.
We needed
a strategic partner
that would offer
their side
or prepared parts.
We came
to a contact
from a company called
WooThemes,
a South African company.
I sent
a cold email.
They didn't answer.
Then they answered.
We started talking.
We wanted
a partnership with them
because we didn't have any side.
We are a new actor on stage.
We started talking
and they asked
for a partnership.
We couldn't offer them
any side or income.
We could only offer them a company.
But there is a potential.
We gave them
3 or 5 percent.
I don't remember.
It's been 10 years.
We gave them a percentage.
When they acquired
Automatik,
a co-owner of
All Things WordPress,
they bought WooThemes.
I think they
changed their name to WooCommerce
because it was
their most popular plugin.
They bought WooThemes
and got a share.
How they helped us,
we don't know.
At the same time
it was a problem.
It was more of a bragging right.
A co-owner of
a company called
Automatik
has 44 percent of the shares.
But it was
just a bragging right.
It's hard
because of certain
legal issues.
It brought some
bonuses.
And also
a strategic partner.
Yes, but
there are also
some egos in the back.
I won't...
In my final phase,
from all of us,
those egos were
very expensive
and I think they could have been
better and more...
I'm not talking about the acquisition,
but overall,
I think that in every community
there were some...
This is related to me.
I'll tell you this
so you don't have any more questions.
Those 10 years
of history,
you can say
that it was mostly business.
What are
those...
How did you
learn the most?
What are those
stories
or pitfalls
that happened
that were
failures?
But they gave you
to move forward,
to think, to change
mindset.
And all of that
gave me something.
Is there something like that?
I mean...
I don't know much about it,
but you could say
that in the whole story
there was
that pitfall that
opened my eyes, changed me
or through that difficult
pitfall I was able to understand.
Definitely,
maybe financially,
financially...
Financially,
I mean, I was very
financially down,
when we started
this whole thing.
Maybe
I bring here
in some way to all young
entrepreneurs
to start from zero.
Because you know much more
every small success,
every step forward.
You are very agile.
At that time I was very rude.
When we started,
if I tell you, or I have to tell
this story now,
it's not too long.
I was at the bottom
when we started Codeable,
I was in debt all the time.
And for three months
I was paying for
car leasing.
And
a detective came to me
and sent me home.
A detective came to knock on the door,
I came to get rid of him.
And I got rid of the bag
that I got from the neighbor,
because she didn't have it with her.
And the neighbor came,
she had Juri under her shirt,
I don't remember,
and this detective was calling me
to the bank, and I told him
I could put a dollar
on the account of the bank
and then he called me home.
He was a very friendly man,
so he wouldn't do anything bad.
And then we kissed
and he left, and in a week
I got a bill for 400 euros for his
bank accounts.
So low, so low,
but I couldn't accept it,
because I sat there and cried for two hours.
Because I didn't know, as a family provider
I totally failed
in providing for the family.
It was very, very difficult,
but the science,
or whatever I was drawn to,
is that today I know the value
of everything, I don't know,
partnership, knowledge,
experience, personal growth.
Personal growth means a lot to me.
Because if I tell you
what you know,
we all start from scratch,
we all are born naked.
And you can only
save yourself when the time comes.
And at that time we believed a lot,
even when I have to say
that my wife is
blaming me, or we are,
because she said, we'll have it,
we'll have a foundation, we'll be strong.
These are the stories.
It's easiest
to thank
success,
but success also goes fast
in the final phase.
You know, a lot of times you're happy,
I mean, you watch
this Instagram generation,
because on Instagram
you only see,
let's say, if they're fake or not,
maybe they're some kind of success,
and they always
don't see the effort,
the path,
and all the fails,
that someone made it.
I'm very sure
that there are people who are fake,
and they are some kind of
fake success, but I don't know,
all these successful stories,
and if you take only
athletes,
if you take only
Olympic athletes,
there is so much dedication,
so much effort,
that we, as
spectators, maybe don't see.
We only see the same medal,
or the one at the end.
You know, like they say,
you sold your part,
you deserve it,
but nobody sees
the effort,
and the path,
that you couldn't take.
I mean,
when you asked what is
the takeaway,
the fight,
it is a fight.
I mean, everyone wants
to put a smile face on,
and go to a party,
but inside you don't know
if you're going to make it or not.
You know,
it is a kind of overthinking,
because you don't write it down.
And it is a
crazy thing.
I mean, in the last 8 years,
plus 2 years of suffering,
even when I decided
to sell the company,
it wasn't easy from my point of view.
On the one hand,
I was pregnant,
and on the other hand,
we were sweating and bleeding.
And as a partner,
it was hard,
but how to start,
I don't know.
I don't have the drive,
the drive,
and here,
to go abroad,
the feelings are intertwined
in the final phase,
even if you leave the legal side,
it can take a lot of time
mentally.
And the wars we fight,
I think we talk too little.
I don't know,
when I'm in other interviews,
maybe it's just a hit,
success, success, success.
In fact, instead of a failure,
it's a million.
But once you learn to keep going,
every time you stumble,
you get up and go,
because if you stop,
you stop,
then you can't go up and down.
Try everything,
until you try everything,
I don't know.
This is without words.
No.
I don't know.
When people ask,
what kind of format we have,
I would keep a mainline theme,
you would help me a little back,
if we go too deep,
to keep that balance.
I share.
You hold, I share.
But now you went so deep,
I don't know how to do it.
A little up.
We all prepared for Andra.
Now I'll interrupt you.
One thing came out
for a whole world,
when I heard it,
I thought,
bullshit.
And Yugo told me,
Yugoslav Petkovi캖,
he said,
that there is a saying
in these start-up circles,
when you need money,
ask for advice,
when you need advice,
ask for money.
And it was so easy,
easy for you to understand.
It turned out to be spot on.
Really.
When we fought for a day,
no, no, no,
when we went for advice,
I'm exaggerating a little,
but the day went by quickly.
You can have an idea,
but today
we were working hard.
We didn't need money
more,
but we were busy anyway.
Now we don't need it,
because Vlada can give it to you.
But this saying
reminded me,
when it was said about us,
about all circles of money,
or about everyone in the world,
it's kind of state-owned.
Thank you, Yugo, for listening.
We asked Dra쬰n before,
what were
your biggest fears
when it comes to Codable,
or maybe even now,
in this sub-ethnic sense,
and what are the solutions?
Probably the biggest fear
is to come back
to the position
if you can't provide for your family.
But probably
you have a lot of fears
and worries
as a founder,
as a co-founder,
as a technical leader.
What are your biggest,
for example,
if we are already like the first one.
Two.
We, two women,
quickly reached
a family role.
To be a pressure provider.
And that's
the biggest fear,
what if not.
I have a buffer
that allows me
some amount of experimentation
or laziness,
if you want.
So that fear.
But it's a stupid topic.
People miss it sometimes.
So I didn't
get unlimited
sales from people
to be able to enjoy
my whole life.
So that fear,
how will we move forward?
I mean, how?
Will I succeed again?
I don't know, some statistics say
that 99% of fairs fail.
And now if I have one war,
can I have another war?
And this is directly linked
to my second fear.
Because I had it for the first time.
Very long, very powerful.
We call it impostor syndrome.
When you are new somewhere,
you have a feeling that you don't fit in.
That people are smarter than you.
That they are more capable than you.
So, in short,
you have a feeling that you are
inferior to everyone
in the industry.
And, for example,
I know a lot about new jobs.
I'm full of research.
But still, some people do it
two years more than me.
And these people have a place
for something more than me.
But if I tell you an anecdote
What happened?
I met my hero, so to speak.
I mean, I had a man
who also had a startup
for online freelancing.
And not only did we catch up with this company,
we overtook it.
We overtook it for a long time.
And we met a guy, and he said,
Dude, you're less like that on the inside.
And he said, Dude, you're less like that on the inside.
And you know, it's like, open your eyes,
that we're all some lollipops at the end of the day.
You know, when we all fight,
we want to improve our lives and the lives of others,
in the final phase.
And that fear, that impostor syndrome,
which I now have again, on hardcore,
I mean, those ends are just before the sale,
as they say, at the time of recording this.
And I have a lot of, you know,
what if it doesn't go well,
you know, I mean, I'm really torn.
It's like two years, again,
and things, positive things,
because of which I don't sleep.
I mean, I'm getting into something new.
But again, it's just eating me up, you know.
I still believe that when a few of them are sold,
there will be a review, and they will say,
Wow, look, I have this up and down.
But now it's crazy.
I'd hide in a closet, but it's like,
yeah, I have this syndrome.
I totally understand.
I mean, I totally, totally understand.
No, but, you know,
do you have, like,
in a practical world,
how do you prevent, or,
that this thing doesn't eat you up,
the impostor syndrome?
Do you rush forward?
No, I mean, do you rush forward?
I don't have, like,
I don't have my heroes, you know.
It gives you, or,
how do you say, write it with your heroes, right?
Because you will meet them.
For example, if you're in the same job,
you will meet your heroes, so to speak.
Because you go to the same conference,
they repeat, you know,
topics are intended, or other network events,
you meet them.
And I mean, what happened to me,
is that when you meet them,
you realize that they are all so bloody under the skin,
and they have totally identical
problems and happiness,
and the same things meet them,
and the same fears, and so on.
And the same mindset.
And in the end, you realize that you have
become more friendly to people
than to some
inferior being, right?
So, you know,
go to those people,
get to know them, and you will see that.
But, I mean, because I haven't met those people yet
in the world of typesetters,
I still have, and I believe that I will go
through that, for example, when, I don't know,
the sale will take place, and people will be happy,
I will get to know them,
but I'm not there yet.
I'll drink a glass of water,
I'm going to turn this side now.
Right, right.
It's not an empty glass, look.
It was half empty, wait.
Okay.
Look, um...
Now, um...
And you just made such a flowchart
diagram, how good.
I like that you're getting ready for that.
For me, right?
Yeah, yeah.
Look, um...
I hope that those who
saw YouTube
with your typesetter,
that they will forgive us because we went
full Codable, and maybe full Excited
are waiting for us to talk about typesetters.
Okay. But I wanted to first tell
what Codable is,
because I wanted to somehow tell the story.
Who are you, where do you come from,
what is your relationship to technology,
where does that passion come from.
Um...
And now...
The next chapter I'm going to talk about
is typesetters.
Yeah.
And...
Now, is it about typesetters,
or about typesetters?
We'll talk about... Which direction are we going to turn?
First, I mean, first we have to talk logically
about typesetters, so we can fit that part
in, but...
I would say, first of all,
both of us love to work
in a virtual world.
You also come from
Codable, which is basically
in the air, right?
And then,
today we are in our own world,
we are fully virtual,
as a programmer, as someone else,
and it's really
a good feeling
when you take some physical lessons
and today you brought us this typewriter,
the typewriter has two keys,
and it's a really
beautiful piece, aesthetically,
and it has its sound,
and it has its color,
and it has, you know,
a physical product,
and it's a good feeling when you take it
in your hands and it's really congratulations to you.
Thank you.
I know it's such a premium product that
maybe our listeners and viewers
won't see it, if they don't really come,
and then you'll do a great job, right?
But it's really impressive,
if you ever see this piece,
try it, you'll see the difference.
When you brought it,
we also put it on the table with the Chinese,
I think, and with some other typewriter,
the difference is very obvious.
I don't know if I'll ever try it,
I don't try it, but
it's impressive, so thank you.
Now, at the end of this debate,
I won't
go too deep,
because you made
a really great intro in the typewriter itself,
I'll put a link below,
so people can watch it.
Also, there's so much passion
and love in this video,
that I can't get closer
to my perspective,
but I'll try it anyway,
so forgive me
and also the dog for doing this.
No problem.
I would go through a process
that you went through,
and I would...
I would prefer you
to go through the process,
I would ask you directly,
why the fetish of the typewriter?
I mean, can I say
about the fetish?
Yes, absolutely.
You're not...
I mean,
your passion
was seen
and heard,
how you express it,
but now,
why exactly
the typewriter?
I don't know. My ex-boyfriend decided
that he's crazy about it.
I don't have an explanation.
But you bought a dog, right?
Yes, no, that was...
I mean, here's the whole story.
I didn't get it.
I solve my own problem.
That was in 2018.
I was in America,
and I brought
a top-of-the-line PC,
with the components you bought there.
It was so amazing.
I think I bought it
in a cheap store,
and I bought it
for 15 euros,
which is a bit more expensive.
No go.
Apple keyboard is a bit more expensive.
You know,
everything is so soft.
It's like aluminum.
Yeah,
it's still flimsy.
Aluminum is also cellophane.
I mean, not cellophane,
that foil.
In short,
I couldn't buy it.
Even today,
my demands were not met.
For a lot of things,
something is missing.
But in the end,
I couldn't focus on both sides
because
first of all,
I wanted to have a smaller format,
like Mono.
For those who don't know,
my keyboard is called Mono.
I think that doesn't mean much.
When I say Mono,
I mean my own keyboard.
I wanted it to be all aluminum,
no plastic.
I mean, it's plastic,
it doesn't matter.
Now I'm waiting for ceramic keys.
My wife doesn't have one,
so I'll get a ceramic one tomorrow.
Wait, wait, wait.
We have a brick.
No, wait, wait.
What's ceramic?
Sticks.
Ceramic sticks?
Yeah, sticks are fully ceramic.
I mean, ceramic sticks.
And they're very soft.
Proper sticks, not gimmicks.
It's a kickstarter.
Is it custom-made?
No, no, it's standard.
The sticks are standard.
Cherry MX made the standard
and they stick to it.
The sticks have different profiles.
Profile is the height.
But the sticks
that you put on the glass
are all MX.
And you're right,
it was a kickstarter project
where I supported it and ordered
two sets of ceramic sticks
because it's for two printers.
Yeah, two sets.
The set is for one printer.
Where did I stop?
65% format,
fully aluminum,
so it's heavy, so it doesn't move
around, so there's no branding.
I hate overbranding.
Well, not overbranding,
but this.
Like an apple or something.
No, no, no.
There's branding, but at the bottom
there's a logo.
It's timeless.
It's modular.
I can change the shape
of the stick
and the inside stays the same.
So you can
mix and match
in the long run.
Do I want to offer it?
No, it has a 10-year warranty.
It will work for sure for 10 years.
If the connection,
for example,
is aluminum,
it will work.
I wanted
from all the functional aspects
that it's top.
That's why I wanted to do it myself
because I didn't get it.
People
are mostly enthusiastic
because they go through
group buy.
But now you have a big problem.
You put a group buy out
and you have to wait
because of shortages, war in Ukraine,
all the global problems.
Because of the situation in the world.
You wait a year and a half, two.
Last year in August I got
sticks that I waited
for two years and a month.
These are sticks
for which I paid 400 euros
for two sets.
It's not for the price.
It's for 1000 sets,
which was very little globally.
And it's so expensive to wait so long.
Now I have 50 sticks in the warehouse,
in the warehouse,
but I don't have any now.
Now it's the same.
If there are two problems
in this fetish.
Is it
something you press on?
No offense.
Do you watch
when you put it on the shelf
and light it up with lights
and say it's art?
No, I mean, the design is already
in the bag,
but you represent some kind of
masterpiece.
I understand what you want to say
and that's what you press on.
I'm fully
attached to
quality stuff
that you use.
If I had a Kenix or Maserati
or something,
I wouldn't drive it day and night.
It's not for me.
Even the watch
that I bought,
I have it on my hands.
It's not for looking.
And I'm the same for this coin.
It's for using.
It's to make you look better every day.
Because of the use,
because of the feedback on your fingers,
when you gently press your fingers
when you rest.
That's its advantage.
It's nice for me
because I designed it myself,
but it's not for looking at the police.
It's the use.
It's a tool.
A tool that brings me
luck.
I have
an audio system
of a higher price
and a higher quality.
That's why I enjoy it.
I listen to music a lot.
I immerse myself for hours
in my work and I have headphones.
It's important to me that the headphones are quality
and that the monitor is quality
and that the ride is on a good table.
Thank God I'm in a position
where I can use these things
because the experience of using all these tools is important to me.
I'm not there
to put it on the wall.
On the wall I have
a canvas
of a sprint.
No.
I don't know how much
our audience knows
about the culture or subculture
of printers.
I know that there is a link
to the mechanical keyboard
on Reddit.
You just look at it
and wonder about the aesthetics and design
of what people do with these printers.
How much love
and passion is poured into it
and it's really impressive
what people do with these printers.
I'll ask you a simple question
and you'll probably
fall for it.
What's the point of these printers?
That's it.
You just press
and it clicks.
If I'm smart,
I'll go back.
The point of a printer
is to make an electric click
when you press it.
That's what I wanted to say.
That's what a printer is.
When I've tried
hundreds
of them,
I personally like
tactile printers
because
they have
an obstacle
or a bump
through which
it has to go.
That's why it feels like
it wants to stop.
But when it goes through,
it goes back.
It's like a stick.
You don't have to press it all the way.
That's the difference between linear printers
and tactile printers.
Linear printers always have to go all the way
because you don't know where the stick
is going to end up.
Tactile printers
give you feedback.
That's what I like
about tactile printers.
Gamers prefer linear printers.
That's why I have more tactile printers.
You know,
when I'm gaming with my colleagues,
I prefer linear printers
because you can press it all the way.
That's the thing.
You switch between tactile printers
and now we're in a different context.
Now we're gaming.
We've had
in our
co-working in Hackerspace
a colleague
who also had a passion
for tactile printers.
We really liked him
but there was a silence
when he went out of the office
with a tactile printer.
It was good because
tactile printers can become very loud
and very fluid.
Some of them
sound like a typewriter
but...
It should get loud, right?
You have silent linear
and silent tactile.
They're both silent.
It's still the same type of printer
except for the silence
and then they don't make
any sound at all.
It's so small that
Apple's Mac keyboard
is much louder than
the silence.
Silence is just a rubber band
around the track
or something like that
and around it
there's a rubber band
like a jacket
and when it comes down
it's a rubber band
and when it comes up
it's a rubber band again.
I don't think the sound
is as important as the feeling
of shaking.
I use a special lubricant
on a Teflon basis
to lubricate my device.
Because the part where
the plastic is shaking
is more pleasant.
It's not like a sound
but it flows smoothly
up and down.
It doesn't mean anything to someone
because it's good enough
and it doesn't mean
a bus or a thousand other
excuses.
I press the keyboard
10, 12, 14 hours a day
and it's an important feeling.
Your keyboard comes as a kit
that you can put together.
I would say that part of
the passion of a person
is to put the keyboard together.
That's right.
You mentioned cars
and you also have
a manual part for a car.
Yes, you used to have a box
where you put the car together.
Where does
the audiophilia come from?
You can put the cables
on the back
but you won't put
the equipment together.
Ideally, you buy a nice
high-quality product.
Where does
the passion
come from?
You buy a kit
and then you say
where you can put it together.
Simply put,
there are stickers in the game.
Stickers are the ones
that give
the biggest signature
to a keyboard player.
Every one of us
has our own passion.
When I buy a keyboard
I don't want someone
to give me a sticker
for which he or she decided.
There are many different stickers
and you can try them.
It's the same with keys.
I gave this group buy
12 sets of keys
with different color combinations
for different applications.
I want to have
my own combination.
I don't want
someone to steal it from me.
That's why I've never bought
a keyboard that already has it.
I prefer to buy a kit.
There's another reason
which is logistic.
I can't sell
a keyboard
plug-and-play
without a CE certificate
for which you need
a CE certificate.
In Ljubljana
you don't need a CE certificate
and it costs you
more than 1000 EUR
to get a CE certificate
so you can sell it
as a consumer electronics.
But that wasn't
the motivation.
I would give a CE certificate
but it wouldn't pay off.
I have 50 keyboards
at home
and I will decide
how to sell them
and how to sell them.
I have an idea for a million
for a better keyboard.
A different format.
Mono 2.0?
No, Mono Max.
A lot of people
ask me about the service.
I would like to have more
than I need in the US.
Mono Max is already
made.
But I will have to
order more
to see if I survive
in the end.
I have a full keyboard
which I made myself.
But I would have to
test it.
In the first series
I invested 50 000 EUR.
If I don't count
minutes of my time.
Direct cash.
Now I have to sell it
to see if I can
get all the money back
and fail there.
Or if it's a successful job.
But this job
is still very
niche and limited.
It's not
mass production.
The goal is not mass production.
The price is also
approximate.
I don't have a plan.
I would like to lower
the price.
But it will be
a compromise.
I have a lot of difficulties.
Tomas, let's do something.
But it's a compromise.
It's hard for me.
Look.
Let me see.
When I open the box
inside are
components.
I don't need a button or a switch.
I bring my switch
and buttons
that I like.
Then I have to assemble it.
I have to solder it.
Is it a practice in this industry?
Yes, it's a practice.
High-end products are usually sold
as kits. It can be already assembled.
But you have to take it apart
so you can
put it all together.
If it's assembled, it's usually
because of shipping, because the volume is smaller.
Not because
it would be a plug-and-play.
Wait, I heard that
you have to fly.
You have to fly.
You had an assumption.
Yes, I had an assumption
that this part is solved.
That it's a practice.
It's hard for everyone.
You have to fly.
For example, on mine
there are 68 buttons.
That's 136
points for flying.
Everyone has two.
Plus caps lock.
Multiply it by 62 if you
put the LEDs up, because PCB
supports
underglow LEDs.
That means that
every button has pins
for LEDs.
If I put
for example
20-30% more
for this part
to be assembled,
do you think you'll be able to fly?
I can do that.
I'll give it to my kid.
He'll be so happy.
It's a student's job.
She'll paint the candles,
fly, and earn something.
I don't do that.
The approximate price is a few euros.
I tried to fly a few times.
Andra is great.
He might be able to help.
But I won't fly for Juri Tipkovnick
without experience.
Why not?
That's the best entry-level.
To fly a glass
on a through-hole.
Now those who listen
know what a through-hole is.
How hard
will it be for the customer
to assemble it?
Nothing.
The whole audience
should know
that they have a
spiker at home.
A through-hole is
connected to a hole
and through it you can see a line.
Everything you need
is connected to that line.
And the price is...
That's shit.
I'll screw it up.
My dog
will fix it.
It's not easy.
But it's the basis.
My son will be 5 years old
and he'll enjoy it.
We'll fly together,
assemble it.
He'll enjoy it
when we assemble
the SSAVs, video recorders, etc.
We are still in the phase of distribution, but maybe we'll get there.
Maybe I'll wait a little longer to lower the prices and then we'll do it.
What do I have to write under this video?
I want a printer.
Where do I put this?
Isn't that already a meme?
No, it will be now, but this video will be deleted from Zuni, or this podcast.
Where do I spread this?
No.
I mean, you still have an opportunity.
Now I had a funnel here, but since we've been here for a long time, I'll try a few more of these segments.
Drawing. You drew in AutoCAD Fusion.
Yes, Autodesk.
You wanted to sketch it, but you realized that Fusion wasn't the best, it was simpler.
No, I used AutoCAD Fusion directly.
You used AutoCAD Fusion for that.
Yes.
Now, when I talked to you, you said AutoCAD Fusion, completely simple, purely trivial, you already have that.
You forgot to say that your parents have a studio at home, and that you are also a high school art student.
That data is also missing.
Okay, you know what, it's been a long time ago.
But yes.
I grew up, well, a little bit, because I always, since I grew up, that I somehow appeared in public life, I'm an IT guy.
I'm known as an IT guy.
I grew up in the Aluminium factory in Ljubljana.
And those problems were very close to me.
At that time, I was still working in an engineering high school, here in our town, in Ljubljana.
And yes, I really grew up with Aluminium, since I was a kid.
My father had a studio in Ljubljana, unfortunately, he passed away.
My mother retired, so my sister took over, so I still have a stick, or I don't know, if anyone wants to go to Ljubljana to see it, I sing in the summer, and then we go to Ljubljana.
And you can see there what 600 degrees of Aluminium is there.
Well, that's such a tiny detail that we all have to look at, so people don't think that a WordPress developer has done it, a typist.
I would have said it later.
Sorry, I'm certifying this time.
A printer is basically a very simple product.
Too simple, I said it wrong.
Basic in the form, in the sense of geometry.
It's not nuclear physics.
In English, we call it a wedge.
A wedge.
A wedge with printers.
A wedge in a basic form.
And in AutoCAD or any 3D program, it's very, I don't know.
Because in Fusion or Solidworks, Lada engines and rockets that fly on Mars are projected.
So a wedge in that sense is not something complex.
As far as you know, from the basic school of Thloris, Naris and Stransky Rys, you have a very good starting point.
So this is it. 600 opportunities.
So you don't need it, do you?
I'm preparing another product.
In which I will not say anything yet.
Which is not a printer.
But I will use it on my YouTube channel from scratch.
I made a wedge.
I will try to condense it.
The whole product from the start.
We will go to CNC.
We will go to eluxation.
Everything will be filmed.
The same process.
And it will be the same process as with the printers.
Just another product.
Until the end.
And then I will give it to someone.
And it will be a very productive product.
Great. English or Slovenian?
I'm still studying.
Yeah, I'll see.
I speak English, but I'll see.
Now I'm working on a build guide for Mono.
In English.
And I'll see how people will respond.
And how they will subscribe.
And what the metrics will be.
Then I will decide.
Yes, it is known that it will be in English.
But it will really start.
And people will see what kind of product to make.
What is the thought process.
Who are the masters.
Everything will be shown.
And how CNC works.
I would like to breathe
the generation of makers.
Because for us,
this lack
was the motivation for the YouTube channel.
To be able to show
that it is possible.
That we are going to research.
It has always been close to
younger generations.
I enjoyed it a lot.
I remember
when I was in school.
I went to the computer class.
And I went to school
in the order of a circle.
I enjoyed it a lot.
And I think that this knowledge
or the sharing of this knowledge.
After 40 years I will be old.
I think I have already accumulated
some knowledge in those 40 years.
And I want to pass it on.
Do you realize that
all the younger generations
and your generation
have a desire
to hear this.
Or is it like
we are only interested in the final product.
Because it is too fast.
It is not instant gratification.
That's right.
I think this is our task.
To inspire them.
That they will be interested.
It is not necessary to advise.
But I think this is our task.
Because for this instant gratification
we are to blame.
If you ask me.
Because for you or for me
it is easier
for a child to give you a signal
that you are thinking about something else.
You give him a phone.
I am to blame.
And if a child will see me
as I am inspired
it is not necessary
to have the same hobbies.
But my role as a parent
as a teacher for a child
is to inspire him.
And I think it is possible
if we will show them
through some magic
that they are in awe.
You can also see
what teachers their children work with.
Those who inspire them
interactively.
Those who make them out of themselves.
Those who are not a heavy authority
but colleagues, motivators.
We miss that a lot.
I wanted to ask
if he works for Mac
and for Linux and Windows.
He does.
If he is allowed to type on it.
Yes.
Let me take
a few more of those.
Prototyping.
OK.
In Fusion
you made a 3D model.
Did you 3D print it?
No.
How did you come to the shape
you have now?
OK.
As I said, I will be older by 40.
If I can.
By 40 you already have a reflection
where you are good
and what you are missing.
And again
I miss it a lot.
But I am good at two things.
Accumulation of knowledge.
Learning new things is too easy for me.
If I am interested in something.
If I am not, then fuck no.
And the other thing is
that I know how to surround myself
with more capable people than me.
Or let's say those who complement me.
It sounds romantic
but so far I have always liked it.
Luckily.
When I need someone
I know who to call
I met someone who knows someone else
who can recommend someone to me
and I came to that person.
And specifically
I didn't work directly
on CNC.
But I called a few fairs
and they all gave me pre-calculations
that my head hurts
because they didn't know
what to do.
And I understand them.
I don't ignore them.
They work a hundred thousand hair
and it's their dream.
But then
we were at the seaside for a year
and our kids were playing
with other kids at the seaside.
And then we became friends
and one thing led to another
and we became even older friends.
And it turned out that the father
of those kids we met
is a traveler for a large Slovenian company
that sells machines and tools.
And when I realized
that I need to make a prototype
I called him and asked
if he knows someone
who has CNC so accessible
that it's not too big
and he said yes.
He has a connection with Bo코tjan
who is my colleague today
from Sevnica
who made a prototype for me.
You don't see that today.
It's a rarity.
And then I needed Eloxeria
and Bo코tjan, the one who makes machines with CNC
and he said yes.
He works for Porsche, for Audi
he works for such a world-class company
when it comes to Eloxeria.
It doesn't matter how much it costs
we will do it without compromise.
I don't care.
The price was the last thing on my mind.
Because of the sales of the previous company
I was able to invest
more than one euro
to see what the results are.
The only thing that didn't go through
was the pressure.
It was a very low price.
Is it the same problem?
Are you too small?
No, no, no.
The price was too high.
I don't know if the price was too high
because he has a new question.
They can't afford it.
For this particular company
I didn't decide.
It was four times more expensive
and they said they can't afford it.
This is a phrase
that I don't like to hear.
It's not possible.
This phrase often comes
before someone has even tried it.
It's not possible.
It's a defensive mechanism.
I don't buy it.
For such potential business partners
it's very fast.
I don't know about the pressure
in the press.
In Slovenia, when the price was 10%
the pressure said
I don't want to say this in big words
but they said give this, give that.
Everything will be fine.
If I agreed to do
no compromise
when they won't even read
the material that it's not fucking perfect
not for me, everything will be fine.
If someone told me that
it's not good.
Is it the best?
Let's go home and have pizza.
Look, look.
It will be good today.
Shit, I don't know.
Packaging, marketing, sales.
Ok, packaging.
I didn't mention that on YouTube.
Packaging, I wanted to have
something like that.
Ok, that's a full message.
People don't see it, but all the pictures
are there.
I don't know how to say it.
Anyway, packaging.
I came to a man
who designed it.
The same man who designed
packaging
for the British queen
who was in Slovenia.
I mean,
no one can do it better.
Can someone tell me how to do it better?
It's not possible.
I want to tell you, I came to
a man who is great.
If they chose him or hired him
to design for the queen,
he would do a great job.
The same with packaging.
It's a pity that the queen
didn't marry us.
I think it would be good for her too.
It's probably easier to eat
English than you do.
It was.
Or let's say, designer packaging.
Designer packaging.
I will add that.
Printed packaging.
Freaking art.
I also found him
on Instagram.
Of all the places.
I knew he was working
for ASML.
He was developing
processors for ASML.
For AMD, for Intel.
No, not processors, I mean machines
that make those processors.
They make them in Taiwan.
Machines are made in the Netherlands.
But I haven't worked there yet.
You can be a high-skilled man
if you have a machine
that makes ASML.
A 7-year-old machine
can make it in one go.
They have such requirements.
I mean,
partly it's luck, partly
it's an intention.
I mean, by force.
I'm a bit embarrassed
that I did something
but I have long-term
relations with such people.
Look,
my skill set is just that.
Bring the idea together
and pack it
into a whole car.
Marketing.
What you do here is excellent marketing.
What you do on YouTube
is excellent marketing.
Will that be enough
for you to reach people who need this type of content?
That's the million dollar question.
I don't know.
I mean, that's the biggest...
That's why I can't sleep at the moment.
If that happens...
How will you reach
those people who sold you
12 sets of what you have at home?
I'm going to attack those forums
in the same way.
For example,
this Mechanical Keyboards
will be the first big launch
when I'm ready.
Now I have a bit of time
before the holidays,
but I'm already late.
I'm already thinking about
mid-holidays or January.
I'm going to start.
It's a bit easier now.
I'll see.
I haven't decided yet.
You have a subreddit,
a forum,
and a whole Discord server
for different brands of mechanical keyboards,
keyset makers, designers.
It's full.
I mean, look...
You have to find the tribe.
You don't have to find it.
You have to show that you know what you're doing.
On a professional level,
you can introduce yourself.
And introduce myself
so that they buy
my story.
Because stories are what they sell.
Why...
You probably have an answer.
Why didn't you do that
through crowdfunding?
Because...
That's a very
simple answer.
I believe you.
Because of global logistical
difficulties at the moment,
it's simply
too hard
to keep a promise.
That is,
when you go to crowdfunding,
you promise something.
You promise a product,
some qualities to some people.
And if you're not
able to keep that promise,
your credibility drops.
The longer it lasts,
the less credibility you have.
And today, I simply wouldn't
trust to say that...
Look, a printer could be
30% more expensive
if I sourced it all in Chinese.
30% would be low, for example.
Then I don't have any
supervision over the quality,
if I wasn't there.
If a printer is low,
it's going to break,
and I have to send it back
a month later,
so they can dispute
and say, no, it's not appropriate
for shipping.
I don't have supervision.
If I were to give my name
for a loan,
and then not fulfill it,
it would just tear me apart.
Quality reason.
If I want to sell
something, I need to see
that it's really the best,
so we can solve
every problem.
And also not to exploit
a system with which...
Maybe that's for another podcast,
if I'm not mistaken,
that we're sourcing everything
so we can survive.
Because now,
it's really affecting us.
That means that now,
in the first phase,
the first phase is not touched
by anyone.
The first phase,
yes, it's true,
but it's not
going to the printer
to print something.
No, I will be happy,
but the first phase
is really...
I need to find a rhythm.
I don't have to,
when I don't have experience,
give someone a guide,
but this series is really good
for learning,
and I will have that
in my hands.
I will now try
to translate
our part
in the end.
What would
maybe
1000 euros for a printer
be for people
who are not
interested in printing,
but maybe they are interested
in how printers work,
and maybe they want
to get in touch with it.
I don't know, I had a man
in a job interview
who made two of his printers
ultra-proud.
We have people in Slovenia
who are very passionate about printers.
The closest contact
with you,
or not.
How do they come to you?
Thank you for the interview.
What would you say?
Do you want help?
Do you want to talk to people
around you?
Or will you do it alone?
First,
I am very excited
if I can talk to people
about it.
On Twitter, I seem to be the most
publicly posted
under the tag TomasZaman.
First, they ping me
for coffee.
I am very happy about these contacts.
You never know how you can
help each other.
Unfortunately,
I also don't have time.
I can't always
post things
that are on the agenda,
but in the beginning I am always ready
to connect with the world.
I am also always happy
if they are positive.
I don't know
how to say it,
but I also don't know
how to say it.
I don't need such stories.
I wrote
a comment
on your post.
I wanted to type
the end of the post.
Some comments
are great,
but I wrote
...
The comment
on the video
was
with the word
clickbait
fake
gay shit.
I thought
what the hell is going on with you?
You can have thick skin
for naysayers,
no goers,
and people
get negative
feedback
from you.
People get
negative feedback
for projects
that are ambitious,
that maybe
cross the line.
Where is the flow?
This comment
is not cool,
but people get it.
What would you advise
gay people to do?
Don't be afraid on Twitter.
You get white skin.
Really!
This shit can't come under your skin.
Yes, yes, yes.
Twitter is like that.
A wonderful net.
To see that you are serious
and I don't give a fuck.
Because it's really public.
I adore Twitter.
I met a lot of people on Twitter.
I was on a date
with someone I've never seen before.
But on Twitter you share
a smile and a lot of the same looks.
I would say it's a sub-ethnic soul.
We were chatting for two hours.
What was the best friend?
A vest.
Twitter is a law.
But because it's public,
you get a moustache
and sometimes it bends
like an elephant.
But you get thick skin.
But people,
I want to add
don't let those comments
people
hide behind the name
come from the living.
These are not your pages.
They are not important for the success of the product.
And don't let it come from the living.
Yes, yes.
Maybe that's how it is.
Comments were great.
But some were toxic.
It's probably the same
I don't know.
YouTube can comment
but it's the same thing.
You probably shouldn't have that.
You'll have some trolls there.
These comments
are so off-topic.
When you say
I won't post a comment anywhere
and I haven't even seen the video.
No, I agree.
I've been in the world for a long time
and I've seen
such and different public
and I don't like such things.
Sometimes something drives me
in a positive way.
One person wrote
under a YouTube video
How do you speak like an egg?
Like an egg? Robot?
I don't want to argue with that.
I saw that
I didn't know how to form a sentence.
But I want to speak like a robot.
Which is true.
Starting a YouTube channel
is not easy.
I see a video in 15 minutes
and I shoot it for an hour and a half
because I'm nervous.
Then I go to the bathroom
and shoot another take.
I make 20 takes for the same intro.
It takes 20 minutes
because I see in 5 seconds
that it's a hook.
I know you're trying
but I don't know
Lithuanian,
Ljubljana,
Slovakia,
a hundred thousand things
and I'm not sure
if I'm thinking right.
I'm not immune
to judgment.
But look,
I think that
I'll finish
with one question.
When you were
the technical director
you were also a guest
at a WordPress conference
in the Danube region
where you were dressed
as Superman.
I think it was
one of the biggest conferences
in the Danube region.
this technology in Europe
and you came to Oder and you talked
you basically said it yourself
but there were
1300 people and this video
is now on volume and I think
around 2000-3000 people watched it
so around 3000-4000
people have seen this content
so I would ask you
if you could tell
how did
this project go
because I think
Slovenians couldn't hear
what you were saying
you were talking about
that we are underestimating ourselves
why we are underestimating ourselves
and I know it's not fair
to ask you this question
but I think it's a powerful lesson
and I would like you to repeat it
and put it in the heart
of our listeners
I think that
Slovenians have a big problem
with the head
I have it myself
or I had it
and I think it's the growth
of our elders
because they are
always so much
in the head
like God gave you
a job
or he gives you
an overlord
and that's what our elders are
we were always
Slovenian boys
and I think that
Slovenians still have it in their blood
and I think
you can't get rid of it
I admit that
sometimes you think
you need an external leader
but
I think
that with time
you learn
if you want to live
your time, your knowledge
and in Slovenia
we have so many
quality people
quality people, knowledge
because I think
your podcast is still
and I'm not talking for everyone
for other guests
that we have
something to offer the world
but the attitude is
that it doesn't come in time
and I want it
globally, when I gave it
to a lot of people
I'm talking from my own experience
I sold myself for knowledge
that I had overpriced
then I doubled my price
even though it was expensive
and I had more time
for quality people
more time for learning
for family, hobbies
and more money
so this disconnect
in Slovenia
even more
I think
maybe the western world
for example America
you can be anything
and they sell the American dream
and it's the opposite for them
I think they buy it too much
it's like a mix
of European modesty
and their American
overabundance
of everything
they meet halfway
and they're both at their best
if I choose
someone from the press
I didn't do it myself
I don't have a machine
I only have my hands and my head
if it's like it is
for my taste
you need a lot of people
and you find them in Slovenia
and we have them
the problem with marketing
everyone does it
and I also found out
that we have a lot of R&D
developers
everyone has their secret
laboratory inside
and they're working on something
and screwing it
God knows what the neighbor will say
I would like to add
to say more
what you did successfully
make that synergy
because we're not all good
we have someone
who is
so this synergy
it's a common goal
we also saw
in previous episodes
that we, Slovenians, lack
to have those circles
everyone on their own circle
and we try to fit in
and that's it
and Danes don't understand that
I had a company in Denmark
I got to know the culture
even my partner
was in Slovenia
and they can't understand that
the neighbor is working hard
I'll go to him three times a day
if I need to
how can I help you
that's in their DNA
or paying taxes
for example
when he was told that we're
a Balkan country and taxes are being optimized
and I don't know what
he didn't understand
it didn't go through his calculator
how can you be like that
you can't pay taxes
say a Dane
who has taxes higher than Slovenians
and that's much higher
say taxes
but he didn't know the whole picture
and I'm here
I feel sorry for him in a way
I have difficulties
sometimes
with the environment
you have to crawl under your feet
yes, yes
or vomit
now it's even worse for you
everyone thinks they know everything
but I think that in Slovenia
there is a lot of potential for
the world to change
and even him
but no one knows
that he will say something to us
and no one knows
and here you have to deal with time
I hope
I hope that someone will hear
that we will cooperate
you said it with such a monotone voice
no
I hope that we will cooperate
I can conclude like this
if
when we got
that expensive shit
to record sound
these microphones
and when we talked about what would be the next level
for our production
for our podcast
it was a great video
and we started talking
we have this video today because of you
because you gave us this lesson
because you are interested
in this kind of production
because you see some value
in what we start
and I wouldn't dare
such a production as we have
it wouldn't be in such a spotlight
it wouldn't be in such a great spotlight
there wouldn't be probably Jan and Brodola
who have to help each other
so we are very grateful to you
for everything
now this shit is not under the table
so people
we have to warn that today
we tried to raise the level
a bit higher
we tried to experiment
and we tried to show
that you can do something
I would like to thank you
both on this point
for your time
I would like to thank you for post-production
see you later
people would like
Odins would like
to give feedback
on everything we started today
so we can see what we start well
what we start poorly
tell us if you want more of these formats
if you want more of Sebin
thank you
Tomas, thank you
50 seconds of silence