Here we go, we're recording, we're recording.
Okay, today we have Christopher Černivac as a guest,
Andraž Sraka is with me as well, and I'm Motu Vrgles.
This is the third episode of the podcast in Grodje,
and I'm going to apologize for the previous episodes.
Before we start, I want to thank everyone who listened to the previous episodes,
everyone who gave feedback on the previous episodes,
and everyone who will give feedback on this episode as well.
I still did a bit of that official part.
Okay, the topic for today, I won't apologize,
but I'm apologizing to Christopher because I wanted to say
how he sees the development of a young engineer,
and how he sees the development of people coming into the industry.
I'm also interested in his path through the beginnings,
maybe how good he is in the world in that direction.
Yes, that would be a topic for today.
Let's start, I'll give you the opportunity to introduce yourself.
Hello, I'm Christophe Zototo.
I've been working on various projects for a few years now.
I mainly work on back-end, Ruby, Postgres, Classic Stack, Rails, TSDW.
Today's topic is close to me, it's interesting, it's relevant.
I keep asking myself what would help me,
when I started programming, what would be the bottom line,
when I didn't, what would help me make that leap,
or that chaos at the beginning, when you have a lot of new things,
but you don't know what's important, what's not,
and how to segment them.
That's it.
Unintentional.
Unintentional? No, when you started,
if you look back, what would have been different,
what lessons learned,
I think that each of us would go back with that mindset,
with that knowledge we have now.
I think that we all, when we went through that learning experience,
were probably the most motivated in that moment.
It's hard to say now, that it would change everything.
I think that I spent most of my time,
when I was learning how to program, how the system works,
I needed to fully identify what I need to learn,
and what is relevant to me.
I think that was the hardest, because you have that catch-22,
you have a lot of knowledge you need to acquire,
but you don't have the knowledge to assess what's needed,
and what's not.
That's a classic example.
You need to have the necessary knowledge,
that gives you insight, so you can see,
if you still don't know everything,
why you're not pushing in the situation.
You have to go through a lot of things to get to that level.
That's right.
At that point, I think that the curriculum is well-organized,
it's not market-oriented, because there's a conflict of interest,
or maybe some friends who are already in the industry,
and they know a little bit more.
I think that in that initial phase,
it was really important for me,
to somehow cover the whole area.
To say, I'm going to learn this one thing,
and I'm going to learn it well,
and I'm not going to learn anything else,
like AngularJS, or...
But can you quickly assess what that one thing is?
No.
As a young engineer,
if someone on that path said,
this is a task I have to learn,
that would open up a level for me,
to become a better engineer for the moment.
You're asking me that,
when you say, I don't know,
I don't know anything, I'm interested,
and I'm going to give you an example,
when I started my career,
and I wasn't a developer,
I was the most popular PHP.
Can you maybe distinguish,
or at the beginning,
you went through
formal programming education,
you have a different background,
Krištof didn't go through
formal programming education.
I went post-fest.
You went post-fest in the industry,
you did something completely different,
and you come to the industry as someone
who doesn't know anything,
and you do a program for computer engineering,
and you follow that,
but you come in as a total noob.
Now, you learn some knowledge,
like this is a bible,
you learn all that,
and you know everything,
but being an expert in some knowledge,
when you print the book,
and you know what you want to say with it.
How did you establish what you don't know,
at the beginning?
It was clear to me that I don't know anything,
because if I didn't know,
a year ago,
you open some simple tutorials,
on the internet,
you have as many as you want,
and then you learn Python,
in three hours,
but you don't have a clue,
you don't know where Python is executed,
you don't have a context,
and then there are things like that,
that you don't understand.
That's one of those tricky things,
that not only what you learn,
but also how to use the system functionally,
so that you can progress along the way.
That was the hardest part,
to see what is relevant.
It's like a minefield,
if you type on Google,
how to get better at programming,
or whatever,
hyper-industrialized niches,
people try to serve you,
and it's not the best environment,
to learn something.
Here I'm doing something,
but here I'm doing something else,
and I don't even know,
how was it,
if you remember,
was it a part of a community,
or a friend,
or how was that transition,
if you come from an environment,
where it wasn't close to you,
was it that transition,
that someone who had a computer,
started reading games,
and how did it come about,
that this job interests you so much,
that it's a potential career for you?
To start doing that,
I would say,
let's say,
that I identified three things,
first, that you don't have a computer,
as a role model,
and second, that you can have a job,
and serve with it.
The concept of programming is interesting,
there are some services,
let's take a look,
and then I spent a lot of time,
trying to figure out,
what is the programming language,
there are some recurring concepts,
you have other paradigms,
but it's not completely different,
it's not like if you learn Python,
you don't have to translate anything into Javascript,
or something like that.
After I entered the rabbit hole,
I identified C,
as the language I had to learn.
Those were some of the arguments,
that convinced me,
I don't know if I still have them today.
Low-level language,
most of the software is written in C,
on all machines,
by default, if you have Linux,
and so on.
Plus, various YouTube tutorials,
that are also written in C.
So I decided to learn C,
you have online courses,
like Harvard,
and then I found a cool book,
in English,
I could improve my pronunciation,
but it's 300-400 pages of C,
a book to learn C,
and I decided,
this is what I want to do.
No other tutorials,
just to focus on one thing.
What was great about the book,
is that it had a lot of ideas,
so whenever you adopted a concept,
you had a lot of ideas,
and you implemented them.
So this was a task,
that you could check,
or was it an example,
that you looked at,
and based on that,
it was clear to you?
You had a dream,
then you had examples,
then you had 5-6 tasks,
and then you wrote them down,
to make them more complex,
to make a matrix,
and so on.
So I learned a lot,
and I wrote the first non-trivial program,
which is more than 10 lines,
and it lasted for hours,
10 hours,
and it was a complete mess.
You know you forgot semicolons,
because you have signatures,
because you have beginner,
unfriendly error messages,
and you don't know error messages,
and it takes a lot of time,
but you learn a few more things,
and you move forward.
When did you realize,
that you failed?
Did you think,
I'm going to try again,
and now I'm going to fail,
and maybe it's not for me?
You have to have some inner motivation,
if you don't have it,
you can get into a situation,
where you are more motivated,
like I said,
the sun is the battle,
or the army,
when you fight for something,
you fight for it.
Maybe you have to find the reason,
and stand by it,
and the army in front of you,
and you fail in the process.
It can't be an option,
it has to be a wall,
that's why it's not acceptable.
The other part is negative motivation.
Positive motivation was,
that I was surprised,
how much pleasure you get,
when you solve a problem.
You get a feedback loop,
like a medicine,
you get pleasure,
and you feel like,
let's solve the problem,
and when you do that,
it's clear to you,
that even if you are in the problem for 6 hours,
you are going to solve it,
and you have to be confident,
that you can do it.
It's not only for nerds,
that have been doing it for 5 years,
on some obscure machines,
but you can learn it in 20 years.
That was the first step,
that I know something in a language,
but what was the question,
if you want to have a job,
I know C, but what?
That was my next question,
how do you know,
that C is not something,
that you can live from now on,
and how do you get from C to Ruby,
and maybe another question,
if you know C, what are the algorithms,
quick sort, bubble sort,
something that middle school students,
train on.
A really cool thing about the book,
and the CS50 Harvard program,
is that you get to know the concepts,
maybe not in detail,
but the concept of sorting,
and how it's done,
and the concept of memory management,
that you go from nothing to one,
to a computer that works,
so you can imagine,
how it works.
But how do you do the transition,
I know something, I'd have a job,
that was another thing,
you get to know the industry,
I didn't know how many programmers,
there were 5 or 10,
you don't know,
or maybe 50,
you don't have a feeling.
And then I started to search,
how to get a job,
and then you have stacks,
one of them stays in the middle,
and then you fall into that part,
and then you find...
So you identified,
that it's good to get into some structure.
Yes, exactly.
There's an ecosystem of things,
you don't have to say,
I know C, but nothing else.
There's a curriculum,
it's called Lawn School,
I liked it,
in the sense of the slow path,
take your time, master your shit,
that's it.
What was cool to me,
was that you had a very focused way of learning,
you learn how a method works,
that's what you learn,
nothing else.
And that helps you understand things,
that you don't have a lot of knowledge.
Another important thing,
is that they tell you,
if you want to work in this industry,
you know the programming language,
but it's good to know a few things,
or to know how to use git,
or how to work with command line utility,
or how to work with a storage solution,
or Postgres, a database,
or if you want to work with the web,
you have to know the concept,
and the protocols,
which are very simple,
and then you expand that picture,
so you can write something in it,
but the code is in some context,
and then you learn that.
And when you get used to it,
and you want to write an application,
and I was at Heroku,
a simple application,
and I was like, wow,
that thing is alive,
and it jumped.
You didn't try it.
No, no.
It was great,
but as you said,
you had a military-disciplined attitude.
There is a mission, I'm getting there,
no matter what.
And now you created some courses,
which you had the opportunity to have,
which are international,
for a local community,
which I think,
some local developers,
developed something,
so that's why my question,
or the following question,
is how do you know that this is a goal,
and that you will achieve it
with a really good focus.
And now you described your example,
you had the opportunity to see
a book on the Internet.
When I was learning C,
there was a book.
The Internet was a dial-up,
and on the page there was Google,
and a book.
You went to the book,
copied the examples,
and learned from them.
Now you mentioned a local community.
I would say that the third leap I made,
as you said,
now we have the Internet,
it's simple, you get a hit,
and you can do this,
get some people,
social circle,
I didn't know that meetup.com
had such a thing.
With time I learned Ruby,
and I was like,
can anyone in Slovenia do this?
You are a pre-Ruby on Rails.
Why Ruby?
I don't have to answer that.
I sold it to me.
General purpose language,
widely used, OK paid,
and I was like, OK, cool.
I didn't know anything better.
What attracted me to them,
was the approach.
I think everyone starts
by doing a course,
where they tell you that you know it,
but you don't really know it.
You don't know how to write anything,
you don't know how to edit codes,
you don't know how to commit anything,
and that's why I liked that approach.
Let's do it the other way around.
Let's do a little bit,
and learn it well,
and then a little bit more,
and so on.
Why Ruby?
They had it in the curriculum,
but if I go back,
I started looking for people
who work with Ruby in Slovenia.
I started a Ruby meet-up,
and Otto Brgljeza,
who organized it,
showed up, and it was the best.
You can ask these people real questions.
What do you do?
That's important for someone
who's looking for a job.
How long did it take
to start learning Ruby?
Less than a year.
I started learning Ruby
in February,
and then I started
doing other things,
and I started in January.
It took me 11 months.
I prepared a lot of material,
and I realized that
anything less than 20 hours a week
is useless.
You need a critical mass of time
to invest it.
I spent more than 20 hours a week,
or sometimes more.
I didn't do anything else.
I drew from other things,
and I decided what I would do.
You have a military attitude.
Yes, exactly.
Very, very focused.
I would say that for someone
who graduated from high school,
or graduated from high school,
or graduated from FACS,
it's not at that level.
I know that some people
are more like that through the game.
You play with it a bit,
then it accepts you,
and then you let it go.
I don't have that attitude in life.
It's the same concept
with other skills.
You don't have to study,
you don't have to do anything.
It's not a hobby,
but let's admit it.
It's a proper way, isn't it?
Yes, yes.
Now, you said that you won't record everything.
I'm happy that you understood that.
That you understood that.
What surprised me when I first saw Christophe,
when I first met him,
was that he came to Ruby Meetup,
I introduced myself,
I asked him how it started,
and he came with very specific,
unconnected questions about Ruby.
He was asking about things that,
with which you are in the picture,
as an industrial production code,
you are working on,
you are learning,
for example, I don't know,
how some objects are adopted,
how they are simplified,
you know, how the object model works,
and I don't know what else.
And they were, of course,
very incoherent, unconnected questions,
yes, yes, yes,
but, no.
The main question was,
if you got down to some things
that are too deep,
too unconnected,
from some useful values,
you know,
my challenge,
what I saw was,
what do you need at that time,
to be complemented with what
we see in the industry,
to be complemented with what is useful there,
to be complemented in the right way,
and to be given an opportunity.
As a mentor,
or as someone who builds
some teams,
those are the three things
that I saw.
I saw that you are interested in things,
that you are very open-minded,
I saw that you are focused on some things,
are they right or not,
is it a matter of debate,
consistency,
you see in a person,
community outreach,
and passion.
Before,
there were a lot of meetups,
a step forward.
Yes, that's it.
I felt like a kid on a candy store,
you know,
when people know about those things,
you don't even ask them, you grab them.
Those were some meetups,
something for a stand.
Beer was needed.
Let me say this,
for example,
blockchain, bitcoin,
a lot of people are doing it,
it's revolutionary,
blockchain will change finance,
industry, internet, everything.
It's all cool,
but you worked with Ethereum,
you worked with Solidity Contract,
and then...
I wrote a whole list.
You wrote a whole list.
Where do you draw the line?
What do you think?
You managed to combine
some Ruby knowledge,
C-knowledge,
and then you simply ate
a lot of it.
Yes, I think it was interesting.
What's your take on that?
My take,
from the perspective of someone
who would like to learn programming,
is not to follow the hype.
Well...
There are a lot of things like that,
and a lot of new things.
One of the things I noticed
when I started
is that it's not used much anymore,
it's a legacy.
I haven't been in the industry for 5 years,
but on the other hand,
there are a lot of things
that don't change,
and from time to time,
a long time ago,
we talked about algorithms,
basic concepts,
things like that.
My focus would be
on things that don't change,
so that you understand
those things in depth,
and that you don't fall
into the hype,
like, solidity is the next big thing.
You don't know how to program,
and the first thing you jump on
is solidity.
I'm not saying...
I wouldn't say that,
because a lot of specific things
are done by scientists anyway,
so it's risky.
So...
I imagined it like a concept.
I imagined it,
and here it is.
It's a game.
There are some tokens,
and other things.
I don't know,
my experience with the crypto world
was in 2018,
when I was inside.
ERC-721, or NFT,
came out of nowhere,
I think.
Now it's bleeding edge,
I don't know how it is now,
maybe it's better,
but you find bugs in the compiler,
things like that.
The ecosystem really exists,
you don't have good ways
to test things.
If you want to help
with material, books, blog posts,
and so on,
there's so little of it.
Things like that.
You spend a lot of time,
and you have to know
that there are very few people
who can help you,
because you're a pioneer
among those hyper-nerds
who designed Ethereum, VN, etc.
Where do you become a nerd,
or a geek?
It's the second or third time
I've been asked this question.
Are you a geek?
Am I a nerd?
I think we should first
tell what it is.
Tell us what it is,
because you've said it twice.
I think that
in the general public,
a nerd is a model
that deals too much
with specific problems,
and it's hard to tell
what it's dealing with.
It's developing
kernel modules for something,
and you don't understand
what it's talking about,
and you start using a word
that nobody knows about.
I would say that it's a nerd.
To devote my whole life to it,
I would agree.
How would you describe a nerd?
I'm a poor guy.
A poor guy.
At least,
maybe a little bit
of a Hollywood approach.
When these things
become,
I won't say mainstream,
but they've started
to be used in mainstream sitcoms
and movies.
I would compare it to a nerd.
Not all people
who deal with it are nerds.
But there is a certain profile
of people who deal with this stereotype.
I don't do it as a crime.
I don't think so.
Moto, are you a nerd?
Are you a geek?
I actually enjoy
what I do.
When people ask me what I do,
I say I'm an artist.
It's the same here.
A nerd doesn't enjoy
being called a nerd.
Maybe a nerd is more of a state of mind.
If I'm not mistaken,
what surprises me
is that
a lot of labels
have prejudices.
For example,
if someone
comes to you
as a programmer,
it's great.
If someone comes to you
as an engineer,
it's great too.
I think that
a label like Junior
or Junior Developer
can also
exaggerate people
in terms of their opportunities.
Maybe if
Krištof
was a successful engineer,
it would be less successful.
But if there was
a force
on him
to have a formal education,
or if there was a force
on him to be Junior,
it would be great.
Do you think that
formal education
would be
too much?
If I look at myself
with a formal education,
I don't think
it would give me
a skill set.
It would be
more of a passion
to deal with technology
and develop it.
I can also comment on that.
After Fest,
I started
getting a formal education.
I would say that
in the final phase,
you have to learn on your own.
At the beginning, I said
that the hardest part
is to prepare myself
for what I have to learn.
That's what the faculty does.
You come in, they give you books,
you learn, write and that's it.
But the difference is
that you write it down
and move on,
so you can understand it.
The faculty can't guarantee that.
It's not like
you can say
on a high level
that you heard about Java
and you know how to write it.
But you can't distinguish
between people
who spend hours and hours
digging into the location of the object,
garbage collection,
trying to understand it from the inside out,
and someone else
who has a stack overflow script.
Maybe it's just
the formal education,
but in a sense,
what they give you
are the foundations.
I think that
you are still a bit
accustomed to
computer science,
or a developer,
or an engineer.
You don't know how to work
with computers.
If you don't buy some components,
you don't know how
the computer works,
and how the operating system works.
Why do we have an operating system?
What are some functions?
He builds it on some application
that runs on the operating system.
He lacks the basics.
So, if I look at it
from a formal perspective,
what he gave me
and what he gave me to look at,
those are the things.
When I went through this process,
I thought,
why do we have to deal
with a task, a book,
or something bigger.
But those are the foundations
that later make you
realize, aha, that's why.
I agree.
For me,
this was the best fact
that a student,
if they don't deal with it,
their theory,
the theoretical basis of things,
is deeper.
As a self-taught,
you're more oriented to practical things.
Can I write a program
that does something?
Do I know how to use
Ubuntu Box in this or that way?
Meanwhile,
here you get
a more conceptual understanding of things.
You get to know
mathematics, logic,
and so on.
Even if you want to take a research paper,
you take it in your hands.
That's something
that the faculty can help you with.
But my opinion is
that if you want,
you can learn everything
straight from the textbook.
You have to know
and rely on yourself
to know what's relevant.
Do we have time for questions?
I would like to hear
this comment
about formal education.
I see,
as one of the
Slovenian developers,
from the community,
I see a lot of posts
where students ask
if they haven't asked
if it's worth it
to finish formal education,
or if it's worth it,
because what we all learn
is based on computer science.
Is it worth it
to work with
one student
in an industry?
That's a question
that hasn't been seen
that often.
I would suggest
that those
who are already
in the system,
who have been here
for several weeks,
because you get
a curriculum,
as you said,
and you see things
that you wouldn't see
and you get things
that you need,
but you also get
a certain breadth.
Especially now,
if you go into
some scientific fields,
then you absolutely
need that,
but I think
we both need it.
In this team,
For sure.
Formal education doesn't hurt.
Yes, absolutely.
What I see in companies
is that it becomes
a problem or a challenge
when you're
an engineer for a while,
and then maybe you get
some inspiration to go
to a bigger system,
where a formal education
is more convenient.
Or, for example,
if you have a formal education
in computer science,
then you go to a company
to study or something else.
I wanted to say that.
A good insurance policy
is that if you get
IT full time,
and you want to work
in the public sector,
then you're like,
I'm done.
Half of our employees
work in the public sector.
I wrote down
three things for you,
so you can choose one.
Are you ready?
Go ahead.
You're going to choose.
First, let's talk
about side projects.
How do you choose them,
and what do you do?
It's a bit boring,
but it's a safe route.
The second thing is
what do you eat
in a company,
so you can eat
Venezuelan spammers.
Then I have cockfighting.
That's an interesting topic.
It's very popular
in East Asia.
In East Asia.
And then I have
philosophy,
and we had a debate
about known unknowns,
and unknown unknowns.
It was Rumsfeld who developed it.
Those are four topics
that you can choose.
You said three,
but you said four in East Asia.
Yes, yes.
Those are just some options.
I can only choose one.
Yes, I can choose cockfighting.
Cockfighting is interesting,
but let's talk about
Venezuelan spammers.
It's not because they're from Venezuela,
but because they're spammers.
It was an interesting area
where we worked.
It's called fraud prevention.
It turns out
that if you pay money
on the Internet,
it attracts different people,
and they try to hack the system.
Then you have different ways
to prevent it.
If you want to
prevent specific people,
you have to track them.
Then you have an interesting
dynamic where
these people develop a software
or do various things on the go.
Then you detect it
and prevent it.
Then they adapt
and start using
the new system.
Then you detect it again and prevent it again.
So you have a nice arms race
for the people on the Internet.
Here we had
various things,
from the simplest to the most sophisticated.
You can see
that people are immune
to your system
and then you try
to clear the database.
These were very good challenges.
Andras is very big
in this area.
I think
that this is
constantly
evolving.
You will see
what will happen
in the future.
Even if they
automate on the other side,
what is it
for Mechanical Turk
and all those indices
that can click it manually?
And
on the other hand,
there is a lot more.
There is a labor force that is really undervalued.
This labor force is so big
that there are
whole farms.
On the one hand,
you are fighting against this fraud
and you are looking for
human behavior or anomalies.
And in the end,
you see that it is very difficult.
You can have a human
that just clicks
a lot of times.
One of the approaches
that we had was very economical.
We were aware of
this.
It is very interesting
that some groups are falling apart.
Scammers or whatever.
And then you contact the support.
Those other scammers
are also anonymous.
And if you look at them,
it is interesting.
The whole economic approach is like
let's make sure that people
don't pay or that they have to pay
all the time if they want to go up.
And in this way,
you can convince
some people.
Or maybe
their account is not that good
and they will go somewhere
where the account is better.
Does reCAPTCHA work?
No.
Telephone verification works?
Email verification works?
No.
I haven't found anything that is not silver bullet.
You can use all of it
and someone will know
about it.
And verification through Facebook,
Google?
It is a little bit better,
but not enough.
Only because you outsource
New York customer, Google and Facebook.
Let's ask differently.
We assume
that you will always have
a percentage of fraud.
And how to reduce
this percentage as much as possible.
We know that there can't be zero.
Which mechanisms
could be in place
when they reduce it
to 10%?
And that you prepare
those 10%?
We had much more sophisticated systems.
We had machine learning algorithms
and detection of different patterns.
In my experience,
with every additional thing
you want to do,
with every additional thing,
you reduce the percentage of fraud.
And maybe you set
different incentives
so that people pay less.
And so on.
When you have
more fraud,
you have to be careful.
Because you don't want
to make the user experience worse.
Or make it harder
to onboard legitimate users.
So you have to be careful
between yourself and others.
You don't want to be...
I think the safest system
to reduce it to the maximum
is KYC.
Everyone who wants to sign up
to your service,
has to show up personally.
You have a physical person
who checks it.
You already have
some services
that are quite elegant
with the phone and so on.
But what?
In the end,
it's always the trade-off.
You go to the tech shop...
Plus, it's not the best
for onboarding people.
Our idea was to enable
as many people as possible
to come to the platform.
Specifically, we served
as a platform
to share your opinion,
to have a wide sample.
And of course,
the problem is that
when you become such an obstacle,
you can't get people out of the sample.
That's an additional
specificity of our environment.
But yes, it's a very interesting area.
Yes, now we will
conclude this.
Not for what we would like,
but for what we will miss.
We are cheap.
I wanted to say
that if people want to contact you,
if they want to talk to you,
if they go through some
beginner's steps,
if they really want to know
if it's for them,
they can contact you,
but you don't have Twitter,
Facebook, Google,
phone...
In a way, it's understandable
why you said that
it's a starting point,
that there is faith
or a way to get
some knowledge.
I am very happy
when people start helping.
I have prepared
emails, for example,
a beginner's step
for someone who would be interested.
Template?
Do you give a challenge
or is it more like
you choose it first,
or do you assess it on the basis
of the question you get?
No, no, the guy made a course.
No, no, I didn't go that far.
But let's say I have the basics for that.
Some raffles,
but the point is
that a lot of people ask me,
a lot of people express interest
if I would, and then I'm like
oh, the best, I can help you.
And then I have here
an email with a pointer
for a first step for someone
how to go in that direction.
So yeah, I'm not on Facebook,
I'm not on Instagram, I'm not on Twitter.
LinkedIn?
Yes, I'm on LinkedIn.
Thank you, Krištof, for being with us.
Thank you, Andraž, for your time.
If you liked this podcast,
please let us know,
give us feedback,
if it makes sense,
if we should do it again.
Let's talk about a topic.
Yes, a topic.
Let's not say
that we'll know what to say,
but we'll have an opinion.
We'll choose people
who have a different opinion,
so this debate will look
more interesting.
That's it.
Ok, it didn't work.
Bye.