About 10 seconds before the start, we can start with the 2nd episode of the 3rd season of Ogrodie.
It's almost the 40th episode of our podcast.
Today, a bit more simplified, we'll talk about data science, a bit about Aero, a bit about Python,
we'll have a bit of fun with Roman's and Andraž's computer.
We had fun with your computer.
I'm still jealous that it's my computer.
Today, we visited Roman Luštrih's Ogrodie.
Roman is one of those people who saw that we'll be doing our podcast.
He said, guys, wait, I'll come and show you how to record a podcast.
Hold my beer, and he showed us the equipment.
Thank you for that, too, three years ago.
I already forgot about that.
You brought us a beer and said, guys, you need this, you need that.
If you open a beer, I'll record it even better.
I've never done that before.
Exactly, I just came.
Today, we have a big man in our podcast.
I hope it'll be fun and interesting for everyone.
You can have pompous presentations.
Twitter influencer, podcaster.
I'd go on Twitter and see what they write there.
Geniuses or geniuses.
Geniuses.
I'd go on Twitter and see what they write there.
Genitals.
Nice.
That's quite intimate.
It depends, sometimes yes, sometimes no.
I think that from our audience, people probably met you the most at the Python meetup.
Yes, the locals met me at the Python meetup.
Those who do a bit of Aero met me at Stack Overflow.
At Stack Overflow?
Yes, because I started there in 2009.
First, I studied at Aero, then when I started going back to society,
I wrote a lot of answers.
One of my answers was asked,
what comes up when you start getting to know the basics of Aero?
I think it happened once or twice,
that a key researcher from Flow came to me.
When I was still working at the Department of Biology,
they called me on the phone,
Roman, come down, we have a researcher here,
who also works at Aero.
I came down and introduced myself,
and Roman came and said,
I know who you are.
From where?
From Stack Overflow.
I see your post a lot.
It happened to me twice.
Most of our guests,
after our conversations,
we also talked a bit with Andraž,
it seems that people who are primarily developers,
and then conquer some other domains,
you are not a developer.
What do you think about that?
You are right.
I am not a developer.
I was inspired by computers.
When I was 12 years old,
I got my first Commodore.
I knew how to play a game,
I knew how to run,
then I got a PC,
and then we started playing games.
There was no real school work in 1997.
You had to work on a computer.
Then I came to IRC,
and I did a bit of scripting.
I have always been into computers,
but my passions were more or less alive.
I am also a veterinary technician.
The short story is that I am a veterinary technician,
then I am a gynaecologist,
then a failed student of zootechnics,
a biologist,
and a statistician.
I still lack some kind of a ceramic,
but I can cover it.
It will go well.
No, I have decided not to use ceramics.
But I have mastered the skill of using
isotects and styroduras.
So if I need it,
I will come to you.
What do you do in biology?
You research from the field of biology,
and for you Python and R are tools
that you use to help.
Is that how you imagined it?
Yes, I got it from a practical point of view.
When I started writing my thesis,
I had to analyze the data.
How do you do it?
I asked Jerpota, Jer Nepolajnar,
if you have ever looked at Wikipedia,
and he said,
come and look at R.
I downloaded it,
tried it a bit,
I was impressed,
because it was so easy,
so logical.
What drew me to it is
that it is very well documented.
None of the tools I have used so far
have been so well documented.
Not only that,
but how do you do the analysis?
It was very relevant to me,
because I needed a lot of analysis
for my thesis.
I just put my data in there,
and it was a bit of an error,
because I didn't understand
how to do all the details.
But when I looked at it,
I got the results,
the table, the picture,
and it was clear to me
how to program it.
Then I started to use
more advanced techniques.
At the beginning,
I just analyzed the data,
and then I started to program it.
Over time, as R grew,
R got more and more popular.
Do you think that
people who don't know R yet,
for example,
are listening to you now,
that the first thing
that comes to their mind
is probably some kind of
data analysis,
at the end of high school,
in high school,
I hope not.
Or maybe never.
But I imagine that
people first used Excel.
Is that OK?
Excel is a very good tool.
It's not perfect,
but it's a good tool
for collecting data.
It's good for visualization.
But if you want to do
a little bit of real science,
where you want the data to be repeatable,
to be documented,
you need a practical code.
Because you can't write in a document,
in Excel, first I clicked on it,
then I opened the menu,
and then I just picked it up.
In R, it's all in code,
documented,
you write a script,
and it can be executed.
On the assumption
that Excel has support for Python,
do you think that will be...
Yes, that's also...
Is that an opportunity
to look at Excel?
Yes, I mean,
on the one hand, it's possible.
I imagine it has some advantages,
but
most people,
when they start,
they think that
it's not that much of an added value.
It's probably something,
but maybe they could try and see.
I mean,
those who deal with data more seriously,
because we don't have it.
I mean, we don't have it categorically,
mainly because
it includes so many technical problems.
Let's take an example.
For example,
scientists went to change
the name of a human gene,
because Excel changed it to a date.
OK.
But,
does that require a tool?
Of course,
because you have to define
the type of column,
and then it's fine,
but the average user doesn't understand that.
And then,
let's say,
if you import CSV,
or some flat file,
a file that doesn't have
a definition of types,
it will ruin it.
And then you will have to
fix it.
And of course,
you ruin it.
I think that's how it is.
And you also see that
tools are more appropriate
for your work.
Yes, that's right.
But, as I said at the beginning,
data collection,
if you want to collect data,
it's ideal to have a form
where you have pre-selections,
and you just click and don't move.
In Excel,
you can do whatever you want,
which is very convenient
and fast,
but it can cause a lot of trouble
in the dataset,
and cleaning the data
takes a lot of time,
and you have to be careful
that the data is not
consistent.
On the other hand,
you need to be a programmer,
and you need to know
what tools to use
to define it,
and how to do it.
Andraž,
what is your experience
with R?
Yes, I tried it a few days
before this recording,
and then,
because I've been programming
Python for many years,
and there's a book
called Panda,
I was like,
aha, now I understand
why we do things like that
in Panda,
and I was like,
I think I've found my way.
I went to Ops,
which we also had
in the previous episode,
because it's an open data portal,
and I took the PC access,
I forgot the format
of the data,
which is a more commercial software,
and I installed a library in R,
so I could go through it,
and I did,
and I got the data frame,
and I sorted it
by age,
average,
the lowest age,
and all the municipalities,
which I was interested in the least.
And I did that for about
one hour,
because I thought,
OK, what can we do in one hour,
and we can do it really fast.
And now I'm looking at a few books
that explain statistics
and how to use it,
and maybe because of that
it's a bit more interesting.
So, you can actually
put a code on top,
and that means that
when you have an experimental article,
you put some visualizations there,
and then you put the data
in the A app,
and then in the B app,
and then R code.
That's right, you can put it
in a script,
or today I've noticed
that people put a link
to GitHub repo,
which is a bit stupid,
because in the next few years
it won't die,
and it will be repetitive,
but people will still
take the article,
and then deal with it.
What you mentioned,
one thing,
which I've already mentioned today,
is that it's very well documented.
You have a lot of help.
In addition to those vignettes,
where the analyses are somehow
described,
you have books in each area,
and how to do it in R.
I think it's very well done,
because you take a book,
and you rewrite it,
and the things you have in the book
come out.
And you really have that,
from mathematics to biology,
time analysis,
ecology,
I learned all those things
through those books,
and not only theoretically,
you open a book,
and you see mathematical formulas,
and they come to you.
But actually,
people who are serious
make tools in R,
a function package,
and you just say
the name of the function,
some data,
and things come out.
Of course, I could take
those mathematical formulas
and write it myself,
and then it takes a lot of time
to iterate
and make solutions yourself.
But it's a shame
that everyone does it themselves,
because if you can do it in one way,
people can use it.
Scientists are users,
most of them,
99% or more,
are users of those solutions,
and it's much easier
for us,
first of all,
in time,
to make it more consistent,
and I believe
that R was deserved
for being a place
where we were able
to make science
at a next level.
We're not there yet,
because, for example,
reproducible science
is not there yet,
but I think Python is growing
and is on the right track
to make it possible.
If I want to learn a domain,
for example,
I have some patterns,
some measurements,
and I want to know
what the average value is,
and how those values
are distributed,
instead of just taking
a textbook from math
or whatever,
I can take a book in R
and there are some basic concepts
in there,
such as probability,
or mathematical confidence,
or correlation,
and then you play a little
and it's interactive.
Right, and you have all of that.
There's also a book,
R for Dummies,
because if you're too grateful,
you'll also need me.
Humblebrag, no,
not humble.
And you have exactly that in there,
the basics of R
on basic concepts
and basic knowledge,
the biological part,
I have a full book,
and I have,
let's say,
3-4 meters,
I only have R books,
how to do something in R,
or in S, technically,
but it's the same.
How is S connected to R?
S is a commercial package,
and then these two guys said
fuck this shit,
and they wrote an open source
part of the code for S,
also in R.
OK.
Can I ask you,
very quickly after all these R tutorials,
can you come to,
in Python,
is this data frame,
the concept of data frame,
does it have something similar,
or is it also called data frame,
or some internal structure,
can you tell me a little more?
Right, in R you have
a vector,
a vector is an array,
one-dimensional,
then you have a matrix,
which is two-dimensional,
then you also have a multidimensional matrix,
then you have a data frame,
then a sheet,
a sheet is basically
like having
a map,
and then you can jump inside,
you can be in a school,
you can be anywhere,
you can be in any element,
you also have functions
that know how to systematically
access those elements,
recursively,
and so on.
And at the beginning of the topic,
you can make some type of
very complex objects,
that carry some kind of information,
for example,
you have a complex object
that carries a sparse,
how do you say it,
a data frame,
and then you also have a metadata,
which is a typical data frame,
and you have two completely different concepts,
but in one object.
And it's combined,
and you act like it's a data frame,
a typical table
with rows and columns,
and that's it.
Do you work with large amounts of data?
Like R,
I don't know,
terabytes of data,
is that an abstraction,
or is it still R,
or are you always in some kind of subset?
How is it inside?
Not natively,
everything is stored in memory,
and then you limit how much data you have,
which is a bit easier today,
because you have an instance,
and then you have this memory,
you do something,
you close it,
and it becomes 5 euros.
But I think,
you can have large clusters,
which are gigabytes and gigabytes,
or terabytes,
large files,
and you can't store them all at once,
it doesn't make sense,
why would you store cluster data
for the whole world,
if you only need it for storage?
And you have methods,
you have a package,
where you tell it to store
from this geographical width to this,
and so on,
a square,
and then you analyze it,
while you work.
So, one kind of theory,
and then you also have,
I think,
in DAPACIA,
they have some formats,
where you can work
in a similar way,
only with metrics,
I mean,
with tabular data,
everything is technically
a table,
you can work in memory,
but you can also
work with a bit of switching,
with unusual data.
I wanted to say,
that Erson made statistics
for his needs,
and it was like,
organically,
good word,
but it's not super consistent.
You know,
the name of the argument
in one function is different
than in the other.
Sometimes there is a lot of
pressure,
sometimes little pressure,
because for someone
who is new to it,
it's very fluid,
for us old people
who are used to it,
it's like a dream,
but today,
I don't know,
in 2010,
it started to grow,
well, not grow,
and it developed
not only for statistics,
but also for other things.
For example,
they made a framework
for writing
web apps,
like Shiny,
or Django,
or something like that.
Ok.
It's not as good as Django.
It's like when you export
Python plugins
into a widget,
you know that.
You can't export it,
you can deploy it,
like Streamlit.io
or something like that.
You have elements
and you just install them.
And then you export it
as a web app?
Exactly.
You just have .R file
and you deploy it
to a server
and it serves as an app.
So you get some interactivity
on the data.
You have a slider
and you can move it.
Exactly.
You can interact with it
back and forth.
By changing your inputs,
you can influence
the user interface.
It really helps
if you have knowledge
of JavaScript.
But even without that,
you can do really interesting things,
really big things.
Boilerplate for example.
If I had a dashboard
and I showed this
and that on it,
I could do anything.
The most important thing
is that you have CSS
and those colors.
That has developed a lot
and is used a lot.
In addition to being used
in different areas of science,
chemistry, pharmacy,
biology,
economy,
spatial problems,
and so on.
Can I ask you
where does this RStudio
come from?
If you watch a lot of tutorials
and you have the language R
or S
or KT,
what is this RStudio?
What is it?
That's a very good question.
On Stack Overflow,
people change it non-stop.
Sometimes, when I don't know
what to do,
I try to fix tags
because people give RStudio tags.
But RStudio has nothing to do
with R as such.
Sometimes we had R,
which is a program
with a lot of tags.
Sometimes it looked like
you had a terminal open
and a text
and a notepad.
You copied and pasted it
into the code.
We also had some plugins
for Notepad++ and so on.
But it was very complicated
to install for new users.
Then some good guys
came in
and started working on IDE
which I called RStudio.
You install RStudio
and everything works.
You have a text editor
and you write a note,
you assign a cursor,
you press CTRL, ENTER
and it comes out
and everything works.
Is it similar to Jupyter Notebooks
from Python?
No.
It's possible too,
but not in the basics.
We used to have a terminal
and a text editor
and it was integrated.
You click on a function
and press F1
and a help file opens.
You can also change
the key bindings.
But this helped
new users.
When we had a workshop
in R,
the first thing
to do
was to open
and it works.
It saves a lot.
It's not a perfect product,
but it's good enough.
It has it's problems.
You can also look at
the relevant results
and the data frame.
You can look at
what's in your memory.
You can look at it
and manage it.
Yes, you can
interactively
with those
data frames.
And then you have a problem, if you don't do it in the script, you don't know what you've done or you forget what you've done.
Although you can look at the story, but it can be a hundred times worse and then you get lost.
When I was playing, I installed R, which is also open source, then I installed RStudio, which is also a community version, which is a Fero license.
And then I wrote it down, and as they say, one window I had for visualization, the other was for Ripple.
So I had an ultra-specialized development environment for that.
Considering that you use Python a lot, do you notice that there are no functions or libraries in R, for example, that are used in Python?
I think about it a lot, because I use Python and R a lot in my day job, and I see that there are better solutions in Python than in R and vice versa.
So I have a love-hate relationship with all topics.
Specifically, for example, I got into object programming.
In Python, I really don't like it at all.
In R, it's almost a disaster.
In R, you have, I think, four or more types of object programming.
Pick one, and then it's not so nice.
For example, with Python.
That's one thing, for example, because Python is much better.
The other thing is that in R, the solution is much better.
As a community, we are lucky to have a package called ggplot2, which implements the grammar of graphics.
It's a concept where you draw on layers, first in the back, then you give points, then you give lines, and you can change each layer in your own way.
It's really good, because you get data when you have one column down, and you choose two images for male and female.
It's like this.
Tilt down, and something happens.
It's really well done.
In Python, it's unfortunate that the matplotlib is so extensive, and it's terrible for me.
For the same image in R, I need three or four types.
In matplotlib, I'll need 150 types.
Everything can be done, but it's not easy.
You need to know all the features.
That's right.
It's really complicated, but everyone is trying now.
There's a plotline library in Python, which implements ggplot2.
The syntax is very similar, and I often get stuck in it.
I try to draw a picture in the theme, because it's faster.
There's a lot of artificial intelligence in LLVM.
A lot of tooling is developed in Python, and in C++, with nice wrappers and bindings for Python.
If you look at all the new-age technologies, Python is in the lead.
What's in R?
Nothing.
As I said, it's all written in Python.
R is behind it, because it's all about deep learning.
There are libraries for deep learning in R,
but they're just called Keras or Python.
I tried it, and it was so buggy that I had a Python error.
I said, fuck it, and went to Python.
It was much easier.
Maybe a notebook, like Jupyter.
I remember when I started a year ago.
Everything was OK, but now it's really good.
It's well integrated, it's easy to use, and it's top-notch.
The machine learning aspect is much more developed in Python than in R.
As I said, statistics were made in R.
In Python, you don't have the capacity to work with specific statistics like in R.
You have very complex statistical models,
which are mostly used by specialists,
and in Python they're not, or if they are, they're poorly implemented.
You have a lot of work to do.
When I calculate a model in Python, I call it a plot,
and the diagnostics tell me that it's not in Python.
You mean in R?
Yes, in R.
Not yet.
In Python, the computer science part is used,
and it's not focused on diagnostics.
In statistics, we're the stickler for the rules.
You have to look at the assumptions first,
and it's very important to have that.
In some aspects, Python is a bit behind,
but I'm convinced that in some aspects, R needs a lot more.
When I found out we were going to film this,
I thought, what are you going to watch in these debates?
You're going to watch YouTube and write Python vs R,
and you're going to watch those videos,
and it was good for me, because it's very relaxed,
and it's a community.
It's not a question of one or the other,
but the answer is yes.
The basics are so simple,
that it's easy to understand,
and if you need a specific domain,
you can look at it in both languages.
For me, the visual part of R was very interesting,
when you look at it like Python,
because it's really...
The matplotlib is terrible.
Typically, all the data is filtered,
and it's hard to keep track of it,
because it's so rigid.
So, those who are listening to us,
and are now tacticing whether to watch one or the other,
I think the answer is yes.
Maybe we could go a bit back,
and a bit forward.
You work for the company Genialis.
Not Genitalis.
Can you tell us a bit about what you do there?
For example, what are you doing,
what is your job, what is your mission?
Can you tell us a bit about what you do?
Any data scientist, statistic, whiz?
Magic, black box.
And then I come out and nobody knows what happened.
I was going to say, why are you crying, but yeah.
I'm not crying because I'm fulfilling my mission.
Strictly speaking.
Genialis is a company
that was established
by one of my colleagues.
They were biologists,
biologists and mathematicians.
The last thing we did,
the last pivot,
was to focus on
solving cancer problems.
And then we had a debate,
how can you tell your grandmother what you are doing?
If it's a ceramic, it's not a problem.
But sometimes it's a bit harder,
because we help our partners
to solve cancer problems.
For example, you can imagine
that cancer is not one disease.
It's many diseases.
One cancer, which in the past
was thought to be one,
is not the same disease.
And the medicine we have
against cancer
works for healing one cancer,
but not for all patients.
It works for 80%, 50%,
maybe even less.
Those who heal themselves against cancer,
go through a cascade of treatments,
to heal themselves.
And when you get to the 3rd or 4th position,
you don't have much time left.
And it's very important
to know if the next therapy will work or not.
For someone who doesn't have much time left,
it's very important to know
if they try this,
and if it will heal or not.
For example, we try to develop
a tool that will tell you
if it will heal or not.
So that you don't waste your time
with something that we know
or suspect will not be effective.
It can be an added value.
One added value is that you are healthy,
and the other added value is that you know
if you will respond to a treatment.
When I go to the office,
I think about it,
and when I come back,
I think about something else.
As a data scientist,
you get your input
with some data,
such as DNK,
or other data that you can use
to make predictions.
Yes, we tell you some facts
that we hope we will learn
from a daily record.
In our company,
we mainly deal with DNK data.
Our cells have DNK,
which is the daily record
that is passed down from generation to generation.
The result of this DNK
are proteins.
The appropriate level is RNK.
This is when you copy the pattern
and go to someone with this pattern
to make this protein.
We know how many patterns
there are for a single protein.
The more patterns there are,
the more proteins are produced.
We know how to copy this part
to some extent.
On the basis of this,
our team tries to develop
a model
that will be a product.
I mentioned interdisciplinarity.
We have Fruity,
we have physics, biotechnology,
we have biology,
computers, etc.
The approach is multidisciplinary
and only one person
can do this.
You need a team.
As you said,
junk in, junk out...
I can write that on my T-shirt.
If we sample DNK,
RNK,
it's a whole process.
The whole process of collecting
and digitizing it.
This is what happens
at the beginning of production.
For development,
you can use archival data.
It's not necessary.
The patterns we get
are...
Are you looking for a political speech?
No, no.
Are they big?
Is it a JPEG format?
A gigabyte file per person?
Or is it a terabyte of data?
One form of data we get
is a text file
which is 2x2GB.
DNK is a helix
with two legs.
where you choose one and the other.
Each goes to its own file.
It can be just one,
but that's very specific.
These files can be small,
depending on the technology.
You can have a special type of technology
for collecting very specific things.
You can get a whole genome
in one file.
That's a 50-100GB file.
Of course, there are other approaches.
How do you do that?
Let's give him a smart question instead.
I went to a few workshops
for machine learning,
but the problem is
that you get a lot of data
and then you try to reduce
that amount of data
to make it useful for learning
or for the model.
Then you filter it out
and you can't do it like in high school
where you had to measure
how valuable the data was.
When I was at the ML workshop,
I realized that
you have to filter the data
to know what it is
and then reduce it
to make a model.
The part where you write
the model,
for example,
the machine learning model,
it's not that important.
There are a few parameters
that you create,
but we dealt with pre-processing data.
Do you deal with that in your work?
Do you reduce it
or do you deal with the pro-model?
My answer will be twofold.
When I studied statistics,
both before and after,
when you look at the books
that I mentioned,
you have a notebook
and you make a model.
That's how it is.
More than 20% of the work
is data injection.
It's a time sink.
You can use it endlessly
to inject the data.
That's a big problem.
On the other hand,
when you get the data,
even if it's huge,
you can't share it on a laptop.
When you handle it on a platform,
you just upload a sample,
generate a pipeline,
and that's it.
Two hours later,
you have to invest in automation.
That's a big problem.
A lot of tools are written in Python
and they are not fully optimized.
However,
if you wanted to do it in Rust,
it would take a lot of time
and you might not have the knowledge.
Most of them are open source programs
that have already been confirmed
by the community
to do what they are supposed to do.
A lot of people have used it,
it's proven,
and you want to use it.
You want to use your tool,
even if it's faster.
It's a very complex algorithm
and it's hard to fork it.
You do it when you can afford
to do it.
Until then,
it will take 5 instances.
For example,
when I was working in the previous service,
we analyzed the data.
It took me a week.
If you could parallelize it,
it would take 3 hours.
A lot of optimization can be done
to parallelize it,
but above all,
you need to feed the files,
because the disk is so big.
People are so fast.
For example,
when I was working in the Biology department,
people were analyzing the data
and suddenly realized how big it is.
They got 10 samples and now it's full.
It's a platform that handles it.
As I said,
we get huge files
and through these algorithms
we reduce it from a few gigabytes
to 200 kilobytes.
Then it goes to modeling
where no magic happens.
Are these vectors?
No, they are labels.
Labels and genes.
It's one type of data.
There are others,
but most of them are individual labels.
These are labels with a few samples
and a lot of genes.
The human genome has 50,000 genes.
50,000 columns.
It's different from
what the partner has access to.
If you work in a studio,
you can get 10 samples at the beginning.
That's not much for such a thing.
But it's very hard to get samples.
It's expensive.
It's relatively expensive.
Of course, it's not a lot.
But getting people to be prepared
and to be able to handle it
is very interesting
in the field of clinical studies.
You see what the real problems are
and how to convince people
to participate in your studies.
So that you can start.
Clinical studies take place in larger phases.
One, two, three, and so on.
You have to recruit people.
It's hard sometimes.
People die, I hope,
but they can leave.
For example,
in this field,
in ecology,
it's a very similar problem.
You have a limited season.
You imagine that one butterfly flies
only one week in a year.
You can't recruit that many.
You recruit them,
you wait for a new season,
but you don't get the data in time.
It seems to me that there are challenges
in the whole science.
On the one hand,
you can get data quickly,
you don't have to process everything,
but on the other hand,
you have to use tweezers.
Zadnic, I know you announced
that you are looking for
a data scientist for Genialis.
I saw that you had a job ad,
and we talked about it.
I'm just wondering
if it's hard to find a data scientist
that has a good idea for work.
Are you looking for a biologist
or a statistician,
or a mathematician?
Which line can prepare you
for such a challenge?
It helps a lot to have domain knowledge.
You can learn it quite quickly.
I assume that everything is possible,
but it's much easier.
I haven't tested the hypothesis yet,
but I think that if you get someone
with the biological knowledge,
you can teach them to program it.
On the other hand,
if you have a computer scientist,
it's full of basics,
but there's also domain knowledge.
I'll give you an example.
Someone from Slovakia has been studying
for four and a half years,
and it's very difficult
to pay off that four years
with half a year of education.
I think that's the direction, and I also think that my co-workers are very mathematically and linguistically primarily illustrated,
and they learn how to program.
We have a lot to compete with, we are very lucky, I really have excellent co-workers,
and I feel the most comfortable in this world, and they are really exceptional,
so we are really lucky to be able to lead such a team.
In addition to being able to lead a good team, I think we also give back a lot,
and we have a lot of foreign students, and we try to portray these juniors,
to direct them,
so I think we are unique, no matter how many people there are,
because I often hear that in some meetups.
I don't know, for us, we are lucky to be able to fill these positions.
You will ask him the same question about the Python meetup,
how did it work out for you?
Maybe we will go to the pool of water, and Andraž will formulate the question.
It's a question we had several times.
You are active in the Python community, and you are the co-organizer of the Python meetup,
and we talked about how difficult it is to find sponsors for the Python meetup.
What do you think about that?
It wasn't like that, we talked a lot about the Python meetup,
and I know that people are asking where the next Python meetup will be,
and if Python is really widespread, and a lot of people use it,
I know that you are looking for sponsors,
because if we don't have a Python meetup, we won't sponsor it.
Why is it so difficult to get backing for something that big?
It's really not difficult, if you are so little engaged.
For example, I've noticed that it's unproductive to say,
come to the meetup, come to the company,
so that you can be a sponsor.
You don't get anything.
When you get to know the person, you start talking,
you come to sponsor them, and then it really happens.
I think that in the past, money wasn't such a problem,
that it was a jump change for a company.
Sometimes it's a problem to get a sponsor,
sometimes it's not.
So I think it's a bigger problem.
The problem is in the organizers, because we are a bit lazy.
It's not our primary job, and then I have to work 8 hours a day,
and then I have to work from home,
and then I have to call a new company,
or hire a new person,
and then you have to postpone it,
because it's not your primary job,
and then you have to wait for something to happen.
Then people come to you and say,
we would like to have a talk,
and we would like to sponsor you.
It's possible, really possible.
As you said, it's a big community.
I think that at meetup.com,
it's probably the biggest computer community in Slovenia.
I think that 1300 members,
or something like that,
compared to others, it's a lot.
It also has some history.
Yes, people started before me,
and now we have our own history.
I have a very bad memory,
so if you've listened to the podcast Metamorphose,
you know what I'm talking about.
I came there in 2016,
and it was more than a year ago.
Do you have a feeling that this community
has an influx of young beginners?
Yes, to some extent, I think they are coming.
They have their own members,
and then sometimes new people
come out of the vault.
For example, they have a lecture
or they know how to say something smart.
The point of a meetup
is the community itself.
I think I'm learning a lot.
These lectures are fine,
but the energy they give you,
and then the pizza at the end,
and when you talk,
you can honestly say something,
or they say something,
and the community,
because sometimes you see
that the university is looking for this,
and you know it,
and you connect,
and it's an added value.
I would recommend people
to come to meetups.com,
if they haven't yet.
I'm looking forward to the next one.
Recently you promoted
or helped to organize
a meetup called R-Ladies.
Can you tell us more about it,
because I also saw
that you helped.
If I go one step back,
when I was still working
in biology,
there were a few of us,
and when we were working in R,
we started to hang out.
We were working in R,
and we started to hang out,
and we were like,
let's meet up again,
and we did,
and then we said,
and now we have a good name,
we said that we are alcoholics,
and then we started
to organize lectures,
and the first lecture
that I had,
in the biggest lecture hall,
was full,
and a lot of people were interested
in what R was,
because everyone was talking about R.
It's like sex,
everyone says they do it,
but they don't really do it,
they just choose a topic.
Or public tests.
And there was a lot of
attention to it,
and then it became a thing,
and then I went there,
with a fax,
and then that.
That was the main problem
of getting lecturers.
You have so many researchers
at BfA,
and they work hard,
and they teach everyone
from what they have,
and then they run out.
And R-Ladies
is more
at the beginning,
with the new
generation,
or what do you call it?
Yes, and then we have
the alcoholics,
we also have a Slack channel,
and some people
got together there,
and one girl said,
what if we had an R-Ladies meetup,
which is a worldwide initiative,
where different places
around the world have
chapters,
some chapters,
and they organize
where girls or
women
talk about what they do,
and when you watch those videos,
you choose what
they do.
And also in Slovenia,
we have a few
entrepreneurs,
and I help them a bit,
as much as I can,
but the main thing
is that I am
a part of it.
Can you tell us
about
maybe
a few institutions,
or companies, or organizations
that you know use R-Ladies in Slovenia?
Just for the feeling.
Yes, for example...
I don't know,
startups, or big companies,
small banks.
The biggest company I know is
Univerza Ljubljana,
which is our joint faculty.
Maybe Teološka doesn't do it,
but Philofax.
If I try Philofax,
I'll probably...
SPSS?
In Teološka as well,
as Angelo Loka dances
at the end of the needle,
which was a question at the time.
No, that's just a bad question.
First of all,
researchers from different institutions
use R-Ladies a lot.
I know that the biggest
system bank in Slovenia
also uses R-Ladies,
among others.
I think there are a lot
of companies
that are
research-oriented.
R is a fast tool
to use.
Python is also
a niche
for itself.
But I think
R is very popular.
Maybe I could sit down
and start writing.
I would be interested
in how many users
there are.
You don't have to speak.
I know, I know.
You have more experience.
We're already on the subject.
You also record podcasts.
Yes.
You said at the beginning
that metamorphosis...
We didn't say that.
Let's go first
to the sponsors.
OK, let's go.
This is a good clip.
Here on the table
we have stickers from Aurora Coworking.
Aurora Coworking
is
a community space
where we thank our guests
for the opportunity
to record
in a slightly different setup
than usual.
Thank you, Hosea and friends,
for this opportunity.
The company 3FSV and Human Frog
have decided to support us
this year.
We thank them
for making it possible.
And of course Patreon,
where we are also supported.
We make ZDV easier.
Thank you to everyone who supports us
and helps us to work.
Let's move on.
If you want to talk more with us,
come to our Discord,
where we can develop the topic further.
I think you're also there.
I'm also there,
in the afternoon.
I saw that.
You can also
ask questions.
Is Human Frog like Human Fish?
Do they have beer?
Human Frog
is a company
from Žabec Group.
They rebranded it.
I think some companies did an acquisition
and grew a little.
They rebranded it.
I won't say agency,
but a whole suite
of IT packages.
It's easier with them.
I wanted to record
this podcast
about metamorphosis.
I listen to it a lot.
I choose some
scientific articles,
but I choose
news about science.
AI is also very popular.
Last year,
there were a lot of algorithms
for protein unfolding.
Probably not folding,
but OK.
What did you say?
Unfolding.
People said
that modern technologies
are not really for humans,
but they are really
interesting.
We all know chat GPT.
One of them was protein folding.
What do you think about it?
Can you tell us something about it?
Let's go back.
I mentioned DNA.
DNA is made of proteins.
It's not just a record
of amino acids,
but it's also a form
in which they are folded.
It's a very complex process.
It's very difficult
to experimentally
make it in a laboratory
and then look at
the 3D structure.
You try to
get closer to the ground
and how would a computer
teach you to
input and output.
Then you learn
how it unfolds.
Simulations are
perfect for that.
You try to tell
how a protein
is made.
You make a DNA
and you insert a bacterium
in the cell
to make a protein.
You try to tell
how it unfolds
and then it unfolds
depending on its function.
Will it fold or not?
These big systems
are used for that.
You need a lot of
computational power for that.
If you are in a
biotechnology industry,
it's very difficult
to develop
products
like biodiesel.
You want to split
a protein to get more
or less waste.
These are very interesting technologies.
I don't know
how much
the ROI is.
How much is the return
on investment.
It's not my area
so I'm not familiar
with it.
I've seen
that it bends
and it's a full breakthrough.
Yes, I know.
It's easy to hear and see.
I've read
that people
played games
with folding
and they got
datasets.
It's a very
hardcore problem
and it's difficult to develop.
I think
it's a bit obvious.
I've been with you before.
When we were talking
about what we would talk about,
Brodo said
that when
the end of the world comes,
he would go to Roman.
He said, Roman is
the one I want the end of the world to come to.
I said, why?
He said, Roman is the one
who will be armed.
He knows what's happening around him.
The most important thing
is to get to know each other.
It will be a good company.
It will be pleasant.
There won't be any problems.
Are you ready?
I've got a haircut.
Let's talk a bit
about
what you've been doing
as a practicing data scientist
in the research lab.
Can you tell us
why it's good to have
your arsenal of weapons?
You can tell us both.
Is it supplemented?
No.
It's a different person
who said I would have a sabre
on a lonely island.
I was relatively
active in the lab.
I'm still running
all the time.
I'm preparing what's going on.
The stories are very interesting.
My work started
when everything started with Corona.
Corona is a virus
that was popular last year.
Thank you.
When everything started,
we came up with an idea
how to estimate
the size of the virus.
At the beginning, it was relatively small.
I wrote a simulation
where I estimated
how many people
could be tested
in order to get
the data.
If you have a virus
that is not yet
detected at the beginning
and is very small
and difficult to detect,
you need a lot of people
to be able to detect it.
100 people
is nothing.
In the end,
you can't do anything.
You can't do anything in the interval.
That's why I calculated
and put it on the Internet.
Then I went to the FBI.
They were
a support
for the people
and they did
the first study in the world
where they estimated the prevalence
of the virus in the population.
They came to similar numbers as I did.
That was a validation.
Then I helped
with the pipelines
where the data was updated
and then updated on the other side.
It was more or less like that.
At the meetings
where I was involved,
there were a lot of people
and now someone else
has to say something
so that it's not a ping-pong game.
The other 18 of us
were on the bus watching the sky.
A lover of efficiency.
No,
I feel
the need
to be pro.
To be fair.
I know they are intelligent
and they have something to say,
but it doesn't mean
that you should
step on someone's foot
and then I say something.
I am a pro.
Roman is a real master.
He doesn't know yet.
That wouldn't be me.
That was my instinct.
It's a walk.
Meetings for a tracker
are in Bosnia.
I'm used to it.
I would have a meeting at 6 a.m.
but I don't listen to it.
Why not?
If anyone
wants to work with a tracker
contact me.
I'll find someone for you.
Can you tell us
about your arsenal?
I've always
been passionate
about contraptions.
I'm a geek.
Not only in life,
but also in weapons.
It's a lot of fun.
I've never had
access to it.
When I started making money
I thought about
...
Sorry, what?
I don't know.
I was always passionate about
contraptions.
Then I bought a civilian version.
Then you join a club
and
you go to meetings
and competitions.
It's a warning.
It's a sausage fest.
It's a very interesting sport.
For me it's a weapon.
I see it more as a tool.
It's a loud gun.
I'm fascinated
by how it's made.
For some weapons
I make ammunition myself.
Why do you get lost
in it as a geek?
How many bullets,
how many bullets to shoot.
It's a very good hobby.
You can spend
a lot of time on it.
Yes, time sink.
You can go back to it.
Then you have people
who pump their hair
with bullets.
It's a skill.
In Slovenia
it's still developing.
Yes, it is.
Do you think it's developing
in Slovenia?
I wouldn't say so.
In Slovenia
the third or the biggest
organization
are hunters.
Everyone has a weapon.
There are a lot of weapons in Slovenia.
It's the same in subcultures.
Hunters are a subculture.
They have their uniforms,
ties.
The state helps you
in hunting.
Do you know what a hand is?
Yes, it's called a deer.
A hand is a sign
of a deer.
Do you know why it's called a hand?
Because deer don't know
the letter F.
It's something you can
somehow get into.
It's not like you go to the door
or the shooting range.
For example, in Ljubljana
we have a commercial shooting range.
It's the easiest
way to get to know someone.
What are the biggest
challenges?
For example,
someone who doesn't have
any contact with the weapon.
For example, someone who prepares it
through American movies,
media, etc.
What is the biggest
experience you have
when you get to know
the Slavic environment?
Are we more regulated
in Slovenia?
Are we less regulated?
Is it a problem?
What are the technological aspects?
I think that in Slovenia
the weapon law is quite good.
It's quite regulated.
In the beginning,
everyone can get a weapon
for some reason.
Again, if you are accused
of committing acts
related to violence,
then they are cured.
But there are a lot of people
like that on other channels.
I have a forum
called Strelac.
There is a thread
where we put all the news
from the area of
weapons, shooting, etc.
or at least in Slovenia.
And he's been doing this for, I don't know,
10 plus years.
You're not on Stack Overflow, you're on Strelets.se, right?
Yes, almost.
And it's
very popular
and a lot, and one day
I'll take the time and go
analyze it.
And I don't think it's a problem.
Of course, there are weapons
involved in criminal acts, but I think it's
like that.
In the movie, they think it's a big deal,
but it's really relatively small.
Especially with legal weapons.
You should know that
legal owners of weapons are like
the police. We're afraid to do anything
to get a lot of weapons.
The same goes for hunters, for example.
And
it's
pretty common.
My association with the movie is
when they say
what a shock you get when you come to the shooting range.
It's
a kind of indiscipline.
It's not like
waving your hand.
The first thing you do is go home.
Even when you're at the shooting range,
just to point at the gun,
you aim at the gun.
You just write it down and go home.
That's how it is.
In the first place is security, in the second place is security,
in the third place is security.
Then they start shooting.
I also think there's a lack of luck
in our country.
Everything happens.
Hunters are unlucky
because in the shooting range
anything can happen.
They bring you a bullet,
or you hear gunshots
and someone shoots.
That's what happened.
That's how it is.
Will you answer this question?
Yes.
I found Balončko
as a joke.
For me it was great.
One time we were riding a bike
in a bar.
It was
an amazing experience.
You're like a log,
very aware of things.
It was great when he said
Do you see that growing there?
That's it.
It's an invasive species.
We are getting...
I don't know, American
or something like that.
People are getting it
and then they try to
cut it out of the bar.
I know
that there are also
a lot of
interesting activities
that you do.
I'm so interested
in what else
you do.
We often say
we have to be eco-friendly,
we have to take care of nature.
But there are also activities
where you can get rid of invasive species.
Yes.
I'm interested in what
things you do
that are more
activistically interesting than
the asphalt on the ground.
That's true.
As a biologist,
you have easy access
to all the societies
that exist in Slovenia.
You have a lot of
different activities
that you can join.
For example,
it's great that
a lot of people are interested
in joining children.
It's fun for the whole family.
You can also
talk about botany.
You can go to a lake
or a lake where botany
is very interesting,
or to the mountains.
You can also go to
Engolaš and back down
to the city of Dajansko.
You can also see
what's interesting outside.
You have a society
that is involved with bees.
You have trips to different parts of Slovenia
and you register bees.
A lot of photos
with macro photography.
You have beekeepers,
as they are called.
You have a society that studies this.
They also have competitions.
Who will be in more beekeepers
in one day.
You have bats.
You have
swans and
swans.
Birds.
Birds are the biggest
society in Slovenia.
You probably heard about DOPS.
They are also very active.
They organize different events.
They register swans,
water birds.
There is a lot of activity.
There are a lot of good people
who will gladly tell you
anything.
They will help you get involved.
You have a lot of books.
You don't need more books.
On your phone.
It is very nice.
You have a lot of free time.
You don't need a computer.
It is very accessible.
Slovenia is very lucky
to have diversity here.
People don't realize
how much diversity we have here.
Different plants and animals.
For example,
in June,
I go to the grassland.
Not the best grassland,
but an average good grassland.
There are more species here
than there are in the lowlands
throughout the year.
The lowlands are flat.
The vegetation and vegetation
are all cut down.
It is relatively destroyed.
If you go to the military training
you have to wait.
I am dissatisfied.
These are the best grasslands
in Slovenia.
I have seen them.
There are so many different plants.
It is a trip.
If you are a fan of plants
and biology,
don't miss it.
When we go to the military training,
we go to Maja,
to Bloška Polica.
You come up
directly from the orchids.
Orchids are very endangered.
Some of them.
But they are
for sale.
Extensive grassland
is cut down.
It is relatively polluted.
That is what is destroying.
It is very interesting.
That is why in Slovenia
people are so opposed
to the military training.
It is really something extraordinary.
I know a few foreigners
who got married
because they were so upset.
Even with the women.
I have the same feelings.
That is a
beautiful story.
We could
translate it
into beer and food.
Life and food.
You said
that you prepared a few questions.
I don't know if we gave you
an opportunity to...
No, no.
We didn't touch
all those topics.
Do you have anything else?
No, one thing I thought
we would find out.
What is bioinformatics?
Exactly.
Roman is a bioinformatician.
My name is
senior bioinformatician.
I think
when you look
at the online definition
of bioinformatics
and how it is related
to data science.
I think bioinformatics
is just one part
of data science.
When
computer scientists
discovered statistics
they called it
data science.
But it is really
analysis of data
and everything related to it.
From building
infrastructure
to modeling.
Bioinformatics
is debated a lot.
I think
when you dive
into data science
biological and molecular
aspects
you get bioinformatics.
Someone who has domain knowledge
from biology
and programming.
It is fast
and good enough.
It is related to what we discussed
before.
Someone with domain knowledge
can learn to program
fast and good enough.
Of course, it would be ideal
for everyone to be a computer scientist
and to know all algorithms
and RAST and C.
But reality is
that you have a week to do something.
I learn how to
set up a location
and pointers.
I want to click and get a picture.
OK.
Roman, thank you for all your work.
Thank you for the organization
of meetups
and events.
Thank you for your contribution
to society in a technological
way. Thank you, Andraž.
Thank you to the team in Grodno
for the recording.
Do you have anything else to say?
Thank you.
Thank you for the invitation.
At first I said
I would come because I hoped
there would be a VIP.
But I don't see him yet.
Let's go somewhere else.
Thank you for your attention.
Thank you for your support.
See you next time.
Thank you.
See you at the end of the world.
There will be me and Brodo.