So, the timer is on, we can start this episode of Ogródie in our subsection or our special
section of our show dedicated to English-speaking guests and English-speaking audiences.
This branch of our episode is designed so that we can get the best experts in the field
and they still can be shared among our audience.
So welcome to our episode.
Today we have a very special guest with us, Mr. Gunnar Mörling and my host, András Brodnik
and myself, Otto.
Today we are attending a Make-It conference in Portoro, Slovenia.
So this is a coastline of Slovenia that you might see behind us.
But sadly not listened to.
And yeah, when we were deciding the agenda for the Make-It conference, we really wanted
to have you in this conference as well, because in a while there was this excitement in Java
world where people were trying to solve this really interesting challenge that you designed
and people have gone crazy about it.
I managed to meet a few of these crazy people that actually solved your challenge and I
hope that we'll talk about it.
So, welcome to the show and if you can introduce yourself to the audience, that would be great.
Yes, of course.
So thank you so much for having me.
Really excited to be here.
Really excited to be at the conference.
And yes, my name is Gunnar Mörling, I work as a software engineer at a company called
Decodable.
We built a managed platform for stream processing there.
And yes, this challenge, the One Billion Road Challenge, actually was like a side thing,
which I started, you know, after Christmas and it ran for January, it really took off.
Thankfully, Decodable also sponsored it in the end.
But yeah, so that's the story.
Sweet.
Sweet and short.
I would like you to tell us, like, what is the definition, what's the challenge about?
Right.
Let's start, let's go directly to it.
Absolutely.
What's it all about?
Right.
Yeah, I mean, it's pretty much in the name already, right?
So it was, it was a challenge and the task was to process a file which has one billion
rows of temperature measurements.
So it's essentially like a simple CSV file.
Well, not quite because the delimiter is not a semicolon, not a comma, but it's a semicolon,
but it's like a CSV file.
And there's essentially rows of temperature measurements.
There's a station name like Hamburg or Portorosch, and then a values associated to that.
And the task was very simple.
You needed to calculate the min value, the max value and the average value per station.
The only caveat was, well, as the challenge name says, it's like one billion rows, which
means with this file, a bit depending on the names and how long they are, it was about
like 13 gigabytes of size and you had to process that file as fast as possible.
So very simple task, I would say, very simple to explain and still people spend like one
month and I guess hadn't we, you know, cut it off on January 21st, people would still
be working on it probably.
I like that there was a deadline to it.
Yes.
But you just had to put an end to the madness.
We'll go deeper, but just like for people that listen to this, try it out.
It's still a really lovely challenge, although you cannot submit your solution at the moment,
you still can challenge yourself.
Absolutely right.
And you can go there.
I mean, all the implementations are there, so you can check them out.
But I also would recommend people, you know, try it out first by yourself without looking
at what others did, you know, to get some ideas, then of course take inspiration.
But this was part also of the challenge to, you know, so people shouldn't work on it like
secretly and not see what others do, but they could take inspiration and be inspired and
learn from what others did.
Yeah.
I meet a lot of people in December where there's this Advent of Code challenge, right?
And yeah, it's Christmas themed, but look, you don't need to grind every day for the
new to solve all the stars to all the challenges, but you can learn also through the year.
The challenge is given, just explore what other people do.
And I think that's a really important point.
It's not like, yeah, if you don't have children or a lot of free time, then yeah, you can
do it in a specific timeframe, but like you can learn your whole life.
Yes.
And I mean, I was thinking to do it during Advent of Code, but I decided against it because
I felt.
That would be too much.
Yeah.
It would be too much.
Exactly.
And also it would just be nice.
It's a bit slow and maybe people are looking for something interesting to do.
And also, you know, I just had some time myself after Christmas to, you know, define the challenge
and that's why I said, okay, let's do it during January and see what people do with it.
I want to go now talk a bit about rules, right?
You wrote these rules.
And first rule, there might be more.
I think I wrote out three of them, but there might be a few like technical details.
First one is no external libraries.
Yes, exactly.
Why is that?
Mostly, well, for two reasons, really.
So one of, I mean, the goal of that was, well, to, you know, provide people and also myself,
frankly speaking with the means to learn something new and find out about new APIs in Java, you
know, the new possibilities like foreign memory and foreign function API, vector API.
So learn about those things.
And if you were just to use an external library, I mean, there would not be that much learning.
I mean, you would learn about that library maybe, but I think, you know, it makes more
sense to do it yourself and like really dig into that and like finding out about all the
possible optimizations.
So that was the one reason.
And then the other reason, well, just for me, I wanted to, you know, keep things manageable
in terms of evaluating this.
So I felt, okay, if it's just like a thing, so this was another precondition, a single
source file, so I can look at it, the entire code is there, you know, so nobody is running
their Bitcoin miner in the library on my environment.
Also was a reason to do that.
And one rule perhaps that kind of like stands out, I guess a bit is this, it needs to be
done in application time.
So nothing extreme in compilation time or anything like that.
So everything needs to happen in runtime and runtime only, right?
Yes.
Right.
So, and this was there because, I mean, how would you draw the line otherwise, right?
Because let's say, then I could just go solve the task once, store the result in a file,
and then my actual measured run would just load that file and like print out the numbers
from that.
That would be kind of pointless, right?
That's why I said, like, you cannot keep state.
It needs all to happen at runtime.
And that's what it was.
And we're still talking a bit about rules.
The, you can get the sample data, you can generate the sample data, but in the like
test runs or benchmarking runs that you actually do, do they run on the same sample data or
how does the sampling of the data works?
Right.
So this is actually a very interesting question because people did something which I did not
expect, which just goes to show my own naivete when it comes to that.
But so, yes, I had this data generator and this was there for practical reasons, because
I felt I cannot distribute a 30 gigabytes file.
I guess I could have done a bit more or whatever, but so I thought, okay, people should just
generate themselves.
And then I don't have this distribution problem.
Now, the challenge was that this used a very specific key set.
So I went to Wikipedia, I dug out like 400 something different weather station names
and like the average temperature, which actually exists at this location.
And then the generator would create like a normal distribution of random values.
You did actually put more effort into making it realistic.
Exactly.
So it's somewhat realistic.
And now people optimize a lot for that specific key set.
So, you know, they, and I assumed, okay, this, those are just examples.
You shouldn't like make any assumptions about these station names, but people optimized
a lot by, you know, choosing specific hash functions, which are collision free for those
names and this kind of stuff.
And so, which is then in the end, we had like another evaluation where we actually ran against
like 10 K different stations, also like longer names and so on.
And then actually the leaderboard also was a bit looking different between those guys
who, you know, very much optimized for the specific key set versus those guys who tried
to solve it in a generic way, as good as possible.
And then there are a bit, okay, these are like rules, but then there you have like,
you have like few hints in there.
So it's UTF-8 and there's only 10,000 cities.
Yes.
Right.
And people ask for that.
So to be honest, this didn't exist initially.
I wasn't really thinking that much, but then people asked me, yes.
How many stations can there be?
Because they wanted to know how large the table is, table B and stuff like that.
How long can those names be?
What's, you know, very specific questions around like encoding and so on.
And then I tried to, you know, put some rules into place.
And the challenge then was, of course, people had already submitted entries at this point.
And so I also didn't want to create a frustration for those who already had entered,
like by invalidating them.
So it was a bit of a balance to, yes.
Okay.
We want to make it more specific without invalidating existing entries too much.
I mean, there was a little bit of that.
Yeah.
You're kind of like, you're modeling the rules.
It was a bit like, you know, building out the plane while you already are flying.
Yeah.
Common problems when inventing a new sport.
What about AO?
So the, the, the disk performance and stuff like that.
Yes.
So IO, right?
So this is a very purposefully, not a part of the challenge.
So the way it is designed is, so initially I said, okay, I want to do like five or runs
of each entry and I will discard the slowest and the fastest run.
And I will then, you know, from the remaining three runs, the meantime, that's, that's the
measured time.
And the idea is that the slowest run would load the file into the page cache of the machine.
And from there, it's always served from REM so that IO isn't part of the equation.
And later on, I actually made it even more explicit and I just retrieved the file from
REM disk.
So it's always guaranteed to come from memory.
The reason being, I just felt, okay, IO is harder to measure.
And I also wanted to be, this is a CPU bound problem and people should spend their time
to, you know, CPU optimize and not the IO path.
But maybe there could be a challenge also geared towards that.
But then I think it's also a bit more complex to run.
So that's why I decided against it this time.
Yeah.
Probably there is a problem with controlling the environment.
Did you have, have you had any like problems with that?
Yes.
Funny you should ask.
I, I, I certainly did.
So what happened is I, you know, I was trying to be cheap because I paid initially for it
out of my own pocket.
So what I ended up doing is I got a virtual environment on Hetzner cloud.
It's a German cloud provider, like really, you know, fairly priced.
And I thought, okay, I want to have exclusive CPU calls, right?
I don't want to have like noise neighbor issues and like competing workloads.
So let me do dedicated CPU cores, but then I should be fine with this virtual environment.
Also, I thought, because what happened is at some point I woke up the next day, like,
you know, 40 more PRs or whatever waiting for review.
And I ran the evaluation scripts and like, I realized, oh, all those times are off.
Like everything is like suddenly twice as fast as before.
So I ran like an existing entry and it wasn't running in half of the time.
And I was going, well, what's, what's going on?
What's happening here?
And actually I filed even a support ticket with them.
And yeah, they told me, so they moved this workload to a different host.
So even with my dedicated course, they were just better course, like from one day to another.
And then all my measurements were off and I had to redo it.
And at that point, well, I decided, okay, I need to get like a dedicated box, which,
you know, I really manage or which I can manage together with the community.
So nothing can happen to that.
So that's what we did.
And of course it was a bit of a challenge to A, just get it.
It's more expensive, of course, thankfully Decodable helped to sponsor it.
And then also I just needed to get help with managing it because for instance,
I wanted to turn off the turbo boost.
I wanted to disable hyper-threading to make it more comparable.
And people from the community came and helped with it.
So at some point I asked on Twitter, so hey, can, is there anybody who can help me with it?
And Rene, who I didn't know before he reached out and he said, yeah, I can help you.
So we made a phone call and we, you know, I told about the things I needed to get done
and he was saying, yeah, I can do all that.
And so he sent me his SSH key.
I uploaded his SSH key to the environment.
We had never before, never met before.
So I gave him the key to the kingdom and, you know, he just did the right thing.
And it was just great to see how it can work with the community.
Can you tell us a bit more about how you evaluate these things?
Do you run them like sequentially, daily, like?
Yeah.
So what happened is I ran them when a new entry came in or when an entry was updated.
So it would do a GitHub pull request.
And at this point in time, I would create the, I would run this entry.
Okay.
And I had some shell scripting for that, you know, which made sure like the environment
is configured correctly, which made sure like the correct number of CPU cores is used,
which ran the test suite, which we had at some point.
So it was like invoking a single shell script,
which again folks from the community built to make this as easy as possible.
Are you using any kind of like benchmarking tools or is just like start time, end time?
No, there was a benchmark tool.
Now I'm blanking on the name.
I really should know.
But it's like a Java specific.
No generic Linux tool for just like running, you know, process a couple of times and then,
you know, calculating like the average value and stuff.
Okay.
I got some technical hints, but I'm not sure what he wants to tell me.
When you are...
I think he's like, can you please not touch microphone like you are doing it right now?
Don't do that.
Problem is it's sliding slightly.
Okay.
I would like to move like from benchmarking perspective.
Like if you should like re-evaluate all the solutions or only by submissions, like if you
change the underlying system that runs it, like is there a time when you rerun all of them or
like I do nightly runs or things like that?
Right.
So I could do that.
So actually the scripting infrastructure allowed to rerun any number of entries or
all of them if I wanted to.
And I did it typically.
I mean, so the thing is, I wasn't initially, I wasn't really interested that much in this
leaderboard and like, who is the fastest?
For me, it was more, Hey, let's learn about this stuff and find out something.
But then people are, I want to be the fastest one, right?
So they care a lot about the leaderboard.
And so that's why at some point I rerun, let's say the top 25 entries or so with
different configurations.
For instance, I wanted to run with all the 32 CPU cores with hyper-threading and so on.
And so I did that at some point and then, you know, the scripting allowed to rerun those
25 or whatever entries with a specific configuration.
We'd really love to now jump more to submissions.
Yes.
Can we do that?
Sure.
So obviously when I explained first time this challenge to Andras, he said, well, you guy.
The funny part was like, I was like, I'm doing that for a customer without actually.
Okay.
Well, it's not the same.
I think there is a bit of a less of data.
Explain the customer case, perhaps just so we have like a.
We get all the permits from the US, so building permits because there are public data.
And then, of course, you get that raw data and you need to normalize it.
And the catch is we do not seek for SAP one minute, whatever, right?
It just needs to be relatively simple to understand for a senior.
We don't want to write.
So every line of custom code or regs that I write or whatever complicated, it's not
a benefit.
It's a curse, right?
Yeah.
And for so I wasn't the author of the solution.
There was a funny, funny detail, which is you just basically install out in a Docker
container.
And then I think it was like not that complicated code.
It's something similar.
We split the different states.
And yeah, I do it that way.
And it runs.
I don't know.
I don't know the data set.
It changes, of course, all the time.
Maybe it runs half an hour, but it's OK.
It's streaming, right?
Because Unix pipelines are basically streams.
There is a funny detail.
It stopped working when I was moving that to another environment because I was using
so that the colleague who wrote it was using GNU, of course, and I don't know what the
default installation on a different system was was not working with a silent error, like
exiting with zero, not outputting any anything.
So, yeah, when I heard of this challenge, I was like, because.
I tend to.
I understand that you have this challenge, the catch is to learn something new, to optimize
really fast, and but I usually look at problems.
I'm like, OK, I have this challenge.
How can I make it so people will understand it for the next 10 years?
Absolutely.
And what I observed there in the challenges, I mean, I did a very simple baseline
implementation and this one ran like in approximately five minutes.
Pretty canonical Java code, I would say.
And then like improving all of that by one order of magnitude.
So taking it to 20 or 30 seconds, you can do this quite easily.
And the code will be still very well readable.
So it's code I would write like, you know, every Java programmer would write.
And it's easy to understand, easy to maintain.
But then if you want to go another order of magnitude, so you want to go down to like
one point five seconds, like, you know, top of the level, then it's getting like really
crazy.
And this is like super dense code.
You need like three lines of comments for each line of code to make sense out of it.
And I wouldn't recommend people to go there like in their usual day job, I guess.
I want to slow you down just a bit.
Right.
OK.
I broke this down to like three levels.
So let's take it slowly because we want to go deep on these.
Level one would, let's say, be an AOC solution.
Right.
Or in your case, baseline, you're a Java professional.
So obviously five minutes.
That's kind of like five minutes, 10 minutes is like average or perhaps more senior engineer
would take it like that or do an AOC solution.
And that's, we said 12 or 13 gigabytes of file, a billion rows to process.
And that's like a baseline.
How far on the list of top submissions would that get you?
Would that get you in the top 25 even or?
No.
As is today, no.
You would be very much at the end.
At the end of it.
Sort of socialized.
I don't know, to be at the top 20 or so or maybe top 30 would have to be below 10 seconds.
Below 10 seconds.
OK.
We spoke in this conference with three engineers that did take the challenge.
We spoke with two senior engineers.
Best times we have is around a minute.
OK.
And 74 seconds.
So these are like Slovenian times.
OK.
It's impressive.
I mean, my own implementation was like five minutes.
I'm at the end of the leaderboard.
I was always the slowest one.
And both of these solutions that are like still very good in the leaderboards.
Both of these solutions are, as you said, readable.
Right.
So people can understand them.
They're like still single file, standard APIs.
You can maintain them and it's good, good modern Java code.
I think it uses GraalVM as well in both cases, but it's cool.
So if you write like that, you're good.
Yeah, totally.
It totally depends on what you want to do.
Right.
So if you need to run this like once per week or whatever, it's perfectly fine.
If you want to win a coffee mug in a challenge, you probably need to do some more.
OK.
But now let's go to level below.
Right.
OK.
We also spoke with Peter Levert.
He's a Slovenian guy.
OK.
He's the best Slovenian guy.
Oh, nice.
His time is four seconds and 209 milliseconds.
That's really good.
Yesterday we had a pleasure of talking to him and he guides us through the whole solution.
Right.
That he wrote.
I will not pretend that I understand all of this.
It's really dense code.
So for four seconds, it has to be like really, really tough.
What was really surprising was that he aimed to build a solution of his,
and I'll link all this stuff there below.
He tried to aim to not use unsafe.
So he still uses Java APIs.
But we can perhaps break down his solution just a bit, or at least what I called,
but you can expand it.
So first thing is like memory mapping.
Right.
That's something that I think it gets common when you go below these numbers.
And the idea there is that what you read a file and you map it into a memory.
Right.
And then you start walking around.
What was the idea there?
Can you tell us more about that?
So, I mean, what pretty much most people did at the top of the leaderboard was yes,
to memory map the file and it will be mapped into off heap memory,
which means that there is no garbage collection, you know, interfering with that.
You are just in control of managing that by yourself.
There's a new Java API, the foreign function and memory API, which people used,
which allows it amongst other things to map this entire 13 gig file into one memory segment.
So before you also could do memory map files with Java, but you were limited to two gigabytes
with the direct byte buffer in the past.
And nowadays you can, you know, map the entire thing all at once.
No garbage collection.
And yes, that's what people did.
From which version of Java do you get these things?
Uh, it's, I'm not sure when it got promoted to stable, but recently, maybe like 20 or 21,
it got promoted a lot of incubator into the stable one.
Uh, we also met the vector APIs here at this stage, right?
Right.
Can you tell us a bit more what that is?
So it's not to be confused with collections.
Oh yes, exactly.
And this actually was one of the things I was really hoping that people would use because
personally, I'm just super interested in it and people did use it.
Yes.
So the idea there is that your CPUs, they have extensions to the instruction sets,
which allow to apply the same operation to multiple operands at once.
So you can do the same thing for multiple values.
in parallel, and you know, if you apply the same operation,
like a comparison or whatever, to eight operands at once,
you know, this might be eight times faster in theory.
And this is called SIMD,
so single instruction, multiple data.
And so, you know, things like Intel CPUs,
they have AVX2 with AVX512 instruction set extensions,
which provide a wide range of those vectorized operations.
And the thing is, in Java, until recently,
you couldn't really use those extensions,
not directly as a Java developer.
So the Java compiler would auto-vectorize code
in specific situations.
If it, you know, you had like a loop,
and the compiler would detect specific patterns,
then it might be able to emit vectorized code,
which make use of those SIMD instructions.
But you, as a application developer, you couldn't use that.
And this is changing now with this vector API,
and it's still in incubating state,
I think like the eighth or ninth incubating release.
So it's, you know, baking for some time,
but you can use it already as a preview feature.
And the interesting thing there is,
you can now do those things.
You can say, okay, I want to, you know,
I want to look for a line-ending byte
in eight or 16 bytes at once.
And the nice thing about this is, this is a Java API,
so it's portable because with other languages,
let's say Rust or C, you also can use those instructions,
but you would go down essentially to assembly level,
and you would be specific to the architecture
you're running on, and your program wouldn't be portable.
Whereas with the Java API, it actually is portable
because the JVM takes care of, you know,
compiling this to Intel instructions
or Neon instructions on ARM.
And now I feel like we, as Java developers,
actually are at an advantage
because we can use vectorized APIs
and still we are portable across platforms.
Beautiful.
Would you say that that's like readable?
Oh yeah, I think it's-
Like for the level of-
Right, I mean, you need to get
a little bit of hang of it, right?
To understand, okay, I want to, you know,
work on multiple elements of an array at the same time.
Then there's also this thing like,
you always have like a remainder of your data.
So let's say for the sake of the example,
you work on an array, which is like 20 bytes long,
and you can process eight bytes
with vectorized instructions.
So you can do this twice, like first eight,
second eight, and then you have like four bytes left.
And then you typically have to do this
like in a scalar way, you know, for the remainder.
So there's, you know, things you need to understand
and make you like learn about.
But overall, I feel it's code,
which still is fairly readable, yes.
Awesome.
The other thing next to memory mapping vectorization
is usage of parallelism.
So parallelize as much as computation as possible.
Right.
That is also, plays a big role in this optimization.
At least that's my impression.
Yes, absolutely.
So you want to make use of all the CPU resources you have.
And so coming back to like readable
and, you know, maintainable solutions,
if you use the Java Streams API,
it could be as simple as adding a parallel method call,
like, you know, calling this method parallel.
And it would be parallelized to those eight cores
and gives you a nice speed up.
But what's happening there is, well,
so the computation would be happening in parallel,
but reading the file,
that would still be a sequential thing.
And this is where it goes back then to the memory map file.
So this is something which you need to parallelize yourselves
by using like threads and, you know,
making sure you process different chunks
of that memory segment with different threads
and people absolutely did this.
I think that, I think you mentioned this from your talk,
that your baseline, you can correct me on this,
your baseline was five minutes,
but with usage of parallel APIs,
you managed to get down to one minute with it or?
Yeah, so it gets, I forgot to say numbers,
but it gets like four times faster.
It doesn't get eight times faster
because the file reading is not parallelized that way.
But still it's a nice payout
for like a simple method call, right?
Yeah, it's amazing.
You basically added just like a dot parallel.
Exactly.
That was it.
And implicitly it is kind of a map reduce,
kind of like Wiggly and it's like an insane boost.
Yes, exactly.
If you compare maybe with other languages,
then it would be much more trickier.
Right, yeah.
So good value for the money, I have to say.
Before we jump more into like unsafe world.
Oh, yeah.
I do want to mention hacks.
And like one of the hacks that you,
I'm calling it hacks,
but, or clever approaches to solving this thing was like,
one was where you mentioned that you took names
and people consider to the collision, like keys, et cetera.
One thing that we, I think was also in Levert's solution
was that taking the names of cities
was not like very efficient.
Right.
So he got smart, for example,
and he just took like a first character of the name
and last character of the name.
And use that as a key.
Because for example,
he found that that's going to consume less memory.
It's going to be faster.
And it's still kind of like less collision.
So people find like these insane optimizations of some kind.
And then there's of course the risk
that you make assumptions about the specific key set, right?
So this might be fine for a specific key set,
but a solution was considered only valid
if it worked for all possible keys.
So doing something like that,
you would still have to do like the fallback
to comparing the full name.
You know, if there's equality in the short version.
Yeah, I see like, I'm not sure how like,
they're very, these are like extreme optimizations
to a degree.
So like changing the file format,
obviously all this stuff, you wouldn't benefit for it.
Changing the values too much.
Like all these things,
probably the solutions are not that generic.
It's like small cheating is like
not implementing the whole hash map inside of it,
but like doing.
Right, I mean, so many people did custom hash maps,
custom maps, I should say.
And so what happens there is essentially
you store the values in an array.
You take the hash code of the key
to find the index in the array.
And then of course you need to handle collisions.
So you need to, if you, you know,
you go to this array bucket or to this element
and there's a value there already,
you need to compare, you know, the name.
Is this the bucket I want to add to or not?
And if it's not,
you want to go to the next free slot in the array.
And this created a bit of a nightmare for myself
because you cannot test for that in an automated way.
You cannot prove the absence of hash collisions in a test
because people could use arbitrary hash functions,
arbitrary seed values.
So I always had to review for that.
And it was like, you know,
quite a bit of effort to understand.
So actually in the pull request template at some point,
I made a comment.
So if you have custom HashMap implementations,
point me to the place where you deal with collisions
so that I could understand about it.
I wonder if you would have like a team that would help you
and you could delegate it and then like,
like have a pre-review.
Right, yeah.
But I was thinking like, would that even help you
or it would just like taint your view on the code
if you know what I mean.
Because then it's tricky.
You may skip something else.
Right, yeah.
That's a good question.
I didn't think about it.
But I mean, actually people helped a lot already.
People built this test suite, which initially
I didn't have any tests.
I wasn't really thinking of that.
But people built this TCK, you know,
test compatibility kit, which you had to pass.
People did that.
They helped with the environment, as I mentioned.
They helped with just all the infrastructure
for evaluations.
And there was a guy, James Nockland,
who wrote like amazing shell scripts
for making sure the environment is configured correctly.
And then for, you know, running the benchmarks
and with like colored outputs.
So for me, it was just like a lesson.
How do you write excellent shell scripts?
This was a nice takeaway for me.
Before I ask you how to go below,
to get to the top or to below two seconds,
you, I think that this challenge,
I'm not sure if you published it on Hacker News
or it somehow got into Hacker News.
Right.
What did that thing do to this challenger?
Oh, yeah.
No, actually, it could have been that I put it there,
but somebody else also put it there.
But yes, at some point it was actually
on first place on Hacker News, which was great.
Beautiful, congratulations.
Thank you.
You know, first time that I had that.
And it definitely helped with, you know, popularity.
People, more people learned about it,
more people contribute.
And then of course you also have like
the typical Hacker News guy, right?
Commenting there.
And there was like the one comment,
actually, I had it in the keynote earlier this morning.
Yeah.
How hard, this is not a hard problem.
It's a trivial problem.
Like everybody who can program a little bit,
they can solve this in like half an hour.
And then, yeah, sure.
Like guys like Thomas Wurtinger and Alexey Shipilev
and Cliff Click and all the other big hitters,
they spent like an entire month
to optimize this, right?
And like going down to the instruction level.
And then you have like the Hacker News guy,
how hard can it be?
I do it like in 30 minutes.
It's always like that, but it's funny.
Again, you get, it gets the,
on the surface it looks easy,
for such a challenge it's really nice
because it appeals to people.
Right, you can explain it easily.
Easier to explain, rules are simple.
Data is there, results are,
you either have the results or you don't.
So it's like indisputable.
Yes.
Yeah, it's challenging.
I love it.
And I also think this will be,
you know, the biggest challenge next year
if you wanted to do it again,
to find another problem which is like that.
So you can explain it easily
and still it has lots of potential
because I think you could find things,
you know, which are also very tough
and which give you enough substance
to work on for an entire month.
But it would also take you half an hour
to explain it.
And that would make it, I think,
much less appealing, as you say.
Like, from the outside world,
like people ask, why would you do this stuff?
And I keep telling them, like,
that's completely wrong question.
That's, you should never ask that.
Right, because we can, right?
Not because you can, but equal,
like you wouldn't understand the answer
to that question even if I provided one.
To be honest, like, I think that this challenge
is one of super useful.
Like, it's pretty commonly that you get,
like, large files of text
that you need to do some transformation on them
and then maybe save them as a parquet file or whatever.
So I think that this one is really realistic,
especially now in these golden data science,
AI learning days.
And I think that this one is really the most applicable
I've seen so far, if you ask me.
Yeah, I mean, it has been in my mind for a while
to do something with a billion rows.
Yeah, and then at some point I thought, okay, let's do it.
And I think it's particularly interesting, of course,
if you work on tooling around it, right?
So if you were to create a database
or work on tools like Org, I guess,
then of course you would imply all those techniques.
Okay, question, how do you go below two seconds?
Yeah, I mean, perhaps like, if not a Java developer,
Java has this kind of like, I don't wanna say bad reputation,
but like people say, you know, it's not performant anymore.
It's not suitable because of the garbage collection
and you should just reuse Rust and things will be magical.
But like the leaderboard speaks for itself.
I mean, obviously the top implementation there
are crazy optimized people doing insane stuff.
But like these times are still acceptable,
reasonable for the given challenge.
So Java is still very, very much relevant in this space,
even in big data, all these things, it's there.
And this was also exactly one of the things
which I wanted to get out of this challenge,
to make this case and to help debunk this misconception.
And I think people definitely learned about it.
Okay, so my understanding of what it takes
to go under two seconds.
I'll try to summarize it, but you'll expand this.
Okay, so different distributions of JVM,
that kind of helps.
With GraalVM, we get this ability to do like,
do the more binary way of things,
compile stuff into binary, run that.
I think that is kind of like where a lot of these solutions
build upon that.
You wanna explain that perhaps?
Yes, I mean, a few thoughts on GraalVM.
So first of all, I mean, it also can be used
as a JIT compiler, just-in-time compiler, right?
As a replacement of the C2 compiler in your JVM.
And even doing that, actually for this particular workload,
gave a nice improvement of a few percent.
And this is, I think, also an interesting takeaway.
Just try GraalVM as your JVM,
not thinking about native compilation or whatever.
It might give you an improvement
in terms of throughput and latency,
essentially for free, right?
So that's one thing.
But then yes, of course, people like GraalVM
also because it does the ahead-of-time compilation.
And now I did not expect the times to go into
that low range where this would make a difference,
but actually people ended up going there, right?
And because now what happens is all the compilation happens,
well, it builds time,
so we don't have to just time compiler.
There's no interpreted phase.
The compiler doesn't need to warm up,
all this kind of stuff,
which means we have peak performance right early on,
and your process is to start up faster.
And now, well, if you look at those times,
like 1.5 seconds at the top of the leaderboard,
if you are faster to start up by 200 milliseconds,
that's a significant difference in that range, right?
And that's why, yes,
people at the very top of the leaderboard,
they decided to use GraalVM native binaries,
which for me made life actually a bit harder
because the compilation takes a little bit longer.
So whenever I ran those entries,
then I had to spend some more time
for building those binaries.
Well, even like in production setups,
if you do ahead-of-time compilation,
you're willing to sacrifice more time and build time
because you get speed up in the runtime, right?
Okay, that's one.
And then the unsafe world.
Right.
That's a big thing.
Right, there's unsafe.
Yes, exactly.
So essentially, it bypasses all those boundary checks
and it allows you to directly work on this memory data.
So it's again, a bit faster.
Also, of course, like, well, unsafe, literally.
So I remember Roy van Rijn,
one of the top contenders,
when he played around with unsafe,
he did it wrong.
I mean, you get stuff wrong, right?
It's just natural.
And then, well, in that case, the JVM just crashes.
And so he shared a screenshot of his 30 JVM crash logs.
So it's a bit more frustrating, I guess,
in terms of a developer experience to do that.
But yes, so that's one thing.
And what I also found interesting,
you can disable garbage collection altogether
if you implement it the right way.
Because if you don't allocate any objects
in your inner processing loop,
you don't need garbage collection,
which means you can spend those CPU cycles then
for working on your actual computations.
And again, it's just a bit faster.
So that's what some people did.
And I think that's also very applicable to other problems.
So let's say you were to use Java for,
let's say, a CLI tool, a very short-lived process.
Maybe you just can disable garbage collection altogether
and it will be a bit faster.
Well, one thing there is that my understanding was
that top solutions also don't use a lot of objects as well.
They try to use as little objects as possible
and try to optimize that as well, not much.
Yes, absolutely.
So they would work with the byte arrays directly
or maybe making a string object point
to a specific section of the memory segment.
Yes, all that to avoid allocating objects
as much as possible.
One thing that I also learned by talking to Levert
in his four-second solution,
that he spent a lot of time running the compilation
with some additional flags so that he actually sees
a lot of how the compilation happens,
how the inlining happens, all that.
That is also kind of like what helps you in a way.
I think it can make a difference at the very top.
So I remember Thomas Wurtiger here specified
lots of compiler flags and options
to get out the last few percents.
I suppose it's something which you do really at the end.
Once you have sorted out all the other stuff,
you have done all your profiling
and you avoid all the unnecessary allocations and whatnot,
then I guess you can get the last little bit
with those kinds of things.
Trying to see how a compiler actually gets stuff.
Yes.
And also it's getting then machine-specific, right?
So this also was very interesting.
So Roy, at some point,
so he was working on his ARM MacBook, like M1 MacBook,
and the evaluation machine was an Intel AMD EPYC server.
And now he got to a point where he did optimizations,
so it was faster on his local laptop,
but he submitted it,
then it was actually slower on the evaluation machine
because it had different lengths
of SIMD instruction sets and so on.
So he dug out an old Intel MacBook he had somewhere
to have better odds to come up with changes,
which also proved beneficial on the official environment.
As I'm listening to this,
did you thought that disabling a garbage collector
would be crazy for production code
before you had this challenge?
And now you think it's more understandable?
Did it change some views when it comes to...
Because after I'm listening,
what you are saying is like,
yeah, if it's a short-lived task
and you just have the objects,
they're not collected,
who does really care, right?
So I had heard about it before.
So I think it's actually common
in high-frequency trading and so on.
So what they do there is they try to avoid
or don't do any allocations
in the steady state of the application.
And then they keep it running for a day
and it doesn't need to do any garbage collection.
And then they, or maybe, you know,
it just does so low allocations.
And if they start a process with enough memory,
it is enough to keep running for an entire day.
They would kill it off after the day and like restart it.
So I had heard about it before.
I personally haven't done it before,
but yeah, I guess I would,
in particular for CLI tools, I guess I would...
Nothing crazy, right?
Consider it well enough.
Yeah, yeah, totally.
We're on that point in our episode
that I have to ask everybody to like and subscribe.
Oh yes, of course, like and subscribe.
Like and subscribe.
We appreciate that.
More followers we have,
the easier it is to make these things.
And I should also mention
that we are very grateful for our Patreons
that supports us and our partners
who are 3FS, Kaldi, and HumanFrog.
These are like web or tech related companies in Slovenia
and they support us and it means a lot.
So thank everybody for the support
and make it for also hosting us.
Okay, that's a PR part.
Right.
Super important to be sustainable.
Super important.
Do you wanna talk more perhaps about these two seconds
because otherwise I'm gonna move more
towards a few other things.
Right.
No, I think we got it covered mostly.
Oh, actually there's one thing which I will like.
This was my most favorite thing, I think.
So in Thomas Vertigo's implementation,
there's an interesting detail.
So you see essentially his inner processing loop.
He has it like duplicated.
It's like there in the source code, like three times.
So he has, you know, scanner objects
which process different lines of the file.
And he has the same loop with different scanners
like three times.
And so you look at his code and it's written there
and you would say it's like sequentially executed.
The thing is what happens, the compiler figures,
there's no data dependency between those different chunks.
And as CPUs have like multiple execution units,
it actually gets executed in parallel.
It runs concurrently.
So you look at the code sequentially,
but it actually gets executed concurrently.
So it saves time.
And how he arrived at three, so it was like heuristically.
So he tried it with two copies of the loop
with four copies of the loop.
Three was the fastest.
I had no idea about this.
I found it super interesting.
And of course, this also gets into this question
like how maintainable is this code, right?
Because imagine like the new guy comes onto the team.
He's like, oh, there's like the same code,
like three times.
Let me clean it up.
I want to like refactor it, make one loop
and boom, your optimization is away, right?
So I guess he would want to put a comment there.
Perhaps a few words about like the top guys.
My understanding is that the top solution,
it's not written by one guy.
I think three-
It's a team effort.
And these are guys that are actually working on GraalVM
with Oracle, Oracle Labs, is that correct?
Yeah.
Do you know the guys or?
Yes, I knew Thomas before we had met before.
They're scary a bit.
Say again?
They are scary guys.
Oh, I don't know.
I think they are nice guys.
And actually this was exactly also in the spirit
of the challenge to learn and inspire each other.
So at some point Thomas saw an interesting optimization
in the solution from Mary Kitty.
I forgot his actual name, but he goes as Mary Kitty online.
So he had a very nice trick.
And so Thomas incorporated that.
And then they said, okay, let's team up
and make it official, which then proved to be a problem
for my little certificates at the end,
because I gave like a PDF to everybody with their time.
So I learned how to do mail merge
and create individual PDFs for 160 people.
But they're listed on one page, okay.
Yes, exactly.
And the problem was, so they had like three names.
So for them, my template wouldn't fit.
And I had like to do it like a bespoke one just for them.
Do you think that like these,
the side effects of these challenge,
like we did some challenge two years ago, much smaller,
but, and the challenge that was,
I'm gonna post link below as well.
But that challenge was so intrigued to some people,
we didn't limit languages.
So one of the guys decided
to write his own programming language.
Oh, wow.
So yeah, Janko, if you're listening, cheers.
And, but the side effect was he learned
that he can make his language better
because of like trying to do,
trying to understand these challenges,
kind of like solid problems in his implementation.
And he proved like, do you think that something similar
might happen from this challenge or lessons like that?
Right.
So I don't think anybody invented
their own programming language,
but definitely people told me many times, yes,
that they learn so much about Java, learn new things.
And also it's definitely helped to debunk this misconception
like Java is slow.
So many people made that realization.
And also for other ecosystems, right?
So people may be not as familiar with Java as we are.
They also learned, oh, actually there is something going on.
It has like all those new APIs.
It's really optimized, really competitive.
So I think people took a lot from it.
Yes.
Is there any traction from academia?
I know that might sound silly, but we would help you like.
I have not seen any academic paper yet, maybe, yeah.
To come.
Yeah.
Did you also, um, you made the decision this is going to be a Java challenge and it's for
practical reasons, I guess, imagine, but if you go to 1BRC.dev, it's a webpage, I don't
think you created it.
I know, I did not.
It's very interesting.
Yeah.
And 1BRC also has a collection of links to other programming languages.
So you can see the solution in C, Python, all these different languages.
Did you have a peek into these solutions as well?
Yes.
Briefly.
So I mean, what we do have, so I mean, why was it Java only?
So yes, first of all, for practical reasons, I just felt like, you know, that's what I'm
most familiar with.
And if I need to learn how to install like Rust tool chains or how to compile with C
or whatever, it would just take, you know, so much more time.
And I wanted to limit it a little bit.
So that was the one reason.
The other reason is, well, I wanted to help and promote Java also.
And that's why I limited to Java.
But then we actually, so all this happens in a GitHub repo, like, you know, my name
Gunnar Molling and then 1BRC, that's the repo.
And we have a GitHub discussion there, which is called show and tell.
And people are very much invited to share their links to their non-Java implementations.
This also got really huge.
So there's like, I don't know, 60, 70 threads of discussions there with other implementations
like Rust and .NET and C and even COBOL and, you know, all kinds of languages.
Some of them I hadn't heard about even before.
Then other tools like Org, you know, on the command line, but then also databases, Postgres,
Apache Pino, Snowflake.
So people, you know, did it with all kinds of tools and languages.
So I kept an eye on it.
I enjoyed reading the blog posts, but I couldn't run them on my environment just to, because
of the time reasons.
I guess we were more like at the end of these kind of things.
We will go swimming later on.
Oh, okay.
I guess before we talk more about price.
So I guess the price was, there was a price.
At least that's my understanding of Twitter threads or whatever.
The most important thing in life.
Yes.
So obviously the price is, you're the top dog in the industry, I guess.
Right.
So the price is learning something new and being part of it.
But yes.
So initially, I mean, so this was like really, you know, my own private effort initially
at least.
And so I said, okay, I will pay for a t-shirt for the winner.
I will pay for a t-shirt out of my own pocket.
That's what I decided to do.
And then, well, it really took off and I felt, okay, maybe we want to do something more.
And then I spoke to my employer Decodable and they were happy not only to fund the evaluation
machine, but also I have a company credit card, so I just can pay for some prices.
So what I did in the end is I did t-shirts for the top three and coffee mugs for the
top 20.
And then I sent to like South Korea, Taiwan, Croatia, actually I was in Zagreb and U.S.
and so like Brazil, like all over the world.
So this was my biggest challenge, like shipping this stuff to people all over the world.
Beautiful.
So at this point, thanks for Decodable for actually supporting you on this.
I guess if people have ideas for next year, they should contact you on Twitter.
Right.
Yes.
Send me an email to Gunnar at decodable.co.
People asked what would be the challenge next year?
There was one guy who said next year, next January, I will take a week off.
So I have the entire time to focus on my implementation.
Let's see whether we actually want to do it.
So I'm still recovering from this year, but I think, yeah, by next January, if there's
a good idea, as we mentioned, you know, it needs to have the right balance between like
easy to explain and providing lots of potential.
If you have that, if a community comes together, if it's automated, because frankly speaking,
I don't want to run all this stuff manually again on this machine, so it would have to
be automated with GitHub Actions, I suppose, like people could like really self-certify,
you know, and it would be like a GitHub Actions runner on that machine.
If we have all that and people help doing that, I would definitely be up for doing it
again.
You have any more questions, András?
Otherwise, I'm going to slowly...
No, I think that was an awesome conversation.
Very, very nice.
I would like to like perhaps wrap up with like last kind of a big question or what are
the lessons that are not technical that you got out of this?
Right.
First of all, yeah, never underestimate how much people would do to win this kind of thing.
So this definitely, you know, I did not expect this, like people would spend an entire month
on doing that.
Then, yes, people will take advantage of whatever they can, so they will optimize for the key
set.
They will, you know, bend all the rules.
There was stuff which we didn't even talk about, like unmapping the file.
So they will do all kinds of stuff.
So I did, you know, did not expect that, but still, you know, it's all good and fun.
And then of course, yes, I mean, I guess I was hoping to see it, but it also definitely
happened like how the community comes together, not only to participate and take something
out of it, but also to help and organize it and help and run it.
And this was just so great to see, because at some point I was just overwhelmed.
And I felt, oh man, it's so much, I spent like 12 hours a day trying to be on top of
stuff and people helped and, you know, this only made it possible.
And I guess the last thing is, yeah, I mean, it was a bit of a viral thing, right?
It really blew up.
And what I also found very interesting, so like how you lose control over the narrative
and how, what happens, right?
Because people will take it and make something out of it like they want.
And you know, at some point there was like a bit of a fight between like Java and other
languages and I didn't really want it to be like that.
But at some point, yeah, you're not like fully in control.
You're just like participating in that.
It feels like a modern, big open source community kind of a thing where a lot of problems kind
of here.
Right.
And it can be a bit scary, right?
It can be a bit scary.
Because it just, stuff happens and you try to navigate it as good as you can.
So this also was definitely very interesting to observe.
Okay.
I guess any last words from you Andras?
I would invite our community to join us on Discord and share the attempts or the solutions
that would be awesome.
Like to see what we can come up with.
Yeah.
Yeah, definitely.
From my side, I invite you to follow Gunnar on Twitter.
It's a stream of very useful information also from Flink and DCDN.
So yeah, you should follow him.
And thank you from bottom of my heart for taking the time and taking us through this
challenge.
We're really looking forward to what you'll come up next year.
Okay.
Awesome.
Yeah.
Thank you so much for having me.
This was great.
I really enjoyed the conversation and this was really fun.
Thank you.
Bye.
That's it.
Have a nice day.