Hey everyone, hey all the ladies and gentlemen that listen to us.
Today we are recording at Deobsday Ljubljana 2024.
This conference is kindly hosted by Ivan and Marko from Povio Labs.
Thanks for everyone organizing these conferences.
I think that the guests and Otto, we know how hard it is.
So yeah, we are amazed at the local community that we can have so many good conferences
in such a small tech community.
Yeah, we have a big heart, but the numbers are not that huge.
I would also like to thank all our Patreons, all our supporters, 3FS, HumanFrog and Kaldi.
That means a bunch to us, this is still kind of our hobby and you know how it is with money
and hobbies.
It's not very profitable or shouldn't be, right?
At least that I tell my wife.
Yeah, okay.
No, no, we will get rich, Otto's wife.
So today, me and Otto, we are welcoming Taylor Dolezal.
I hope that's okay.
Yeah, perfect.
Amazing.
He's head of ecosystem at Cloud Native Computing Foundation.
I will use Cloud Native Foundation.
So yeah, welcome to Ugrodje, the framework podcast.
Thanks for having me.
This is going to be fun.
Yeah.
Welcome again.
I mean, first time in Slovenia, probably jet lagged.
You're pending to have a talk in a couple of hours, if I understand correctly.
We have a lot of questions about this foundation that is essentially responsible in quotes
for most of the infrastructure that we run in production around the world and in our
offices and in our home labs as well.
So yeah, let's get started.
But like before we can actually tell to our audience what this foundation stands for,
we need to establish your character.
So I think Andras has like a very first question about like an icebreaker on how, just to see
who you are really.
It's a classical ops one.
What's the most significant production F up that you had in your past, in your career?
That's a good one.
I'd say some of my favorites have to deal with Kubernetes and working with that.
Probably I used to work at Walt Disney Studios.
And so I was working with the groups in the theatrical distribution group and we were
one of the first to get Kubernetes spun up.
We already had applications that were containerized and working with that.
But I remember it was before we had these really awesome GitOps tools like Argo and
Flux.
And so you were just applying manifests directly.
And so I remember naming, caching, right, those are the hardest things for all of us.
And that and DNS.
But there was a time where I had some, I liked scoping everything with namespaces so that
I can name everything the same.
But when you don't check your context before you go and apply those things, then that can
cause a kerfuffle.
And so I remember I applied a whole bunch of things to what I thought was the staging
namespace for all of these, like millions of orders were just about to come in for Disney.
And yeah, that's some of the microservices there.
I pushed them up.
They weren't able to resolve because they're looking for the production FQDN net URI.
And so I had that, thankfully I was sitting close enough to the development team.
They came over and they said, hey, is prod down?
And I went, no.
Hold on.
I went and changed it back.
So only impacted about three minutes, but I think that was the biggest one.
Some of the bigger ones at Disney working like with the wider teams was some DNS issues
because we linked everything off studio.disney.com.
And so when anything further down the chain there were to break, we would have lots of
FFs, as you would say.
Yeah.
Yes, as usual, right?
Well, before you go more into like your role now, you came from DevOps, system ops background.
Is that correct?
Right.
Like how do you come from being more operations engineering kind of role into kind of like
leading the vision of ecosystem and managing the stakeholders?
Can you tell us a bit more in that regard?
Yeah.
I'd say a whole bunch of good decisions and a whole bunch of mistakes is what led me here.
I started off working with, I wanted to be a software engineer.
And so I remember vividly back to one of my math classes, I had a TI 83 plus calculator
and someone was showing me, there were like ones you could borrow from the classroom at
that time.
And I remember somebody showed me the snake game or nibbles as it was called.
And so you'd see the snake go, try to eat the food and you grow, not try to like crash
into yourself.
They went, oh, hold on, check this out.
And they changed a little asterisk to like a zero or an O or an M. And I was like, what?
That was it.
I knew what I wanted to do for the rest of my life.
And so I started programming with that, working my way through there.
I got started with like VB6 and .NET and about 16, I wanted to get into game design and stuff
like that.
I learned very quickly that licenses cost a lot of money and I didn't have that at 16.
And so that's where I got into open source PHP and then Ruby, Go, and then kind of found
my way, made my way closer and closer to infrastructure stuff when I started up my own consultancy.
And I had a client say, okay, Taylor, this code's great.
How do we get it live?
And I went, oh, I didn't think about that.
And then that was my trek into systems, systems design and distributed stuff and everything
else.
But yeah, really fun.
It was kind of scary to learn that everything is basically a while true loop, but you know,
it's fun.
It's fun.
Yeah.
So if we move, if we go forward, like when we research our guests, right, then there
is, you're ahead of ecosystem and we are watching the Cloud Native Foundation landscape.
I use it all the time.
It's an awesome kind of JavaScript app, whatever, right?
But yeah, I guess that what does head of ecosystem, what's your role?
It's right.
It's not a common corporate role.
No, it's, it's something I try to figure out every day, honestly.
Like a startup.
Exactly.
We're about, we're just about 10 years old as a foundation, but there's just so much
going on all the time.
We went from one project Kubernetes, we now have over, I think it's over 200, 203 if I
counted right last time.
I didn't count it individually on the landscape, but we just rebooted that app too.
One Easter egg for people, if you don't want to type in the landscape.cncfio, I can save
you a little bit of time.
Okay.
Just type in L.CNCFIO, then it'll load it up, but we added a stats page that rewrote
it in Rust.
And so that was kind of like a cool thing that got done recently.
As head of ecosystem, it's my, it's my responsibility to work really closely with our end user
community and what's, you know, what's end user.
That's also very generic.
Those are people that are taking and really adopting these cloud native projects within
their organizations.
And that's more of an Apple, an Intuit, a Mercedes Benz.
It's groups that aren't selling cloud native services.
They're not cloud service providers or consultancies, and they're building their entire business
on these platforms.
And their core competency might not be technology too, right?
We want to save a lot of those organizations time and money with adapting and adopting
a lot of these workflows with cloud native.
Because again, they have other things to do, selling cars, you know, B2C software, all
of these other things.
So I do a whole bunch of research.
I work with people on programs like our Zero to Merge program, where we show people how
to contribute to open source and be marketable.
Do keynotes and get to talk to people.
I get to travel like this and interact with the community.
And then really just work, one other thing that we did was spin up an end user technical
advisory board.
And that's made up of about 13 individuals, some appointed, some voted in by the community.
And that gives a much better anchoring point for our community to be able to talk with
people.
Because we used to say, hey, you know, we care about vendors and end users, and it was
just kind of hand wavy.
We could connect you with end users, but there wasn't that interface, so to speak, for that.
And so now we have that.
And then a whole bunch of things lined up for KubeCon, which will be exciting.
Can you like, there is like, can you tell us a bit about this dashboard, just for people
who don't know.
There is like a chart.
Just explain to us, please.
What is it?
So, if you try to take it in all at once, you will get a headache.
I can vouch for that.
I've made jokes about that.
There's lots of memes and stuff like that, too.
It's a, my recommendation is when you take a look at the landscape, you'll see a whole
bunch of projects.
And it's within differing categories.
There's like app definition and delivery.
There's observability.
And then if you take a closer look, you can see subcategories in there, too.
So, if you're looking specifically for like databases, you'll find that subcategory in
there.
And the goal, I recommend to no one that you go and adopt all of those projects and try
to plug them in all over the place.
That's absolutely where some confusion came in earlier on, because, you know, with like
10 projects, sure, there's enough of a problem space that it might make sense to adapt all
those.
But now it's-
You don't need everything in the big picture.
Okay.
Exactly.
And for those that like to play with Legos, it's kind of like, okay, this one, here's
the shape of the piece.
And it just comes in a whole bunch of different colors or ways in which it actually fits into
what you're trying to build, I think is a good way to think about it.
Again, yeah, never, if someone wanted to adapt all those, that'd be a work of art rather
than something usable, I would say.
But do you still collaborate?
You told us that you collaborate with end users more or less, okay.
But do you also collaborate with developers of these platforms, with engineers?
Like do you bring the knowledge that you obtained from the end users to them or how does that
work?
Definitely.
Do you help shape the roadmaps or what's your role in that then?
With that, it's really about educating the end users on things like project health.
You know, it's end users that are taking these projects and adapting them.
You want to know that they're going to be around tomorrow.
And the fact that they're already in the foundation is a pretty good indicator, but even within
our projects, we have sandbox, incubating, and then graduated projects.
You can expect graduated to be very rock solid.
It's proven itself.
And our technical oversight committee, another governing body, has basically said, okay,
it's gone from sandbox to incubating to graduated, all right, great.
Sandbox is more the experimental and exploratory projects that we have and that we have the
most of those.
With any good software lifecycle thing, you'll see a lot of those either get archived out
or people stop working on them, et cetera.
Incubating is going to be a little bit more solid and then graduated is going to be most
of all.
With the TAB structure that we've established too, we have some technical advisory board.
And not spaces, the TABs.
They have a couple initiatives that they're working on right now.
One of them is project health, and then another one of them is linking end users to projects.
Basically feedback and getting that in.
So just like you said, I'll talk with a lot of folks, but it really is introducing them
to the projects rather than me stepping in and saying like, hey, project, you got to
do this.
We're a vendor neutral foundation, and so we're not looking to pick the winner or be
king makers.
We're looking to just help out where we can.
Security audits, patent litigation with open source, all of those kinds of things.
When you say you want to help with these things, does that mean that you try to recruit open
source contributors or do you actually pay for engineers to work on these problems?
Is all this stuff voluntarily or do the vendors have the ability to pay for these things?
There is probably some money involved.
Tell us a bit more about the economic or business, I'm sure the business model is the right question.
I think for that, it's good to zoom out because we'll get that a lot of the time is like,
hey, this foundation, you should pay the maintainers, you should pay people.
We don't disagree at all.
But when it comes to setting up, it's kind of like a community garden is what we try
to establish.
We don't go and buy the produce that people have worked hard to make, but we try to set
up the plot, give you fertilizer, the tools, and then help out with marketing and other
things like at the farmer's market for this analogy.
Otherwise, you get into a whole bunch of things where we're maintaining and sustaining
a project that only that one person's using.
You can kind of get into those things and extrapolate.
But again, we really want maintainers to be paid, so we'll help out with connecting them.
Someone will come in, they'll get trained, they'll start making contributions, they might
become a maintainer.
It's a lot easier to get hired and go to places, typically vendors, but some end users as well.
They're always looking for that because that's a very solid person.
You can look and go see the resume all you get right there.
And so we try to help out projects specifically when they need security audits or have to
go through litigation or have a new need that's popped up that we can help out with.
When you take a look at the foundation and how it makes money and kind of like where
that goes to, it's really three things.
It's memberships, which is companies joining and then you get benefits like KubeCon tickets
and training and certification, things like that.
Training and certification is yet another stream of revenue that we take.
And then we're more so focused on the certification piece.
There's a whole bunch of great training, education, things like that.
Some people are putting that up for free.
Other people have books.
We want to allow the space for that because everybody learns different.
And then events like KubeCon, CloudNativeCon and other co-located events or one-offs that
we'll have too.
So those are the three ways that we make money.
That goes to pay the staff, that goes to help out with the administrative and logistical
things for projects like Zoom accounts and hiring people as project managers.
They'll come in and can help out with some of these services that projects have.
Artwork that gets created, a whole bunch of other things like that.
It's kind of like what the makeup looks like.
When I was researching, Cloud Native Foundation is a foundation that was founded by Linux
Foundation, right?
That's the relationship between these two organizations, right?
Correct.
Okay.
And then there is also Apache Foundation.
And I was trying to do a research like, what's the relationship between Linux Foundation
and Apache Foundation?
And then there's like a really nice...
Somebody wrote like a really nice answer on the Quora, I believe so.
And he explained like these two organizations, they don't really compete between each other
if something, they complement each other, but they're like one of two of the biggest
probably in the space, right?
So this is like Linux Foundation is on top of this.
That's how I understand.
Okay.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
There's the Linux Foundation and then we're a sub-foundation under them.
So similar to like OpenSSF Foundation and several other, like PyTorch is under Linux
Foundation, LF and AI.
You can tell what's been on my brain recently, but keep hearing about it.
That's how that's set up.
And then that gives us a really good structure and keep it lean and small too.
I'd say the biggest difference with the Linux Foundation and the Apache Foundation is, again,
kind of looking at like operating revenue.
You see Apache is like really lean, but then you have a lot more people donating their
time and then not as many services provided.
We're big fans of the Apache 2 license, you know?
Yeah, it's in the similar space, but different, yeah.
Exactly like you said, we can help complement one another and then we'll regularly talk
with them and people like OSI and just a whole bunch of other initiatives that are going
on.
I think that we're all about trying to share out that information with people and then
just eliminate duplication of work where it doesn't make sense, right?
At the end of the day, that's truly what we're trying to aim for.
So we were mentioning a lot about the end users and those are basically from our perspective
because we are in an emerging market, right?
Those are huge corporations, right?
We don't have such corporations here.
So I would think that maybe, of course, we are not in SF area, but for us, those are
maybe 20% of companies looking at them globally and the other 80s are not the members, right?
And my question is, okay, how do then the other 80% shape the technology that we basically
use, right?
Because of course we are on this free when, right?
We are riding along whatever Cloud Native Foundation or the big guys do.
Sometimes it's relatively complicated.
Sometimes we are super grateful for all the technologies.
Is there a way or how can maybe we do some input or how does that come in?
I think when you take a look at the foundation and projects, it's again, if you had a whole
bunch of cloud service providers all working on distributed storage or something like that,
they might have eight different ways in which you interact with that.
And then that becomes very difficult as an end user to be like, okay, we want to move
from cloud service provider one to two.
They do it a completely different way.
We have to rewrite everything.
So that's where standards and the foundation comes in.
So vendors have really realized this, that they can plan a lot better across their teams
as well when they have a shared specification that they can use.
Like OCI, the open container interface, there's storage interface, the network interface now.
And so they've learned the benefits of working on that and then sending people to kind of
interact with the community, work on those specifications and have those conversations.
Vendors really do want to sell to end users too.
So that's like how many end users are members within the CNCF?
That's a good measure as far as what's the health, are they staying, are they going?
And this year it's been, with a lot of people moving their budgets around for like AI and
trying to understand the shape of that, we've seen the lowest churn for end user members
thus far.
So I've been really happy.
I've had a lot of conversations with many of them and they're like, I'm glad that they're
staying and really investing back into the ecosystem.
But that's the biggest thing that they'll share back with is just trying to save time,
trying to make sense of things.
One of the things that the end user technical advisory board is working on as well, we have
a site up right now, but it's going to be, there's going to be examples in it just before
KubeCon called architecture.cncfio.
And that's when I was an end user working at Disney, that's the thing I wish I had was
give me some reference architectures, just show me some workflows and patterns.
The tool's not enough, right?
I know I have a hammer.
What can I do with it?
Is this for eating soup?
I can use it wrong.
Yeah.
It might hit my thumb.
What do I do with this?
And that's what a lot of end users are asking.
Like they might've heard about, by now, hopefully heard about Kubernetes and know when is and
is not the right time to use those things.
That's the frame of knowledge that we're sharing right now is trying to show what workflows
are possible and then how people are combining these things together.
It's not enough just to show the one project.
They're really curious about how you string these things together, how you utilize those
interfaces.
And then that creates a really good communication dynamic between vendors and users or vendors
to vendors and users to end users.
So for example, like you have Kubernetes and then you want to have cloud ops and then you
maybe adopt Argo or Flux and observability and container storage.
So you're targeting to have like white papers or like blog posts, something like that.
We're starting to do more.
We're learning from a lot of like the big media companies, right?
Where you could take a look at this project, see related content.
So if you go and check out like the CNCF blog, you'll see more, we've been doing more experimentation
with that.
It's leading to a lot of people being like, oh, okay, now I understand where all these
things are.
The way that the reference architectures will be set up is basically it'll kind of look
like a case study.
You'll have a whole bunch of links to the differing CNCF projects and then charts like
a mermaid JS graph to be able to see how these things link together.
And then we're hoping that that leads to more case studies and end user journey reports
and like actual assets that give you a better picture for what's going on.
I think it's kind of related to the question, like sometimes in these environments, like
you feel that you have a bubble and then your bubble, there's like Kubernetes and Flux,
for example, might be the way to go.
And you think that's the shit.
And you talk to a couple of buddies and they say the same thing, but like in your position,
you probably don't have, you should not have these bubbles or you should be aware of them.
How do you like have a better understanding what is like, where the thing is going?
Because you cannot prioritize everything.
You cannot do everything equally.
How do you navigate these things?
Even for you personally, how do you?
So I've been at the CNCF for about two and a half, going on three years.
I've been in the community since like the days of Docker and Kubernetes was coming up.
I remember learning about Kubernetes at a meetup, I think somebody hosted a WordPress
site in their demo and then they took out the persistent volume and then it came back
and I was like, whoa, this is wild.
But I think that by getting to talk with just a whole bunch of people and see the landscape
of what people are talking about are like, oh, this group is in finance.
This is typically a pattern that they'll use.
If you go and take a look at manufacturing, they might love it and they might implement
something completely different.
So you start to learn the more time you spend talking with people, what the shape of their
workflows look like.
Media, Disney is going to act a lot differently than say like Intuit or Mercedes-Benz.
So you kind of learn where the echo chambers are just over time and talking with people.
So you get to pop a lot of those bubbles, but that happens a lot of the time.
And then end users specifically, they'll hear about the latest and greatest things
within technology or patterns and whatnot.
And there's either not the time justification or the ability to go learn the thing.
But with like these reference architectures, it gives people something to copy and to try.
And so that's the thing that we haven't had for a long time, or it's just been word of
mouth or in a case study.
And then you kind of have to go and dig and talk to the people implementing that.
So it's becoming easier to drive that change once we better understand the problem rather
than just have like the ingredients or list of the tools that we're going to use.
Um, but yeah, it's really interesting within the community hearing kind of what's repeated,
what becomes the echo chamber versus what people are actually doing.
Um, we, we mentioned into it a few times. We, so here we know what Mercedes Benz does,
the right cars, and then Disney is like media. What, what's into it? What's their core business?
Uh, their core business is they, they have a whole bunch of things like, uh, male chimp
and turbo tax and some things that, yeah, in the States I'm grateful for.
So turbo tax is like how you submit taxes, right? Okay. Okay. Yeah. Yeah. It's like a wizard. You
go through, you know, I, I, I, Hey, I, I'm envious of everyone here in Europe.
So super important. Yeah. I would like to continue this, uh, from this bubble of the
last before, um, as you said, you have three stages of, in which the projects are, um,
do you like you personally, do you have time to explore these tools on your own? Uh, and like,
how do you play with these things? Do you just like, uh, make them demo apps? I imagine you do
because you will have talking hours, like, but how do you explore these things? And how do you
find these new incubating projects, I guess, for you personally, or in the wider organization,
how do you find these challenging or interesting things? There's a, there's another thing that we
added that's helping me learn a lot of these things, especially like within the new sandbox
projects that are coming in. Um, we just like went through the summer, the TOC went through the
summer schedule and a lot just got accepted. Um, and so when we do like our all hands and things
like that, we've done the funny, like Pokemon, like shadow. And it's like, what project is that?
You know, what does it do? And so those are areas where we learn. I think that there's,
it's great to involve play with learning too. Um, there's a little game controller at the top,
at the upper right-hand corner of the CNCF landscape. And you can click on that and it'll
ask you questions about projects. So I like note cards and that way of learning. So I love that
the projects team decided to add that as a good way to like introspect and look at that. Um, I
learned mostly by demos and then it's being what I've, I've been in this industry, I want to say
like 17 years, maybe 20. I've just stopped counting. Um, that's for, that's a job for
program to do. Yeah. Plus, plus that's how many years I've been here. But, um, you, you start to
learn and see that it's a lot of repetition of the same patterns, right? If you learn the
fundamentals, you're going to be set for a very long time. And not many people do, they might
know how to work with a certain framework or library or orchestrator. And, um, that's, that's
also great. But if you really have a sense of the fundamentals, you're again, just going to go
really far. And I keep seeing repeated patterns or some projects I'll look at and be like,
really? And, you know, and I'll, I'll, I'll question what the use case is. That's what
really urges me to go check it out is like, huh, I had a really strong feeling about this. What is,
let me go check this out. Do we need to restart pods and do this? Does this thing make sense?
How do we actually do policy and introspection? Um, it's fun.
If Andras now has a new, um, Kubernetes related project, let's just put it like that.
Yeah. Of course. I write a operator in Go. Like for ordering pizza.
Yeah. Pizza operator written in Go.
It has a, it has a really good read me and it has, let's say 200 stars on GitHub.
The custom resource definition, there is a hard limit. It must not have pineapple in it.
Yeah. So, so let's say, let's, let's say that we have an operator and let's say that there is a,
let's say, like I said, a hundred stars and people are actually using it. So how would
like his project get into the cloud native foundation and how would the roadmap look
like? Can you give us like an example on top of it? Yeah. Yeah, absolutely. I think in this
hypothetical too, it's imperative that businesses have pizza parties. And so this is a business
critical. Exactly. It's critical for Disney to Intel to have pizza because no pizza, no team.
Yeah. And I'll, I'll, I know I'll be filing issues too with like stuff cross not, you know,
like what kind of cuts it's going to be good. It's so to get this started, what you'd want to do is
take a look at, there's a CNCF sandbox repository. And in that is an issue that you can create and
kind of like list out what's going on with your project and features and just kind of give the
overall description. And then there's a schedule in which the technical oversight committee will
review differing projects that are coming in. We've had not to pick on anyone. I honestly can't
remember the names, but we've had people submit, you know, vaporware or an idea. And that's not
necessarily what the technical oversight committee or TOC is looking for. They're looking for
projects that have a compliant license, you know, OSI approved license. It has a community,
you have maintainers, and there's some other due diligence things which are published in that
sandbox repository. So you can take a look and see if it actually matches up. And then once you get
in, then you start to get some benefits available to you. Like if you wanted to schedule community
meetings and have us do that with some of the tooling we built and so that you can get reporting
on that, all of those things start to open up as well. And then when you want to go to, let's say
it's really successful, you know, everybody loves the pizza operator and you want to go to incubating,
then you would signal to the technical oversight committee, like, Hey, I think we're ready.
More due diligence. And then the same thing with graduated and all those things are published.
There's a lot of due diligence work that the technical oversight committee does that I had
no idea about until I joined the foundation and got to like read through all of the read-me's and
things that they take a look at. So if Andraž then also needs like a test Kubernetes cluster,
is this something that you guys can help with or not?
There's, I know that there's Equinix is an organization that's partnered with the CNCF
and there is a cluster that's available for testing on some things there.
There's also like GitHub runners. We've had several cloud service providers donate credits or
allow for us to set up a runner on their cloud to be able to scale with different projects.
Same thing with ARM. And so again, if we need like, no, this will only run on pizza cloud,
then we can try to figure out what that looks like, if that's something that we can work with
them on. But that's another benefit that the foundation has, is being able to go and talk
to these organizations or service providers to get those credits.
There's also like this social element, right? We know that of course Intel is contributing to the
pizza operator and then yeah, maybe you can establish some additional channels just to
open a conversation because they're obviously, yeah, using the, yeah, stuffed crust patch.
And in this like...
Pizza and chips.
Let's say that not everybody is a fan of pizza and let's say that somebody now
finds an exploit in this pizza operator, as we call it now.
Some Hawaiian guys.
Yeah. So, and let's say that Andras is not aware of this stuff and let's say that
somebody somewhere would find an exploitation. How would then this information get to Andras?
Would you guys help to try to patch it, try to talk to him, try to prioritize or like,
how does this work? Do you guys help in this case or not?
There's a couple of good recipes that we have for this. And when projects join,
there's a whole bunch of things that we make sure that they have. And that's like a security
distribution list. We'll tie that into GitHub if it makes sense. We try to set up projects so that
they have the most success possible. And so with something like that, whether if that came out as
like a fuzzing or security audit that we did, we would let the, we wouldn't go say,
hey, world, check it out. Oh yeah. And maintainers too. Yeah. We won't,
we don't give that the same time. We'll give that to the project maintainers directly so they can go
and triage, take a look at things and then kind of get a sense for ETAs. And then we'll go and
publish that after we found everything, of course. But I think that's my favorite thing about the
foundation too is like, if it's a survey, a security audit, anything like that, you'll get
to see all of those things that you can learn from them too. But patching this specifically,
typically, like we don't have anything that's proactive besides the community taking a look at
this or the security audits, but when people raise it, it will get to someone. And I think
that's the thing that, that's what really helps out with these projects rather than like, hey,
we just found something in the struts library or something like that, that we've seen in the
industry. And then it's like, okay, we don't know when a fix is coming, but we'll work really
closely with folks to be able to get ETAs. And then we have so many members that are vendors,
they all want to see this succeed too. So they'll, they might step up and say, okay, we have a couple
core maintainers, or they might have people to lead into the project. So they're there for the
long-term too.
Let us have a short off-topic break. And thanks again, our sponsors from Caldi, 3FS and Human
Frog and all the Patreons. I have a thing to admit, right? Like I'm a huge fan of craft beers,
and we have a few pubs here in Ljubljana, and there's an app that I have on my phone. And
whenever they connect a new keg or barrel of beer, I get not really a notification,
but it's popped up, it pops up, it says, hey, there's a new beer. And I know if I have tried
already or not, because I checked them in the app, right? It's like connecting Pokemons, but
it's just like drinking pints of beer. And I wonder if there's a lot-
I wonder where you're going with this. Please continue.
You were talking about bubbles earlier.
Yeah, sure. Go, go.
Like there's a lot of projects joining in like from different like sandbox or like incubator
and the landscape, especially the recent years with Kubernetes is changing relatively rapidly,
right? Because a lot of new awesome things are going on. And I wonder what's the easiest way
for me to subscribe to an Ares fit and just like see what got promoted to which stage, right?
Because sometimes I go through the landscape and I'm like, oh, that's amazing. Yeah, that's- well,
I will not implement it, right? But I know that it's there. And then when a problem pops up at a
customer that feeds that project, then yeah, of course you do additional diligence, but
it really helps to be- I think it's more productive to know what is there than reading like
hacker news every morning, right? So I wonder if it's there like a list or
how is that communicated, how the project gets promoted?
That's a question I did. I want to see this too. I found a couple of things. The CNCF- I actually
worked with the CNCF website developer. It used to be truncated RSS so that you'd read it in your
RSS reader as many of us do. And it was only the first like hundred words. And I was like,
no, I get that you want people to click a link and go through, but I also just want to be able
to read my RSS reader and get the sense for what's going on. So that's been expanded. That's
a decent way to keep track of a lot of things, but it's just a lot, right? So there have been
talks of tags and some other ways in which to fix that taxonomy, but that's a known problem
within our ecosystem is so much news. How do you keep track of it? In the new landscape, there's a
metrics tab, I think, or stats. And if you click on that, then you can see which projects have moved
within the year, how many have been accepted, and you can see some graphs that'll tie to that.
I don't think that lets you click and then introspect what those projects are necessarily
though. But that's something that, yeah, that's on my personal wishlist too, is to be able to take
a look at that or who donated this project. I love history because it's a collection of just
what choices were made at certain times with certain effects. And that's kind of what you do
with an SRE. That's what I'm doing within the ecosystem. So by being able to go back and look
at that full history, that's really helpful. We don't have that tool yet, but something that isn't
out of mind. We have a couple of things that we're going to work on probably 2025 and take a look,
a deeper look into something like that. So I would say stay tuned. Check your RSS feed for
what exists today. Is there an API for the project listed there that will be open?
There is. What's really funny, well, funny and interesting is that the landscape database is just
a giant YAML file. So does it have an API? Yeah, kind of. There is an endpoint. I'm not sure if
it's documented for the CNCF website, but there is a way to be able to list out projects, things
like that. I'd say dev stats is probably another good way. That definitely has an API. I've used
that. You could see people's contributions, company contributions, and then the list of things
and projects that are there. So that's probably what's best as far as what's available today.
Big organizations will utilize that API too and pulling metrics as well as doing the same thing,
checking to see where a project's at, et cetera. Challenge accepted. I will find the YAML.
I'm not exactly sure how should I make a parallel out of your beer analogy now,
but I have this question. Let's say you have very good oversight in what's in the ecosystem
and that there are 200 and more projects in there, but are there gaps in the ecosystem?
Are there holes where you think somebody should make a project in this space?
Did you so far identify these gaps or are you somehow insinuating to the people that they
should probably do something in there? It's a big opportunity, or do you have that insight as
well? Can you give us some pointers on that? Yeah, there's no gaps. It's perfect.
It's perfect. Yeah, that's why there's 200 projects. Yeah, of course.
That's why we accept more and more projects every single year.
I'd say some of the, personally, what I've seen, I've loved seeing projects like for the tests
where you can spin up MySQL in this incredible clustered way. Personally, I'm seeing amazing
things with Postgres running in the browser with Wasm. Super cool.
That's Otto's favorite tool. It's so cool.
Having a Postgres compiled, running in browser, and then you have the chat GPT or whatever
the fuck it is. Yeah. And you just write a query and then it generates the whole
tables for you, relationships, graph is there. And you just start querying and it says,
I don't have data, but I can make data for you. And you say, yes, make data. And then you have,
it's like, future is now, right? Yeah, exactly.
I'm not sure that's cloud native. I'm too old for this.
Everything is in browser. Sorry, I thought you touched on that.
Exactly. No, that's insane. Those are the kinds of projects I want to see. I've gotten to work
with big teams, small teams. I think at Disney was the most enlightening for me because we had
21st Century Fox come in. We just got out of all these data centers and got rid of Salesforce and
these other things. And then we acquired 21st Century Fox and all of a sudden our backlog grew
again. And so we're like, ah, we just got out of this data center. But the biggest thing was
learning about teams and what they were expecting. And it's, you're always going to want storage.
You're going to want to have a way for the app to access these different services and things.
You want an application to learn about how it's being used and make its own changes to things.
Like, okay, maybe cold storage is fine. Nope. This is accessed a lot. Let's move it up to warm. Oh,
no. Hot. We really need hot. Okay. Let's double active. International app. You can have something
shape itself. Those are, I think, multi-cluster. It's there. I think that that's a little bit of
a gap right now. Identity and access management in a true multi-cloud way. That really difficult
to do. Multi-cloud DNS, like auto failover. If Google shut down and you need to shift over to
Azure, Amazon, or Oracle, that's still lots of manual steps in the mix right now.
Same thing with CDNs too. So there's a lot of functional gaps like that, that I see still.
And it's just been, who's going to come up with the project?
But from the end user's perspective, you have to be big enough so that you actually need to
tackle these kinds of challenges, right? Exactly. And is it truly in a cloud's
incentive to really make that the focus? I would say yes, with a specification,
like if all clouds kind of talked and they said, okay, cool. We could get out of the business of
constantly rewriting this or building on this legacy thing that we've had for a long time.
Like OpenID Connect, can we just make that work? You see Keycloak coming in. That's an
interesting project to check out for OpenID Connect and authentication authorization. But
yeah. Personally, I want to see the test for Postgres. That's kind of cool.
Some of the AI stuff is still up and coming as well. There's an alpha feature in Kubernetes
called Dynamic Resource Allocation. And that allows for you to be able to more efficiently
schedule CPUs, GPUs, and other things. And then you can work with WebAssembly on Kubernetes now
too. It's not a replacement for containers. It works really well in tandem with. But
that community, I think, candidly has spent more time with specifications and standards,
and then now they're just moving into actually making actionable things.
But it's kind of, when you're setting up the dinner table for so long and your family's
waiting to eat, you're like, you get people that lose interest. So I feel like that's...
This WebAssembly, we touched on this demo that we equally share passion.
This idea is very interesting that the next generation of containers is going to be WebAssembly.
I've heard this two to three years ago. I've seen a couple of projects that are actually trying to
build whole durable computing platforms on top of these things. These are very interesting ideas
that will probably shape a lot of these tools if they actually make it to more adoption, I guess.
I think it needs more stories. We had at KubeCon... Where was that? I think it was in Paris.
We talked about Zeiss. They couldn't grow their data center size, but they were asked to do more
with their compute and their applications. And so they turned to WebAssembly to save the day
and were able to more effectively and efficiently utilize all of their compute using WebAssembly
and all the features. Where do you think this
game comes into the play? Why do you think these WebAssembly would be more efficient than Zeiss?
It took a little bit of rethinking of the way that they set up their applications,
but more efficient in that their workload specifically is one that was bursty. So
things would come in, you'd scale up, you'd be able to handle that at an immense scale,
and then scale back down. So I think that WebAssembly does really good at those kinds
of workloads, whereas containers are better at others too. Running a database in that
for production, that might be something that needs to be thought about.
It's funny how WebAssembly nowadays is used on the backend because it's a multi-arch assembly.
It goes around.
So it's just like, oh my God, so funny. If you think about it from five years ago.
It's wild. I remember ASMJS, and I got so excited way back when that was a thing. But yeah,
even Disney Plus, they utilize a lot of WebAssembly for their front end to create really
nice UX, UI, but we're seeing it skew into the backend.
So, sorry. So it seems that the Cloud Native Foundation, you are starting to becoming
relatively serious design slash RFC organization. Even if it's not super official or semi-official,
there are pages about those standards that then different vendors agree on, and there's maybe a
larger open source project adopting that standard. And there's maybe a smaller one for us plebs,
so that we can also maybe have distributed storage, but with not such much complexity.
It seems that that's a really important role nowadays.
Absolutely. I think that there's, and we have lots of reports to help show that too,
because that's been our hypothesis for a while as well as a foundation is like,
if we have this set, does it become easier as an end user or vendor? You can get that
implementation or that spec built at home too, and you can build against it and be like, okay,
one day I can make a product that'll integrate with this specific workflow, or I can shift over
and you're not locked into a specific vendor. That's, I think, the real benefit and treasure
of having the community keep everybody honest too, and in a vendor neutral way.
One thing right now I want to see, I'd love it if we had, like if OpenAI were open to donating
their model spec to a foundation so that it could be vendor neutral. Everyone kind of utilizes
OpenAI's API structure and their model spec and everything right now, but it's still owned by
one vendor. And so you see people shaping to that rather than thinking critically, I would say,
about how it works, this is great, but it'd be nice to be able to have something like WC3 or
those kinds of bodies managing a specification and then bringing in the right people to be able to
interact with that. I was sort of thinking, you said that you're with Cloud Native Foundation
for two, almost three years now. This whole AI wave hype explosion, it kind of shook the circle.
Oh yeah. It's like, wait, what?
Whatever you were doing now, there's like a GPU in the mix and the workflows are different and
people have now these beastie machines and everything needs to be, you know-
Cool lights.
Yeah. Demos are becoming insane. I'm not sure if I'll have a job next week, but
this has probably rapidly changed things for you as well. How do you guys tackle these challenges?
I guess it's a different environment now.
It's been really interesting. That's my soundbite.
It's really interesting.
But Kubernetes is a great platform to build platforms. And so there's a lot that it already
did. And so we would have folks from the press and media come out and ask like,
hey, what's going on with this? When's it going to be ready? And we're like, oh, it is already.
They're like, wait, what?
And so as you deal with batch workloads and stats and things like that, yes, that's already there.
When it comes to some of the other inference things or being able to,
like, you can't right now in Kubernetes tap into a GPU and say, I want 1.5 GPUs, right?
You don't have that kind of experience. And that's why NVIDIA bought RunAI is because that's
really what they're looking to do is how do we virtualize this and make it make sense?
That's what the Kubernetes community is working on, both NVIDIA, Intel, and several others
in that dynamic resource allocation feature so that you can actually schedule things more
effectively. And then even existing CPUs and other kinds of devices that you're plugging in,
you have more control over it. In testing that, I think that they said that they were
able to raise some data centers where they're testing from like 60% efficiency to like 90.
So they're seeing some wild things happen when you're just able to better schedule things and
then more quickly make changes. Orchestration's crazy and difficult on that front. So that's one
of the ways in which we're shaping and changing things.
Organizations I've spoken to, a couple of different archetypes for that.
Some are like, AI, let's go.
And then you jump in and they throw a bunch of stuff out and they realize, oh,
no, we still need about 70% at least of what we're doing already.
This is just going to augment it.
And then you have other groups that I think are thinking more effectively
about it, where they're taking a look at like how they route those kinds of requests.
Hey, this has personally identifiable information in it.
Nope.
Don't even send it out of the app.
Yeah.
Um, or let's send it to a small language model or our own trained LLM rather than
to the vendor that's going to cost like 30 times what we want to pay for this.
Um, and then others like Adobe that completely got rid of all of their
closed source stuff, um, behind the scenes for their, for a couple of their
platforms and, uh, are utilizing open source now to interact with that.
So really cool stories that we're starting to see come out.
And then I think, again, you know, if you know your fundamentals well, uh, you're
not going to be throwing away as much of the application as you need.
Again, a lot of it, you know, does it need AI or can you actually do this with
stats is, is a reasonable question to ask.
I know not a fun one.
Cause you're like, no, but my AI project, but you know, it's, um, you take a look
at it's, it's, what do you want to do?
And AI is great for like reasoning.
So if you've a crazy, if then else case statement kind of thing going on.
Sure.
Maybe that's something that can help on that front.
Um, data classification is a big one.
And then a lot of organizations aren't ready on that front either.
They don't have the right taxonomy and they need to go before they even train
their data or work with it in that kind of vectorized way, they, they have
to get their data in order.
And so that's also something where you can use AI to help out a little bit
with that too, but not a lot of people want to jump in and a lot of
borderlines are still the same.
In that regards, in terms of data, I would say like, okay, we have vectors
now on vector databases and all that stuff.
But, um, but there's like still at what point we won't need to write YAML files
that you guys really love or Jinja templates that you love even more.
They're right.
The best decision is you take a templating language for HTML and start writing YAML
and that's the best, right?
And then you miss one minus on a tech and yeah.
That's what I'm using AI for.
It's like, it's my YAML file.
But yeah, in terms of like defining these, uh, specs for, for Kubernetes
and things like that, will a lot of these things kind of be offloaded
to this modern tools as well?
Do you see changes there as well to be made so that you don't have to have
human that defines all these things and misses or like, do you see these
things change there as well?
I've seen, I've seen a lot, a lot of focus on, um, internal development
platforms, um, not just backstage, but even being able to like, okay, what
does the developer experience look like?
Like Intuit's an incredible job with this.
They'll have their dev team come in.
They'll kind of have a sense for like, okay, this is going to be either an
Angular app or Java or kind of like a sense for what tools they're using.
They'll check some boxes and they'll say, okay, here are the
things I want to use and go.
And then those, uh, teams, the infrastructure team, security team,
all of these teams can have come together to create these templates
and then regularly keep them updated.
So as the dev teams are working, they just kind of understand already
what they're going to use.
They're like, Hey, I need this kind of storage or that kind of thing.
They're able to self-service, add that in, and they have a great platform to
work with that is going to stay updated.
If things are breaking, they have really good telemetry and,
and tracing on what went wrong.
And then they're starting to take a look and they've open sourced a couple of
things that are not in the CNCF yet that are like AI ops.
And so actually like this is an outage.
It learns from that and then is able to tell it what, what you fixed, if you
need to manually intervene, and then it's able to go and take that knowledge
and go to apply that stuff, which is really cool.
So no more panicky Prometheus querying and then figuring out which tags are
okay to not query a bit too much.
Okay.
Yeah.
And you know, the goal, no more 3am calls, please let me sleep.
Then we could do code and kind of like orchestrate what's coming out of all
of these tools that we have.
More beer and more pizza.
Yeah.
That's all we need.
First AI, then escalate to human.
Oh, I love the future.
I love the future is now.
Yeah.
I, I guess I also, okay.
AI is shaping, I don't want to go into more because we do have this AI
fatigue that's creeping in, but that's not my.
Uh, probably there's, I think that's, that's my one, like, if I have a one
nugget of wisdom to share on that topic, it's, um, AI isn't the product.
It's a feature.
Yeah.
It's the, it's the feature that helps you enable that.
Please don't make it the product that's wrong.
Product fit.
Beautiful.
Uh, I had like a, another, I saw another, let's say movement kind of a thing
going on, uh, where development environment is also changing in sense that,
you know, if you used to have like your development machine and you run
everything in there, okay.
If your infrastructure is so simple, you have like one node cluster on your
machine, you do things like that.
But I also sense that a lot of these things is moving to like environments
that are in the cloud or semi in the cloud or pre provision for your development.
Do you also sense that things are changing there where engineers
kind of like have sandboxes or what?
Can you tell me a bit more on that as well?
Do you sense this?
Absolutely.
I think even when, like, uh, I've been a big fan of visual studio code for a long
time, and then I just recently got introduced to like cursor, that's really
cool, but you know, like I'm also flying a lot and getting to travel a lot more.
So I'm like, ah, okay.
The plain wifi is not going to cut it when I want to do development or try things out.
Um, I can't host an LLM and work on this at the same time.
And it's, it, that fatigues me to no end.
Um, it's a lot easier for organizations to justify their spend for folks, as
well as get them the access that they need when we're kind of going back to
this, like dumb terminal or simple terminal, and then a mainframe kind of
setup where you can plug into the cloud, um, and have your GPUs, all these things
that, or run times, all these things available to you, there's a lot more
certainty around that too.
So like with GitHub code spaces or get pod, there's a whole bunch of things
available on that front.
Um, that are, they'll make it easier for developers in that sense of standards
and being able to give feedback, you know, across your team, like, um, works
in my machine, doesn't work on yours within our setup, even though we're
containerized, what's going on here.
Um, it helps eliminate a lot of those problems.
Like this, like development with live environments and things tooling around
that, like, uh, what is telepresence or things like, we see a lot of movement in
that direction.
At least that's my feeling.
It might be again, my bubble there as well.
It's no, it's, it's huge from what I've seen.
And anecdotally talking to so many community members, that's, that's favored
because it's, this is what is going into production.
It's not, I'm, you're guessing less.
Yeah.
You're less guessing this.
Uh, yeah.
The era of jump boxes are over.
What you probably want is submit the request, get it approved, and then jump
in with the privilege that you need to debug something if tracing is not enough.
So, yeah, I think, uh, yeah, there's a lot of work on that front and, uh, our
lives are getting better at least from the operational perspective.
Uh, uh, when I go, um, I had another question.
It's not related really to this one, but, um, there is Argo CD, right.
For the continuous delivery and deployment, um, in my bubble, that's
kind of like the way to go if you want to deploy these things these days, but
there's also Flux and I think you still might have clients on Flux, but both of
these projects are cloud native projects, I think, right?
So they're in a sense competing with each other, right?
How does that happen or work?
It's like, I think it's good because competition is good, but
they're like in a similar space.
Do you have all of these overlaps in there as well?
It's like, it just happens naturally.
Yeah, it'll happen naturally.
And you'll, I think that that's really good because you've had standout projects
where they don't have a competing project or anything even remotely close to it.
And they're constantly asking like, are we hitting the mark?
Is this okay?
Is it, it, it, it leaves a lot of question.
Not that it's wrong, but it's just a lot more difficult to bounce off something
and get that sense of what you're, if, if what you're working on makes sense to
the community.
Yeah, that's, that's entirely, that's around our whole concept of no, we don't
want to be a kingmaker or pick the winners.
We'll establish this really nice atmosphere for both Flux and
Argo to be able to exist.
And then I think they'd even tried to like make the GitOps toolkit and then
they decided that wasn't the right direction forward as far as like combining
the projects.
It's like, oh, these are pretty similar.
Can we, can we mix it together?
No, we can't.
And then, but this project's kind of went forward.
I think anecdotally I've seen more developers favor Argo and things like
that.
And then the UI, I think that was like the standout thing.
They're like, yes, this is what we want.
And then Flux, it would typically be, that's, that's mostly what I used earlier
on was it's not, not standing up crazy infrastructure anymore, but Flux was
really nice.
And that pairs well with like SREs and that kind of mindset too.
It just fits into that workflow really well.
And I like that because it allows you to solve problems in different ways.
It's like, okay, I like this brand of whatever I'm trying to do.
I like that it allows for that.
Um, the ecosystem is, so all this new wave of tooling, especially for
Kubernetes, it's now old news, right?
Um, so it's getting more mature.
And with that, it also happens that some project might not, let's say survive.
So that the active maintainers have, maybe they just started duck farm or
something else like, uh, growing hops.
If you go back to beer, um, is there like, if you promote some projects to, I
don't know, mature or, um, will also there be like a flag retired or?
Yeah.
Well, we have like a archived and so people will signal like, Hey, is this
project alive or check into this or kind of see if it's abiding by the code of
conduct or whatever the governance of the structure is.
And then if it's the TOC, we'll take a look at that and I'll say, you know, like,
no, this is, everything is above board here.
Or they're going to say, Nope.
Yep.
This is valid.
This is worth archiving.
Um, and so we've seen, I think nine projects archived so far and it's, it
will continue to grow over the years.
But it's, yeah, it's, it, it'll happen at some point in time.
It'll be really interesting when Kubernetes gets to that frame, you know,
like, or what did that kind of evolves into if it'll split off
into some, something else entirely.
Um, I like what you said to around like stability and like, it's, it's
becoming that boring thing, dependable thing in production.
And we've even seen, there was a couple of years ago and, um, it's
in a night just like this and, and San Francisco where a bunch of venture
capitalists were looking at the contributions to the Kubernetes project.
And they saw for the first time ever, it had like crusted and it was starting to go
down and then went, and then, but if you zoom out, you'd go back and you click on
dev stats, you go all CNCF, it's still hockey stick up to the right.
And so rather than think critically, someone freaked out and said,
Oh, Kubernetes is going down.
And it's like, yeah, but that's a good thing.
Um, that's because people are focused on Argo.
They're focused on open telemetry backstage.
They're solving other problems now.
They have, they feel safe enough to be able to divert their
attention onto other things.
That's, I think that's really cool.
And so if we continue to do that and think critically, like, okay, this is good enough.
Or what can we take out of this?
What's extra?
What do we actually need here?
Then what's the problem we're trying to solve?
Then you're going to have amazing things happen.
But those are the thing, like engineers have like now learned what kind of
workloads do you need, like for what kind of workloads Kubernetes is the way to go.
Whereas like you can now do a lot with, I don't know, Docker swarm or Docker
compose or things like that.
You can get pretty far with that.
Um, this week we attended a Microsoft conference or NT conference here in
Slovenia, and there was like a one senior Microsoft engineer and he explained
there's like four ways how you can run containers on Azure, right.
And this goes from like very simple, just one container.
We take care of everything.
And then it goes like you can use their managed Kubernetes and
there's like a lot of options.
I don't even remember now, but there's like four options how you can run it.
And you can like tune into which, like where your organization is, to what side
you actually want to have to deal with these things, where you want to
offload this to third parties.
So I think like people now, they don't just say Kubernetes is the way to go.
Go for it.
There's a lot of options in a lot of directions.
Uh, even like you said, Docker, you don't have to use Docker daemon.
You can use the, these, uh, what is it called?
Uh, container deal, whatever to run these things.
So, um, yeah, there's a lot more options, but, uh, yeah, ecosystem
round is between mature and mature.
Um, which brings me to my next question.
Um, and, uh, I, I, I thought I'm going to rephrase it differently, but I have
this like a really interesting quote and it says, Go is the PHP for zoomers.
So my question is this to you guys, like, uh, a lot of these tools, majority
of these tools is written in Go.
And, uh, does that scare you guys, or is this the way to go?
Because I seen his face, like when he comes in, he tries to explain that he
is SRI and he has a really mature ecosystem and then he shares the stack
traces from Go and it's like all fire and shit.
So the question I have for you, I guess for both of you guys, do you think that
the Go is the right decision for these things?
I know that it doesn't make sense to rewrite all of these things into something
else because it's so mature and so big and complicated, but still like, do you
still think that the Go is the right tool for these things?
So I know this is a personal opinions and all, but still like a PHP for zoomers.
Do you use it?
That's funny.
I think that that's always something that's, that's kind of going
on underneath the surface, right?
Like if you are trying to squeeze that performance faster than C or C++, it's
going to be really hard, but there's, there's not a glut of people really
writing in that anymore.
Um, Rust has been something that's been really interesting.
That's come up.
That's like finally starting to like energy efficiency and then
performance, like, Oh wow.
It got up there, but it's really difficult to learn with all the
constructs of borrow checking and everything else and components, et
cetera.
Um, I'm seeing more Rust projects come into the ecosystem.
I'm also seeing a lot more Python because of AI and that ecosystem as well.
Um, when anecdotally I've taken a look at, there's some nice, um, like code
quality tools that you can use to check open source repositories.
And, um, and typically what I've seen is like, when you're looking at TypeScript
and Python, usually the code quality is a lot lower, um, with known problems
and, and just ways that you write code and that vernacular, that, um, uh,
idi, idi, idiomatic language concept.
Um, but with Go things have been really solid on that front.
Rust, you see some good competency there too.
I think it's good for right now.
It's, it's really down to readability and does this work the way it should?
If there's a big performance thing or something like that, then that would,
that would freak me out, but that if you're using too many dependencies and
not really watching that, and that balloons up, you know, same kind of thing
with node, uh, that's also scares me.
And I'm like, how many packages?
Oh my gosh.
You know, it takes 30 minutes just to do your NPM install.
Um, but, uh, I, I think good for now.
I am curious to see what shifts over to, I, I've been big in like Ruby, Go, PHP,
and Visual Basics, so clearly I've picked winners and it's like I never
had a hard day in my life, but, uh, um, uh, like Elixir is cool.
Like you start to see some things, but it's kind of, uh, choosing the right
programming language when it has its day in the sun, when you have the community
there, I think it's magic when you have that, you have a lot of the cloud
native community there right now.
Uh, but I do think it'll shift a little bit into Rust and, and I'm curious to
see what else comes out of that mix too.
You have like Mojo on top of Python.
Maybe that will up-level the language a little bit, but, so yeah, all that very
long roundabout way to say like, yeah, I think it's magic right now.
Please let, let it go.
Let it go now.
Yeah.
No, like, just like the song.
Um, I think that we are now at the point where you cannot just use the tools
that at least at my level, I know, well, I tried to learn Go a few times and it's
a simple language, but it's not easy.
Right.
Because yeah, the, the, the constructs and all the stuff that it has in, it's not
really hard, but when you go to real, if you open up, I don't know, something
code available or open source and just start reading stuff, um, then it, it gets
a bit tricky, so, um, I think that, yeah, it's, if we want to grow, we need to
learn, um, the tools that we are using and also the languages that they're written
in.
Um, so yeah, I'm now on, on that path.
Uh, so yeah, probably I will, I will have to, uh, get someone to help me out
because you, you get the basics, but then there are patterns that are not that
simple.
Right.
Um, so yeah.
Um, and I think Go is a good language, especially for this underlying tooling.
If we are talking at the projects in the Cloud Native Foundation, I think it's
probably a really good choice.
Um, I'm getting maybe a bit skeptical if that's, if you, if your app needs to be
written in Go when you start, if you're not like, uh, the 20% of big companies in
the world that will scale and be distributed, then maybe you can do back
end templating and some Django, Elixir, Phoenix, Ruby, and you can support your
local business by local.
I mean, 2 million Slovenian big company, right?
Because we have different standards and you might not want to break your head with
ptrace and tracing and how garbage collection in Go and why we are memory
leaking.
Right.
Um, yeah.
Uh, but we, and Otto, we work together.
So, uh, Otto was my, uh, manager and sometimes I ask him, should I do this or
should I do that?
Um, because I was a bit, well, of course, unsure and you want to have people's
opinions.
And he said, yes.
So probably you, I think it's a must.
You need to know some Python.
You need to know some Go, even if you are not working, even if you are using Java,
if you use Kubernetes, look, if there is a simple operator, you might want to skim
through the code and have a basic understanding what it does.
And then you see some, that there are some queue length that is parsing some YAML and
maybe that's also useful for you.
So I would say yes.
So learn.
And when we come, when we do like a smooth transition to learning, uh, Cloud Native
Foundation also have certifications, right?
What are the most popular ones?
What do you offer?
I think KCA, KCAD.
I think it's KSA.
That's not a secret organization.
It's Kubernetes Security Administrator.
Um, it's not like NSA, uh, but, um, those are the most popular right now just because
they're it's Kubernetes and it culminates a lot of things, whether you're developing
on top of it as a developer, whether you just want to be more infrastructure minded and
work on that side of things.
Um, we have a kubestronaut program where if you have all, if you get all the five existing
certifications right now, we send you a jacket and we put a spotlight on you, you get in
a blog post and like, I think there's over 500 kubestronauts so far.
It's been a fun way to gamify, um, the training inserts.
We had one discussion with, uh, uh, Andraž and he was like, this guy is kubestronaut.
I was like, what?
Yeah.
And he was like, no, no, no.
This is, no, no, no.
He was like, this is elite.
Yeah.
He's like elite.
There's like two guys.
Uh, something four or four.
He's like, he's elite.
I'm like, we are a big community.
Yeah.
We know everyone.
We've, we've been, we've been talking about potentially doing a helmet too.
So you may see that happen.
You need to have five certificates to, to be kubestron, right?
Yeah.
Okay.
They're hard to get, but like, what, what do you, what do you test for?
Like, how does it work?
I'd say so.
The, there's like the security one I'd say is like, that's pretty hard, you know, with
anything, if you know the answer, it's easy.
I know that, um, I'd say that was pretty intense.
I'd say the KCA, um, I'd say that for me personally, it was a little bit easier just
cause I knew Kubernetes from that side.
Um, the developer, uh, one was the one that was, that had me thinking, cause you were
delving deeper into and working on things like pizza controllers and, you know, those
APIs and what that looked like.
But, um, yeah, security is always going to be a pretty hard one.
And then we just changed the, uh, uh, lifetime of those certifications too, from three years
to two, just because so much changes within that time period too.
It's not a good measure.
If it's like three years aged out, that's like what?
12 Kubernetes, you know, releases.
That's a lot.
Um, but, uh, or nine, nine now, but, um, yeah, it's, I really like the, I do like that focus
on education then seeing where all of these people are learning across the CNCF.
Yeah.
I may, may I please like, uh, have the final question then?
Are you fine with that?
And then we have some pizza and some beer.
Um, okay.
We know that if you want to become a senior in this space, you become QB astronaut and
that's kind of like a certification.
You should do it.
But I have a question for both of you guys.
Um, what would be a good advice for somebody that has seen some of these things, wants
to go into ops, uh, SRA, uh, wants to work with Kubernetes, wants to explore this stuff,
wants to become more familiar with the stuff, but it's a complete junior.
Uh, so, you know, can you give some advice to like very, very beginners or let's say
it like that.
Can you give me some, something there, please?
So that's, let that be a kind of like, uh, yeah, my advice would be like, try and learn
everything that is popular or that you find useful.
Right.
So build it in your Dell clusters or in your free time, or even try to ask your manager
if you can play around with some technology that you're, you might not even adopt just
to explore a bit, because as Tyler mentioned, you will get some foundations, right?
There are patterns that repeat.
Um, but then especially if you're folk, if you're folk in the past, if you're building
features or shipping a lot of code and adding value for customers with creating new things,
um, all also, if you move to ops or SRE, try to be humble.
Um, the most important thing is to provide value stability, um, and not to write a lot
of custom things, custom code, right?
Um, because sometimes me, we maybe do too much of, I don't know.
bash? Well, you can't escape bash, right? And you should probably be really good at it, but
you don't maybe want to write like a simple Go CLI that takes some templating and then does
something so another system that is commonly available can pick it up. I would suggest that
try to write as minimal amount of code as possible to achieve the majority of things, because, well,
if you're working especially for, I don't know, international customers or growing customers,
you need to understand that teams will grow. You will be at the company for a longer time,
but the new folks that will come in, they will know the basic stuff or
for stuff that is six months old or older, and there is constantly new stuff coming in from the
community, and maybe you want to avoid your custom stuff, right? And always focus on the customer,
right? The most important thing is to provide value and to make everyone happy and provide
them a good experience, and yeah, you can hack then at hackathons and stuff, especially if you're
coming from a role where you are the featured guy, and then when you move to ops, it's
a bit of a different story, but don't worry, it's still fun and exciting.
I really like that, and you kind of said that too with your answer about Go. It's reminding me of,
there's, who is it? I think it's PragProg, the publisher. They have seven languages in seven
days and those kinds of things, and I really do urge people to go and think outside the box.
When you're learning, learning shouldn't necessarily be easy. Think about physically
when you're working out, you're sweating. If you're not doing that and you're just going
through exercises, whether it be exorcism or code kata or something like that,
if it's not sticking and there's not a lot of effort there, it's going to be a lot harder
to remember that, right? You don't remember the easy things, you remember the hard things,
for better or for worse. That's good learning, and so that's something to take with you as you
go through when you're choosing what you want to get into, you're just beginning.
I work with a lot of people and they say, oh, I want to do open source. I'm like, cool. Let's get
more specific. What do you like? Do you like security? Do you like a specific project? Do you
like the community? What are the aspects that are driving you towards, you just said open source,
is that something you heard from a community that you're in? Really understanding the intent
and the motivation behind that is incredibly important. Sitting there and kind of working
through that yourself will help you. It'll save you years of time. I can guarantee that.
What do you want to be when you grow up? Think about that. I'm still doing that.
And that really helps illuminate, okay, cool, I like security things, or I like
working with scaling applications or containerizing them, or you just get a better
sense about the ecosystem on that front. That is where the landscape is helpful, because then you
can take a look and say, okay, I like these things. We do have a textual representation of the landscape,
too, the landscape guide, and then you can read through what each of those sections looks like
for people that are struggling or trying to make sense of what's going on.
And then, like was said, too, I think it's great to dive into what's popular, take a look at some
tutorials and things like that. You'll be surprised at the amount of tools that are at your disposal
as well. You don't need to run a multi-billion dollar corporation or something like that.
You can load test it locally with tools like Hay and everything else, too, and simulate what some
of these things look like if you want that kind of experience, too. So there's a lot of creative
ways to think about how to get started and then situations that you put yourself in. But I'd say
make it something that's fun. Don't just go through the motions. Try to make a real-world
project, too, if you can, if you're just getting started with something. There's nothing more
magical than writing that first CLI that pulls from an API and you're like, oh, the weather is
22 degrees. There's a magic in that and being able to iterate and try new things, too. So make
it magic and make it something that you really feel passionately about. Beautiful. I guess
let's wrap on that, I guess. I would like to thank you, Taylor, again for taking the time.
I'm looking forward to seeing your demo as well. Andras, thank you for your time as well.
I would like to encourage everybody to like and subscribe. Sharing this stuff helps a lot
with the promotion. And I would like to thank our sponsors, Kaldi 3FS and Human Frog, for
supporting us. And thank you for Patreons and everybody who has taken the time to listen to
this. Until next time. Thank you. Thank you. Enjoy.