What are your plans for the future?
He will be a journalist. At the beginning, he will talk for a couple of minutes about some stupid things that we talked about.
Then we started talking, and at the beginning it will be Grodje Špica, and then we will start.
It will be very organic.
I think that lately we are filming a lot outside of our normal setup.
Yes, that is true, but on the other hand, if someone says to you that the biggest Slovenian technical conference is in Primorje, in Porto Rojo, in Bari, in Slovenia,
then in Primorje it will happen, it's hard to say no.
When people say that, they ask themselves what they have been waiting for so long.
It is not clear to them what they are asking, but it's good.
Greetings to all of you who have joined us.
Specifically, from the 29th NTK conference, Luka Minojlović is with us.
He is one of the co-organizers of this event.
We were a bit worried about what would be the best moment for Luka to be stolen for this honor, for this speech.
He said before that he is the leader of the majority.
You are the programming part, or rather the part where you attract the lecturers,
you create the hype, and then others join in.
Am I right?
I would say yes.
What we are doing with our colleagues from this team is a work in progress.
We are getting lecturers from Slovenia and abroad,
some from the former state of Yugoslavia,
and many from other European states, sometimes from the whole of America.
The conference is going on and on.
I have been called so many times by lecturers who are experienced.
They don't come 10 minutes before the lecture, but one minute before,
and then they set up an alarm where this person is,
and then we try to call him on all channels.
In the beginning, it is going on with its own pace and its own way, which is now verified.
Let me put it this way.
I am now a fourth-year student at NTK.
The beginnings are a bit different from other stories,
but we will get to that.
How do you see this?
What was NTK conference in the beginning,
let's say in the late 90s,
and what is it now?
Where do you see yourself?
Let's say I am not a regular guest at this conference,
but I see this Microsoft ecosystem,
and this corporate scene.
Now I have a feeling that there is a lot more freshness,
which includes open code.
Let's start with how Microsoft has changed.
There is more freshness, more small firms, startups,
open ideas.
I don't know, you tell me.
I think Microsoft ecosystem is very wide.
Their product range is very wide.
Microsoft was the main driver of the conference,
which is why it was named Microsoft.
They were looking at their products,
because Microsoft was interested in promoting their products.
At the time, it was much more strict,
they were looking at other vendors,
if there is a partnership or a sponsorship slot
at these stages of the conference.
It's been a long time,
since Microsoft is no longer in the spotlight.
We still protect the Microsoft ecosystem,
and the audience, which is generally
transferred to the Microsoft platform.
But we are very happy,
if other technologies, other views,
or synergistic effects are stolen from us,
in combination with Microsoft.
Welcome to all content.
The conference was more product-oriented at the time.
Microsoft, with its big launches of new products,
also started a conference, which was very important.
I think it's still very important,
but it's a different time,
and Microsoft has somehow missed
all the regional Microsoft conferences.
This is no longer such an important focus for them.
I believe they are interested,
that this is still happening.
They got an opportunity from agencies,
which organize these events.
In the final phase, they also got an opportunity
from the community, which can now be seen at these conferences.
Microsoft has everything,
despite the fact that this community is perhaps less active
than it was 15 years ago.
They still choose very good experts from it.
They have a teacher,
the backbone of these conferences.
People with the name of MWP,
fans of technology,
entrepreneurs, and so on.
It's still leaning on them.
They also have a generational menu for you,
plus they gravitate towards new technologies,
which makes me very happy.
That's why you and your colleagues
might be talking to some other platforms.
I'm happy to hear your feedback,
to join us and share your knowledge.
This conference has been going on for 29 years.
I'm here for the first time this year.
Sometimes I wonder
how old it is compared to me.
Yes, it is.
I've already been here with my new solo a while ago.
When I heard about the brand Microsoft,
which organizes these conferences in Slovenia,
I remember that a neighbor of mine
used to work in an IT department
of a Slovenian company.
I know that she had a brand in Slovenia,
but I don't know if she still does.
She had a nice bag,
a Microsoft logo,
and I thought it was very interesting.
I've seen the Microsoft logo on Windows,
but I've never seen the Microsoft logo anywhere else.
You can see it on a physical bag.
People who work with Microsoft technology
get together.
It's very interesting.
Today is a conference
organized by Windows and Microsoft.
We've been together for 30 years.
It's interesting.
I still don't know the exact title of the MVP.
What does it mean?
Does it mean Most Valuable Player?
Professional.
You were before Dončić.
Those are Dončićs in IT.
What does MVP mean?
MVP is a title
given by Microsoft
if it sees that you are active in the community
and that you have an impact in the community.
You work on these technologies,
you like to present them,
you have an opinion.
It's true that everyone finds
the same personality
or the same area that is really cool for them,
where they can be more professional,
and that's why they trust them more.
I've seen certain Microsoft technologies
and I'm still enthusiastic about them.
I like to present them.
In my time,
when I was 43,
I was as enthusiastic as I was when I was 20.
I still believe that I stand for it.
If we present it, it will function as you wish.
I wouldn't say the same for every Microsoft technology,
and I wouldn't stand for it either.
It's true that the more you dig into it
and get to know it in detail,
the easier it is for it to work.
I know you as a developer.
Microsoft has a lot of development tools,
but those developers who have worked
or are working in other environments,
probably haven't been so lucky
with this product range,
and it's only normal
to be the first one.
I think that every computer
in Slovenia and beyond
has come to NTK once in a while.
Either way,
we're lucky here.
If nothing else, it's an event
that you meet once a year,
even with those you really don't see.
It's hard to find the time,
or maybe we forget.
It's so beautiful to see it here.
This morning I met a guy
I don't consider a guest,
but more of a guest than a speaker
who came to me and said,
where are you?
Where are we going for a coffee?
I noticed when you helped us
look for a parking lot.
When you go to these conferences,
people greet you and are very friendly.
I don't know if you know everyone by name,
but it seems like you're a big group
of people you really know.
People really trust you
and I see you have a lot of permanent guests.
I think there are a lot of...
We chose a term a while ago.
People who still have them are always sicker.
But I think there's a continuity
in your careers.
I think it's done.
It doesn't just happen to me.
As a teacher, I was the first
to embark on this path through Microsoft.
It was a long time ago.
A grant from Microsoft,
a grant for a sponsor called...
HUM.
I can hear you, Vrhunsko.
It was a grant
focused more on
innovation in the office.
It was around 2002-2003.
I had the challenge
of installing the first DSL.
At the time, these modems were
jamming.
It was like pulling it out of an electrician
and putting it back.
Today, it's called Watchdog.
I wrote Watchdog in Visual Studio,
which stopped a relay,
reset the modem,
and called it Not Offline.
I was a student of musicology,
so I didn't know anything about it.
I hated that it was always on me.
I got a second award.
The first one was from a colleague
who worked for Office.
He later worked for Microsoft in the US.
The award was to join NTK.
At the time, it was a wow to me.
It was a wow to a rising student.
After NTK, a gentleman from Microsoft
called me.
He said,
where are you going to put NTK
in a show?
I don't remember which year it was.
It was for Exchange,
for the Microsoft 2007 system.
It was truly revolutionary
from Microsoft's point of view.
It had a lot of new features.
It was the first tool,
for Andraž, who was in a special class.
It was the first Microsoft tool
that you couldn't even install on a GUI.
You had to go to PowerShell.
It was very interesting.
I had a slot from 10.30 to 11.30.
I thought I would have a slot from 10.00 to 11.00.
In short, from 10.30 I went through the slides
and from 2.00 to 11.00 I said,
I'm done.
I forgot the whole slot in the slides.
I had a nice demo.
The hall was not too big,
so I could see what the new server was bringing.
One of the audience members said,
you still have half an hour.
I said, wow, half an hour and a demo.
I was totally into the demo.
I got very good ratings.
There was an older gentleman,
I think he worked in a seminar in Ljubljana.
He said, you have such enthusiasm,
so that was it.
Then Microsoft took me to Windows Server 2008,
which was a revolutionary Windows server
with a lot of new features and a totally different model
of operation than before 2003 or 2000.
That was all day long.
I said, wow, I've been doing this all day.
You know how it is, 8 hours is enough.
Then we repeated it more and more.
We were doing server presentations all over Slovenia.
I remember Maribor, Ljubljana, Novi Gorica,
and the whole of Kopru.
We repeated it in Ljubljana,
because it was very interesting.
Microsoft got me into it.
I started writing my blog,
I was very active,
and I was involved in meetings
with my colleagues who are a bit older than me,
for example Miha Pichler,
and other colleagues like Matjaž Ladava,
who has been working at Microsoft in the US for many years.
He was very important to me,
because he was from our end,
but he worked in Gorica,
and he inspired us a lot.
When he saw that we were behind him,
I got the name MVP,
if I go back to a simple question.
No, of course, explain a bit.
I got the name MVP,
and I first went to Seattle.
In Seattle, you sit with a product group,
and older MVPs like you,
who have been there for 15 years,
talk about the difficulties of the server,
it's very interesting and educational.
Does that mean that you devote yourself to Microsoft,
with MVP, or through that group,
you give some suggestions?
So you always have a live connection with Microsoft.
Yes, there are times when it's less,
and times when it's more.
At that time, it was very intense.
During the pandemic,
we didn't know how to do it,
whether we were going to do it virtually,
or in person.
Now, things are back to normal,
and those who went to the Summit,
I haven't been there for a few years,
are still participating,
if not, we have meetings,
and if we comment,
they also have limited resources.
You have to look at things objectively,
my problem is probably not that big,
and we have to deal with those compromises.
When I was younger, I didn't understand it,
now that I'm older, I understand it better.
The resources are limited, priorities are set.
One of the things I noticed,
as a first-time person at an NT conference,
is that today there is no such day,
but people really go to the conference,
but today there were a lot of people,
very well-dressed, very busy.
I don't know which conference you go to.
I know that at the B-Sides conference,
which Andraž organized on Friday,
probably more people came in hoodies,
and favorite Pikachu T-shirts,
but it seems to me that today
there were a lot of well-dressed people.
If I understood correctly,
the business aspect of the conference,
if we have a tech track,
where is the business aspect,
because I see that it is a very important part of the conference.
Yes, on Wednesday, the second day,
it is also dedicated to partners,
and we also call it a business day,
which also has a special program.
It is not so much a technological topic,
but a decision-maker,
and a global vision that Microsoft has
through its products,
or topics that are trends in terms of leadership,
in terms of modern entrepreneurship, etc.
Various topics are discussed,
women in IT, etc.
But today there are definitely
a number of people present,
those who are here because of the technological lectures,
and those who are here because of the business impact.
A number of partners and sponsors are present here,
and it is certainly an important element
in terms of the development
of future businesses over the summer.
Of course.
If you have here,
everyone who has mentioned IT in any way,
including us,
why not create a business here?
There is probably some synergy,
some partnership,
why not use it here?
It is definitely not a bad idea.
I would like us to go
to a conference like this one,
and maybe
change a thought
that I had with one of the participants today.
He came from
a large Slovenian company,
not very large,
but relatively large for Slovenia,
and he said,
we have a budget for education,
our stack in the company is Microsoft,
everything we have in the company is Microsoft stack,
and we are invited to this conference
and education over the summer.
We are here today to learn,
to talk to professionals,
to see what is new in the field.
In our organization,
for example,
we use Windows,
which is a default workspace
for many Zune organizations,
and it is a fully-dominated
IT world.
I hope that today we will come
to an IT conference like this one,
because...
Sorry, go ahead.
Finish your thought.
Luka started well,
but for me it is musicology,
and enthusiasm,
you are full of enthusiasm,
a very positive person,
and a very positive approach.
In addition to the community,
it is all a volunteer,
enthusiastic thing.
In the final phase,
you also found a job,
a career,
and you are actively engaging with it.
Keep it up.
And here is the thing,
all IT is visible to us.
I had the opportunity to see
how IT is done in a few companies.
You said it much more elegantly.
I know.
You went straight to the point.
What I wanted to say yesterday,
and it would be great to talk to Luka,
is that IT is really
in such a low voice today,
if we look at it from the point of view
of the public administration,
IT firms,
and Luka will present it in a very positive way.
Or am I wrong?
Well, you know,
I came to the conclusion
that maybe it is necessary
to keep IT together.
Not Slovenian.
Yes, it is possible.
It is like Andraž's spinning top.
Slovenians have very good spinning tops,
but we have a lot of them,
and each one for himself.
The greatness is in knowing how to cut it.
It all started differently.
My grandfather was an electrician.
He was educated in Italy.
I was an electrician out of love,
so I was fixing televisions all day long
for various people,
even though he was retired later.
Computers were an addition to it.
My father, who saw that I would play too much games,
decided to buy a computer
that was too powerful for current games.
I had a 486 100 MHz,
which was full, but only 4 MB RAM.
So you couldn't do it.
Then at some point you raised your hand.
Suddenly the 486 was installed as an operating system,
and then I got interested in it.
Let's get back to the main topic.
I learned that it's better to learn less and help each other more,
to cooperate and to learn, because Slovenia is full of exceptional graduates,
truly exceptional. Andraž and I had the opportunity to meet them at the Lockchill competition,
and even though, by the way, when I went to musicology in Ljubljana,
I was helping a computer guy at Filofax when I was a student,
and I remember that at Filofax, there were public computers,
because not every computer had one, so you could surf the Internet on a public computer.
I remember that one day I was in Cleta, and I lived in Rimska, which is right next to Filofax,
and I took a carrier that didn't have Wi-Fi,
and it had a modem, and a network, but it had a PCMCI card,
so I had to call a taxi.
So, I went there in the middle of the afternoon,
to check my e-mails, and to download what I had downloaded during the day,
because we didn't have the Internet in our apartment.
But, I wanted to say that this community concept was very close to me,
because it started with me visiting CyberPipa in Ljubljana,
and I met him there for the first time.
We got to know each other, and he stayed in my mind,
and even after all these years of meeting him again,
I knew that he was the one for me.
And this CyberPipa was such a great concept for me,
because they were putting a monitor on top of each other,
and he was overlapping, and his colleagues were doing the same.
And it was so good for me.
I was active at the club of students in Goris,
and I would never be here today,
if it wasn't for the club of students,
because the club of students in Goris was a very advanced club.
And we had a server at the club, and it was interesting for me,
because I kept this server and put it on top of each other,
and I put the first point of Wi-Fi,
and I didn't even have Wi-Fi in the Czech Republic,
it was completely unrelated to Wi-Fi,
it was sitting in a field, no one used it.
But, at the same club, we worked freely.
We were young, and we wanted to...
No, we were working on a magazine, radio, TV, festivals, concerts,
I don't know what we were doing,
and in that spirit, I also took over IT,
let's do it that way.
Today, when I met Matjaž Ljadav, Miho Pichler,
that there are some Slovaks in Ljubljana,
that they meet here at Microsoft,
three lectures, half a pizza and a beer.
Oh, the best!
And all of this is voluntary,
and together we talk, we exchange ideas.
When I started writing a blog,
I know that someone from Goris told me,
hey, don't do that,
you know, you're spreading knowledge,
and they will help you with your blog.
If that was the case, then I wouldn't have a blog.
On YouTube, we don't need to talk to each other,
because everything that you know,
and what you know, and what I know,
and what he knows,
is recorded dozens of times on YouTube,
in the sense that, if someone wants to do something,
in any field of our three,
good, they can do it.
But, you see,
there's another factor.
A human factor.
And when we talk about public administration,
about the weaknesses of the ethics,
we know how it feels.
And he loves his job, he enjoys his job,
he really manages it with enthusiasm and zeal,
or is it his job where he's been unhappy for 15 years?
We don't know.
And that's why I'm responsible for not taking over.
We don't know what people are doing,
they can be underpaid, they can be dissatisfied,
they can have their own difficulties,
they can enjoy it, it's a full factor.
And it doesn't change the job.
If you work in a computer,
in a certain period of time,
now you have to work for five weeks.
These are very big things.
But in the computer, there's another factor.
We have an ego with these computers.
It grows over the years.
It grows over the years,
but we have to know how to manage it, I think.
If we manage big systems,
and networks, and code,
and GitHub, GitLab...
I would say...
I think it grows over the years,
but you can also let it go over the years.
You can put that ego aside.
I agree.
When you say it's a connection,
it can't happen if the ego is gone.
Of course.
And that's something that's fully present in the computer.
I remember a lecture.
At the time, someone jumped out of the audience.
He was like,
that's the other product.
I get it.
We're here to talk about this solution.
Someone can come and say,
I know everything.
There's something for everything.
We can compare it.
And we can see that the other thing
has something much better.
OK, we're at it now.
Let's focus on that.
It's not like that anymore.
It was also a good school for lectures.
When I'm in heaven,
I sit down to breathe,
and then react.
This is my experience.
I'm connected to NTK.
I don't know.
NT4 was the last version
I had controls with.
And then,
I switched to Linux,
and then Unix,
and everything was connected to Unix.
And that's how it was.
That ego thing.
Linux vs. Windows.
And because of that,
there was a big rivalry.
I would say,
we're not going to hang out
with these people.
It's like the whole war
is going on.
I never imagined
that one day
we would be
dealing with the same people
on NTK.
And we would be
on the same page.
If you think about it now,
20 or 30 years ago,
was it really like that?
Today,
the ecosystem is totally different.
Yes, it is.
For the audience,
so we don't lose them
when we go way back,
I would like to say
that I compiled
a lot of stuff.
In high school,
we had some C-sharp
tasks,
and we had to do that.
And the whole vibe
was on C-sharp, Visual Studio,
.NET.
And how do you deal with that?
If you use a mono version,
0, 0, 1, 2,
whatever,
Miguel Decaza,
and then you compile it,
and you get a check.
So it's possible.
It's possible.
It's possible to be a player
in open source and
with Microsoft technologies.
And definitely,
the mono contributor
is now working on .NET
and is employed by Microsoft.
And now that .NET is developing,
we all know that it's more open source
and in different platforms.
And definitely,
new people, new ideas,
new economy, new collaborations.
People know that it's the way to go.
And we will definitely work more.
As you can see,
this shift that happened,
it's a community,
a community that came
to Microsoft.
This is just the leadership,
which has changed a lot.
A lot of people
with open hands
and now we have open source.
And last but not least,
GitHub became a Microsoft product.
I didn't buy it.
No, I sincerely believe
that it came from all,
not from the risk community.
Because I remember
a lecture
from ten years ago
when we started using PowerShell
a little more,
2012, 2013,
which was given to me
by a woman,
in the sense of some
system administration.
Once I was joking
and you will see
that Windows Server 2.20
will be in a riot.
And today,
we have a lecture
where Windows Server 2.25
will be,
but the virtual machines
will be Microsoft Linux 3.0.
It will be able to spin
the virtual machines quickly.
On the other hand,
the virtual machines
can do a lot of other things.
I think that the transition
to the cloud took a long time.
It was necessary to find
an alternative
to Microsoft's
crazy basics
to be able to run
something too simple
and lightweight.
The use of energy,
storage, all these things,
all these factors,
I think, have forced Microsoft
to look for alternatives
where it would be possible
to enable all this storage
with some other platform.
When I was in Dublin,
in the data center,
they were shocked
that one of their main concerns
was how much computing
for how much energy
was needed to run
a Windows Server.
It was also necessary
to simplify the carriers
of today's computers.
Why would a Windows Server
run on a small container
for women,
if it could run on
a Linux or some other platform?
And it would be better
and more performant.
I think it was connected
with the overall development.
I don't know.
I won't even
get too close to it.
It could be.
I congratulate you
that it could be.
It could be just the opposite.
You won't have a Windows subsystem
for Linux,
but you will have Linux subsystem
for Windows.
Why not?
It could happen.
There's nothing wrong with that.
Hyper-V...
Can you tell us
what does Hyper-V mean
to me?
Hyper-V, in my opinion,
is a very good virtualization platform
for those who bought
a Windows Server
and got it out of the box.
And for those who run
Windows virtual machines.
That's why Hyper-V is an excellent platform
because it enables
everything that big companies offer.
Yes.
There are a lot of other players
from free to commercial ones
that offer something more.
Especially in the field
of special features
that probably
90% of Windows ecosystems
don't need.
Or
specific
for workloads.
Now you have Linux
which is better.
Last year,
VMWare had a virtualized machine
running faster than bare metal.
That was a marketing
move.
But,
yes,
there are platforms that
are better than Hyper-V
because it has its overhead.
I've been using it
since it was very, very easy.
In 2008,
it was Hypervisor that couldn't
be trusted.
It had some limitations,
memory slots,
CPUs, disks, etc.
But over time,
it developed into a nice
virtualization platform.
Do you already
pay for PowerShell
or do you click on it?
It depends
if I click on something trivial.
For example, today,
when I set up a demo
I always use PowerShell
because it's not smart to click
on each virtual disk,
repeat it, and then
you call me and say
let's go.
I think it's better
to automate and script
and so on.
I think PowerShell
doesn't have to worry
about typical Windows
repositories.
They're already quite familiar with it.
I have a forum on Windows machines.
I'm totally illiterate
in Windows machines.
Maybe that's why
there are so many questions.
He's changing his job
and if he doesn't choose
Mac or Windows,
maybe he'll get a job
on Windows.
I have to answer
that I have no idea
how it works.
I don't know where we are
and how it works.
I know there must be something
but I really don't know.
What I'm interested in
when I look at
your pages
and what Loki tells me
about his pages,
I have an exceptional
and unique opportunity
to meet a guy
from IT
and healthcare
from non-Windows environment.
Loki works in healthcare
and healthcare homes
IT in this segment.
We have you.
If I understand correctly,
you also work a lot
for healthcare homes and IT
in healthcare as such.
I really wanted to talk
about this topic and get
something interesting out of it.
Because as a user
of healthcare and healthcare
in Slovenia,
it seems to me
that you could have done
a lot better.
Sometimes I'm shocked
when something doesn't work
and I'm like,
why doesn't it work?
I'm just curious
what challenges you see
and what you've experienced
in Slovenian IT and healthcare.
Can you tell us more about it?
You can start, Loki.
I know you don't like it,
but go ahead.
I'll try to think
and not judge.
I see
the classic problem
of lack of resources.
I think
that, of course,
there are financial resources
for certain things,
but I also see
human resources.
I think that healthcare
is very undernourished.
If you have
an IT institution,
it's usually one
that controls
and is actively involved
in the work.
Now it's abandoned,
it's overrun
or divided into parts.
I think that
the environment is
so non-stimulating,
that if a person
has so much
intelligence,
he will eventually
lose it and go
to a less stressful job.
I had the opportunity
to see a lot of
good people
who left the sector
because they were
too busy.
I won't say
what happened next,
but with some passion
and enthusiasm
it's possible to create
a solution that would
drink water,
that would digitize
our healthcare system.
But,
I don't know,
that was my part
that I had the opportunity to see.
I agree with that.
Maybe I would add
that communication
is a big problem
for those people
who work in this sector.
They either have a hard time
expressing their difficulties
or they are
less engaged
in communication.
I often see
that you don't trust yourself.
You don't trust
to try
to activate something,
to improve everything.
What if it doesn't work?
Let's test it tomorrow.
Let's pick a day when it's not so busy.
Let's try to do it
in an isolated way,
in a more secure way.
I often see things
in the same place.
Let me give you an example.
There are
a lot of softwares.
I'm coming back to
a generational leap.
In a lot of households
older softwares
that started
to be built
at the end of the 90s
are still being built
on the same basis.
We know that
there are a lot of modern
softwares and security softwares
that are probably
being reduced.
But there are a lot of
new add-ons,
new programs.
I think that
these software houses
are probably not able
to make a cut,
develop a new software
and replace it.
This, on the one hand,
gives an opportunity
to new software houses
to come up with
some modern concepts.
I don't think
this is an infrastructure problem.
We have too little hardware
and the main problem
is the software we use.
I don't like it
for these reasons.
I think that
these new solutions
will be removed.
Moving from one software
to another is stressful
not only for the computer.
A healthcare worker
will spend three minutes
every month
using a software
if it is not
an intuitive software.
Maybe that is why
there is a demand
for these software houses
to be reassembled.
These are not
some office users
who, even now,
if the day before
their shift in Bosnia
is over,
they have to catch up.
No, these are healthcare workers,
nurses,
people who are sick
in front of their doors.
Not healthy people
who can wait,
but healthy people.
These are sick people
who have a fever, a headache,
etc.
These are different situations.
I remember that
at some point
something happened
and I was called
by a nurse.
She told me that
I should rest
because I was 35 minutes
behind the car.
If I can catch up,
I will be there in 35 minutes.
So, you need to prepare
a mechanism to manage
these people.
The other thing is
communication.
Also from the side of us,
IT people.
It is a bit like
going back to Uniego.
This is a very advanced question.
Did you learn this?
Yes, I did.
Or were you raised
with this?
I think that
the skill
of working with people
is lacking.
But you can survive
if you don't have
a phlegmatic
in the IT environment.
If all of this
causes stress,
you will get sick.
But some people
suffer from this.
I understand this.
My colleagues don't worry too much.
They don't trust everyone.
There is also
an education
on how to use computers
in a safe way.
We need to
be aware of this.
If you compare yourself to IT people,
what kind of a scene is this?
Where do we live?
It is like a garden.
A radiator won't work.
What kind of fears are these?
IT people are like you.
Let's go to those who have
better skills in communication
and not to those who are
in the wrong direction.
That is why
healthcare is so specific.
It is not an ordinary
company.
That is why these programs
are so important.
I would like them to be
intuitive and
to enable me to do
what they do.
Do you think that
if there were more
computers,
it would encourage people
to upgrade,
to have better security policies,
to have better planning?
Let me give you
a plastic example.
Is it possible to regulate
your daily routine?
You have
an electronic
wallet
from a patient
and you have a system
where you can log in
and have a look up and down.
You have a PDF.
What if someone
sends you an e-mail
about complications?
How do you deal with that?
If you have set yourself
a standard,
we need a system
that has a traceability
to look at things.
If he has the opportunity
to transfer it and
send it via e-mail,
he can also send it
via his Gmail.
It is very difficult.
As you mentioned,
there are
programs
that are developing
and there are things
that...
I had an example
when we were building
an e-mail cluster.
We said that
inbound and outbound
e-mails are not monitored.
When you send
an e-mail,
the e-mail must be
by default.
We had a project
in 2020 or 2022.
We tested
all the ideas.
In the end,
we realized that
the analysis that you send
sends an e-mail
and doesn't support the task.
Now,
communication with the producer
is done from the e-mail.
These are things
in their legacy
that didn't exist
in the design.
Now, you can catch it.
These are things
that, as you said,
we don't get a black screen.
Where is the beginning?
Is there a problem on the network?
Ok, they send you an e-mail.
So, yes, there are a lot of things going on.
And now, because of IT, sometimes it's too late, sometimes I don't know.
Sometimes they change a cartridge in the printer, someone is looking for a phone, and then someone tells them that there is an investigation going on.
Well, that's also a very important aspect.
That's also why I believe they don't deny it.
Because I know that in the past there were trends, where companies came, for example, an IT company, they went around,
and then they explained to other companies, for example, at one time they came, and then they did a thorough inspection of the environment,
and then they gave some of their guidelines, right?
A lot of data.
All right, all right, right?
And now they solve a machine that costs, I don't know, 200,000, 300,000 euros, which analyzes the cover,
and doesn't know TLS, and what are we going to do now? Are we going to change the machine now?
Look, honestly, it's unbearable.
It's impossible.
It's impossible to change.
It's impossible to...
I mean, what would that mean?
It means that we would have to change those machines in, I don't know, I'm talking now, 8 to 10 years.
If those machines, unfortunately, live for 20 years, right?
Now, we have to be so flexible and understanding that, okay, we will be able to solve it with some other protocols.
For example, I had an example of a software package that communicates with a database,
and I made sure that it communicates plain text, more or less.
And one day, I sniffed it out with Zorka, and I made sure that it can be understood.
It can't be understood in plain text, but it can be understood, right?
And then I asked them if it could be solved, and they were a bit shocked that it would be difficult,
and that it would cost some money.
And okay, we solved it in a different way.
In the Windows environment, the IPsec between machines and servers is now really unbearable when it goes online, right?
So, there are also some other alternatives, right?
And that's what I imagined, and I also wrote a blog, and I saw a guide on how to implement such things,
with which I can solve a problem that the machine can't solve, or the programmer's house can't solve,
or I could even imagine an unforeseen cost that is too high for the organization, right?
Because I also do that, you know, I would also do everything perfectly, right?
But unfortunately, we have to live in accordance with our abilities, right?
And I think it's better that the nurses are paid better,
that they do their job better and are more satisfied,
or that they have better tools with which they work.
So now I'm thinking that we have to replace that machine
because I won't be able to do it, and that's why I did all this, right?
So, it has to be done in a healthy way.
And you have, you know, I'll ask you like this.
Some kind of marketing slogan is
all companies have become tech companies,
some are disappointed, others are not disappointed.
Do you have that feeling that these are not speakers who are disappointed,
that they are very technological organizations,
that this machine, as you said, costs 200-300 bucks,
that the data is very sensitive,
probably the most sensitive data that we all exchange,
that, I don't know, in England we saw that before the cryptovirus,
the whole hospital was closed.
Do you have that feeling that we are not doing enough
on, as I said, the education of decision-makers in these organizations?
Do we give them enough opportunities?
Are they good enough speakers?
Can they push some agenda for change?
Do we have the capacity, or are we really just going to put out fires?
Because, looking at the output that I see as a user,
I have a feeling that they are just putting out fires.
I don't know, what do you think about that?
Well, I can speak for the Novogoriška scene.
I can tell you that the service for this is excellent,
for more than 10 years.
And that it is displayed to users every year, which is great.
That everyone is asking questions,
even if the management is not as technically capable,
because it is not,
but everyone is asking questions,
they are discussing,
and so on.
I have warned about that a lot,
just like Andraš said,
don't send it to Gmail,
or don't send it to your,
or don't take a picture with WhatsApp and send it.
Let's not do that,
because we don't have much influence on that.
What we do, we don't let it go,
end-to-end encryption,
I don't know what,
we all love these platforms,
but these platforms are not ours,
we have nothing to do with them.
And once sent, it's fine,
that's the story,
it's gone now,
and we don't have much influence.
I especially emphasize this for younger users,
because now there are so many young people
who find it difficult to choose
and especially when it comes
to the use of technology,
everything is changing for them,
and they should be warned about it,
not to scare them,
I don't scare them,
but I warn them,
look,
these applications are not suitable
for this beginning,
we have other ways
to use them,
even if it is a little harder,
you will use these two clicks
and you will be told
that everything went through these platforms.
But ok, I understand,
there is a certain state in the country,
I don't know how to manage it,
ok, then people are self-organized,
they make groups,
ok, understandable,
but now we are back to normality
and let's go back,
let's correct these protocols again.
I don't have any problems with that,
but I warned about one thing,
that important services,
such as health homes,
municipalities and so on,
and in my opinion,
even if we work in the computer,
we could have a small plan B
in the case that the computer does not work,
because we don't have to be so angry
that we are not able to do
most of the analysis
that the computers do not do,
in the extreme case
and in some transitional period,
it will not be forever,
but let's say
that we are able
to work for a week
in some way,
but still satisfied,
even in the case that the computer does not work,
because I am someone,
look, I like it,
I like to work,
I try to do my best,
but attackers have 24 hours,
and I just go to sleep,
and it is not in this world
that it is so much talked about
and nothing will ever happen,
and in this scenario,
although remote,
but I hear that it can happen,
and in my opinion,
we need a day like that,
it is not that we will have
hand pumps for water,
but we also have to think
about such things,
especially if we look globally
at what is happening in the world,
the final phase,
what happened in Gartner
with the best software
for protection of computers,
what can happen
in such a company,
and where am I
in the whole Gartner?
I see
in all our public institutions
that
during
all this knowledge
is happening
through some stories
like,
I don't know,
in the hospital,
these stories
of how this happened
are actively raising
some alarms
that we need a disaster recovery plan,
because in the end,
even if you want
to close your business,
and not continue
to close it,
they will say,
okay, but have you prepared
a scenario?
As you said,
all the knowledge
is passing through time,
things are being given
to some roadmap,
the question is
if we are already there,
if we are ready,
if we are actively working on it,
but
if, I don't know,
if I use this segue,
you are also actively involved
in the Lock Shield project.
What did this project
give you,
in the sense that
you said, hey,
these are some very good practices
that I started to use myself,
because all of us
who came from there,
I won't say that we know it all,
but we had an opportunity
to see the environment,
and we were well prepared,
and we were still surprised.
What is something
that you pulled out
and said, hey, I started
to use my side,
and automatically,
it's not like that,
good practices are being used.
And before you answer,
EPP.
Let's thank our sponsors,
3FSA, Humelfrog, Caldio,
and all the Patreons that support us
in these episodes.
Before I pull out the Lock Shield,
tell us what Lock Shield is,
please, for those who don't know what it is.
That's all. Thank you.
I've never heard of it.
Andraž will help.
It's a branch
of cybersecurity,
where you train
in an environment
that is already compromised.
The environment is trying
to fix itself and defend it
against future attacks.
A bunch of countries are participating,
if I'm not mistaken,
24-25 countries,
mainly members of the NATO,
but also some members of the association
or some candidates.
It's an exceptional experience,
which was first
fascinating to me,
how much security
Slovenia has in different areas,
and how many young people
are very talented
and, I would say,
very experienced are there.
Every day,
when I returned home
after the war,
I didn't sleep in Ljubljana,
and every time I came home
I thought,
we have to do this,
we have to do this.
I prepared a lecture
at some of the conferences
where I repeated
that we don't talk
too much about security
in Serbia,
what is publicly
announced is announced,
we don't go into too much detail,
and with this lecture
I didn't touch
what would affect
the security,
but only some of the mechanisms
that we used.
I didn't say
that we don't see them
in the field.
I have been in Ljubljana
for a long time,
and I was inspired
when I saw
how the problem
started to arise,
that you are not blind
to everything,
that you see
what is going on
in all areas.
The beauty
of this field
is that there are
real attackers,
and the attackers
are actually people
who start it.
It is not a simulated
or a script,
but these people
can repeat
different things
in different hours.
In short,
you have to react
according to your abilities,
because it is also nice
that you can't carry
all your tools,
all your most expensive products
that you have,
but you work with a set
that you like.
I really like
that we try to find each other
with some experience, knowledge
and cooperation
in the final phase.
It is a very good experience
from my side.
If it is your sales
in Zamesh
in a few years,
what is the next step
when there are
smaller companies
that are getting better?
You were on the Windows 10
system,
what is the next step?
I think it is very banal
and you will say
that we still don't see this
in the companies.
One thing is that
we tried to screw up
the Windows Firewall
so that it can't be taken out
and nothing can be done.
Only those policies
that come from the central management
can be applied.
And this
drastically reduces
the potential attacker
where he can
attack.
The second thing
is logging.
We are talking about Microsoft
because I am the head
of the Microsoft conferences
in the region.
In short,
Microsoft has a very good
central logging system
that you rarely follow
and on which
you can build a system of alerting.
It is impossible
that IT doesn't know
that a new user has been created
in Active Directory
and is not aware of it.
This is a banal example,
but IT colleagues
who work in Pentest
will tell you
that when they come to the location
and ask for the news
that we have created a user
in AD.
If IT doesn't know
that a new user has been created
I think that
it is missing a lot.
I have listed two things
and there are a lot of others.
But let's start with this.
Back to basics.
Windows Fire or Windows Vista
will be better.
Let's do this to the end.
Let's do it on servers,
on clients.
You will see that
we will feel much better.
If someone wants to take
a step forward
you will be as good
as you were when you started.
People still think
that everything is inside
and we have everything.
If we stop,
we will have less trouble
because everything will work.
But then you get rid
of a lot of other problems.
Firewall is that.
I would like to ask you
this question.
You have been a teacher
for a few years now.
What did you learn?
I know that you didn't work
on Windows desktops
but you were more in
a different field.
I was in a few networks.
Now we are a bit
off-guard.
I know.
There is a lot of work
in the background.
We talked about this
a bit.
I just want to hear
on the record.
Something small.
My
full
experience
is that
if I go back
to communication
in IT,
there is too little
reasonable operation of the Internet.
People
who manage
systems,
I don't mean
Windows system,
which is the same problem
for people who manage
Linux servers,
Kubernetes,
etc.
There is too little
segmentation
or writing
firewall rules
what is allowed where.
Sometimes
people know how to write
source
with IP
from
this port
for this type of traffic
and that is a lot.
As soon as you realize
that
they are mixed
UDP, TCP
it is all the same.
There are IP addresses
with very
wildcard masks.
This is
something
that we
as people who work
in the network,
do not express
in a very strong way
that
some users or administrators
still do not know.
It is the same
as we discussed
some episodes ago
how developers
still do not understand
how the Internet works.
There are some hardcoded
words inside, etc.
This is
one of the problems
that if you realize
that
someone
who manages
firewall
must write
a traffic engineering
rule.
It is easier for me
if someone comes to me
and says
this is my type of traffic
which is legit
and it must be open
so it looks like traffic.
I can make
a strict rule.
If someone comes to me
and says I have a service
that must communicate
with a satellite on the other side
and I say
where is that satellite?
Can you show me
in a vlog
that I can do it
without those who must understand everything.
Sometimes
it is not necessary
to have a user on the other side
who will understand you.
Someone who is
a manager
or a maintainer
of a service
must understand
how things work
on that network level
what must be open
where are those
tasks to function.
I think
that
maybe
it is clear to me
and I don't have to expect
that it will be clear to you
but
on that
it is a task
that I have a feeling
that we tried in the first year
and we thought that we succeeded
and we tried in the second year
and we see if it is necessary
but it seems to me
that it is easier
to prepare
but
as Luka said
if you start
logging
and you set up some central logs
then you have a point
of reference
where you can start
looking for who did something.
If you don't have anything
to learn
it is very difficult
to be blindsided
because you don't know
what happened
because I can say
that these are tasks
that we always learn
and we always learn
how to do
very basic things
but still
I don't want to say
such a thing
like
guessing
but you have
tasks that come
with some
computers that are
default
or factory
these are tasks
that are easy
to remove
but still
my question is
do you see
that last year
there was a test
where you did
a clean install of Windows server
and you put it on the internet
and it took a long time
to complete it
in minutes
and at the same time
you installed Red Hat Linux
without Firewall
and you got it up
do you see that
Windows operating system
is getting better
that the default settings
are so
hardened
that
you have to
do some tasks
for example
I have a task
where I work
with a soft keyboard
and
I didn't give
a right to
share the screen
but my Zoom
can't share the screen
because by default
there were only two
do you see
that Windows
is getting better
or not?
Yes, definitely
in the last time
Microsoft is doing a great job
and the default settings
are closed
if we are talking
about Firewall
and you have to
open everything
later
there is an art direction
we have a festival in Gorica
where last year
there was a guy who talked about
defaultism
he said that the phone is best
installed when you come to the store
to take it
with the best sounds
and the best way to put everything
because this default
they probably overstudied
that it is the best peeling
and he talked about defaultism
and he let people
go to his Facebook account
and opened it
so that people
can go inside
and create there
in the past it was a disaster
in Windows
much worse than now
now you have a bunch of mechanisms
that are already included
or they came with some
compatibility
on different servers
if you installed RDP
brute force attack
it will lock your account
so it will warn you
that you can't log in
while you are in the console
that you have to turn it off
and that something is happening
so these things
Microsoft will take seriously
I think it is not logical
to look at the size
and impact of these attacks
that damage the whole economy
if we go back to the other two things
lock, shield
one more thing
we are doing things
that we will need
because when you are under attack
you can't deploy in the monitoring system
it will be a bit too late
and probably other resources will be wasted
this is one thing
another thing
when it comes to Windows systems
and networking
it is also an interesting thing
One day, one of my good friends, I teased him a little bit,
in that way, I called him a lot of times, and I said,
Hey, is it possible to set the IP on the server 192.168.1.0.0.0?
He said, no chance.
What, 192.168.0.0.0.0.0?
I said, no, that's not a chance.
We come to such things, when we laid out subnets,
and I said, these are just two legitimate IPs,
why can't I set them?
But for a Windows system, that's completely taboo.
Also, probably on Linux,
if you tell it where the zero is at the end of the IP,
it will look weird, in my opinion.
But, yeah, that's how I got started with it.
And I said, then I stopped, and I said,
You know, that's a senior IT guy,
he knows how to set up a Windows environment,
whatever you want, just look at it,
the network is a dot for us.
Here, too, in my opinion,
that's between us,
that network hub has always been a little bit stronger.
I have a feeling that the network wouldn't be,
or rather, the internet,
probably wouldn't be as successful as it is now,
if it was more secure in the beginning.
The question is, if it would expand so quickly,
if it would have such adoption,
if it would have so many users,
if it would have so many people.
We didn't know it was unsecure.
Everything was built on trust,
emails, sometimes you sent emails,
you went to another SMPD,
then you sent it there, then there.
If we go back to the beginning,
pure enthusiasm and good intentions.
I would like to ask a question to both senior IT people.
I recently saw on Twitter
of a very senior IT person,
and it's a beautiful screenshot
of a disk manager for a ride,
and everything is fucking red.
You can see from the color that it's a shitshow.
It says there that two thirds of the disks
went to shit.
It's a shitshow.
Be moral.
Do you want me to be moral?
OK.
Many of our colleagues probably
said what you just said,
and I agree, it's great.
But let me try to solve this real case.
How to communicate this
with your stakeholders and organizations?
That something is serious,
and we already know that
neither time nor money, la la la.
What is the value in such cases?
Something that should have been
resolved a long time ago,
something that should have been
upgraded a long time ago,
something that we will understand
100% that is very difficult.
How to communicate with stakeholders?
How to solve these problems?
Because I know that our audience
has this experience.
This is a very interesting story.
We have a security team.
We have a couple of projects
that we want to start as a security team.
We want to start with some
client-side ideas,
to some firewalls,
or some big firewalls
that you have in front of endpoints
and similar areas.
As I said, the number of projects
that I could name within security
was so large,
that in a way,
those stakeholders who gave
as if they understood it,
gave it as a gift,
but then what is needed?
We need to buy this,
we need to replace this,
we need to solve this,
but we don't listen to it,
we don't find the money.
We have a strategy,
a strategy that was so...
At some point, it seemed to me,
OK, let's not drag everything together.
We have packed everything
into this ransomware readiness.
Because we are trying
to make sure that nothing goes wrong.
So that we can do some web application security,
we can do some pentests.
Here, our audience will not be
But that's why we put it all under the roof,
so that the decision-makers understand
how this kind of attack happens.
That all the computers are simply hacked.
You have the whole company,
you can't take any action.
You come to the front page of the newspaper,
to 24 hours,
to the big media,
you are the main story.
And that's how the hacking begins.
Who will be those who will stand in front of the camera
and say, we didn't count on that,
we weren't prepared,
we didn't even have a backup.
In a way, we chose such a strategy,
because it will be one way for these people
to understand the scale,
who will come to an incident.
There are different incidents,
different types of incidents that can happen to you.
Let's say, some leakages,
some data,
so that no one can access your systems,
and possibly the data of your users,
and so on.
That was such a task,
that we started to move things in the same direction,
and we also succeeded on the board,
to get enough listening,
enough resources.
Let's say that things were still moving slowly,
but people on the other side
have actively understood the distraction,
which a security incident
can cause for itself.
And how?
I had an example,
which was more related to the organization,
and the complexity of the organization,
and the late responses.
It came to the point that,
I mean, it's not a bad or a terrible thing,
but we lost one day of work,
which is bad in every way,
and we lost a lot of time,
which is bad in every way.
It's not a bad thing,
but it was a lesson for me,
that I have to be more organized,
and when something is really critical,
I have to work harder,
even if it's not for me in the final phase,
because I was blacklisted,
I was fired twice,
and the third time,
it was for a bigger company,
and it was for a girl,
who was already out,
and she was out for three months,
so the waiter came,
and she was about to overheat,
so they put a fan in front of her,
to cool her down,
and after that,
it was still poorly documented,
and poorly connected,
so from that UPS,
it was connected to another UPS.
And on the day of the power outage,
it was Thursday,
no, it was Friday,
it was late afternoon,
and they called me,
that everything is quiet,
and I said, are you sure?
I was sick,
and I had a low fever,
and I wasn't sick,
because I had a fever of 40,
and I saw it twice.
So I thought,
why aren't you more serious?
Because it just went by,
and it was for me,
and for them as well,
because we could only go back
to the situation on Thursday night,
because the storage didn't survive,
everything was corrupted,
and so I realized,
that it's more critical,
and I'm much more vocal about it now,
I'm much more explicit when I write an email,
I say, look, from this moment on,
I don't have to take any responsibility,
because it's such a critical element,
that it's really a problem,
if it's not in the system,
as an operator.
There were some drills,
that worked out,
because in Slovenia,
I successfully wrote the documents,
and when the management said,
when are we going to do that drill,
that I'm going to turn off the UPS,
well, no.
That's why I have a company,
that needs to be repaired once a year,
and that's on Saturday,
and we're really going through that,
because there's no other way.
And until we had the aggregators,
we were still aware,
that the scripts for shutdown,
work as they should,
when you have complex systems,
but there has to be a successor,
if you want things to be healthy,
and not to rebuild 100 years later.
And in the meantime,
we did a successful shutdown,
and then we added some good chevapchiches,
and when the repairs were done,
we burned them,
and lived happily ever after.
The agreement is,
that we test it during production time,
so that when we do it on the 9th of the morning,
the aggregator starts,
and we monitor what's going on,
because we said,
this is a real scenario,
and none of the other scenarios are real,
and we have to try.
Everything is in the cloud,
if you have a datacenter,
everything is virtualized,
we're still talking about some spinning parts,
and sometimes the problem is,
that when the shutdown happens,
things don't spin anymore,
an update happens,
things don't get lost,
and the virtualized datacenter
doesn't come back.
That's why,
in this environment,
I see that the drills,
are the real scenarios,
that happened to us,
and now we solve them,
because we know how to solve them.
Does your company have some labs,
or some capacity,
so that their employees can learn,
run, test,
I know that a lot of our listeners have home labs,
I've seen beautiful pictures,
they have everything at home,
but how big is your company?
I'm interested in that.
I work with people who are crazy,
who are huge enthusiasts,
passionate about their work,
and think proactively,
and you want to create an environment
where you can play and test.
I don't know how to imagine,
that you're dealing with
an architecture of systems,
and you don't have a lab,
or an environment where you can test,
look, and so on.
When I was preparing for this project,
and I was working in our datacenter,
in the laboratory environment,
I saw a lot of gratitude from people,
who said, after the lecture,
that they can connect with the company,
that they don't want to test in real life.
Try it here, do it there,
and you'll see how things will react.
I always tell them,
if anyone wants to test anything,
send me an email,
I'm always ready to help.
This is another question,
I know it's a bit bigger,
but I love Wi-Fi,
and I think you're the same,
and a very specific Wi-Fi,
not the home Wi-Fi,
where you set a point,
and you both decided at some point,
that you, as a student,
you both decided at some point,
that you'll set up city-wide wireless access,
can you both tell me a bit more,
why did you want to set up your wireless,
what did you learn from it,
because it seems to me,
I don't know if it works today,
maybe it will fix it,
I don't know if it was a new technology,
but why did you give the city Wi-Fi?
I was impressed,
when I was in Nizozemsk,
I saw these squatters,
who squat some old houses,
and usually this house
without water, electricity,
and somehow internet,
and that's how these people
solve this problem,
and they connect some aggregates,
or they connect some electricity,
and that's where they get the internet.
And this sharing,
where you don't just switch
to a neighbor's access point,
and the internet starts there,
but these communities,
which exist in the city,
I found it very interesting,
because it was used
on a very simple device,
but not here,
there was a Linksy 54GL.
Was it used for domestic use?
It was used for shopping.
There were a lot of these routers in Linksy,
you could flash them,
and there was a bunch of
Linkstate routing protocols,
which enabled you to create
some kind of mesh,
which connected to each other,
and there was a pretty large
routing table,
so that you could access
the other end of the city
And you created the mesh
only with the domestic routers?
Yes, of course,
you could modify the antenna,
so that it had a better range,
there was also a DIY scene,
where you could learn
how to make antennas,
and a little bit of radio engineering.
It was a pretty simple approach,
how to make a signal
connected to one end
of the city to the other,
and that was it.
Let's go to the revolution,
let's share the internet
to someone on the other end of the city.
Is that how it works now?
I had a great project,
which I started in Ljubljana,
and I got a lot of enthusiasts,
who climbed on the roofs
and installed it,
but the times were different,
so you have to understand
that there was no LTE,
so that you could go
to a broadband internet.
There were some first optics,
where people had a broadband internet,
but...
But where did the traffic go?
You had the opportunity
to have the internet,
you installed a router
next to the access points,
and you shared your internet,
but no one had access to the internet.
Today, it is very unimaginable,
we still need this kind of wireless,
because when you take your phone out,
everyone gives you some data transfer
with enough capacity
that you don't need it anymore.
I imagine that in some rural areas,
where you have more experience,
people still drink water.
You know what,
I heard about their project
in Ljubljana and Slovenia,
and I probably heard something
about CyberPIP.
We started in the same way,
NWRT 54G was at the club of students,
and we had a multimedia center there,
students had a bar,
we gave them a bar,
and then we started to share it.
It was a bit different than in Ljubljana,
we didn't hack Linux,
but we connected those points
to the existing access points.
The point was connected to a central point
on the Internet,
and we were afraid that if someone
would do something stupid in a bar,
like a deliberate activity,
the owner of the bar would be in trouble,
and the point would be in the trash.
That's why we decided
to go through a central point
where we will connect,
ULAN Novogorica celebrates its 20th anniversary this year,
and there are 500 points,
500 routers, which is a lot.
I learned a lot from that.
About 17,000 devices are connected per day,
not on purpose, of course,
but it's still an impressive number.
And about 100-150 megabits,
we vary it by a second,
if you are at the central point.
When we had the Technical Culture Day,
some students came,
and we were talking about local Wi-Fi,
and I didn't care who was using it.
It was a great experience for me,
I'm 20 years old,
and I don't think anyone can take it away from me.
But I learned a lot.
If you don't have an operator,
you don't have it.
But you already have some kind of operator status?
No, no, no.
That should be regulated at some point.
The truth is,
nobody cares about it,
or nobody cares about it as much as you do.
It would be nice if young people would take it away,
and young people would say,
yes, we use it all.
I was worried that packages would be overpriced,
that it would be obsolete,
but it's not like that.
Those students told me,
yes, I only have 2 GB,
and I'm on Wi-Fi all the time.
And I believe that a segment of the population
doesn't care about the price of those packages.
Especially in vulnerable groups,
like the elderly and young people.
In short, using it is great,
so it makes me happy.
And the fact that they don't pay anything,
is it purely open?
No, it's purely open.
In 2012-2013, we had a captive portal,
which was a greeting at the beginning.
You were greeted at the New York airport,
but then you moved on.
But when people started using messenger platforms,
I decided to remove it.
People are connected now,
but they didn't click on the I agree button,
and the messenger is stuck there.
For some time, I tried to whitelist it,
but it was difficult with the technologies available in 2013.
Maybe today, with a next-generation firewall,
it would work,
but I have to make sure that it doesn't eat up
my life plan.
Wait, you're saying you have 500 devices?
You know what they used to tell me?
Our access point,
we have 2 access points,
and one day, a girl came up to me and said,
you know what, you give everyone the Internet,
but you don't give us Wi-Fi at home.
It's not OK.
I have an access point on both sides,
facing the public,
because I think it's cool
to protect the spirit of some community.
People either can't access it,
or they're stuck on it.
Do you flash those devices?
Yes.
Do you have a group that helps you?
Once, I was on a...
What's it called?
Sinok.
Yes, Sinok.
I said, I'm the only one talking.
At the beginning,
we were a big student club.
Together, we worked on the computer,
but in the end, I was left alone with it.
Give us more about those devices.
Is it a low-end router?
Do you give it to someone at home,
and then you connect it to an antenna?
It's very different.
which had Wi-Fi in them, most of the points were like that.
And I took it to the bar and said,
look, you just flip it over, they'll give you a steering wheel here,
we'll spread it, I don't know.
In the meantime, I asked them how wide they were,
and they said, I don't know, 20 megas,
and I said, okay, we'll turn 10 megas QoS up,
and people will have 10 megas to surf.
And so the points grew over time,
all those routers came together,
then it went bankrupt, I don't know,
some bar closed,
they took it all out,
they changed it, and they threw it in the trash,
they don't know why.
Those MikroTiks were a bit worse at the time,
they looked like some kind of fire-fighting system.
But anyway,
there are about 500 left,
which are still being made.
Those MikroTiks,
then later I started adding
some second-hand CISCO access points
to that router, so I had better radio.
Because MikroTik is a cool routing device,
WPN and all that stuff, QoS, no problem,
but it's a bit shabby on the radio part,
especially the older ones.
And then I started buying
those second-hand CISCOs,
which are much better than that,
and I started adding them from the side,
and that's how it is,
then I really did it.
So technically,
you mean,
it's some kind of WPN,
you use WPN,
and what kind of type?
All sorts,
just to turn it inside out.
So, you support everything.
Yes, I mean,
we have a point on the local offer
of KT Novogorica,
which I also participate in,
and we are ready to
add that business-wide.
And this router
will receive that WPN from all sides,
and then
the market will be honest.
I don't know why,
but it sounds like a bad idea.
I mean, at that time,
people were
buying everything,
drugs, whatever.
We had an episode
where someone set up a tour
because he wanted to share
his internet,
and he had a hard time with that,
because of his IP.
Absolutely.
There are definitely
vegans out there,
and there are a lot of
vegans in the lobby,
but we can't sell
drugs or mercury
because of that.
I mean, I count on people's kindness,
and if something happens...
You don't record
any incidents that would...
In those 20 years,
maybe it was twice,
but it still turned out
to be more...
Spamming.
There was a forum,
and someone was arrested,
and then there were some protests.
In short, there are more things like that.
I agree,
this is becoming more
vegan than ever,
and the question is
if this will continue
in the future.
Even if there won't be
any episode,
it's been a long time.
20 years is still
not a long time.
You can cut it off now,
and no one will notice.
Did people thank you back then?
Did people know that this was happening to you?
Those who knew,
I assume they were grateful.
The guys who
recently did that,
they were like, really?
You know what?
Times have changed.
Today, you can't tell someone
what kind of person they are.
What is he doing?
Why is he doing this?
It's very unusual in today's world.
But you know what?
There is a chance that
this will be normal one day,
and we won't have to ask.
You probably also
learned a lot,
that this was
a playground
where you learned a lot.
I assume you also
automated a lot of things.
You were able to quickly
see what works and what doesn't.
Absolutely.
That's another point.
If you work
in a certain environment,
you return something to it.
I think that's better for everything.
Yes.
That's also
one of the things
that Otto added
to this podcast.
We are here because we have
enough time in this industry
to return something.
I think it's impossible
to approach people
who are very experienced.
Our goal is
to try to be a fence
through which we can
transfer knowledge to the next generation.
Maybe we will record it
so that it will survive for a long time
and people will be able to see it.
If they are
senior people,
it's clear to them.
It's a no-brainer.
They want to understand
why they need a platform
to be able to transfer it.
I think I could
summarize our episode
to the end.
I also had a question about
why Loki had such a huge antenna.
I don't know what he gave it to me,
but he had an antenna under his nose.
When he came inside the office,
he saw the same antenna.
I can't deny that.
I think it was in the city of Ljubljana.
I don't know where it was directed.
It was an antenna in the city of Ljubljana.
There was always a problem
when there was a message on Saturday.
When the messages were sent,
the access point was turned off.
It was a problem.
It was the best location.
You can't go back to the beginning.
You can't physically go back
to the beginning.
I would like to sum up
the last episode.
The last episode.
I would like to add
one more thing.
You bring back
so many things
from the community work.
I was very impressed
when you posted on LinkedIn
that you have a workshop
for children.
Where is this passion?
I would say,
OK, I have my own child.
You want to reach
your children in some way.
But it works
with young people.
It is a transfer.
Where is this energy?
OK,
young people
bring back a lot of things.
As an example,
it is a law for me
that we taught them
how to drive a 7-seater.
I would say,
we put this in Docker.
We are all with a console cable.
I would say,
we are all in a wheelchair.
We are all in a wheelchair
with a console.
These workshops touch the surface
of all these things,
but we treat them as if they are big.
As if they are grown-ups.
We work on real equipment.
If five engineers
will come from this, it will be great.
I would like them to take this into account
from a broad perspective.
To know that it is not only art
how the Internet comes to their homes.
That we went to see the sewage system.
That we went to see the data center.
That we showed them
that it is not like that.
That there are some instructions
that manage it.
If you want,
there must be a flow.
We brought a server to the data center.
We moved some monitoring systems there.
They brought a typewriter home.
Then they engraved their temperatures.
Then we set up a VoIP center.
They brought their phones home.
They called each other in the evening.
It must exist if you want it to work.
They are not masters for Cisco.
They are not masters for MicroTik.
But they know it.
They have seen it.
We don't have to erase it.
They know where it comes from.
Hyper-V was so expensive
that they don't even watch
how they create a virtual machine.
Now that he knows what virtualization is,
he can work on VMware, Proxmox,
Hyper-V, whatever.
Now he knows it.
He never forgets it.
He doesn't erase it.
That's great.
Let's wrap it up.
Where do you find...
I have a feeling
that those of us
who meet today
with the young generation
entering our industry,
they are not interested.
They don't know.
They would pay a lot.
They would be in a director's position.
They don't feel
that sometimes
you have to grind something.
You have to do it.
Do you feel the same?
Or is it just
a burning desire
for young people
to be more interested
in these things?
Two things.
First, the older ones,
when they see that I publish it,
they get to know me,
they know that I work with enthusiasm.
They are like,
where have you been?
I will show you something.
I use them,
today they are more instant.
They want it all instant.
That's why I designed
the program From Zero to Hero.
They come in,
they don't know anything about Cisco.
They click in the console
and see what we have changed.
They are excited about the success.
We try to make
all these things
so that they are modular
and that they go from zero to hero.
When he is awarded
that he succeeded,
it motivates him to move forward.
I will use the same
principles they have.
If you publish CCCNA all year long,
by the end of the year
there will be only one position.
They will go home and won't come back.
If it's logical.
You try to make it
this way.
For example,
we will make a hotspot today.
What is a hotspot?
When you go to Wi-Fi,
you open a portal.
We have our own point,
we go with the phone up,
we surf the law.
Now let's make a hotspot.
Let's write your name and welcome.
Then you say,
I was at home when my friends came.
He brings a micro-stick
and has a hotspot
for his friends.
Now he learned the hotspot.
He knows how it works.
What is on the flyer?
Then his friends
mounted a micro-stick
and moved the hotspot.
If you sing them in this way,
they like it.
They are motivated
and they like it.
From somewhere
it is a skill
how to work
in some training.
How to
pour
and how to have
the engagement.
Is it a trial and error?
Yes, absolutely.
Is it a trap?
Yes, it is.
Exactly.
Two things are changing
in the history context.
When I was a student,
it was a different audience.
Today,
children are different people.
But you can always
motivate them.
Someone has been coming to us for 5 years
and I told him,
you are a mentor,
I have nothing to teach you.
You can start doing real things,
but you will be a mentor.
You will start teaching
and you will come to us
and go further.
I am not interested
in doing this until the end of my life.
I am interested in
mentoring people and
start cycling further.
Start with new technologies,
new things, programming.
We broke it on modules this year.
We have different modules, different areas.
It is great.
I don't have anything to add.
I just want you to save energy
and the spark you definitely have.
On behalf of the community,
thank you for your efforts.
Thank you too.
It is a great honor for me
to be your guest in Grodno.
I respect you and you do a great job.
Thank you very much.
At this point,
thank you, Luka,
for your time
and for hosting us here.
Thank you very much.
I think
you are giving a lot.
A lot.
With a spark.
I have a feeling
that people in this industry,
in our industry,
are lacking in their own way.
There is a lot of cynicism,
negativity,
something is not allowed.
When we first met,
I thought
you are really
doing a great job.
Thank you.
If you like it,
please subscribe and share.
Support us on Patreon.
Thank you for being with us.
See you next time.
Maybe next year.
Yes, next year.
I could sell something.
Both of them.
Thank you.
You