What do you think about 9mm in your home country?
Here it is, we're here. What did you ask him, if he has a 9mm at home or what?
Where are you now, in Texas or what?
I've been in Texas for three and a half years.
Austin, but Austin is completely...
Austin is completely different from Texas.
Austin is in Texas.
It is in Texas, but Austin is...
It's the main city in Texas.
It's completely European, isn't it?
It's a liberal oasis in the middle of the real America.
But are they all armed or just those who protect the country?
Most of them are, you just don't know.
Can you carry a hidden weapon?
You can carry it, but only if you need a license.
Otherwise, no.
Otherwise, you have it at home.
Okay, okay.
Greetings to all our listeners.
Today, Andraž and I invited a special guest to the episode of Grodno.
In Slovenia, we call him Mike, but here they call him Miha,
because people know him better.
He's more unique.
Now, Mike is known in Slovenia for his passionate love for Ruby.
And I'm afraid that today you will also speak Ruby,
like the language of the future.
I wanted to introduce him to our audience,
to tell them about your journey from Slovenia to Tuin,
where you've been for 15 years now.
To tell us that it's a place for good engineering,
and how engineers can succeed in this world.
To share your story with us.
That's the idea of today's conversation.
Did I forget something?
I wanted to say that today we're not sitting in the office,
like we usually do in Grodno.
Yes, we can say that.
Today, in our traditional office,
where we usually don't have so much heat,
we looked for a studio,
and Kaldi hosted us today,
and we're now in front of them.
So, thank you, Kaldi.
Yes.
First of all, Miha and I were in elementary school,
so I've been preparing for a while.
Miha is a server engineer,
and Miha is an orc,
because Miha started working with a website,
when we didn't know what a website was.
So, first of all, can you tell us
how Miha started playing with PHP and web servers?
Yes.
Before PHP, there was HTML, CSS,
and before all that, Visual Basic.
I don't know exactly what kind of order, but yes.
That was when I was in elementary school.
I always had a computer with me,
because my dad used a computer,
and I was at home with a computer.
I used to play some games,
but I never really got into them,
and I also liked to create things.
And yes, I really liked the front page,
if I remember correctly,
because the front page was from Microsoft.
And it was like, what you see is what you get,
because there was a word for HTML 9.
And that's where I started playing.
I was the first one to register,
I already had some MihaRebenik.com,
and I have a really bad memory for a long time,
but I remember that Revija Pil,
which was in Slovenia, had some...
That still exists.
That Pil still exists.
But at that time it had, I don't know what,
some kind of a trend, a split page,
I don't know, I don't know.
In general, I didn't register,
and I didn't win anything, but...
That's how I started playing with PHP,
because HTML was so static,
and I was looking at those URLs,
and they had some questions in them,
and something could change,
and I didn't know what was going on.
And so I discovered PHP,
and it was great.
Watch out, you'll jump over the fence,
and you'll get eaten.
Yes, yes.
Yes, PHP was great.
It was the ultimate hacker tool.
You just typed something,
it was like HTML,
it's called full...
forgiving, right?
You can...
you can forget something,
and someone else did everything.
So to start with, yes,
it was great.
At what point did you realize
that it's a medium,
that it's a tool
with which you can communicate with the world?
I think that's really important,
that underlying message,
and how it helped you in your projects.
Yes.
I don't know.
I mean,
I don't know if I was actually studying
like that at the time,
now that I look back,
but I can say that I discovered,
yes, once I created my own
MikesRDG site,
which was like a local Facebook
for my group,
in a broader sense.
You know,
there were albums,
and some stories,
and pictures,
and yes,
at the time,
I realized,
ah,
there's something here,
that's really cool.
You had a bit of influence
from that,
you know,
like a geek,
you all...
And that with Velenja.
Yes.
That's...
That's the voice
we don't have to hide.
Yes.
Let me just say,
maybe in this chapter,
in my...
Now you have Stack Overflow,
now you have GPTA,
and all those videos,
and the whole building process,
and all the crazy stuff.
How did you learn
to compile your Apache,
your PHP,
your Linux kernel?
I told you,
I have a bad memory.
No, but...
It's different,
how do you perceive,
I don't know,
maybe that
learning process,
how did you get
to some knowledge,
for example,
what does it look like today?
Yes, yes, yes.
I mean,
at one point,
I was reading a book,
The Unix Bible.
Yes.
I mean,
sometimes things
just develop a bit slower,
and you can read books.
So that was...
Otherwise,
I think the biggest thing
was just cleaning up,
experimenting.
I mean,
that Unix Bible,
for example,
gave you enough knowledge
to be able to do,
I don't know,
man,
and then you changed
the domain or whatever,
and...
Yes.
I think that
it's like some...
like a...
like a finder or something,
where I had
endless time,
and...
I don't know,
I was reading,
typing,
formatting on the computer
every few days,
and so on.
And do you think
that maybe,
like,
if you compare
those times,
that now there's
so much technology,
that it's really hard
to be up to date,
or are you so
involved in some,
I don't know,
let's say,
from a project,
a family,
to...
to a regular job,
that you don't find
that...
Yes,
I mean,
at the moment,
it's really my insight,
probably when you're older,
when you have
some other obligations.
But,
in a different way,
it's easier
to fake it
till you make it
in the network,
right?
Because,
because stack overflow
is great,
but, for example,
now those GPTs
are stack overflow
on steroids,
right?
Because,
in fact,
not only does it try
to find the right answer for you,
but it also customizes it
exactly for you
so,
if you try to
set something up
quickly,
it's much,
much easier now,
right?
Well,
but I'm looking
through this prism
that,
because you went
in that direction,
right?
In fact,
those foundations
for you
are probably
much better set
than,
I don't know,
someone who
wants to come
quickly,
right?
And all this,
I think,
I've noticed
that I won't
be able to
do that,
right?
Because people
come from fax
and they know
some things
much better
than I do,
maybe,
I don't know,
some very specific
algorithms or
something like that,
but they've never
set up a DNS
server,
right?
Or something like
that,
and they also
know the theory,
but it's not
the same as
you said,
right?
If I played,
it was fun
to have my
friends there,
and you get to know
them so deeply,
you never forget
them and,
yeah,
they're really
in their foundations.
So,
that self-taught
aspect,
I think,
all universities
are probably
great,
I didn't finish
the computer
studies at
the university,
so...
Because you
got into work
too quickly
and stuff like that?
Yeah,
yeah,
too much,
I mean,
I think that's
the thing
that made me
happy.
I can't
explain
why,
why not.
I mean,
my experience
is that
no one
asked me
about
any paper,
you know,
you're...
Yeah,
not yet.
Maybe
next year
when they
say,
Andraž,
where's
your diploma
from Unix?
Yeah,
yeah,
I was
so surprised
when I saw it,
even for me
that exclamation
happens when
you make a connection
like that.
A person
compiled Linux,
a person
compiled Apache,
Alok waited
for hours
to get
this configuration
flag and
then you
have to
go back.
But in
some way
it just
seems like
it's also
part of
that charm,
that call,
to learn,
to expand,
you know,
you don't
appreciate it
if you're
really just
on that
block.
No,
that story
that,
you know,
I had
a mechanic
who went
to fix
my washing machine
and then
you get
someone
so passionate
when he
disassembles
you and
starts to
disassemble,
that's
such a
motor that
it's
like,
you know,
it's
scary,
like,
OK,
let's just
talk about
the washing machine.
And then
you also
have people
who deal
with oldtimers,
cars,
you know,
and it's
pretty much
the same
with people
whose
work
screws
from the
server
to,
you know,
a complex
thing.
And
I think
that
when you
were
younger,
you were
prepared
to
forget
the time
and,
you know,
computers
are like
that,
sometimes
you really
screw
them up
and
you dig
yourself
out of
the mess
and
when
you're
years
old,
you have
to
still have
probably
the
feeling
that
you're
going to
die
and
you're
going to
die
and
you're
going to
die
and
you're
going to
die
and
you're
going to
die
and
you're
going to
die
and
you're
going
to
die
and
you're
going
to
die
and
you're
going
to
die
and
you're
going
to
die
and
you're
going
to
die
and
then
you're
going
to
die
and
you're
going
to
die
and
you're
going
to
die
and
you're
going
to
die
and
you're
going
to
die
and
you're
going
to
die
and
you're
going
destined
I
should
die
it wasn't
made
and
it
was
destined
and
you
should
die
and
you
should
die
you
should
die
but
it
shouldn't
have
to
be
destined
my
first
life
it
was
destined
and
you
should
die
but
it
shouldn't
have
to
be
destined
my
first
life
it
should
be
destined
my
first
life
it
should
be
destined
my
first
life
it
should
be
destined
my
first
life
it
should
be
destined
my
first
life
it
should
be
destined
my
first
life
it
should
be
destined
my
first
life
it
should
be
destined
my
first
life
it
should
be
destined
my
first
life
it
should
be
destined
my
first
life
it
should
be
destined
my
first
life
it
should
be
destined
my
first
life
it
should
be
destined
my
first
life
it
should
be
destined
my
first
life
it
should
be
destined
my
first
life
it
should
be
destined
my
first
life
destiny
my
first
life
it
should
be
destined
my
first
life
it
shouldn't
be
destined
my
first
life
it
should
be
destined
my
first
life
it
should
be
destined
my
first
life
it
should
be
destined
my
first
life
it
should
be
destined
my
жд
never
will
be
destined
my
first
life
mine
it
was
presumed
it
should
be
destined
my
first
life
it
should
be
destined
my
first
life
mine
it
was
presumed
it
should
be
destined
my
first
life
mine
it
should
be
destined
my
first
life
mine
it
should
be
destined
mine
it
should
be
destined
my
first
life
it
should
be
destined
my
first
life
mine
it
should
be
destined
my
first
life
mine
it
should
be
destined
my
first
life
mine
it
should
be
destined
your
second
life
mine
it
should
be
destined
mine
it
should
be
destined
your
second
life
mine
it
should
be
destined
your
third
life
mine
it
should
be
destined
your
fourth
life
mine
it
should
be
destined
your
fifth
life
mine
it
should
be
destined
your
sixth
life
mine
it
should
be
destined
your
seventh
life
mine
it
should
be
destined
your
eighth
life
mine
it
should
be
destined
your
ninth
life
mine
it
should
be
destined
your
tenth
life
mine
it
should
be
destined
your
twelfth
life
mine
it
should
be
destined
your
thirteenth
life
mine
it
should
be
destined
your
last
life
mine
it
should
be
destined
your
tenth
life
mine
it
should
destined
your
tenth
life
mine
it
should
be
destined
your
tenth
life
mine
it
should
be
destined
your
life
mine
it
should
be
destined
your
tenth
life
mine
it
should
be
destined
your
tenth
life
because
it
should
be
the
tenth
life
for
yours
as
mine
it
should
be
destined
your
tenth
life
mine
it
should
be
destined
your
tenth
life
for
mine
it
should
be
destined
your
tenth
life
for
mine
we
should
be
destined
yours
tenth
life
mine
it
should
be
destined
your
tenth
life
mine
it
should
be
destined
yours
it
should
be
destined
ours
it
should
be
destined
yours
it
should
be
deserved
it
should
be
destined
yours
it
should
be
destined
yours
it
should
be
destined
yours
it
should
be
destined
yours
it
should
be
destined
But still so painful for girls, you should put
self-hosted
No
I mean, Rails was so painful that it was built by Heroku
but on the other hand
because it was Heroku, it probably succeeded in a lot of Rails projects
because it couldn't be otherwise
I think that's how the system grows, with Heroku
Now I asked Ruby and Rails
programmers who still
program in Ruby in Slovenia
and in Slovenia there is a Ruby Meetup group Slovenia
rug.cs, on the other hand, is getting even better
the team with Kristof Črnjivac was activated again
Now they gave me a few questions from Ruby
I can put them here in the corner if you want
Or with that drop, that organic one.
I don't know if I want to talk about it now or...
Those guys are always interested in why they chose Ruby.
Why did they choose Ruby?
And all those guys who prepared that question for me,
knew that Ruby, the author of Ruby Cats,
he said that the mission of Ruby is to create a language that would make programmers happy.
To make them happy and satisfied.
And that's some kind of, as you said before, some kind of cultural awareness,
or some kind of culture that comes together.
And some vibe.
That's what drives me now, right?
That you're among happy programmers.
A little hippie scene, you hear?
I'm going to look at the next car when I get home and say,
hey, let's start a Ruby project.
But it's not far from the truth.
I've always enjoyed the fact that only IRB,
Interactive Ruby, Command Line Interface for Ruby,
and I don't know, I had some data,
convert it to CSV, sort it,
just the syntax, everything that's written.
And you don't forget it.
That also tells me that it's really something natural.
And Rails was a pure extension of that.
It was exactly built on that happiness.
People say that everything converges in Python.
Well, go!
It's hard to say, right?
But...
How do you feel about that?
Is Ruby still a valid option?
Is Rails still a valid option?
Because if we go back to those projects that you mentioned,
like Split and Open Source,
Split was different when Open Source was developed than it is today.
There was no such thing as a mobile app,
there was no mobile web development to the extent
that server-side rendering was...
You couldn't do anything else, right?
You couldn't do anything else, yes.
But how do you see that?
As far as those technologies are concerned,
I try to be very pragmatic and agnostic.
I think that when people say what's better, what's that,
it doesn't matter at all.
If you can find the right solution for your problem,
you can use it.
And sometimes the problem is different at the beginning than later,
or when the company is bigger and so on.
And from that, I would say directly that...
Yes, Ruby and Rails are definitely, for some things,
probably still the right choice.
Maybe later you have to rewrite, but...
But you can't...
I think you can't always, at the beginning,
sometimes not because the investment would be too big
to choose something else,
sometimes you don't know,
or you don't know, or the project will fail.
Maybe you'll be able to cancel it in half a year
because you didn't find a partner.
And you, why would you need a year
to be fully architectured, with a full language?
I mean, I don't really understand,
that Ruby for this...
Also for this MWP,
it's good enough,
it allows you to get to a certain result quickly.
And then there are the details,
whether to still run it on Ruby,
or work on rewriting.
Yes, I would say that it's an example.
I think it's probably a very good example,
precisely because you can prototype quickly,
you can iterate quickly.
And that's the most important thing
when you're doing a business,
you have to adapt quickly
and develop things.
You'll solve the scaling problem
when it's a scaling problem.
But do you think that,
as we said before,
this well-known video about DHH
represents Rails?
At that time,
Rails as a tool
had certain
convention, over-configuration,
certain assumptions,
certain decisions,
the market needed such a framework.
Today, I think,
it's harder to say
what the market needs
for some MWP prototypes.
Maybe TypeScript
should be bundled in the framework?
Or not?
Are all new projects with TypeScript?
Probably not.
Maybe Javascript?
There are some hard assumptions,
I don't know,
for such projects
which are already
in the company,
I don't remember now.
37signals.
My question is
is the toolbox
or the framework
today a real checkbox
for things?
I don't have an answer,
so I wonder what you think.
I won't say I have an exact answer.
The caveat for the last Rails
was 4signal, now it's 7signal.
But I would say
probably yes.
Because again,
I mean,
even if you make a product
which can be
real-time and use
some 3D browser,
vector apps,
for example Figma,
sure, you can't use Rails.
But for 90%
of some things, you can still use it.
Even if you make
a web app
which is extremely UI-heavy,
a daily app,
Pages, Word,
whatever, you can't use Rails.
But for whatever,
there is a base
and some information which you will present
in 100,000 ways,
you can probably start with Rails.
How far will you go?
That's a question.
Now, the convention over configuration,
I don't know.
This philosophy always suited me.
Because I strived
that again, 90%
of products are identical
and have identical needs.
D.A. Chech said
that you are not a snowflake.
I strive with that.
Rarely someone is so unique.
It's true that engineers
know things, tweak things,
it's all fully valid.
But for something
which was marketed as
getting things done,
convention over configuration,
that's it.
But if you look
at the jobs
at the moment,
to record Rails,
to look for Rails developers,
or Ruby developers,
some new products
and so on.
In a way, you see
that it's a trend
set by big players
like JSO,
Go,
etc.
Python.
Python is
now this
numbering
problem.
AI and so on.
It's all
connected to that.
When I first looked at Python,
I chose Python
instead of Ruby.
Because
you can't be similar to anything.
Python doesn't have Django.
I was even before that.
When I started,
I was even before
Python.
Usually, whenever Unix
was launched, I was almost
a year old. Python needs
some time to grow.
But yeah.
I think that
Ruby is still
in that trend,
but those
who know,
will take Ruby,
and won't rely on some trends.
We can ask
a counter question.
You worked a lot
with Ruby and Rails.
Did you have a use case
when you came to
another project,
like C-Sharp
or Java, and said
fucking shit, man.
It was easier with Ruby.
Yeah.
I said, fuck, I have to
go through that door.
No, no.
You weren't in that situation?
No, I wasn't, but I was definitely
in a situation where
in my last Ruby project,
which we can talk about later,
you definitely
don't do that in Rails.
You don't even start that in Rails.
Yeah.
That, and type safety.
I'm a big fan of type safety.
I think you have
someone with type script
or something that C-Sharp
or something.
Yeah.
What you said,
about the trends,
yeah, you're right.
Ruby had a short
heyday, maybe
when I went to Silicon Valley,
it was at the top
among trendy languages
and companies were looking for that.
But trends are trends.
Just like
you need a tool for the job.
You can choose what you need.
Things have gone forward
in the React ecosystem and JavaScript.
I think that
in general,
Ruby is fully object-oriented.
If you write
functional Ruby,
people will return your pull requests.
And the listeners
among us
are the listeners who returned
the pull requests we wrote
to the functional Ruby.
I could see it.
Can you say something about that?
I think it's a trend
to have a functional approach,
a strongly type functional
language.
Maybe that's why it got less popular.
I don't know.
But for me,
maybe because I grew up with it,
but it was very natural
to me.
You can fully apply it
to a lot of different domains
and you can model things.
In the end,
people
want to use it.
No,
we're too much into it.
Let's go to the next chapter.
Today,
let's talk about YC.
I will try
to make an intro.
When I was preparing
for this episode,
I went to the RTV Slovenia archive
to see
your story with YCM.
Your story with YCM.
It says that
YC is the most elite
and respected incubator
in the world,
in San Francisco.
Paul Graham has been leading it
for a hundred years.
It's an incubator from which
Dropbox,
Airbnb, Coinbase,
Reddit,
and probably
for some time
a lot of tech companies
from all over the world
that are billion-dollar companies
have been in there.
Together with Robert Farazino,
Rock Gregorić,
Rock Rulc,
I probably forgot someone,
in 2011,
2012,
you applied
to your company
at YC and you were accepted
as the first Slovenian team.
I think that after that
two or three Slovenian teams
were accepted, but you were
the first Slovenian team.
Oral is the only one.
And you came there.
Now,
according to some statistics,
I would like to illustrate
what this event means.
Some 10,000 companies
apply twice a year,
and in the summer they accept
1.5 to 3%
depending on what comes in
from all over the world.
And yes, you were accepted.
Now,
on RTVE,
when people ask
what do you suggest
people to watch,
it's a full achievement.
Because of that,
I think you got a lot of opportunities
and that's why you should watch it.
Now, I'm curious,
what happened in 2011?
What did you do
with the team
to come here today
and tell us what happened?
I think we should go back to 2010.
After those
opening hours,
I got to know...
Those opening hours were interesting.
The Slovenian ecosystem
helped in one way or another.
For example, I met Roka Gregorić
and Robert Farazin there.
Both of you helped
with some things.
Once, when we were
heading home
from a meeting
where we work,
I went with Robert
back to Maribor
and they said they were starting a project
and they needed a web guy.
They had everything covered,
but they didn't have a web guy.
So, I went to check it out.
At the time, they had a whole office.
I went to check it out
and they were cool.
I didn't care
what they wanted to do.
That was
my topic
because at the end of the day,
it's not that important.
It's more important
who is there
and give them some energy.
What did we do?
At the beginning, there was a product called M-Matcher.
It's not a big
media record,
but we wanted to
create an SMS marketplace
where
we would create an early version
of a matching.
I would sell bananas,
he would buy a seed,
and he would know it could match.
The technology was an interesting problem.
We could create
relevance, scoring,
and we had our own algorithms.
I created a web app,
then we had SMS services.
That was the first time
we applied to YSE.
Probably 20 times already.
That wasn't a problem.
We got
a second prize,
a second place,
at a Nokia event in London.
Those were the scenes.
Your goal was
to get some
funds,
some capital,
to strengthen the business,
or
to look for
a way
to open
a door of recognition
in Tuin.
Everything you created,
probably, in the first place,
requires some capital,
to escalate things,
or distribution,
or recognition.
Back then, we were
like IP2 in Slovenia.
We were
a young company,
we needed some income
to survive.
Those were
different motivations.
YSE was a motivation,
and then the next league.
Everything changed.
You go to an American market,
American investors,
and it's something else.
It was like Hail Mary.
But look,
if you like it, you like it.
If you don't try,
we were a good team,
the product was what it was,
and we tried.
It didn't work.
There are more rounds.
You apply to YSE,
you get a letter,
a video call,
we didn't make it through.
But at some point,
when we decided,
we said,
this is not it.
Maybe YSE would be the main reason.
But we let it be,
and we started doing double recall.
Maybe everyone knows that.
For a while,
on most of the Slovenian portals,
we were
trying to reach
the American market.
For those who don't know what it was,
it was a way
to pay for yourself.
You don't watch
only banners,
but you engage with yourself.
You had a picture,
and you could re-write it.
It could be a BMW,
You dedicated more time.
That's why we agreed
that it was worth
it.
The advertiser doesn't have to pay more.
It could be a micro-payment
for an article.
You got an ad.
It was a BMW.
There was a window
where you could re-write
on the picture.
You got more engagement
from the viewer.
Awareness.
Not the case
with banners,
but it could be
something else.
That's why we developed
our own ad server,
our own Captcha system,
and a library
where you could publish
the plug-and-play notes.
We also
did business development.
We had
a 24-hour magazine
and other sites.
There was also
some revenue.
Then we applied
to YC.
And it went
a bit better.
I think
our hypothesis was
that they liked
the market we tried
and that we went out
and that we had some income.
Maybe it was only a month.
But...
It's something else.
It's a topic
that I've been thinking about.
If you don't launch something
that is cool and doesn't
care about you,
and doesn't give you a single euro,
you'll never know anything.
Anyway...
In the beginning
of 2012,
we did
a personal interview
and we were told
that we could come in.
And it was like that.
YC went through a lot of evolution.
They either
expanded
or tried
new things and structures.
They took
only 30 companies
for half a year.
We were the first batch
and then doubled.
There were 60 companies in the batch.
There was a rule
that you could come to Silicon Valley
for 3 months.
They gave you a minimum
of 15-25 euros.
You could be there for 3 months
and go to office hours
and talk to people.
At the end, there was a demo day.
It was in front of investors
and YC knew that
they have a huge circle of
respected investors
and that they could see
their projects.
At the time,
there was almost no reason
not to get an investment.
YC was such a filter
that people were like,
whatever.
Just because you're already in it,
you have a lot of potential.
In this process,
you got an investment.
What else
did they give you?
Mentorship?
Before we talk about mentorship,
let me ask you something.
What else did you have to say
about the applications?
In the ICO application form,
there was a big drop
but it changed a lot
over the years.
What are they looking for?
Let's start with you.
I don't remember the details
but I know
what people are looking for.
The whole thing is
people are important,
ideas and everything else is not.
If you have top people
who are capable,
who want to do something,
if there is no first idea,
there will be a second or third.
Most of the questions I got
were about the team's background,
how the team gets to know each other.
You can record yourself
and present yourself.
For us,
the main thing
was that
they saw us
from Slovenia,
ambitious people.
The team,
not the individual,
but the synergy
between you
and the energy
of the team.
That's the main thing.
I know that at the ICO
you can present yourself
at the beginning
without an idea
and at the end
it was different.
It's totally normal.
How long was the incubation period?
Three months?
Yes, three months.
But you can
present yourself
without an idea,
with MWP
or with something you already have.
That's right.
Everything is taken into account
and it's decided.
At the beginning
there were two founders,
because a single founder
is quite difficult.
You don't need to be able to
do something difficult.
So, yes,
everything is taken into account.
Is technology important to you?
I've heard that
companies already have
revenue and business models
throughout the year.
Do you think that
companies that already have
a fit have changed?
It's hard to say.
Also,
the technology.
They look at the whole package.
They present
the ten trends
and within
those ten trends
it would be really cool
if someone did this.
But this is just
a datapoint for people.
At the end of the day
they look at a package.
In our country
we were advertising.
We had some kind of
food delivery.
Some kind of
mobile style for girls.
You know,
a totally different society.
Rap Genius
was in Germany.
Wikipedia for rap songs.
Anyone could have
some kind of appeal
to have some audience
Oh, man.
Apart from that, do you have a confirmation, or do you think that Jansko was accepted just because of your team?
Or was the idea itself good enough to convince her?
I'm guessing that you got some kind of investment, and Dabo said something, right?
I can't say for sure. I think they said it was because of the team.
But it definitely helped us to go out to the market, because it's a step that shows that you're serious, that you believe in yourself.
And also that you got a one-euro note shows that there's nothing wrong with business, because if people don't pay, it's hard for people to give money from themselves.
And you can do something to make it useful, or solve a problem.
The motto of YC is to make something people want. And that's a very powerful statement.
And now, what did YC give you? What did they give you in the package? What did you get out of it?
It's an endless thing. For someone like us, I'm from Velenje, he's from Maribor, and also for some Slovenians,
because we were technically more powerful, but otherwise, if you come to the American market, which is the biggest in the world,
where the competition is the biggest, both in terms of staff and products, and you come to Slovenia, it's very, very difficult.
I won't be serious, maybe you'll ask me where I went to school, and I'll say University of Maribor, so you didn't go to school.
When you said you were in YC, there was instant recognition. In Silicon Valley, it was like a badge of honor, everyone knew.
Silicon Valley is not as big as it used to be, in New York, everyone knew. Now, more people know, because start-ups have been there for a long time.
But yes, instant street cred among people, among investors, and also among potential partners, for example.
That's one of the main things, because the money helps, although now they give a lot more, in the past they gave very little, but it helps.
So that's the main thing, the network, those people who are batchmates with you, most of those people go ahead and do crazy things.
Either their companies, or they are employees, and then I don't know where they are, and that network is priceless.
Because you go from being a Slovenian and you don't know anyone, and you don't know anyone, to now you know, you have a guy on Google, then on Facebook, and so on.
Mentorship was also great, we already went through the board with PJ, and then we went to have a great conversation, he is a very interesting person.
It says there, everything that Miha says is written there, right?
Well, that's from the first year, what's written on the Internet?
No, but it's written there, that it's a daily delivery of what's written, that's what I wanted to say, but I wanted to ask you now, there are some very famous,
those, how do you say, some, not opening hours, office hours, sorry, yes, those office hours, it says that they are recommended,
but you shouldn't go if you think you shouldn't, but, can you tell us a little bit what those sessions look like?
Yes, yes, I guess, yes, they are not mandatory, but as far as I know, everyone goes, religiously, folk wrote bots, that they tried to get a slot for PJ,
because he was so busy, and everyone wanted to talk to him, you can get full invaluable advice, because there were people like, I don't know, Paul Buchheit at the time,
who was the creator of Gmail, and you could go with him for an hour every day, if you wanted, and I, as a person, saw such a scale,
and such things, which I probably have never seen before, but I've seen them a few times, and you can really get some answers,
especially since they got to know another kind of folk, right? So, yes, at those office hours, you can validate ideas, ask technical questions,
ask for intros at the end of the day, to other technologists, I don't know if they are, you can bounce off an idea, if you see that the original idea doesn't work,
you can go with them and come up with some other idea, which you did at the end, you know, just everything, right?
But do they have domain experts for specific topics, or what does it look like?
At the time, it wasn't that they were, you know, in some buckets, they were just folk, fully capable of some credibility, which they did create in the past,
but they were among others, like, for example, Gary Tann is now very famous, maybe one day,
Jean-Claude Saint-François, by the way, is very popular there now, and he's not there now either, or he was the CEO of Y Combinator in the city,
Sam Altman, everyone knows him, for example, OpenAI, he was just a kid there at the time, who also had an office hour now, and so on, right?
Only three months is probably too long, if you have a whole lot of work.
I mean, you came with a small team, you were a small team, you went there, a new environment,
and find a place where you will eat, where you will sleep, la la la la...
Was that a priority?
I don't know, at the end of the day, you could sleep, but this mentorship, office hours,
working on a product, a daily, active product that people use, that was quite a lot of pressure, probably, for such a small team.
You probably went there to spread it quickly, or what?
No, we didn't spread it that much, but yeah, it was everything you said.
I wasn't the first player in America, but I was the first to go live in America.
It was mind-blowing, just because of that.
There are some things that you only see in movies, and there was one aspect of that, because you really want to explore that scene.
Then I was in Silicon Valley, and that was a place I never even dreamed I would ever show up there.
I knew it existed, I knew all the cool things were happening there, but then I was there.
So yeah, those were some kind of mental...interesting moments.
Well, that must have been a shock for the team.
Yeah, yeah. I mean, Valda, we were all...
To acclimatize, we've been there for a month.
Yeah, I mean, the biggest shock was when you see how hard it is to find things there, for example.
It was like that back then, and how expensive it is, and all that.
And how hard it is, when you're someone from Slovenia, who doesn't have any financial history or anything like that,
to be able to qualify for some rents and all that.
To be able to buy your own house and all that. Those things were all very interesting.
But in the end, we found a house in, what was it, Old Palo Alto,
where we actually stayed, four houses south of Pol Graham,
and 500 meters away from Steve Jobs, who was still alive at the time.
And we were there like we were in a student dormitory.
Three bedrooms, four bathrooms.
Yeah, when you imagine what it was like.
We went to the market, bought a kilo of pate and some soups, we cooked ourselves.
And we worked, I mean, we worked a lot.
And you still had those activities every week at YCU.
That was in Mountain View, that's where Google Headquarters is.
And we drove there.
In Pol Graham, were there any milestones?
Or were you like, hey guys, welcome, we're going there in three months?
Pretty much that.
They trust you, that you know what you can do.
And in the beginning, every friend is pretty stupid.
I mean, it's not like you're satisfied with the initiative, that you came to them.
If you don't do something in the end.
I mean, you know that if you need help, you'll come to them, right?
Yeah, kind of.
How did you deal with those teams?
I mean, you flew to them, you ran to them.
How did you deal with each other?
Did someone else come to you?
Did you have that kind of interaction?
Yeah, on different levels.
In our case, I don't know how much.
I mean, we hung out more as a social network.
You know what kind of problems you have, and how to solve them.
Or what kind of technological things.
Because most of the people there were very good in terms of technology.
There were those interesting aspects.
YC is known for that kind of dogfooding.
That you try to sell to other YC companies first.
Maybe the whole company is in your batch.
And they assume that they are your partners.
Or the opposite, because now they already have a couple of employees.
In that sense, it was a lot.
It was also during their foray.
There was a member of a company from YC.
And then, they already have those three pages.
And they are all from YC.
But, oh well.
That's it.
That's the network effect.
When you build something from scratch,
you have to take advantage of every advantage.
Because if you don't, you're dead.
Because everything works against you.
The competition is big.
You can use anything,
because there is no other access to it.
That's one example.
If you have access to the YC network,
if you don't use it, you're dead.
But when you were there,
did you feel like that?
As you said,
you went through the filter.
But what you say,
everyone is much better here.
What are we doing here?
We don't give a shit about that.
We don't care about that.
Let's go for it.
Let's hear it.
Andraž still doesn't know
Robert Farazin.
I don't have to talk
about Robie.
I'm not talking about Robie.
Yes.
But,
I would call it
imposter syndrome.
I didn't say it directly.
I got it a few years ago.
I think it's because
I'm older.
It definitely happened
that you came there
and there were a lot of people
who graduated from MIT
and Stanford.
I didn't even include the facts,
because it's not important.
But deep down,
you heard it all.
It was a very interesting feeling
for me,
because I had a lot of
imposter syndrome,
but the environment gave me
a feeling that I shouldn't have it.
And also,
when you change with people,
you can change in everything.
And so,
maybe it's classic imposter syndrome.
I mean, you know,
Do you think it's a part
of American culture?
That they encourage
a little more,
that's why we noticed
that we could quickly change
that culture.
And if not,
we had it later,
through the years,
with some Slovenians.
Slovenians have a hard time selling themselves.
We know a lot.
So definitely, yes,
it was also a part of it all.
What happened
after three months?
Well,
we built a product,
a dashboard,
so advertisers
could self-manage
the ads and all that.
And we prepared for that demo.
We didn't pivot.
In Slovenia, the story developed
because this is the Laufell server.
In America, we tried
some business development.
We tried to connect the contacts
so that maybe some sites would come.
But going to the daily.cn is not the same
as going to the traffic.com.
So now we don't know
how to connect them.
But also because of
the work you do as a business,
or because of
the stack size,
where do you see
the biggest problem?
I think the biggest problem
is that there is a scale.
And the scale of their traffic
may be the scale of the company.
And when the company is big and serious,
everything lasts longer.
Before you even know
the right people, it lasts.
And in those three months,
you won't go anywhere.
The YC network doesn't help you that much.
But we found each other
in some kind of nature.
We prepared
for different demos.
I know I worked on that.
You were in Rubio,
you did some kind of proxy
or double recall project
on any site you wanted.
It was a live script
that was running on your server.
You took cnn.com
and gave it the URL.
It was looking for a member,
it was logged in,
and it clicked the double recall.
We had a lot of sites,
Fortune, CNN,
and that's what we did
when we went to meetings.
We tried everything
in a technological way
to get closer.
At the end of the day, this technology
has nothing to do with business.
Products for publishers.
Products for publishers
for news sites,
for publishers that publish content
and give it for free.
But now there are users
who choose that.
And advertisers.
Three of the most important
stakeholders are.
And probably
I don't know
media
as such have a hard time
paying them.
It's been a hundred years
digital has forgotten them.
Whatever.
All this space
in the last ten years
has been a little hard
with monetization.
Do you think there is a hypothesis
on the internet
or do you think there was
more of a problem
that people were
held back
or
they don't have food?
Or do you really think
it's more of a business problem?
I think it's primarily a business problem.
But a business problem
also in the sense
that from a business point of view
the hardest problem there is
where you have three different stakeholders.
In fact, you can make a marketplace
where you get all this.
Unless you connect
with some ad network or something.
But at the moment we started
we didn't think about it all.
We just had some idea
we saw how fast we can do it
and how fast we can make a prototype
that people can start using
and some traction would be in Slovenia.
Because of all these problems
we stopped
after three months.
So what happened
after three months was
a demo day at YCU
where we raised
1.6 million
from investors
and at first
we had a plan to do something
but then we realized
that this business
we weren't passionate about
it would take too long
and the odds of success
were low.
And then
we decided to try something else.
And then you pivoted
for this investment?
Yes.
Now let's drink a glass of water
and I will cook some meat.
Let's move on.
Mihas is probably also
taking a break.
I would like to thank
our Patreons
who support us on this mission
and help us
to make episodes on this level.
I would also like to thank
3FSE,
Caldi and Humanfrog
who are our partners
and support us on this path
because of these companies
and employees who support us
we can work on this level.
Like and subscribe
if we have more followers on YouTube
check out Premium Sebin
and also for Patreon
if there are more people
we can do Premium Exclusive Sebin.
That was EPP.
We can also go to Discord
there are more than 700 people
so you can join
and talk
and chat.
Did I forget something?
No, I think that's it.
So,
after YCO
after this story
how did I manage
from Robert's CV
and your CV
and your team's CV
you went
to do other projects
then I think you did
Dubjoy
if I remember correctly
which was a tool
for making subtitles for videos
for voiceover
and some
different projects
then we go
to some points
to milestones
I won't say
that it's a trivial path
but that's what I know
then you go to Coinbase
and if I understand correctly
you were healthy before that
and with Coinbase
you went from bad
I think if I understand correctly
you went from a startup
to a company
that had
2015 I think
made a company IPO
and I think it's worth 10 billion dollars
or something
it's a very big real company
that's on the stock market
and it's one of the dominant
players in crypto
in the crypto world
and
if I understand correctly
early days are very connected
with Bitcoin
and that's it
tell us a little bit more
how did that transition in Coinbase look like
and is Coinbase
now that you already had a startup
look completely different
experience
was it the same as Robert Parazin
no
it's done
in the beginning
we tried
to pivot
every month
a new product
we didn't fully launch them
we didn't validate them on the market
because we always found something else
we were all over the place
at the end there was Dubjoy for voiceover
and we worked on it for a while
it was technologically very interesting
but in May
Bitcoin white paper came
and
I also changed it
and it was so mind blown
and
I don't know
why
why was it so special
what was special about it
you didn't change it
you must have seen it
but it didn't have that epiphany
I don't know
but it was interesting
DJ Chach could record a video
and that's it
they are a bit greedy
I don't know
maybe the concept of Bitcoin
that it merged
more spheres
financial, cryptographic
and technological
or maybe distributed systems
as you would call it
and
inside I knew
that there are problems
with Byzantine generals
and things like that
and it fascinated me
how
all
edge cases were predicted
and said that it will be like that
and that's why the supply of Bitcoin is limited
to only 21 million
and
something was there
and it attracted me a lot
and I wanted to know more
at that time I bought a few
and
when I wanted to buy them
I went to Hacker News
that Coinbase launched
and that it's easy to buy Bitcoin in America
and I said I'll try
and Coinbase was
Rails App
with Bootstrap CSS
and
that was the question
is that also on Rails
is that exchange also on Rails
and yeah
check
and that's why
RDChanit
but
at that time I bought
a few Bitcoins
you were already in America
you moved there
it was a bit complicated
there were some times
I went back
because life was too expensive
we lived in New York
but then I was in Ljubljana
I was in America
in San Francisco
when we bought Whitepaper
but then I moved back to Slovenia
we can talk about that later
but
yeah
then in Whitepaper
I had some questions
about
some things
and when I saw
and I saw
that Coinbase is also in YCU
once YCU, always YCU
so
I started to contact
the founder of YCU
and I asked
Brian Armstrong
if he has time for a coffee
so I can ask him about Bitcoins
and he said yes
we'll meet in a week for a coffee
and he'll start to recruit me
I just wanted to ask him
a few things
we were still working
I was only interested in a few things
he had a different mission
he had a completely different mission
and it was very interesting
but nothing
we made a nice change
at that time Coinbase was only him
I was still the founder
and nothing
then I thought
that DubJoy
is something else
and I thought
maybe
I went to Slovenia, I met Brian a couple of times,
every time I told him enthusiastically what I was programming on Dubjoy,
he just looked and nodded, and wrote some notes.
And one evening, here in Ljubljana, I was going to sleep,
it was almost night, I almost made a mistake in the call,
but I see a phone call, an American number, let's call.
Hello, this is Brian Armstrong.
And he made a whole speech on the phone,
and in a week or so I flew to America for a work trial.
At the time they had, and if you had served for a long time,
it would have been great for you, they had these work trials,
because you came to work with them for a week,
to see how you vibe together, and what you know how to do.
One week I flew to that, and a little later I...
The time was just right, it was a few months after we first met.
Dubjoy also looked like it wasn't going to be a business.
Bitcoin was always more interesting to me, the price grew,
it fell a little, it grew a little, and it was like that.
I couldn't resist it.
Yeah.
And yeah, Coinbase was, when I went to the work trial,
there were five of them.
Then I could wait for the visa for so long,
because I needed a new visa.
That's a whole podcast about American visas.
I waited for the visa for so long,
that when I got there, there were already 30 or something.
So officially, I don't know where the employee number is,
but somewhere between 5 and 20, I would say.
And yeah, I think that when I went to the work trial,
it was just something else.
We were the four Slovenians who went there,
and we tried, and we were okay in some words,
but it was just something else.
I went there, and there were only Americans here.
This was business development from day one.
I coded something there.
He was there on the line from Wikipedia
to prepare donations in Bitcoin.
I knew Wikipedia, it was a big deal.
And so, I don't know, it was just a different vibe.
And if we're talking about Bitcoin,
it was 2014 at the beginning.
Bitcoin was very sketchy back then.
Yeah.
But there was some energy,
and you couldn't overlook it.
And yeah, I don't know.
It made all the sense to me.
And yeah, it was a Rails app,
and I was at the top of my expertise in Rails at the time.
And we shipped the feature there.
You shipped the whole feature individually,
design, full stack.
It just worked.
But during that time,
there were some exchanges.
All of them existed.
Coinbase wasn't the first.
But maybe you remember,
I don't know,
why they were in YCO.
What was that added value
that they used to attack the Bitcoin market
and say, we're so much better now.
If you remember.
Yeah, definitely.
Because it's still a pitch.
And yeah, there were exchanges for Bitcoin.
You had LocalBitcoin,
where you exchanged with someone
on the street.
Yeah, I also exchanged my first Bitcoin.
And you'd say, great,
but not for everyone.
Not for everyone.
And here's the pitch.
Brian could see,
he could believe,
this is the future.
But if this is the future,
let's make something
that everyone can get
and trade
and do anything
with cryptocurrencies.
And all of this is called ease of use.
It's totally dead simple to do this.
And the second thing
is that it's a domestic US company.
Because again,
it's a huge deal
for various reasons,
especially for regulatory reasons.
The US has the biggest
financial regulation in the world.
And before that,
no exchange had been in the US.
The biggest before that
was Mt. Gox,
which was based in Japan.
A Frenchman started it.
Funny story.
When I was at a work trial
at Coinbase, it went bankrupt.
And people lost it.
In today's Bitcoin,
it's worth billions.
And it illustrated
the need for a legit player.
Because yes,
the technology is legit,
it's full high-tech,
but you can make it safe,
accessible and all that.
And that was Coinbase's pitch.
But Coinbase's money
went back
to the IPO
in 2004-2005,
or something like that.
That was...
Yes, almost.
When you came to me,
there were more people inside,
and it was a normal space.
It went through Corona.
Yes, but I'm not there anymore.
If you pick Fiat,
it goes fast.
Yes.
If we talk about YCL,
and all the start-ups,
it's a story
of an ideal start-up.
One or two founders,
idea, pitch, market,
timing is good,
boom, boom, boom.
Logistic growth.
Exactly.
I feel incredibly happy
that I was a part of it.
Because as you said,
a percentage of people
who made it,
if you look at the percentage
of companies that made it,
culminating in a successful IPO,
it's still
an infinite number.
And I feel
very grateful
that the stars have met.
It's crazy.
But your role as an engineer
has probably changed a lot
through that rapid growth.
Did you go into
management roles
or were you still
Mike on the rails?
Everything.
We went through hyper-growth
in one moment.
It wasn't linear.
Let me explain
what hyper-growth looks like
in a company like that.
Do you have people
who went through it a few times
and are still mentoring you?
It's like fire everywhere.
I wish.
In the first year,
we were just a normal company.
We grew maybe
twice, but when you go from 30
to 60,
it's not a big deal.
The human mind
can comprehend.
Then came a moment
when I was 5 years old,
2016,
but I know about the Bitcoin price.
When Bitcoin went up to $6,000,
that was the first
hype that
spread so much
that there was a frenzy
and everyone wanted to buy it.
We made a lot of money
and lost everything
because all servers fell down
and scaling was fun.
Then we went all-in
in scaling the company.
Business flow is growing,
now we can hire a million people
and maybe it will get better.
Was it decided?
Why yes, why mostly no.
I think the ideal company
is a small company
that is super technical
and solves huge problems
with technology.
If you scale people,
it's hard.
You have to manage it
and coordinate
at the end of the day.
Or motivate.
How do you
maintain
that
innovation
in that segment?
In a very short time,
you have to move
quickly,
quickly on a large scale,
things go quickly.
Do you have anything interesting
to add?
The interesting thing is
that we didn't move
that quickly.
At the beginning,
when you scale smaller,
you move faster.
When the company is smaller,
everything is less serious
and it's easier.
You can see
how much
regulation
was preventing you.
Yes, it was a factor.
It didn't prevent me
as much as
the stakes were higher.
Constantly.
Every time
you wrote a code,
it felt like money
was being touched by people
who trusted you.
It's very different
from voting.
So,
we wrote a lot of tests
and all that stuff.
Can we go a little deeper?
I know that
time is running out,
but technically
I know that
time is running out,
but technically...
No, no, I'm good.
Miha is still a bit young.
Yes, that's true.
We are a bit of a tag-team
in the podcast.
Tell us a little
about
the architecture
or the developer
experience.
How much time and energy
did you put in
to make the developers
change the features faster?
Give us a few examples
so people can understand
what can be done to make it faster.
We didn't have a lot of time
because there were a lot of things.
We'll give
Jan an extra
so he won't
get mad.
We were
working on it.
It was
top of mind.
I could have done more, but
automated tests
were one of the biggest
things.
Investing in
fast tests
was a big part of it.
If we needed
50 machines to parallelize
the tests,
we could do it.
It directly correlated
with how fast you can
move as a developer.
It was important
that we had all the critical
flows,
because you can change the code
very quickly.
In the beginning,
it was a big investment,
but you get a lot of dividends
because you can move
very quickly.
When you hire new people,
it's scary.
You move like you're going to break something.
But if you know you have the tests behind you,
it's much easier.
Later on,
two or three years later,
I invested in Heroku
which is another company.
When we had 100 employees,
it was a good push.
Later on,
when we became a real company,
we moved to our own infrastructure.
At AWS, we developed
our own system for deploying
those services,
which was Docker Base.
There,
there was a big impact
that an engineer could
create a new service.
You can go through security,
maybe infrastructure,
but you can also start
development,
deploy a new service.
We had a big impact
because
technology can help here.
People are nice in a different way.
That's a different story.
We saw that before,
that you don't have a positive manager.
Small teams, full of capable people.
How did you organize your teams?
To be effective?
On what basis?
When we went through hyperscale,
there was
endless permutations.
In the beginning,
we were two product teams,
each with 6-7 engineers.
One was in Kerbryan,
one in another.
Each of those engineers
had their own huge feature
that developed them.
Huge feature.
Later on,
in a bigger company,
20-50 people would work on it.
In the meantime,
they hacked it themselves.
For almost the whole first year,
I was alone on a huge project.
There were a few milestones,
but I didn't do it.
I was in that project.
Now, when you look back,
it's crazy.
A designer might have helped
to do something,
but that was it.
Later on, we went through
the classic Silicon Valley
organizational stories.
KPI.
You focus on the product
or the functions.
We tried everything.
What did you say
when you said
this is where we learned.
To pull out
what was
almost the same.
One very interesting anecdote
that is not publicly known,
but it's not something
everyone knows,
is that...
I have to step back
to explain
what Coinbase was at the time.
Coinbase was not an exchange.
It was a brokerage.
The difference between an exchange
and a brokerage is that a brokerage
is easy to manage.
You buy a Bitcoin,
we do some magic,
we tell you it will cost you this much,
we will pay you this much,
you say OK, and you get it.
But in the back, a brokerage
does a lot of things.
A brokerage on your behalf,
on the exchange,
gets some money,
and then you have to deliver it
to the exchange.
Coinbase was originally a brokerage.
We used other exchanges,
for example Bitstamp,
which is an interesting Slovenian company.
Among others.
But we soon realized
that we would need our own exchange
to be competitive.
When we started doing this,
we did...
Brian had an idea
that we would have an internal competitor.
A brokerage
against an exchange.
We would split things a bit
when it comes to functions.
They would have their own
head of engineering.
And then we would fight.
Just like Google wants
two nights of work
to be the same.
I don't know if that's the case.
I don't think so.
Interesting approach.
It's not the best idea.
I don't know.
You split
scarce resources of a company.
You split it into camps.
And now the structure
is completely different
than it used to be.
But it was cool
for me personally
for a while.
I started with
Rails.
I did it for a while.
But the biggest change
was that I went to the exchange.
I was
the head of engineering
of the exchange.
It was Node, Microservices,
completely different from
Rails Monolith.
It was cool for me
because I had more options.
I could hire there.
But as a structure
it wasn't the same.
Fortunately, I could do it all the time.
Just like that.
Do you want to talk about Coinbase?
I wanted to watch Coinbase.
I had a question.
I wanted to talk about Coinbase.
Your last position
in Coinbase was...
What did you write?
Special project.
The last title was...
You didn't write the title,
but you wrote
Engineering Special Projects
and then you wrote Reporting directly to CTO.
I don't know if it's the same
as the guest said at the beginning
that if you don't want to talk about certain topics
you skip it.
Is it a secret project?
Or is it like
we made it, just
hack your own things.
No, no.
It's all public now.
I'm interested in the change.
I can change this.
The best thing about Coinbase
was the first year
and the last year.
In my opinion...
It was fucked up.
The first year
because it was a small team.
We got to know each other,
we ate together,
we were there all day.
We were all true believers.
Everyone who was at Coinbase in 2014
was a hardcore believer
and all-in.
Then you have
career people and so on.
Last year
you gain so much
credibility in the organization
and you get to know
all the executives.
If you're still an engineer
or a manager.
You have a lot of
space to do whatever you want.
At one point
when I was there
at the beginning
they said
what if you do this?
They let us
launch USDC
which is a stable coin
at Coinbase
in
two weeks.
At Coinbase
there were already 2000 people.
To launch something in two weeks
in a company with 2000 people
is quite
a challenge.
It was possible
only because we were there
to launch it.
We have direct trust
of the whole company
to help.
We went back to war mode
in a company with 2000 people.
COO
said
drop everything
in two weeks we'll launch USDC.
Miha and his colleague
Lidata
help them
and they did it.
We had an office
for two weeks
and we launched it.
After those years
when everything was
getting slower
when you knew less people
at the company
it was back to the roots.
It was serious.
It was crazy.
It was fast
to launch it.
To challenge it.
Funny how that works.
It was a lesson.
They gave us
a financial incentive
but that's it.
That's how you do things.
We launched it.
To be time cautious
our city
is still a small company
small start-up
small organization.
Jira
is too big for us.
We heard that Linear
is the successor
of Jira.
Thank you for your work on Linear.
Is it for us?
Yes.
Jira is not for nobody.
You are small, not big.
Linear is great.
I think
it's a progressive UI
that looks like a trailer
when you go inside.
But then you realize
you need more.
On the basis of that
it's a sleek modern UI
local
first sync engine
everything is real-time
multiplayer
top shit.
And inside
is a part of Slovenian knowledge.
That's true.
Miha
you have the opportunity
to talk about
the beginnings of Slovenian
programmers, students
and also experienced cats.
Do you have anything to say?
It's a cliché
but I guess
we know more
when we get to know each other.
I think that's not the case anymore
because with the remote work
only most Slovenes
are working for Twin.
We all know that.
But don't be afraid to go outside
and
if you want to make
a real story, you have to go outside.
Because Europe
is not here for
technology.
Unified market
different languages
etc.
Plus, I don't know
America is
for making big stories.
Incubators are
working
helping
so if people have ideas
no problem.
I also
still live in America
but I'm also here so I'm happy
if someone needs the world
buy paper
or whatever
I'm happy to help
and I'm also
an angel investor
so if someone needs
Zagonski Capital
I'm happy to help.
I agree with you.
From my point of view
what else do you have in mind?
I mean
somehow
outside of
Marseille as a listener
the story of success
which is a little changed
but it's still
a grind.
It didn't happen overnight.
We came from 90 minutes
overnight
yesterday to today.
But
probably you're not
calm
you still have
some goals
to achieve.
I would like to, yes. At the moment I am semi-retired, but not forever.
I had a haircut recently, and now I'm picking up books.
I also have a contract for Linear.
But yes, I would like to do something in the future.
But I don't feel like it. I'm a bit older now.
That's a bit of a problem when you're older.
Do you have any plans to move to crypto?
To Web 3.0 or in the same direction?
No.
Not that there would be anything wrong with it,
but Coinbase was such an intense experience
that you're a bit burned out from the ecosystem.
Everyone gives some kind of startup experience,
but it's never more.
And then there's crypto, which is probably even more intense.
Yes, exactly.
But the counterpoint is, for example,
that I went to Linear almost immediately after Coinbase,
because there were only four of us.
They are three, they are co-founders, and I was a first employee.
And that was a startup again.
But it was totally opposite of Coinbase.
We were all experienced ex-founders.
We all had some financial background.
We didn't have to worry about where we would eat.
And then at the end you see that if the right team,
everything has to fit, the right idea,
but a startup doesn't have to be full grind,
full hectic, and I don't know what.
Linear is like that, I don't know.
People go at their own pace.
The company was doing phenomenally,
and the current valuation is already 400 million.
And Djiren did a great job.
So, yes.
You get a head start when you're a little smarter.
But that's the seniority level.
A little bit of gray hair.
At this point, we would like to conclude.
Miha, thank you for being with us
for a part of your life journey.
We wish you all the best in other vlogs.
And I hope you'll still be rails,
as you said, 5, 6, 7 years old.
I hope so.
Andraž, thank you for your time.
At this point, thank you to all listeners and viewers
for being with us.
Give us some feedback.
We appreciate it, and we hear and see the future.
And now we're going to have a beer.
And thank you, Kaldi, for being with us.
Thank you for the interview.
Good luck to all of us.
Bye.