Welcome to the new episode of Grodje. Thank you for taking the time to attend such a big conference with almost 400 people.
As an organizer, co-organizer, all-round, operational organizer of marketing, it's a lot of work.
So, I will try to respect your time and maybe a little shorter episode than usual, but I hope that we will discuss some interesting topics for our listeners as investigators and participants of some conferences.
Welcome to Grodje. I hope that today we will discuss how to make a successful conference like Makeit.
Let's start with some practical examples. Maybe I will try to ask some practical questions so that I can see how you are doing.
You have been very successful, if I understand correctly, since 1998.
Yes.
And now, greetings to you. I would like to start with the first question.
I would like to know who you are, what you do and how did you come to Makeit.
Maybe Elisabeta?
Thank you. My name is Elisabeta Gruden. I came to this conference because I was employed at Oracle for 10 years.
Today, I also spoke with a colleague from Oracle. We were so young then that this came to our heart, soul and body and we simply can't do without it.
Of course, the feedback from the participants, when we are successful, gives us motivation to move forward.
Great.
I joined the company a bit later. I think it was in 2011. The last conference was in Bernardino.
I joined the company because my long-time colleague, Janez Zaletel, was a long-term chairman of the Oracle users association.
I joined the company, assisted a bit in the beginning, and so on.
We ended up the way we ended up. We are now organizing both Makeit and Jack, and we are taking care of Sebinsko.
Can you give us a bit of an update on what else you are doing besides this?
Yes, absolutely. After the conference itself, which ends tomorrow, I have already spoken to the participants.
I feel a bit strange. I have nothing to do in the evening. I don't need to go to emails, answer questions, etc.
Otherwise, I am a daily service in the company Kontron. I lead the development of 5G technology in Slovenia.
This is my day job.
I am a bit divided into several industries. My main industry is construction and real estate.
And of course our company, ESJUG, which is a company for education.
Besides this event, we are also working on other one-day events, and we are also helping to organize a conference.
Great. Let's start with the official question.
I hope I got the official name of the conference right.
Makeit, Jackon, Openblend, Slovenia, CEO...
Let's put it this way. How did we come up with this name?
CEO stands for Slovenian Oracle Users Group. This is where we started.
We decided that the name of the conference should have its own brand name.
It shouldn't be the name of the company that organizes the conference.
This is Urbano's merit that we connected with Jackon.
This is also a brand name. It all happens under the name Makeit.
One part is Oracle-oriented, the ESJUG part, and the other part is Jackon.
Urbano will tell you more about this.
We have been looking for this identity for a while.
We have replaced it with a lot of names.
Makeit seems to exist now, but Sebinjsko is a bit different.
We have been working on this for a long time.
In 2017 we had SEUG and Java SI.
In 2017 we had both logos on our T-shirts.
It said Makeit.
Someone suggested that we should combine them under one name.
It was Makeit.
I think we combined them in 2018.
Then we realized that the problem is how to combine two different fields.
One part is Oracle-related, based on DBA and APEX.
The other part is from another world.
We decided to create a branch here.
We connected with Jackon, a brand.
We still want this to be one event.
We want it to become two.
What does the brand Jackon mean?
I will put it this way.
We were very naive.
I talked to Markos and Richard, who are the main organizers of Jackon Europe and Jackon World.
They said that they would like to expand it to other countries.
They are still talking about South Africa.
I said that we would like that.
We didn't know what to bring.
We said that we would try to keep it for the first year.
If it works, we will keep it.
If I understand correctly, Jackon also helps you promote the conference between speakers?
Yes.
That was the main thing.
Now we have achieved that.
Next year, we plan to do more events.
Everyone says that there is so much going on here.
It is still an intimate conference.
It is too big.
I would say that we have already lost the romantic side of the conference.
We forgot to mention Open Bled.
It is an important event.
Yes, it is important.
It wasn't easy for Justin.
We have been organizing Open Bled as a Javanese society for many years.
We have been organizing SCUP and Java SI for many years.
Without Open Bled, Jackon wouldn't exist.
We are still working on cooperation.
We are not isolating.
Elisabeta, a question for you.
Do you notice that the participants stick to the guidelines?
Or do you notice that people from Jackon go to Oracle and vice versa?
Do you notice that this is a trend?
We have managed to bring the participants closer to the conference.
We have given them a roof over their heads.
We also have a registration.
Last year we had a deadline.
Everything is happening now.
There is networking between the participants.
There is a conversation in the evening.
They are preparing to share knowledge and experience.
They are learning new business opportunities.
I would like to know how you organize a conference like Makeit.
My first question is when do you start organizing Makeit?
We started the next year before yesterday.
We reserved a space in the hotel.
First of all, you need to know how much space you need.
Approximately the size of the conference.
How big the conference you want.
How much urban space you need.
Not too big.
We have 5 really good halls.
Not more than that.
We had 200 people at the start of the conference.
The maximum was 800.
This size is beautiful.
It is manageable.
What needs to be done?
I have a sub-question.
I divided it into three parts.
What are the most important things to do before, after and after the conference?
Maybe I can start.
We always start too late.
No matter how much we travel, we always run out of time.
You can say anything.
No, seriously.
Let's start in November.
We are a bit late.
It was half a year ago.
More than half a year ago.
More than half a year.
We start with the criteria, tracks,
we publish the call for paper,
then we do the marketing.
That's the main thing.
A lot of publishers are already reserving.
They have a schedule for next year.
It's hard to get a top speaker.
That's one of the key things.
Without a person, it's hard to get people.
That's the first thing.
The choice of location affects the success of the event.
If I understand correctly, Make It was also in other locations,
but Porto Rojo is a destination for that.
Yes, the experiences were like this.
We started in Porto Rojo,
then the economic crisis brought us to Ljubljana.
We realized that Ljubljana was not the best choice,
because people don't take their time,
they go to meetings, you lose people
in the evening events,
when people can get to know each other.
Then, of course, COVID affected us a bit,
but we were persistent.
We shared the toilet twice a week,
so we kept in touch with people.
Then we returned to Porto Rojo after COVID.
We will not give up.
I hope that the forces of the world will support us.
You probably come to this question from this location.
Who is this conference for?
If you are a student,
you probably know
how far you can go.
You will probably have a hard time coming to Porto Rojo,
or it will be harder for you to go to a conference for money.
Or not, maybe I'm wrong.
Maybe this is also a question from that perspective.
Is the conference for professionals?
Correct me if I'm wrong.
No, no.
I think you profiled yourself well for the job.
We wanted to attract young people,
but Porto Rojo is really poor.
Everyone is complaining about me.
How can I not come to Porto Rojo?
Sellers, employees,
students, absolutely.
So this conference is intended
for graduates with a certain amount of experience.
They are already a few kilometers away.
There is a barrier.
They have already given up.
If we go back a little bit,
what should be done in the meantime?
Give me a couple of important wisdoms.
What are you dealing with today?
What are the operational things
that are very important to you at the event?
At the event?
Yes, yes.
If I may add,
Porto Rojo, as we said,
attracts employees,
but there is a small difficulty
in connecting the airport to the airport.
At the beginning we said
that we are trying to attract employees outside of Slovenia,
but how to get there?
It is not up to us,
but this is the area where we still have to work.
If we wanted to have a bigger conference,
we could start thinking about logistics,
how to attract people from other countries.
Yes, from other countries.
What do you do on the day of the conference?
First of all, make sure that all halls are well-equipped,
that there is a large number of tables,
that the best teacher has the largest hall,
that the projectors are working,
that the adapters are working,
that there are a million small pieces,
without which the work is not technically possible.
Who we are here is a problem,
or the challenge is that everything flows correctly,
only the technology.
How many people are working on the day of the event?
Five.
Then there are students.
We are very proud of our staff,
because they are all students.
Now all these children and infants have regular services
and are allowed to come and help us for two or three days.
This is a very big challenge,
but we are very proud of our staff.
because people are very busy,
especially those who are new.
Teachers are a bit nervous,
What kind of mouse does not work, what kind of projector does not work,
and then they jump and we fix it.
Great.
Tell me a little more about the selection of teachers.
When you start to promote the conference,
do a lot of people apply,
a few people apply,
do you attract them?
How is the selection going?
Last year we did not have a hard time.
Last year we were very hand-picked.
I went, this is what I want, this is what I want.
It was very subjective,
what I wanted to hear at that moment.
Last year,
it has changed a lot.
It has changed a lot.
We have a selection.
You will know.
Now I have to pretend I don't know anything.
But yes, please explain.
Two years ago,
I re-selected which
lectures we would have.
And then I said,
maybe the participants did not have the same ideas as I do,
and I thought it would be better to have a program selection.
And we put it together
for Mike and for Jake.
This is a great help.
Everyone has their own point of view.
I will say,
I will do it in a more strict way.
I would like to have more,
but now we are satisfied with it.
What helps Oracle
as an organization?
I will say, a strong sponsor.
Yes, it helps.
Oracle supports us,
as I said before,
as a sponsor.
But you cannot get money back from anyone else.
Oracle supports this conference with its lectures.
We cooperate locally and globally.
Oracle ACE
has about 20 of them.
It is their lecture.
They are well-researched
and well-prepared for the future.
So they support us professionally and technically
for their lectures and not for sponsorship.
Local marketing services
do not exist at the moment.
Our event is not an Oracle event,
but because there are so many people here,
we do not do short-term marketing
as a sales work,
but as a personal and technical sharing of knowledge.
This is definitely happening.
We do not do marketing sales.
We do not do sales.
Even the participants do not expect this.
We have other conferences on this topic.
This selection tries to
make a difference.
There was an interesting phenomenon this year.
There were a lot of applications,
then we announced the dates,
and a few lecturers withdrew.
There were lecturers who applied more than others,
and then they were selected.
This dynamic is also very interesting.
Maybe something more about this
are the lectures,
but also networking, social networking,
and so on.
Can you tell us why this part is so important
for such a conference?
How important is the non-lecture part?
First of all, we do not only have a lecture,
but this year we also added a day before the conference.
This day was yesterday.
It is important that the lectures were hands-on,
that people were deep down in technology,
and that they learned something new,
not just heard what would be new.
Networking is important because,
despite the fact that we all work in our offices,
the Internet opened up to the world many years ago,
but everyone got a phone.
Great.
Let's go to the lecturers.
We touched on this.
Before we go to the event,
can you tell me more about how you market such an event?
How do you think about marketing?
How do you bring it closer to the audience?
How do you approach it?
Are there any hacks?
What is a good hack?
That is a difficult question for me.
I am full of techniques.
It is always like that for me.
It is really hard.
The biggest challenge is to have a good base
where you will send your data.
This base is changing,
because companies are changing,
so we try to keep our base as up-to-date as possible.
Of course,
we use all additional marketing channels.
I think there is always more,
but still too little.
We should use LinkedIn more.
Last year we tried Facebook.
Last year we said,
we are not for Facebook.
We are users, too.
In the end,
most of the people here
really got a phone call.
We call everyone we know.
Have you already made a phone call?
Have you received a notification?
Of course, we send e-mails,
we use social media.
Thank you for reminding me.
What is the percentage of returnees?
20, 30, 40, 60?
80?
70-80.
When we opened this world,
there are always more young people in this field.
But yes, 70-80.
When you come here,
it is like a gathering.
Once a year.
Early bird.
It pays off.
Definitely.
Last year,
we have been doing this for the last 3 weeks.
I was excited.
I called Justina.
What can we do?
Betty, I told you.
We have so many halls.
Teachers came, empty halls.
I was excited for the last 3 days.
The last 3 days of early bird.
Until then, you don't know how big the conference will be.
You hope it will be.
But the last 3 days.
When we have early bird,
we have a feeling that we are busy.
We have a lot to do.
We have time for marketing.
We have to fix something.
We haven't done anything yet.
We have a lot to do.
What do you want to say to early bird fans?
A lot of things.
We have to look at it from a political point of view.
Everyone is the same.
If you don't get an approval,
you send an email, you sign up,
and then we wait for you to get an approval.
To give someone an early bird,
we don't do it when it's already closed.
Fair enough.
A large part of such conferences
are sponsored by partners.
Could you tell me
how it works to become a sponsor of a conference like this?
What do you expect in return?
What do you want and what do you get when you become a sponsor of such a conference?
What do you get?
As a sponsor, we are very open to cooperation.
We have some basic packages,
but you can also get something else.
Basically, you get your own space,
you get the opportunity to have your own lecture,
which, of course, should not be marketed,
but we have a large number of lectures.
In the last two years,
the Call for Papers lecture series
should have been very strict.
Of course, if someone is a sponsor,
if the lecture is not well-directed,
you can still tell them to correct it,
so that you can be in the audience,
because you are a sponsor.
In the lecture space,
you can do whatever you want.
You can play games,
you can drink beer.
We only have full-length lectures,
so you can talk to the parties,
future potential employees.
We must know that such a conference
has a large number of people.
Then you can participate in all holidays,
parties, whatever you want.
We always listen and find a package
to sponsor the sponsors.
It is probably easier to organize
such an event for some support.
I imagine that you are not entirely dependent
on the participants.
We are a technical conference,
so a lot of people come to sell something.
It is a bit more difficult to sell
to another organization,
such as IDA, etc.
Absolutely, whoever helps us,
I will say that the sponsor
brings their own lecturer.
Red Hat brought their own lecturer
and a whole group of people.
It is a big thank you for us,
because they bring the event
to a new level.
We have top lecturers.
It helps.
I have a question for the audience.
Is the conference already so big
that you have already started
to receive applications?
Or not yet?
No.
There is still room for growth.
If there were more participants,
we would make a jump.
We would go to another space.
We have already seen
some of the sponsors' applications.
Let's talk about the lectures.
What did you learn
from the organizers of Make.it?
How did the conference change?
Are people more willing
to come to these events?
Is it more difficult for them?
Or is it easier for them?
Can you give me a quick overview?
Is it easier for them?
You can say that it was in 1998.
It was in 1998.
Let's go with that.
What do you think changed?
There were times when it was easier
to get participants than now.
The event was focused on
the fact that the participation
or sending of participants
to the conference was a reward.
There were not many social networks
and the conference was a space
where everyone met.
Today we all know that we can talk
in different ways.
I think we are somewhere in the middle.
It's not the hardest or the easiest.
I don't think the price is a problem.
It's more a matter of time.
You can't send the whole team to the event,
which means that they will be absent for three days.
That's why we made a map
so that you can decide in three days
to try to get as close as possible.
We thought that everyone would go
to a hybrid conference,
so that those who couldn't come
could listen to the recording.
We decided to come here
and learn something new.
Why weren't the lectures recorded?
Did you think about that?
Maybe not in a hybrid way,
but did you think about it in the past?
No.
Maybe it's not worth it.
I wouldn't say it's not worth it,
because when there was Corona,
everything was online.
We also shared recordings.
I rarely watch such recordings
when I go to a conference.
But I do watch technical lectures.
I scroll through what interests me.
We decided to come here
because we really want to keep it here.
I think it's a good network,
a good lecture and so on.
What you just said, Urban,
seems to me that we really have to do that.
We have to do it in the heart of the conference.
The heart of the conference
is a good program.
We can do whatever we want
if there is no real personality.
If the lecturers are not renowned,
then the conference has no real meaning.
In this personality,
this is the segment where we have to work.
Maybe this is also related to the question.
One of the great things we noticed
is that the participants are invited.
A survey is being conducted
between the events.
There is some research going on.
Please tell us more about it,
because it's very interesting.
The survey is necessary
to get feedback from the participants.
We want to know if the coffee was warm enough.
We are interested in the personality.
We encourage the participants
to give some small gifts,
with a heart at the end,
where everyone can participate.
We want the survey to be fulfilled.
Then we study all the answers
in detail and try to understand
what we have to do better next year.
We haven't received a bad comment yet.
Even if it is a negative comment,
it is positive for us,
because it tells us what we have to change,
what we have to do,
maybe add some personality.
Coffee is missing every year.
What do you think has changed
in the survey?
What is the thing we are starting now?
What is it like in practice?
In practice,
you can see where
the mainstream development is going.
What are the characteristics
that the participants like to hear?
In the last half of the year,
we had a lot of hardcore classes.
Java 22, for example.
There are three questions.
How good is the personality of a child?
What kind of teacher is he?
I don't remember the third one.
Organizational part of the conference.
Yes.
You can learn a lot from this.
You can see in which direction
the next year will go.
You never have enough information
to know what the next year will be like.
You get hints.
It is still hard.
Everyone has some AI.
It is a long time.
You can see that every year
a buzzword pops up.
Is he in this lecture or not?
It is different.
If you want to follow everything,
you are in the right place.
If it is Kubernetes,
we have a lot of such people.
APEX gets some mainstream.
We have more of them.
Let's move on.
I have to do an eBP.
Urban process.
Grodje is possible thanks to our supporters
on Patreon.
We thank them for their direct support.
And thanks to Humanfrog, 3FS and Kaldi
for supporting us.
Thank you.
Like and subscribe.
I have one more question.
Will summer be cooler?
And what will be cooler?
This is a question from our audience.
It is a question for both of you.
It will be a lot cooler.
You get to know the team you work with.
If you don't know what to expect,
what will you do in the final phase,
I will say that I will do very well in the beginning.
I hope so.
I will find out later.
We have a summer break.
I will spend some time and then
another part of the team will come on stage.
You don't know what to expect.
In the beginning it was like this.
Who has to do what now?
Now the roles are divided.
You have a salesperson, a technician,
a website, applications,
so that the participants can vote.
Everything else...
I know I have to be honest.
You have to know that he has your back.
You are protected.
Whatever becomes easier for you.
It becomes easier to dream at night
what you forgot to do.
So that the next day you know exactly
how you will do it, even if you forgot something.
I have to say that I was often asked
if I do other things,
because we are such a beautiful team.
Even if something went wrong,
some of the presenters answered us.
Orban is a cyclist in Portoroš.
When the presenter said that he can't,
I called him. He was at the top level.
But we solved it like this.
It's easier because the situations are unpredictable
and don't cause as much stress.
You have to trust yourself and the team.
We will fix it.
I would like to add
the last piece of advice.
If you are a lesbian, this is the last piece of advice.
Whoever hasn't been with us before,
we won't regret it.
Great. Orban?
I don't know if I have anything else to add.
If anyone would like to join us,
we are more than welcome.
We need a new, fresh perspective.
We have been here for a while and we are a bit tired.
If anyone would like to join us...
Tired of experience.
Let's say it like that.
Elisabeta, Orban, thank you for your time and effort.
As well as the whole Make It team.
Thank you to the military sponsors
for making this conference possible.
Thank you for listening to us.
I am looking forward to your feedback.
I wish you all the best.
Thank you.