DRAGON DAYS CONFERENCE
Greetings to all the listeners and viewers of Dragon Days.
Today we are at the Dragon Days conference.
We are gathering here from the events before the event.
First of all, I would like to thank the patient team
for making it possible for us to film here,
as well as the organizers and the team in Grodno.
Then I would like to thank our supporters Humanfrog, 3FS and Kaldi.
I would also like to thank our Patreon,
for which we are trying to make some small donations,
but we have to be more forward, let's go.
Thank you too, without you it would be more difficult.
Maybe I will make some noise in the background,
because we are at the event and people are moving around.
But we tried to make this event as good as possible.
I would also like to thank some of our friends,
who are our guests today.
I will be with Oto, and we will have some...
Thank you, Andraž.
We will have some debates together.
I would also like to thank my parents,
my teacher.
Moms only on YouTube.
My kids.
Every person is extremely important,
and you have to prepare and optimize for it.
You lose everyone at the beginning.
And what is the best?
Elevator pizza starts with a stand-alone engine.
That's it.
We did a lot of background research.
We are like the American SAS,
when you sign a contract,
you have to fill out a form,
and you come to the social security number,
and you don't have a Slovenian one.
I do.
Great.
You don't have to write a note,
but we pull some details from different boxes.
This is a detail that came to my LinkedIn mailbox.
Oto, would you like to come to the Fuck Up Nights,
and tell us about your biggest fuck up?
Nejc Skobarneja also had a big fuck up,
he had a police at home.
I thought it would be interesting,
and I am sure he will tell us about it,
and then we will go on.
We will start with you.
Can I?
It's a long story.
It will be a shorter version.
I have a friend,
who is very interested in social priorities.
When I was a student,
we had a server together.
We had a hosting on the web.
One day he came and asked,
where should we make a Tor point?
The idea was to make a middle node,
and at some point he said,
let's make a micro exit node.
OK, Slava is from Pugumni,
for activism and everything.
His main sell point at the time was,
you know how many Chinese people,
who don't have access to Wikipedia,
and I thought,
it's true.
So we made a Tor point,
I think it was 2.8 or 2.9,
purely from humanistic reasons,
and we donated our computers for that purpose,
and bandwidth.
This thing started to grow so fast,
that websites started to work with us.
We had a couple of colleagues,
who paid for it,
and we had our own website,
we had a server.
It started to work,
and at some point,
in three weeks,
we said, let's do it.
And we did.
Two weeks later,
a criminal police came to my house,
at noon,
two policemen,
and they came to talk to us.
The story is,
that there was a search,
because of some emails,
that were sent from my server.
This hosting,
that we were listening to,
was in my home dictionary.
That was the first thing,
that we went to look at.
I explained to them,
that we are making a Tor point,
and they asked,
what is it?
It was a bit of an explanation,
what it is, and how it works.
We didn't have any logos,
because the thing was designed
to have no logos.
They accepted my explanation,
and that was it.
The woman was very unhappy.
She didn't know,
where we were going.
It was a criminal case,
and it wasn't a big deal.
At that time,
they told me to calm down,
and I didn't panic.
Anyway,
I speak Chinese,
and that's it.
Three years later,
I don't know if you remember,
there was a meeting in Ljubljana,
at 6 a.m.
Mr. Magajn,
former MP,
I think he was also a media person,
there was another meeting,
and I was there as well.
It was at 6 a.m.
My wife was very upset
with my second son.
The first thing they told me,
was that they were very lucky
that they didn't break the door,
but they saw how careful I was,
and they said,
maybe not yet.
So, they came to me normally,
but I showed them
the order to search the house,
and they started to look
where the computers were.
I was very shocked at that time,
because I had long forgotten
about this case.
So, they called me,
and they asked me to pay
for the child pornography,
and for my wife as well.
It was really unpleasant,
and then I realized,
as soon as they showed me the IP address,
I understood.
So, in those three weeks,
they only found
these things
in the office.
I would have connected them,
but I didn't.
So, I went to explain
to them one more time,
and there were some interesting
details,
in the sense that
Mr. Kriminalist said
that everything would be fine,
and that I would go to the computer,
and he would call someone
on the phone,
and he would give me
what I had to type in,
and we would see
if it was the old computer
with the IP address.
And then I said,
no, no, no, that IP address
is there, next to the phone,
it has nothing to do with my
apartment, nothing.
We have to go there,
if you want to see it.
And he said, no, no,
I have to go there,
because I have the right here,
open the computer,
I have the IP address,
if you want to see it,
let's go inside.
And I was just doing
what I had to do.
And then,
he said,
thank you for explaining it to me,
and I believe you,
but let's go to the computer,
I will take you to the police station,
where you will go with me,
and you will explain it to me
once more,
and then we will see
what will happen.
And it really happened,
I explained it to him once more,
and then he said,
ok, I will take you to the police station,
and then they decided.
And I was like,
ok, I hope it will be ok.
And then I told him
who we were,
and so on.
And that was it.
It would be strange
if you were like,
sorry,
it's just the beginning.
So,
you would be like,
everyone starts like that.
It's a story.
And then,
when I came back,
he said,
criminalist,
how would we know
what you are,
what kind of computer you have.
And that was it.
Let's talk about
the future of Thor,
which is a computer
that is running
a protocol
called Thor.
This protocol
wraps the packets,
it's also called
the Onion Router,
when the packets
that are transmitted
between the nodes
are wrapped
in additional headers
in such a mathematically
interesting way
that you can follow
where the packet went in
and where it went out.
You can't see the whole path,
which means
it's anonymous.
The sender of the packet
is anonymous.
This is possible
if you don't have
a large part of the network
under surveillance.
If you have it,
you can see these things.
Let's say
the whole delegation,
I think I said this last time,
is one of the biggest donors
of nodes for Thor.
So they have their own
exit nodes,
the way you described it,
and they watch what goes out.
I think so,
but also for their own needs.
I said this before,
but also for their own,
because it's so big
that it actually works well.
Who has how much
under surveillance,
I don't know.
That's it.
The best.
I think we liked that hook.
I hope we got
the audience's attention,
because now
in all this
mess of information,
I'm honestly,
when we prepared
with Andraž,
we did something
like a roadmap,
where you started,
and then we also had
a full AI.
They also want to talk
about AI,
because you now have a company
around it,
but I prepared it,
notes,
and yesterday
everything changed again.
In AI?
In AI.
From evening to evening
we talked about
what it looks like
when you create
your third company,
your third startup,
and you decided
to make a new product,
and AI is at the heart
of your solution.
How do you work
in this space?
How do you prepare?
Is it stressful for you
when some changes happen?
No.
For me,
it was the most stressful
after Lani
came out of API
to GGBT,
and we were still
very firmly
in the previous company,
firmly in the sense
that we are executing a vision
and we want to do
as much as possible.
And then API came to stop
and I intuitively felt
that it is a big deal.
It opens up
a lot of new opportunities
that are potentially
much more valuable
than my previous company
still works.
And there was this stress
of this commitment,
and how
to pivot this,
the idea that we don't
have to pivot these companies
to an AI company,
but how to convince
the co-founders
to do something new,
what to do with this business,
and so on.
How to use
this opportunity.
Otherwise,
I trust Twitter a lot,
and I think
it is a trip around the world
where I feel
what is happening
and it generates
some ideas.
And now,
will you?
Yes, I am interested.
We got
API to these LLM models,
but
things are changing.
New models are coming,
some are potentially more valuable,
and I am interested
that you can't rely on one
because we don't know
what is going to happen
in a month,
four years,
or half a year.
And if you have an idea,
when you don't know
what to do,
and then you write
some tests for evaluation
of new models,
how does it look?
I mean,
you don't have time
to evaluate it manually,
or you decide
on your own.
At the moment,
there are three of us
in this new company,
as founders,
so we don't have
much time
to deal with
systematization,
evaluation,
cross-model,
etc.
So now it was more
like,
hey,
let's do some experiments,
let's work, let's work.
But that didn't work out.
I mean,
what is the biggest
risk?
I think the biggest problem
in the development of
production systems
is how to minimize
the regression.
You don't have a model
at the level of a model,
but at the level of a prompt.
How can you,
even if you think
that it's a bad idea,
how can you minimize
the regression?
I mean,
we didn't overdo it,
or we did it by default,
but now it doesn't work anymore.
How can you minimize it?
And this is really
not a clear answer
to the industry
as I perceive it.
What we are doing now
is that you have
an evaluation framework
where you have some data.
Now, for example,
we have so many
generated
prompts,
so many stories,
that we can put a table
and label it.
That's all OK.
Now we put another model,
what is happening,
where are the differences,
where are the differences.
But it's enough
to have all these
nuances.
But our use case
is not critical.
We write everything by e-mail.
If something is written
by e-mail,
you can still
look at the end
and correct it.
They are not kitchen recipes
when you have to mix
two eggs.
First of all,
people probably know
the story of Genialis,
which is
one of the biggest
biotech startups
in Slovenia.
We probably have more,
but on my radar
we already had Roman
from Genialis.
Then the meeting
with Bio is
another story.
Celestia is the third.
I noticed
when I was looking
at the products
and what you wrote,
that
sales
is a mission.
I feel like you want
to deal with sales
and help people.
Is that a topic
throughout all this?
I've never talked about it.
What is my
bottom line?
It's the beginning of a big thing.
That's what I see
as my mission.
To be honest,
if you want to do it
on an important scale,
it's much easier
if you have
financial resources.
That's why
when I started
my first company,
I wanted to be a product company,
not just an operating company
where I would sell my products
and create a good service.
I wanted to create a business
that I could sell
and get some resources
with which I could make
some changes in the world
that made sense to me.
Legally.
Legally, yes.
That's my motivation.
Why am I trying to
create big companies?
It's a great
financial independence
that I've built there
and I could do it
for another 300 hours.
But I'm not interested in that.
I'm interested in building
as big as possible
so that I can
start even bigger.
One big thing I'd like to do
in Slovenia
is a really good
vocational high school.
We have a lot of
young people
who have nothing to do
with what I experience
as a business.
I think that
young people are great
entry point for a business
because they have
a lot of naivety.
One of the key
characteristics of mine
is that I'm very naive.
If you ask my father
he would say
that I'm too naive.
That's what he said
at the beginning.
Why?
He wanted
that Slovenia
would be economically
more powerful,
with more value,
more business,
more life.
That's the bottom line.
Personally,
everything was opportunistic.
I was in security,
IT,
for 10 years.
Then my colleague came
and said
let's make a company
that has nothing to do with it.
At the time,
we thought
it would be an orange
in the cloud,
a data analytics platform.
It turned out
that
we had
the same tool
for video production
as for IT.
We had almost everything.
Why would you be naive?
Then we said
let's focus
on bioinformatics
because it's
a huge space.
In bioinformatics
we started
because
you were
our
founding advisor
and at the time
he was working
in a different field.
He asked
what if we tried
to commercialize
and productivize it.
The company was like that.
I had no idea
about biology and bioinformatics.
It was one of the
worst decisions
I've made in 10 years.
I knew them very well
and I started to learn
things I had no idea about.
I had no idea about
construction teams.
I didn't know that
so I focused
on things
that were
easier to learn
in sales and marketing
than in bioinformatics.
That was the reason
why I got into sales.
I found sales
interesting
because
it's exciting
because you do something
and then you go out
and you have no idea
how the world will react
and you watch the reaction.
That reaction brings me
a lot of excitement
and that's why
it's a huge opportunity.
Our listeners
have a feeling
that it's very technical
even though the podcast
is quite technical.
I think that
Marzlo is thinking
that maybe
I should make a product
that's lifestyle,
business,
whatever.
I think that
a lot of us
struggle with
sales.
Can you give us
some advice
on how to learn
or just try?
I think you have
the best insights.
First of all,
marketing is something
that's harder to learn
than sales.
In marketing,
writing,
some marketing messages,
and then enjoying yourself in that person inside,
who must be a real millionaire, an audience, etc.
Sales is a real thing,
you do something,
and because you are so excited that it exists now and that it helps someone,
you find someone who you think will be that person,
and you tell him with all your heart,
and you ask him,
is that really something that would make his life easier?
But you don't need any marketing messages,
and I think that...
I think it is very important that you are
normally friendly, not a fool, but also that you are not...
Grumpy.
Yes, grumpy,
and that you are an optimist.
Because if you are a pessimist, and it doesn't work out,
then it's hard to inspire other people, because you have to inspire them.
So I think that if you are like that, and if you don't have a formal understanding of sales,
it's great.
So sales is a bit more organic, and marketing is...
It seems to me, as a computer scientist,
that I have always experienced myself exclusively as a computer scientist
until 2012, when a colleague asked me if I wanted to start a company.
My elders are businessmen, and when they asked me if I wanted to start a company,
I said no, I am a computer scientist, I am a programmer, that's it.
And it was the first time that I had that relationship for a long time,
without any connections.
Until now, my ambitiousness to have a company overruled me.
And it was like, ok, now I see, if I want to have a business, I have to start selling.
And then you do what you can do, and then...
Do you think that...
On the other hand, there is this argument,
a lot of developers, and I have experienced it,
if I went into sales, if I sold a lot of things, and then into marketing,
then I wouldn't have time for development, I wouldn't be a developer anymore.
Do you think that this is a skill that every developer has to master, or is it one or the other?
Is it excluded, or is it an upgrade, a skill that every developer has to master?
I don't think so.
No, I know a lot of good engineers, who are super happy, good engineers,
and honestly, if you don't have the ambition
to be a CEO, or a more non-strict technical co-founder of a company,
then there is no reason.
Even if you are a technical co-founder,
if you have a good team, then you don't have to sell.
If you work with an enterprise, then you will be part of the team that you will have to be there.
Otherwise, I don't think so.
So I don't think it's unnecessary.
It's true that here, for example, you have an engineer who is a bit shy.
I mean, when you come to it,
OK, I will work as a freelancer, I will not work as a freelancer.
OK, and then you come, OK, now I have to get a job.
Of course, in engineering, in software, it's not a problem,
but you have one job, and you work with it, and you are a freelancer.
For example, if you work in an agency,
and if you want to sell, you want to have more customers,
then you quickly realize that it takes a lot of time.
So, yes.
Maybe a good comment on freelancing is that
people don't get disappointed when they go,
OK, I work in a big system, I'm a junior,
so I would probably go from a junior position to a senior position,
or I grew up in a company,
now I will go to SP, and I will be a freelancer,
and I will try other things.
People don't get disappointed,
and this decision also means that now you are an entrepreneur.
That's right.
An entrepreneur means that you have taken on a lot of responsibilities.
Maybe you don't get disappointed yet,
but now you are alone in the market.
I see a lot of people asking,
how much do I have to pay now?
How much do I have to pay to go to SP,
so that I will be at the same level as I was when I was a kid?
There are a lot of things that you can't calculate at all.
Are you going to go in that direction?
Yes, I'm just trying.
If you say,
ah, I will, I don't know,
this year,
let's say you are working on some projects,
and they are two-month projects,
that means you will have, I don't know, 6 pages in total.
If they are shorter, you can also have 12 pages.
You have a constantly cold deadline,
cost of doing business,
you go to meetings,
and you lose so much time,
and then you realize,
ah, ok, if I work for a Slovenian market,
and if I work for a Slovenian market,
how much does my hourly wage have to be now?
And then you have,
ok, in Slovenia you have some specifics,
and then it's quite difficult to sell an hour,
because no one really knows the cost.
However,
if you take some extra risks,
for hospitalization,
and you also want to get a bonus,
I think that, I don't know,
in our country, for example,
people often don't realize
that if you are an entrepreneur,
it's good to get a bonus,
no matter what it means.
Whether it's a financial incentive,
or whatever it is.
I often see things like that.
I would say that
in software,
this problem is less acute,
because in reality,
it's much more complicated
than it seems.
I mean, good engineers
always have to decide,
but if you are a designer,
it's a really difficult problem.
To be a freelancer,
and then get websites
that are so recurring,
and you have to cover it all year long.
Yes, yes.
We don't have to work on the marketing pipeline,
and write sales,
because we have customers in one phase.
When you mentioned writing,
I'll get to that now.
Now, I hope that
some of our audience
is paying attention.
Recently, we've seen
a couple of blog posts.
Andraž also saw some videos
where you
wrote that you're looking
for a new co-founder.
I think I've seen two posts
for different use cases.
Those were probably posts
that were totally against job ads,
but now I'm going to
explain one of them,
and then I'll mention the others.
You wrote that
you're looking for a co-founder,
a technical co-founder,
and then you wrote
what you do,
in great detail.
You wrote about the financial results
of your work,
how much you earn,
and you also wrote
what kind of job it is.
I think it was
5000 EUR gross,
15% of the company,
4 years period,
and 6 months cliff.
It's like fresh air
in this space.
That's the first part of the email.
Then you explain in great detail
who you are, what you've done,
who you'll work with,
what you want to do.
I'm also curious,
did you get any feedback
because of that?
Why did you do it?
Did you want job ads to look like that?
No, I did it because
I did it because
I had a great experience
when I wrote
only one post on
Slavic Developers
in two posts
to look for a co-founder.
Six months before that,
it wasn't practical for me.
We had four posts,
so it wasn't a good fit.
I learned that
if you want to
get results
in the end,
you need statistical power
in sales and hiring.
Hiring is just a reverse of sales.
I started thinking
how to get volume,
how to get
more attention
and more eyeballs
only because of Slavic words.
I started thinking
what I would call myself.
In fact, if someone
wrote my whole story
and I don't have a hard time
with transparency,
I always have a feeling
that I don't have anything to lose.
Maybe because I've never
written anything,
but I haven't had a hard time
with transparency.
It's a big difference
how to make a pipeline
of candidates.
We got 30 posts
from which we had
three really good candidates.
We were able to choose
which one was good.
I've seen that blog post
in four days
with 7,000 people,
so it's a good number.
It's true,
but the thing is
that it works
for full senior positions.
It doesn't work well
if it's only
a regular engineer.
Why do you think that?
Because they don't understand?
I don't know why.
I've tried twice
for different positions
and it didn't work.
When we were looking for
a chief AI officer,
we got a lot of rejections.
Maybe because
there was a specific set
of requirements.
One of them is
that in the last 12 months
you have to work on
production systems.
Not many people deal with it.
We got a lot of rejections,
but twice before
I've tried the same post
and it didn't work.
But it was for less senior positions.
But it worked.
We'll put a link
on the screen
where you can watch
all the episodes.
People contacted you
and they said
your voice is interesting
but the pay is too high.
Can it be lower?
No.
There were no rejections.
I've put it on LinkedIn.
People got engaged
and responded.
No one commented
that the compensation package
is too low.
Because
in the round
when we offered
a lower pay for
a senior engineer
but a lot of
equity components,
it's hard for someone
to say
that it's too low.
Unless they're interested in
the cash component.
There was a comment
on LinkedIn.
But 60% of companies said
that it's OK.
One thing
we noticed
is that people are
building public.
It's very transparent.
For me,
these two posts
are very good.
It's a Facebook group.
OK, it wasn't for me.
But I'll write
that it's really good.
I think it's very sincere.
We have a few other companies
in Slovenia
that have pay calculators
and live in Slovenia
and multiply with the index
and get paid.
We have a company like that.
But yeah,
I wasn't really aware
if there are
any other things
that you shared
such as transparency,
advantages...
When we started
Genialis,
we talked about
100% internal transparency.
In the sense that
we had all the pay
internally open
and we were able to prevent it.
We also had a system like that.
If you have an internal
transparent compensation,
you need a different system
because you can't talk about anything.
That turned out
to be a substitute.
Transparency,
although in all other
numbers,
is not a problem.
But it doesn't pay.
Why?
Because it simply
doesn't work.
In the sense that
we are not mature enough,
including me,
to be able to...
We have a lot of examples
with each other
and then you have to
think about it all the time.
I've done it so much
that I'm totally
torn apart.
It's dangerous
to deal with it all the time.
Plus,
it's even more dangerous
that you can't hire a person
if you really want to.
Because,
yeah, there's a system
and someone is really good
but the system is broken
and you want to fix it
but you can't because
if you don't,
you can't fix it.
That's the only thing
that doesn't work.
For example,
you are Bosnian
and we told you
that we have such a system
and you said,
no, no,
it's really hard
to scale it.
Buffer is a company
that went through 100 people
and had a totally
transparent system
and it looked like it all worked
on Zoom.
He knew the company
and he said, no, it doesn't work.
What did he tell me?
There will come a time
when you hire a salesman
and you will have to pay him
a lot of money
and a high commission.
This person will have to
be able to earn
half a million,
a million years.
Your engineer will earn 200 euros
and if he sees your sales
he will pay you a million.
That won't be good.
You can't just be an engineer
and go sell.
If he earns 8 euros more,
he earns 8 euros more.
What did he earn?
In the end, it's just transportation.
Transparency is never
a negative thing.
Let's talk about
AI.
Before you came to
Nine, you had a mission
on Dragon Days
and you were the host.
What is
the most
interesting
aspect
of AI
in your field?
What excites you?
What is the most interesting to you?
Which field
do you like the most?
Shit, this is amazing.
General intelligence.
Again,
I see here
that you have an optimistic
and pessimistic camp.
We are optimists
at the beginning of
exponential curve.
Optimists in the sense
that we are at the beginning of development.
It's not necessary
that everything will be good in the future.
This is a very important topic.
Pessimists do it very quickly.
They say,
everything is fine,
but we are already at the plateau
and there will be nothing left.
I believe that we are
very fast against
general intelligence
at the human level.
And, in my opinion,
much faster than humans.
Now,
this is totally
exciting to me.
If you could
do something smart
to reduce
the use of time for
unrelated tasks in life,
what would it be?
As a developer, as an engineer,
on the one hand, you use
cutting edge
as much as you can,
or cutting edge models
that you can get for your use case
and test them.
But,
how do we get
to the next level?
We will probably
release this episode
before the jump.
Now we have
Co-Pilot,
Cursor,
where all the ideas are integrated together.
In a way, you use
this technology for a short time,
and probably
before or after this technology,
the rest of your job
will be complete,
or not, or maybe not.
How do you deal with this?
Because I notice that
I ask myself
what I build
out of what I do.
Where do I add
value as a developer?
If I write
some stupid scripts
and now generate them,
probably this is not the best use of my time.
I also have to evaluate
as a developer, as an engineer.
How do you deal with this?
I am a slab programmer,
and for slab programmers,
for us slab programmers,
this tool is really good.
Because you can create a cursor
that has this interactive mode,
where you can
put whatever you want,
and the whole project is written
with all the files.
It's really impressive.
I can't wait to try
because I haven't tried it yet.
I really think
that it will go in this direction.
Even if one of my sons
would ask me
if it would be good to go into entrepreneurship,
I would probably say no.
I mean,
I wouldn't advise him to do it.
You have to work in the physical world,
and here you can still do it.
You need a plate for that, right?
Yes, anything in the physical world,
but not in the information world.
I have a strong feeling
that the whole mental
and information world
will come to me.
Artificial intelligence
in the sense of
productivity.
If you are an artist,
that's something else.
But in the sense of productivity,
we don't have a chance.
I mean,
programmers,
that's a pretty solid
title.
So,
for me,
it's exciting.
I'm really
looking forward to it.
I'm really looking forward to it.
Even in that sense,
I started to think about it practically.
The question is
when will we reach the threshold
where I won't have to
focus too much on
employing new engineers,
but more on
what I want to do,
which will be faster,
more expensive, and so on.
I don't think we are that far yet.
We will only write
jira tickets, and then
people will say,
I watched the interview.
I thought a little
about that,
and you can correct me later,
but when Facebook came out,
it was a big deal,
people will know
how old I am when I enter Facebook.
But when Facebook came out,
it was a revolution,
a big deal, when Facebook
released its graph apps,
which enabled
foreign developers
to work with Facebook's data
and their apps,
apps that
worked within
the system.
A platform was created,
and people developed their own apps
within the system.
Well, it's 2024,
we still have some
information security,
data, etc.
But again, it was a platform,
and within the platform you could
create apps. Until a certain point
it worked, but it was a platform
where you could create things.
If we look at Playstation,
we work on its apps.
iOS,
which Apple released,
AppMarket, again you could
create apps for that platform.
And a lot of times
it happened that
a startup created
a product within those ecosystems.
Maybe at the beginning
they were full top-sheet products,
but then those platform owners
said, hey,
what if we created our own?
And they developed their own products
within their own ecosystem.
They had an advantage anyway,
because they knew the ecosystem better.
And here it seems to me
that with such products
you have to ask yourself,
do I really have something
that those who created GPT
don't have to create themselves?
Do I have to think of it as
a technology that I just
install within the product?
Or do I have to think of it as
something that they can eat?
I don't know, it's just something
that you have to think about.
I think that it's very difficult
to be in a foundational model of business
like Anthropic OpenAI and
short application layer business.
It's practically impossible.
If you're going to work on models
within that foundational model
and you're going to be good at it
for a while, until it's
totally commoditized with open source
and so on, I don't believe
that it's going to be an algorithmic
edge, and in the end
open source will prevail.
But if you're working on an
application layer, you're going to
use foundational models.
So, for example, if I'm afraid
for our company,
it's not OpenAI,
it's not that, because
all the other competitors
that work on similar
services are using the same
foundational models.
And then the question is,
why do I have an edge?
Because basically everyone
uses the same technology.
And now, as long as the basic
models are still alive,
you can have a full and thick
wrapper on top of OpenAI.
The thickness of the wrapper is your differentiation,
which is hard to reproduce.
As the foundational materials become more and more intelligent,
the layer becomes thinner.
The reproducibility of your startup is simplified,
which is what scares me.
With every new OpenAI model,
the pipeline that we create,
it becomes more and more obsolete.
It becomes more and more obsolete,
because the whole group is working on zero-shot,
and you always have to use O1 model,
which was released yesterday,
from OpenAI.
They explicitly say, use zero-shot,
don't make a bigger sample,
because you will damage the accuracy of the model.
The data will only go to what is personal,
not to everything.
Very soon we will come to the conclusion
that there will always be less pipeline needed,
that everything will be done in a simplified way,
with context, and you will get a very good response.
You won't have to crush your business problem
on a smaller scale.
That's what I think.
Either other startups will reproduce it,
or sales platforms that are bigger,
like HubSpot, CRM,
with which we integrate.
Why did they do it themselves?
This is an innovator's dilemma.
I don't know.
It's an innovator's dilemma,
and culture values.
You can also get internet in big companies,
when they hack it in half a year.
But it's not a problem in big companies.
It's a very interesting dilemma.
Why didn't they do it?
The problem is that they can't.
You can do it, but you can't release it.
You can't release a solution that works
for 95% of the pages.
It has to be reliable.
If the media comes and says that this product
doesn't work, you're done.
If you're a startup, you're not done.
That's why startups can innovate very quickly.
I have a question.
In one of your blog posts,
you wrote,
when we talked half a year ago,
that you would make your own CRM,
and then integrate it.
When we took your blog post in January or February,
you pivoted.
Does that have anything to do with it?
Did you realize that you should approach it differently?
No, the main reason why we pivoted,
and that's one of the more difficult things.
It's very difficult.
You can write a lot,
but you can't release it to people.
You have to learn from someone else.
You have to do a lot of coding,
but you have to pivot.
That's a very important discipline.
At the beginning, when we started,
there was a lot of metal.
The sunk cost was too high.
That discipline is key.
The main reason we did that
was because we realized that the idea was to make CRM from scratch.
I wasn't aware of that at the time.
VC told me it would be a problem.
If you make CRM from scratch,
you'll work with small companies with very little money.
Let's say you get some money.
When they get to the point where they have more money,
they become so big
that they won't be satisfied with your small CRM,
which has basic functionalities,
but you need a much smaller CRM,
which has a lot of integrations,
but you don't have a chance to develop them in half a year.
And you'll get lost.
That's why it's so small.
In other words, the path to it is huge capital.
And we live in a region that doesn't have a lot of capital.
One startup is very interesting,
Daypeak AI,
which goes from top to bottom.
They got a lot of money.
Here you have a 20-year history.
When you run out of money, you get a new one.
But here, in our capital allocation world,
it doesn't work like that.
You need to have proof points all the time.
I'll give you an example.
A few people I've talked to,
both founders and co-founders,
people who work in engineering in different companies,
they've heard about the AI hype train,
and now they're putting an AI sticker on it,
like there's no tomorrow,
and they get an AI sticker for obscure things.
A lot of people say,
we're making a product,
the investors have nothing to do with AI,
but some founders and investors
tell us to put an AI sticker on it,
because our evaluation will be better.
On the other hand,
we also take blog posts, articles and researches,
when people see an AI sticker
and think it's unbearable,
because people already have the impression
that it's a negative connotation,
because sometimes it means
an incomplete product or a bad product
due to certain weaknesses of the tools.
I'd like to ask you about that.
You wrote that you talked to a lot of VCs,
I think 30 plus VCs,
do you feel like VCs are really looking for startups
that are dealing with AI today?
At the moment,
the tech scene is not at its best,
but do you feel like VCs are looking for companies
that have a healthy AI sticker?
Is it a formula?
There is a hard mentality, for sure.
VCs, like everyone else, are very different.
You have 10% good,
10% bad,
and then you have Gauss.
A particularly acute problem in the VCs industry
is that a lot of VCs
don't have time to prove themselves,
because they are in a 10-year cycle.
You make a fund,
then it takes 10 years for you in the VCs to get to the proof point
whether it's true or not.
A lot of VCs make a fund,
but no one makes another fund,
because they invest in stuff and don't get anything out of it.
So it's hard to say what VCs are doing.
It's not as monolithic
as you might think.
So there are definitely some that are working on it.
Some are down to earth.
They will tell you that it doesn't matter
what you show them.
The problem is the scale of the users,
we don't have a business.
On the other hand,
there's a lot of value in it.
So it's not just hype.
It's a lot of work.
We are optimistic
that it will grow.
From my personal experience,
I was skeptical at first,
but now that I use it in IDEA
things are definitely changing a lot.
I haven't slept for a day.
What's next?
I hope I can say something.
Will there be better models?
Did you know that the mid-layer
where the added value is created
when you work in an AI startup,
will there be better models?
I think there will always be more
impact on the distribution.
As you said at the event.
The price of the software will go down.
What the users will really value
is the understanding of the problem
and the users,
what they really need and want.
You don't have to build AI alone.
You have to talk to people,
you have to be there with them
and watch the world.
As long as you can build it,
I think it will be very valuable.
I think that the whole mental world
will be valued
and it will be a gift to the physical world.
There will be a lot of changes.
What Tesla does with these robots
and a couple of other firms
is very interesting to me.
All these robots will have
some kind of general intelligence
through these models.
The robot will learn something,
it will learn, it will do it,
and it will know.
We will come back to this.
The productivity will be
because of the efficiency
and it will be done.
And in the end,
the human element will remain.
I think it is very interesting.
The IKEA will come later
and it will make the museum
more valuable.
In the end, we are still ready
to pay for a unique museum
where we know there is a museum.
I can't wait to see the code
written by a programmer
and admire its beauty.
If we don't destroy
these sympathies,
there will be nothing left.
You will be a programmer
and I will be a commissioner.
I see some kind of visual
and aesthetic in my code.
Now for the audience
and for the guest,
this is written by a rock,
so it is very visual.
Andraž met a colleague
at this conference
who was in the construction site
and Andraž mentored him.
He said he is going back
to the construction site.
We need to do some media
for the museum.
It will be a product
that will be important in the future.
It will be a user experience
in software.
It will reduce the amount
of code written by programmers.
I think that this wave
generates a lot of things
that need to be done.
From operations,
to front-end,
specialists, designers.
You have a great team of three.
I thought you said three or four.
You will probably need
a mobile developer,
a specialist.
Let's wrap it up for today.
The future will be funny,
if not painful.
Vasy Jamel will write us AI.
Get out of the tower.
Or go to the tower.
Be brave before luck.
Before we say goodbye,
thanks to Patreon, Kaldi, 3FS and Human Frogs.
Thanks to the team.
Thanks to Dragon Days for hosting us.
Thanks to our guest Nejc.
Let's listen to each other.
Good luck.