The first episode of the third season in Grodno.
Who would have thought that we would survive until the third season, but now we have started the third season.
Some kind of government.
So, with brand new stickers, you see, we have a new merch.
The players have made the whole graphic design.
So, we will start on all the channels, with a new look, new colors and a new melody.
Lara has also joined us to help spread the word and the sound to the younger population,
which we don't usually catch with the channels we are on now.
So, this is the beginning of the intro.
I have a full-time job here today.
When I was doing some research, I saw that you have a bigger audience than I do.
So, you have more in common with the audience than I do.
So, if I ask you something awkward, I can fix it.
No problem.
I was thinking today, when we started the podcast,
why would you have this podcast?
Who are the guests? Who will you invite?
I would like to talk to the director of Microsoft Slovenia.
What should Vršič have for Open Data?
Maybe 50K autologs and a letter.
These are some of the topics we need to have.
We already had some other topics in previous seasons,
but this episode with Open Data, I really hope we can start a new season with it,
so that we can show people that this is open data,
and that something interesting can be done with this data.
I would also like to find out what is the effort that needs to be put into making these data accessible,
that they are prepared and up-to-date.
This is one of the themes of this podcast,
with me Magister Aleš Vršič and Dr. Mateš Pesek from FRIA.
You are the Minister of Digital Transformation.
Welcome, both of you.
Thank you.
My introductions are usually too long, so I don't want to lose the guest.
As you can see, you also have the story that the autolog that was prepared and developed
to the point where it is usable for the user,
people use it and it is also integrated into the portal.
I don't remember the name.
Opsi?
No.
Dobro auto?
Yes, Dobro auto.
So, you took open data, used it, developed products and integrated it into a bigger story.
Yes.
Maybe we should start on your side.
Yes, maybe a prelude to that.
I met you and Aleš in 2014 because of Žejna, my colleague.
Ah, ok.
Hruške.
Gašper.
Shout out, yes.
We met once in Kornar.
We started talking about data, what can be done with it, and then we started.
We started with one topic, our VSS studio, multimedia technology.
We started using this data as a theme for our seminar.
So, we took the data, prepared what can be done with it.
On the other hand, we had Aleš, Alenka Občaničnik, Marino Rajic in recent years,
who helped us keep in touch with all the agencies involved.
That was before Opsi portal.
At the same time.
Yes, a year later it came out.
If you type opendata.si and go to the fifth page,
some projects are listed there.
It says 2012.
Yes, Hruške.
I think Gašper was working on it at the time.
He was already very inspired by this data.
Opsi portal, later 2015-2016.
December 2016.
Yes, he was working on it.
We started with the data, and it was great.
We were Aleš, who was in touch with the agencies,
asking for data.
There were a lot of fears.
There was a lot of feeling of isolation from the agencies.
Because when you give the data, people start to prepare what to do with it.
Then, fast forward.
The students didn't find a way to use the data.
There were some interesting inconsistencies.
For example, we took a state budget.
People visualized the state budget,
and it turned out that there is a bunch of projects,
a mass of projects worth billions,
where all projects are worth 100 euros.
Really a lot.
I said, ok, cool, give me the money,
and I'm happy for the next 10 generations.
It turned out that someone, at some point,
when he wanted to open a project,
could give a minimum value, a minimum budget,
which was limited to 100 euros.
These were projects that never took place.
In the state budget, it was still the same location,
and we saw it in the visualization,
as a huge amount of money,
which is something, if it was never realized.
Then, when we went to the visualization,
the municipality used the data on payments,
and the smaller municipality made more money.
Here you can see how optimal we were,
when it comes to using the data.
The smaller municipality used 2-3 dinars
for the payment from the municipality,
and maybe the administrative person.
I know this story,
because we had Transparency International
take a state budget,
and here there is a classic mistake
of an analyst,
when you notice an unusual deviation.
As you said, the municipality pays,
but what is the catch?
Some of the smaller municipalities
are members of the municipal council,
and this municipality would be responsible
for 10 municipalities,
and all the people who are employed
in this municipality,
work for these 10 municipalities.
And it is possible that there,
the public expenditure is lower,
and then there was a mistake,
one was in the data,
and then there was an analyst,
who would have to alert the public,
that there are some deviations,
and check with the owner,
why these deviations occurred.
Either in the data,
in the decimal,
or in the public sector.
A lot of these things
can be easily solved,
because we always have a negotiator
on the other side.
It is much easier
if someone takes the data
and downloads it,
and then tries to get a contact.
The feedback is different
when there are different people.
At Fast Forward,
at 1.2.18,
me and my colleague Vido,
who worked with us in Lebo,
sat down and said,
we are going to hack something on Saturday.
We looked at different pages,
and said, let's write.
I said, the data in the cars,
I told the student,
how old were the previous owners,
who they were, how old they were,
how many kilometers they had, etc.
I think that in January 2019,
while we were driving to the Danube,
on the E-Residency,
the Estonian one,
we deployed for the job,
and since then,
we have had a lot of success.
A lot of positive feedback.
A lot of different stories.
People were convinced
that they were deceived,
because they didn't want to look
at the technical reviews.
A lot of people said,
we have a completely different car.
Everyone gets a technical review,
but they don't look at it.
You made the document,
you didn't look at it,
and now you want the data to be hacked.
But it's cool.
Let's find a way
to crowdsource the data back to the state.
We do this with a lot of bypasses,
because the MZI
is a website
where you enter the size of your car,
or car,
and you get the data,
how many kilometers the car had
for a certain period of time.
A complete technical review.
What happened, was it successful,
was it unsuccessful,
what were the mistakes,
what are the measures
on all three levels of the technical review.
Not all people were
satisfied with this.
Some people who buy our cars
were less satisfied.
Some people weren't satisfied.
I had a very interesting call
a year ago.
Someone called me and said
it's good to have the data up,
because now everyone knows
that he has BMW Analyzing.
Now he writes that the owner is a legal person.
If he is a neighbor,
he could have bought it with Narem.
A lot of such stories come out.
But generally speaking,
this is the first step of the transparency
of our market, which was very broken.
We added a database
of stolen vehicles
from the Ministry of Internal Affairs.
There are also registration reports
for the stolen vehicles.
It is said that
out of 100 cars or other vehicles,
the one that was stolen
was a successful technical review.
The investigation was very suspicious.
The police said that they didn't
find the stolen car.
There were a lot of tweets about leasing.
They called us from the leasing office
and asked if we could get the car back.
The police didn't do that.
We were a bit surprised.
When you have a leasing office
in the background,
you don't know who you're talking to.
If we go to Aleš now...
I want to mention
the story about Vinšte Vilko.
If we had
our Ministry
and the Ministry of Information
and the Ministry of Infrastructure
meeting at the Information Commission,
Vinšte Vilko would have
been prepared in one step.
According to some European regulations,
Vinšte Vilko is a personal data.
In my opinion,
it somehow influences
the car industry
how to limit access to these data.
You have to process all the data
related to Vinšte Vilko
via GDPR.
It represents
a certain challenge.
The Information Commission
approved the whole process.
It took a lot of time.
Now,
I have to change the law
and write that
Vinšte Vilko is a personal data
and it can be public data.
The land plot
for Vinšte Vilko is a personal data
if you have the last name
and the owner of the plot.
Vinšte Vilko is public
and accessible.
You search for Vinšte Vilko
and you can get personal data.
What about registration?
Registration is also a personal data.
Stealing vehicles have been reported.
What happened
is that the police said
that they do not have a database
of stolen vehicles,
only the Information Commission.
Since then, the police have been
updating the Information Commission.
This is a feedback
of the open data.
You can force the environment,
the state as a whole
to make things better, more transparent
and cleaner.
People don't understand
that the consistency of data
is an internal ongoing process.
You don't do something
and then let it go.
That's why
there is a fear.
It's a kind of personal data.
Yes, yes, yes.
But the problem is
that someone has to be behind the scenes.
Often in these polls,
it's someone who is
maybe half a year before retirement,
who has gone through a decade
and knows everything in his head.
You can get this person
and ask him directly
because he knows everything.
All the laws,
who decided 15 years ago
that something happened.
Unfortunately, this is not the case.
We are not yet at the level
where you go up, take the data
and everything will be clear
because you will be documenting it.
But all the polls have a repository, right?
That's right.
They have a repository,
people who are responsible
for publishing the data
on the OPCI portal.
There are different approaches.
We have a system of harvesting
and they send us updates
on which collection
may be removed,
which is a new collection,
which is being corrected.
We have a similar situation
for geospatial data
by the City Administration,
which has a geoportal
under the directorate of WISPIRE.
We read their descriptions
because the OPCI portal
would not be the central
source of information.
We are not in the open data.
We have two links on the OPCI portal
for some time now.
One is open data,
the other is a collection
of information,
where the collections
that are closed
are published.
But it is important
that the user knows
that this collection exists
and that there were not
any other sources
where this information
could be obtained.
Let's look at some statistics.
For example,
the evidence of migrants
led by the police.
I have an example
of a migrant
who walks through the state.
Maybe the state is interested in them.
Maybe they are interested
in the population
and the dynamics.
If this is published
as open data,
monthly and weekly statistics,
we can speculate
that the information
is more transparent
and does not have to bluff
and say that the migrant
is a dark-skinned person
with a dark will.
We are also trying
with the group of
Mateja Šumena,
Lenka Marlina and Mateja Prešeran,
to not open
the data
because it will
contain the most mistakes.
I remember
when I was studying
at the University of Šumrada
for a PhD.
In his book,
he said that the accuracy
of the data is very high.
We will never be 100% sure.
One half of an investment
is possible for today.
The more data,
the more mistakes can be made.
I always say that
if you give data for free,
it is not a crime.
But if you use it for free again,
everyone on this planet
can use this data.
What is the benefit?
We have also made
a contact window
where you can
contact the manager
and tell him
to improve the data.
The data should also
have a structural basis
for the policies.
As Mateo said,
to watch the dynamics
of the data.
Sometimes it goes up,
sometimes it goes down.
When I thought about it,
I realized
that we found
a problem in the system.
The first step
is to have a technical overview
when you come in.
And those who do
a technical overview
also look at the current
status of the data.
You can't register the car
if it is broken.
A technical overview
also has to be a real
status of the data.
Mateo just revealed
a bug in the system.
Now the decision makers
have to fix the system.
I don't know the details
of the registration process.
It is not a big deal
to have an autolog in your process.
No.
The autolog revealed
the system difficulties.
You improve the internal processes.
There are a lot of things
where we were in a hurry.
The minister and other agencies
told us to do it ourselves.
For example,
when we were in Furs,
we asked the minister
if we can get the data
on the state of the car
when we paid the taxes.
It is said that
some amount
is lost for some 100,000 km.
You drive for a long distance
until you pay VAT,
then you drive for a long distance.
The state has two data.
When you get the data
through a technical overview,
it is clear that someone is
fooling the state.
It is not a chance.
Half a year later,
they made an app
where they said it is
the key data for the consumer.
On the one hand,
we told you that we wanted
to do it in the autolog,
but on the other hand,
Furs was doing something
about it.
A lot of things can be
said about the damage
of a consumer buying a car.
On the other hand,
there is the safety aspect
on the road.
We don't talk about it,
so maybe the Minister of Health
or someone else could say
that if we have a car with half a million km,
the catalyst does not work.
We know that you don't fall
because of the catalyst.
There is also the safety aspect
of servicing a car
on the motorway,
trucks, and so on.
It is a big deal
that when an agency
does something,
it sometimes creates a million-dollar project.
We had the opportunity
when we started doing it.
when we started talking
and we said it would be great
to have a meta-app for data
on LPPs, other cars,
intercity traffic,
Avantigo,
all wheels, car-share,
bike-share, whatever it is.
It was also a European project.
We prepared a presentation
with Matejan Cerer from MOL.
He said it would be great
if the municipality could get the data
because a lot of these things
are managed by the municipality,
the coordinator, or the owner.
Before we go to traffic,
I would like to ask you
that you have been working
in Autolok for a couple of years.
You will tell me exactly how long.
Probably 5 or 6 years.
Every year you get a dump
for each year individually.
What did you prepare
in those 5 years?
What did you learn
About 95 million records.
We have technical reviews,
which are 4 years or older.
We have new registered vehicles,
we have some average data
for half a year.
I think the technical success
is still there for 9.5 years.
Some are for a year,
some for a month,
when we have new registered vehicles.
The interesting thing is
that errors appear
when people re-write kilometers
from odometer to computer.
However, these errors
are much higher
in some German records.
In a way,
we can raise
the transparency,
but on the other hand,
we often buy old German cars
and pretend that they have
a small odometer.
In practice,
if there is a demand,
there will also be an offer.
Another interesting thing
is that there are
an incredible number of people
in other aspects of the purchase,
sale, maintenance of vehicles
who use Autolok.
For example, police officers,
car mechanics, etc.
I have always found it fascinating,
because I would expect
that there are other choices.
For example,
I talked to the leaders
of the test sector.
They said that Autolok is great
because we can use it
to reduce the damage
on cars that have been
turned over a few times.
Then we get some harmful examples
of a very expensive vehicle
that had only 100,000 kilometers
and then it turns out
that five years ago
it had 400,000 kilometers.
This means that the estimated
value of the vehicle as a whole
may have paid off.
We are talking about a couple
of tens of thousands of euros.
People are very happy
and we are very happy.
If you were to use
this data,
would you also create
a data stream
or give it back?
What we are doing
is that Autolok has provided
us with a process
on how to correct this data
for the state.
If you make sure
that your data is correct,
and then also in Autolok,
where we don't get an update,
to correct it to the extent
that the data is consistent.
What we did was a bypass
of what most people
would like to have by default.
Maybe it wasn't a political choice
to do this in the last five or six years,
so that the data
is better,
more transparent,
more consistent.
We have opened
the whole NAPI.
You have to stand up now.
Sorry, sorry.
I will just ask you
if you have a microphone.
I will ask you.
What are
the good
holders of this data for you?
Are they
researchers?
Are they people
who integrate it into products?
Or do you know everything?
Do you get any feedback
from use cases?
Basically,
we only complain
because we don't have enough feedback.
For Mateo, we already know
the individuals who give us feedback.
We would like more of this.
Because on the basis of this feedback,
we also benefit from
what the European Commission
estimates every year,
how mature we are as a state
in terms of data,
and what we are proud of.
The last message from the OECD in December
was that we are
within the OECD state,
we are speaking for the whole world,
we are in the top 10,
in the 7th place.
I drank a lot of coffee because of that.
You are talking with a laptop,
give me another one.
The European Commission
is satisfied with the number of places.
According to the percentage points,
we are still at the same,
we are still in the 15th place.
But we should know that
when we look at the OECD,
four years ago,
among the top 10 states,
the OECD had 5 European states
and 5 non-European states.
In the last message,
there were 9 European states and 1 non-European,
South Korea.
I want to say that
the European Commission,
according to its estimates,
has improved the culture
and the view of open data
at the level of Europe.
Europe is a global unit.
We are happy
and I am happy
to meet my colleagues
from all over the world.
Europe,
when it comes to access to data,
is at the top,
among the best in the continent
and in the global system.
Africa is a sad story, other countries are buying their data,
Asia is also a sad story, USA, Canada and South America are trying to make some progress.
Europe is a real mess in the last 4-5 years,
and I have to say that the public will understand,
that the process of opening the data started 20 years ago.
There was also the information value,
the first law that enabled the access of information value,
which evolved over time,
I will talk about it in the European Directive on Open Data,
in Slovenia we have the law on the access of information value.
Here the public should pay attention to one thing,
we have the law on the access of information value,
if someone demanded from the institution to have data for the information value,
he had to get a PDF.
Then the state institution fulfilled this demand.
It is in digital form.
If you say you want to have data for re-use,
and here is the catch,
you have to have data for re-use,
you have to have data in digital form.
And this is where the machine intelligence comes in.
Excel is also based on it.
I don't scan the PDF anymore, but I type the PDF.
No, no, no.
There are clear criteria,
the digital format means that it is based on the table of contents.
Passable.
We have at least three stars in open formats,
CSV, XML, JSON.
PDF, Excel, Word, absolutely not.
Even if someone publishes,
we have a system order.
If an institution publishes some data,
and if it publishes Excel,
this collection will not be visible as open data.
It will be visible only as information value.
You can open them in Excel.
We know that you can open Excel in any other program.
However, if we are strict,
and this is why we said that we don't want a person to decide.
We have decided on the rules of the game,
we have decided on formats that are readily available,
and if the uploader does not meet these criteria,
it will simply not be open data,
and it can become a headache.
Here you have to hit something.
These data are published in some CSVs.
However, these data are somewhat manually dumped,
which means that every year we have a special challenge
on how to parse these CSVs.
For example, headers are manually corrected.
When WTF16 is set to WTF8,
someone in some column header
presses Enter, then Z,
and you have a new line, then Z,
the names of the columns are changed.
For example, we have a whole function
for the age of the carrier,
because someone calculates every year
what the age of the carrier is.
You don't get the year of birth,
which would be a fixed data,
and someone who runs this script every year
will of course forget to put plus one on the current year.
When you read the data,
and then you have data between 2.12 and 2.14,
which are all equal,
because someone forgot to put plus one on the years.
So we rely on individual examples
on how we can generalize these tasks.
For example, the last dump of data
that was published on Ops.java
doesn't have a single letter in it.
I mean, ID or whatever,
everything is a letter.
There are a lot of such problems
that were reported,
and the question is if they will ever be changed.
So you have to realize that
all data are manually variable.
Garbage in, garbage out.
Matej, if you remember,
one of the previous ministers,
Boris Goprivnik,
came out of his cell,
of course, all hyped up.
He introduced us to the students,
and the student said,
what is the problem with the data?
That Mercedes-Benz is recorded in the data
in seven different ways.
Because there is no code
that would say
Mercedes-Benz,
and everyone who is involved
in the system
wouldn't need,
I mean, no one would have to worry
about the code.
Now we have changed it.
To be fair,
if we go to a bigger or larger company
and look at systems
that have been in production
for 10, 15, God forbid, 20 years,
the question is what is in there.
But here you can look at it
as a problem.
Shit, we won't open the data
because people will know we have the data.
You can look at it as an opportunity.
We will open the data,
and people will steal the source.
I don't have my own personnel
who will go to a 30-year-old database
to check it,
but others will do it instead of us
and they will explain the inconsistencies
and we will be able to counteract
our process.
What are the biggest fears
on the other side?
Do you mean that you will leak
some personal data?
No, I mean personal data.
I think that in Slovenia
people are very careful
and they check twice
and there are processes.
It is very difficult
to leak personal data.
Of course,
hypothetically,
from one record
you could anonymize
a tractor
from a 50-year-old woman
from a smaller municipality.
We won't know
which person it is.
No one will know,
but this person already knows
what kind of tractor it is.
From personal data,
it is a topic
where you can anonymize
a person who is the only tractor
in the municipality,
but I always ask
if anyone in the world
knows what kind of tractor it is.
What are the conditions
for Mateuš
when he uses the data?
Does he have to
delete the data
in some conditions?
Can he work with them
as he wishes?
No, no,
all the data
in Euroterm
are translations
that are a part
of the author's work.
We use all CC BY licenses,
four and nothing.
CC BY is
Creative Commons.
For example,
Euroterm is a translation
that is a part of the author's work
and is not commercial.
It can also be used
for commercial purposes.
Even if Mateuš makes a business
and earns millions,
so be it,
he will pay for public service
and so on,
because he will pay
as much as he can
and he will get the money
in installments.
I want to say
that basically
all data levels
are exclusive to
100% of the data.
This happens to us as well.
We had this experience with
car data.
We get these annual and
half-annual installments.
There is a company that
charges you 10 euros
for the same data,
and the next day
you will have the data
in your technical review.
I spoke to the developer
and he asked me
if he could give him more data.
I told him that we didn't have time
to deal with this.
I wrote to the minister
and he agreed to the meeting.
I asked him if he would give me
the data. He said no.
I told him that I know developers
and he wrote me an email
to give me the data.
You pay for the data,
but there is only one
commercial company that
provides the data.
We are trying to get
all the data equally.
On the other hand,
when we develop these stories
for other projects,
we are creating a buffer
for agencies that don't have to
transfer the data to the state
for the infrastructure to
share it.
We will share the data,
we will provide it,
and our infrastructure will take care
of it.
If you find an example
where you think
that this is not what it should be,
you should contact
the information officer
or the Ministry of Justice
if you are responsible for the law.
You should warn them
to come to the opinion
of the users
of the law and
it will be done.
If no one knows
that this is a problem,
no one will solve it.
I am one of those people
who think that we are not children.
I know that the API exists.
The developer knows that the API exists.
The developer wants the data access
if you confirm it.
You pay for the API,
but we still pretend that it doesn't exist.
Sorry.
It is relatively easy to check.
Autopilot, technical inspection,
and the next day
you go to a website
where you write your data
about your car.
The API exists.
The economy exists.
There is some access.
On the other hand...
I will ask you a lot of questions.
We are now part
of the European Union.
This law is the directive of the EU.
Can Autolog do for the German market?
It is not that simple.
We have different interpretations
in different countries.
The Germans are very interested
in private data mining.
The German industry also
forces private data mining
because they have other business interests.
They could not do it
for their market
because they would have a lot of problems,
but for Italy it would be easier.
I think that here we have
an opportunity
if the Balkans
are transformed.
The car is three times new.
First in Germany, second in Slovenia,
and third in the Balkans.
In order to cover this part
unfortunately or luckily,
some data
cannot be obtained
because in Germany
cars undergo technical inspection
after three years.
You have that period.
Exactly.
A lot of cars sold in Slovenia
have 3,000 cars in their fleet,
have their own mechanics,
do not go to a BMW service.
German cars
come to Slovenia
as little needed,
but all of these cars
cover 300,000 kilometers.
In order to cover
any service,
they have to cover kilometers.
Audi A6
is the year 2016.
You ask yourself how you can
not have Audi A6.
These cars often
have very strange
combinations of equipment.
Handles,
tailpipes,
it does not fit into the context.
You will not know anything about these cars.
For cars that have
some damage data,
you will know
that there may have been some damage.
We also talk a lot about
how nice it would be
to have a car like this
in Slovenia.
It would be phenomenal
to know that a car
that had so much value
did not have so much damage.
If you have a 20-year-old car
and it fell to the ground,
it is probably an economic total.
But you know
that it cost
around 1,000 euros.
On the basis of this,
you could decide
what was the real damage.
On the other hand,
people who have a helmet paint their car,
fix every crack.
The damage is also 1,000 euros per year,
but the damage is probably more
because someone took care of the vehicle
than because the vehicle was damaged.
It would definitely be much more
transparent for people
in the market of vehicles.
Let's try to push it to the extent
that an average person
who goes to buy a car
can call three neighbors
and five mechanics
to buy a buggy car
to go back to the market.
Let's talk a little bit
about business models
over open data.
You could decide
at some point
to go to AutoLock.
If you type in the red arrow,
you pay X and get the data.
We are doing this with AMZS.
AutoLock will discover AMZS.
They work in a public interest.
AutoLock is a service
for their larger product.
Also for their products.
For a good car.
On the other hand,
with a good car,
this is my personal opinion,
maybe not their position,
but what they tried to do
with a good car.
Let's sell a car,
but we won't make cars
as transparent as possible.
This game of questions
and offers
is still running on some
other portals,
but it's important
to keep it open.
Not only that,
but here you have
the whole graph.
Of course, this means
a lot more overhead
for a product.
It's a lot easier
to do it without it.
I don't know how we would
do it without it.
It would look like
there are a million kilometers
instead of a hundred thousand.
This is also happening.
But let's be realistic.
There are less than a percent
of such relationships.
We have more than 3%
of negative kilometers
on the summer level.
All these 2%
we celebrate with this.
Let's jump a bit further.
In the OPSI portal,
which is a search engine,
you can search for words
and get the records.
These are the
names of the collections.
Then there are different formats.
Do you decide
which formats
they will be in?
Do you also transform them?
Or did someone
give you the data?
In certain cases,
it is up to the legislator
to decide the format.
For example,
the geospatial data
is decided by the
directorate.
There is
a self-decision
organization.
We try to separate them
from Excel.
We try to
separate them from
CSV,
but it is not a big deal.
We are also
following the example of Montenegro.
Older people know
the views of Montenegro
and their productivity.
They showed us
how they allowed
anyone to publish
Excel in their
open data portal.
Then we decided
to add them.
We have certain collections
that are published in Excel.
We have an app
where you can
add JSON,
XML,
formats that
allow you to get the data.
Even if someone publishes it in Excel,
we have tools
that allow you to add it
in a different way.
Mateo, in your example,
I think that
you are working on your app
in CSV.
You work on your database,
and then on the database.
In your collection,
you also have apps that are not only read-only.
You also have write-only,
which is based on authentication.
Not yet.
We also have
a common app module
which would be a catalog
of all app users
and their documentation.
You should know that
the last version of the
European Directive on Open Data
includes a term
called the High Value Dataset.
It includes collections of high value.
For these collections
and for each of them,
there must be
data available to the app user.
We will create an area
for data
on geospatial data,
data on land and environment,
environmental data,
satellite images,
meteorological data,
statistical data,
data on the register
of business objects,
and data on mobility.
These are the six areas
for which it is already
prescribed that
the app users
must be created,
which will enable
the app user to get
this data.
That's great for us.
The first step for all developers
is to have easy access
to the data,
so they don't have to download
and convert it themselves.
The app must be created here.
Does this mean that
the Ministry of Digital Transformation
will have a coordinator
for this?
Does this mean
that you will develop the app
or will you manage it?
Most state bodies
are centralized.
They have all the infrastructure
in our Ministry.
They are part of the
state government.
They have the freedom
to use the hardware
and software.
As far as I know,
the Ministry of Digital Transformation
has already created
the app users
according to the Inspire Directive.
Most of the data
was created
according to the Inspire Directive.
When Europe came to a compromise
and decided not to impose
additional costs
on the Ministry of State
to develop the app,
they used some solutions
and regulations
that determined
the amount of time
required for the application
and the amount of downtime
for the maximum number of years.
There are some rules
and regulations
that regulate
the data.
The administration
must know
which regulations regulate it.
If you want to get something,
you need to know what it is for.
We have GDPR for personal data
and how you can get personal data.
Then we have the Directive on Open Data.
We have the Inspire Directive.
Then we have
the European Free Flow
of Personal Data,
where the state can
remove certain data
from the state that has
a strategic interest.
Then we have two more regulations
that were adopted
last year
that will bring a revolution.
One is the Governance Act
that regulates terms
such as data intermediaries.
These are the amount of mail
for the transfer of mail and packages.
These will be designed
to allow intermediaries
to exchange data between two subjects.
Like brokers?
Yes, they must prepare
technical and legal support.
They prepare an agreement
to exchange personal and business data
between two entities.
In this way,
it is possible to legally
and safely exchange data.
This data will then be
notified.
You just need to register
your activity
and it can then start
all over Europe.
At the moment,
there is only one Finnish company
that deals with this.
My call to companies
is that this is a business opportunity.
This will then be implemented
in the data space
where it will be necessary
to legally and safely exchange data.
Those who will be the first
will be the first.
Then there is one
that is similarly revolutionary
due to the EU's involvement
on the global stage.
It is the Data Act
that encourages
everyone who has
a computer or a device
to share their data
whether it is a smart watch
or a smart car.
My data, which I have created
with this product,
I want to share
with Mateo and you.
He will have to
provide us
access to this data
for free.
All companies outside
of Europe
that will not respect
this data
will not be able
to access it.
As with GDPR,
if you want to use
an American watch,
you are from Europe,
we are not interested in GDPR,
you will not be able
to access it.
This Data Act will
bring a revolution.
It also talks about
a simpler transition
so that it will be built
into the price of the device.
Theoretically,
is it possible to present
a picture on the Apple Cloud
and then choose Google Photos?
Both on Azure.
No, because if
someone does not have
enough space
and then they want
to take some other data,
it would have to be seamless.
They will build it
into the price of the device
and will say,
you will not pay this much,
but you will pay more.
I expect it to be like that.
You have to be careful
with regard to state bodies.
We will do it legally,
we have legal framework and so on.
We have DRO,
the state cloud.
A lot of agencies
that would potentially
publish data,
or are bound to publish data
in general, do not have it.
Because they do not have
a frame or tech support,
or they do not have
the API running somewhere,
so they have to program it.
Here I see the open data community.
What we have been doing
and are still doing,
in a way,
how to hack it,
we will prepare
an initial access point,
we will prepare it,
we will send the data,
and finally publish it in the community.
It is not necessary
to have a small community
or an agency
with 5 employees,
they will be able to prepare it.
It will not happen,
because they physically do not have it.
things under ZDiAZ, or whatever you send, and then give it back to the sector, and it won't happen.
And here we have an opportunity to do that, because we can do something more with it.
I mean, probably in your position, it's a lot more pleasant than you can say,
where is the scope where the OPSI portal ends, and you say,
ok, that's good, but it's not out of our reach.
I can give you an example from Ogrod, I can tell you about networking.
Networking is now a top topic, and it is changing,
although not so dramatically, but it is changing.
And it is changing with inflation, right?
It is changing, there is now a portal,
myelectro.si, I think that's the title,
which is used by other distributors,
there you sign up with a certificate and get data from those emitters.
There is now a lot of interest in the hacker space,
the hacker community, if you will,
and also in our Ogrod community, we now have programmers
who deal with visualizing, and they want to calculate these things themselves.
And now, for example, 4-5 different prototypes,
or full-fledged products,
which now deal with how graphs look,
or also model the use.
And now, for example,
they ask themselves, ok, I make this product,
it is probably fully usable,
how can I get it open-sourced,
with an option,
with some approach,
so that the tool that solves the problem
gets some kind of backing, in a broad sense.
That's what I mentioned about data management.
In this example,
if you could visualize your data from your emitter
to someone else,
especially where you can pay attention to,
where you go over those walls,
you could create a network log,
or a stream log,
or something like that,
and give them your data,
for example.
We now have an optional dilemma,
we went to a point,
in December 2016,
the portal was set up in this form,
before that,
the open data was determined
on the NIO portal,
so we will say
that this is an optional option.
At the end of the phase,
if we talk about a digital society,
and I am the director of a digital society,
data is also a part
of the digital community,
and it would seem
that the data
should also open up
its data,
of course,
due to the existence
of personal data.
I know an example,
when I was still studying for a Data Steward,
and there was a representative
of MasterCard,
who said that
they share certain data
for the community.
This is a concept
that is still coming to Europe,
and America has replaced
the sharing of data
with a much more advanced one.
I mean, for the money.
For the money,
for the money.
In my opinion,
it seems to me
that in America
there is only one step forward.
Europe, of course,
is successful,
and it seems to me
that we can also
publish data,
describe their collection
based on open data
on the OPCI portal.
This is the dilemma
that we now have
where data is published,
and we have this data
and we want to share it.
I mean, this is a database,
right?
No, this is a business registry,
but if you have a registry,
only data.
You have to understand
that this fear of sharing data
initially stems from the fear
of not understanding what you have.
Also at the state level.
We will not share it,
but it is a kind of power.
If you have information
that someone else has,
it is also an easy position.
It is the same for companies.
Companies say,
we will open some data,
probably at the level
where you say,
go open the data,
everyone would say,
come on, whatever.
If you have individual use cases,
how would it look usable?
Maybe we are interested
in their sensors under the glass,
which are really very interesting
for the community,
how many steps are there for the glass.
Outside of this framework,
this is just my primary activity.
I probably have a bunch of other sensors
that would be very useful.
For example,
if we live in Ljubljana
and we know that
the water level is over 1.9 TDI,
which means that everyone has to go to church
in the winter, the air is polluted.
Now you have a couple of peaceful cities
that are organized.
At the beginning,
it is not too close to big cities anymore.
In Slovenia, there was one,
but Slovenia is now closed,
so we have a clean air.
It is lower in the population.
It is logical,
but if we go to Tivoli,
we will probably have a different picture.
How many people,
how many companies,
where we can collect this data more precisely
and we have a much better reality
of what is happening.
The average values that we collect
are finally published in the newspaper.
In Ljubljana, the average value
was 6 times a year,
or 20 times a year.
We still exceed the average number of days
in which we can exceed,
but in reality,
I live in Šiška,
a lot of people still smoke on the trees,
the air is terrible.
Maybe, Mateo,
as you said, crowdsourcing.
As I mentioned earlier,
you are a prime minister,
so you have to sign everything.
The government says
to cut it short,
but there are a lot of shortcomings.
Someone has to deal
with these shortcomings,
and with the government.
If you don't deal with it,
then it falls on you.
I mean,
if you don't deal with what you know,
then you have to deal
with some policies.
We have to thank Aleš.
He is from our point of view,
as a user of this data,
and a provider of some services.
Aleš, Lenka, Marina,
and Mateo,
that's a shout-out.
They are part of MEU,
and now MDP and MEU,
where we accept calls
where we really don't have to change,
where we look at the state
as an encapsulated note,
internally does these things
in a way that we don't have
to write it down,
but someone tells you
that they could give the data.
If the representative
didn't publish all the data,
we would punish him by law.
But I am a supporter
of some kind of coercion.
Let's talk to people
in a softer way,
let's praise those
who are good,
and not the ones
who are bad.
For example,
I have to praise the Minister
of Finance,
their website is prolecum.go.si.
Slovenia is one of the rare countries
in the world
where you can see
the daily use of state money.
They change every day
how much money we used yesterday,
and how much we collected from taxes.
That's good.
It's a lot of transparency.
I don't know,
you can also look
at all the past calculations.
You can also see
how much money is used for education.
Some people say
that they are gods,
then you go to the graph
and see how much money is used
for education, culture,
and more or less.
Now we are preparing
to publish more data
with them,
I don't know if I can tell you.
It will be very interesting
because of the blog posts.
So, wait for the data
on the OPSI portal.
With the help of Mateuž,
who is a colleague
of the Minister of Finance,
the engine and the foundation
and their students
this application was created.
The way the students
visualized the data
inspired them and then
they published it.
What I wanted to say before
is that crowdsourcing,
the DGA,
is a tax altruism.
What is it?
It's about
setting up organizations
for tax altruism
that will be intermediaries
between the researchers,
like Mateuž,
and the citizens,
if they want to share
their personal data.
Their story is about COVID.
Robert Cook Institute
had a problem because
they wanted to set up
a COVID lab
and they wanted to raise
the temperature of the individual
from the brain.
They wanted to make it simple.
If you have, let's say,
5,000 stars,
or 20,000 people,
you need 20,000 agreements
on GDPR,
and Mateuž won't bother
with that.
He will say,
I don't have time, I don't care.
Here are the organizations
for tax altruism
that will collect
all the agreements
between the researchers.
If we pay these organizations,
it can't be a profitable organization,
it has to be non-profitable,
but we will find a way
to pay them.
There will be a project
and we will find a way
to pay them.
We are always talking about
anonymized data.
The final phases are not interesting
for the individuals,
but for the trends.
You can collect the data,
extract it, and then anonymize it.
Here we are talking about
tax altruism.
It has to be non-profitable.
I thought about it
as a problem.
If they are non-profitable,
they don't have money
to set up an infrastructure.
It would make sense
to have a company
that notifies
the organizations
about it.
It's hard to tell
Transparency International
to set up an infrastructure
and not have money to set it up.
If an organization says
pay as you go,
and it has a researcher...
What we do with a bunch
of data on different projects
is basically that.
We go to the agency
and tell them
we will collect the data,
I think this part
can be treated
as a non-profit organization
that already has
an infrastructure.
You can't go to someone
who has already
set up
an infrastructure
and set it up.
It's not a big deal.
We can set up a thousand
APIXS gateways and do it.
I think it's
phenomenally good.
If we look back 10 years
when we were talking about
NCSV,
it was a huge step.
We were collecting
a lot of data,
we were doing a lot of things,
and now we are talking about
how far we have come.
But in the end,
if you don't hack
and a bunch of people
in the network,
I don't know how many people
on your Discord are hacking
so we can calculate something.
I think someone wrote
on Twitter,
the agency has 60 people
and they haven't managed
to get one calculator up
if they have already
submitted the proposal.
This is the collective
irresponsibility,
let everything be accepted,
let everything be negotiated.
And in the end,
it's just data.
It's up to you and the people
to change something.
This is the bright side of it.
I think it's phenomenally good
to look at the legal aspect,
but on the other hand,
you need people to hack it,
and on the other hand,
you need Vršič, Lenko and others
at the ministry to support the process.
First, they could say
it's not my job,
but no,
I live to take one step further,
to do my best
in my job.
That's why I like
working with them.
I don't have the feeling
that they will accept me
to die because I came
to talk to them and wash
some legal grounds and act
as if nothing is allowed.
I'm not talking about you specifically,
but for a large agency,
we have 5-6 thousand members.
We are like a corporation.
Everyone forgets that
the government of the Republic of Slovenia
with all the ministries,
etc.,
is about 30,000 people
in one police force.
It's a corporation.
Microsoft,
I don't know,
I think it's a similar story.
It looks like a corporation.
You have to sign something
so that the situation
doesn't get worse.
You will always be alone
and you will say,
I don't have time,
I won't do it,
I'm afraid.
With the support of data,
I remember when I was
a student in London
at the Open Data Institute,
there were 10 rules.
A classic explanation
of why not to open the data.
The data will be found inside the package.
So what?
You will help to export it.
It will be worth it.
If we look at the data
from Mravoloj,
it is created
when you pay a tax.
When you pay registration.
Part of that money
also goes to the data.
The data is already paid
by the government.
You always have to look
at the data.
I will ask you now.
You have two or three projects
as an autologist.
A lot.
I would call it
IPAS.
IPAS is
a state entity.
The state is the owner.
I go inside,
I see the data for my company.
Then the key is written
and you say
sorry, this will be 350 euros per year.
Is it
actually the same
with open data?
They publish part of the data
on the OPSI portal.
They publish it
once a month
and refresh the data on OPSI.
I have to say something.
IPAS is
a state
entity.
The problem is
that half of the money
has to be invested in the market.
We get 100% of the money
and we do what we want with it.
IPAS has to invest
part of the money in the market.
We have a good relationship
with them.
They are very prepared
and cooperative.
They have to know their limits.
As we said,
Slovenia
has access to the data
and we are in a position
where IPAS is one of the best in Europe.
For example,
in Italy, you have to pay
for every change.
I don't know how it is
with the change of the owner.
Actually,
all the effort
is in the money
that they get.
I agree with what
Otto wanted to say.
As a company,
you pay for the data
and as an individual
you pay for the data.
We have to decide
which side we will count on.
No worries,
but not on both sides.
A company pays 35-40 euros
for the data every year.
Cool.
But you can't count
for the same data
that someone paid you
to send you the data.
I think it's a bit problematic.
I think it's easier
to see the business model
in the eyes of an autologist
than in the eyes of an individual
who has to come to the market.
Yes, but not on both sides.
The decision is made for one
and that's it.
I think it's problematic.
Why is the IPAS
like this?
Why isn't it always like this?
Because it's always 100%
paid by the state.
But why is the IPAS not like this?
It's something
that everyone thinks about.
Will we pay 2 million for this?
We pay for a lot of other things
or whatever they need.
Let's cover this up
and give them all the data.
But it's not like a company
has to pay 35 euros.
If we count how many companies
there are in Slovenia
on the one hand
it's not that small,
but on the other hand
it's not that big.
We're not in a huge market
that wouldn't be profitable.
And I agree with this.
These 9.5 million
because of the agencies
where there are some
legal violations
on the basis of which
we operate.
That needs to be streamlined.
I repeat,
in my field,
especially in operating systems
and other things,
why is it because of legacy?
Someone wrote something
in 1965.
We've always done it that way.
And it stays that way.
Let's ask ourselves
if it's really necessary.
We operate in a set of things
where the rubber duck programming
would help us.
It's not about the rules.
They probably aren't.
It's the same here.
It's a daily question.
Why do they work?
We look at the data
and we know they worked hard.
I remember the PRS
that was published.
It was without HSMID.
We take the HSI.
We sent it to them
and they did it.
We knew they had the data.
The value of the data is
that you can connect
the business register of subjects
to the data of the law
and place all the subjects in the space.
Then you can work in analytics.
We have a new story
about the number of employees
in companies.
There was a team
that was asked
where to get the data
on the number of employees
in a company.
We asked them
if they had it.
Who could have it?
Statistics?
Maybe they had it.
In this country,
there is no system
to collect data on the number of employees.
It's one of the things
we are discussing.
We would like to try
the data.
The more data there is,
the more interesting it is.
If you are in marketing,
you will attract data
that has more than 50 employees.
You will mistreat
all the smaller data
that may not be relevant.
This is the pleasure
of data,
the added value
that you can give
to the data
with just one attribute.
It's like a geospatial component.
We had the last
talk about data spaces.
If you have a TV for everyone,
they create a thing
with x and y coordinates.
A statistician
has a grid.
They can connect
most of their data
to this grid.
They can also get
statistical data
that is not related
to the population.
For this grid,
they have an application
called Stage,
where you can download
data on this network.
The smallest cell
is 100 km,
which is very thin data
that you can get
for 100 km.
You can scale up
up to 50 km.
It's part of the European network.
It doesn't stop at Slovenian borders.
You can get this data
with minimal
changes
and additions.
You can scale up
to the maximum.
You're well-dressed.
I have short sleeves.
I'm sorry.
I have a T-shirt
in my chest.
We didn't get it.
Sorry.
It's a test.
It's easy.
I'm a Slovenian.
You need a T-shirt.
I need a hoodie.
You need a hoodie.
We made it
from a prototype batch
to see what material it is.
We have a sticker.
I want to call
our listeners
and viewers to join us
on Discord.
If they like it in Grodno,
to support us on Patreon
so we can make stories of this quality.
I also want to thank
Human Frog and
Trifles for their support.
I hope
our viewers and listeners
enjoy it and give you feedback
so we can keep building.
That's the EPP
I have to say.
I would like to ask
because
people will ask me
intentionally, but where is
the open source
component?
Where do you think
the community
can help you the most?
Create
use cases,
create products.
Where do you see
the biggest opportunity?
Where do you see open source
and how important is it?
First of all,
what we are trying to do
is to try to push
the data forward.
We are not focusing on
creating a product.
This product will be obsolete
in 5 years.
If you can build it
as high as you can with data,
then you can come
and have it on the web
in 2 weeks.
We are a developer
with 1 million users.
We did it in 2 weeks
and we still have 10, 20, 30...
How much data do you pay for 1 million?
That's true.
We have to bury the data.
You know, a hundred other people could come in and take the data,
as much as we have for accuracy and other things,
and make their own product.
I don't care. Thank God.
And if I just put my product out there and say,
this is my product, and encapsulate it in that product,
I've basically already failed.
It's much more important to me to put the data out there,
and have a sense of whether it's closed source or open source,
so that everyone can make something of their own in two weeks.
And I was really happy about it,
when I said, we're going to open source this,
and then we're going to look at whether we're going to change anything
in the community or not.
Make your own. I don't care.
We're not going to go around looking at it in a circle.
Do it. But here you have the data,
and you can do whatever you want with it,
and as long as you don't break anything for me,
because I don't have to prepare the service,
then use it.
And that's why I call it open source,
because I see it as open source data,
more like open source of some products,
where you say, oh, I use that product.
I don't know, for Autolock, I don't know,
maybe I used 50 hours with clean data,
I set up infrastructure and everything,
or maybe 100, I don't know,
because we drank a lot of coffee,
and we were drunk with the view,
when the guys were doing it.
Honestly, is it really that fully valuable now,
that I would say,
no one in the world can do it in hundreds,
or in hundreds, or in thousands of hours?
Yes, exactly.
But you can, do it.
Don't worry about it.
Is it really that important,
that it's an open source product?
No, because it has a hood value.
It's not rocket science to do that.
The fact that you can use that data,
because we set it up in the app,
and normalized the data from different providers,
and said, look, here you have data
about all the possible transports,
here you have an OTP server,
which does multimodal transport,
and you can pick up bikes and cars,
and walk, and everything,
and you can say, ok, I'm interested
in ecological sustainability,
or sustainability, or whatever,
and you do it according to your priorities.
Basically, I think it's really important,
that I give you this part,
maybe we can call it a product,
to the extent that you say,
hey, cool, I have an app,
which is focused on this specific aspect,
which I want to develop as a final product,
and I don't have to deal with the fact
that I have to make a policy on them,
and shoot, and all that,
I will do it for you.
You deal with the product,
and it's open source because of me.
So you're more of an infrastructure provider?
Yes, let's put it that way.
We open source data through infrastructure.
And you're a data intermediary?
Yes, yes, I didn't know I was that
until I heard it today.
If you notify yourself,
then you can use this logo.
Aha!
I wanted to say something before,
but...
Oh, cool, in four to six months.
No, no, no.
How long did we need for Zvob 2?
No, no, no, this will go
in February,
the Slovenian implementation
of the European order will go
in February in public defense,
where we will also be active.
We have to look at Aleš,
he's an eternal optimist,
he talked to me about Zvob 2 for years,
but we won't talk about Zvob 2 now.
We can help together.
For example, we have the option
to publish applications
that have been developed,
as soon as the application is published,
you can scroll and say,
ok, I used these options,
so we know where they were used.
That would help us a lot,
because at the moment,
we have the biggest difficulty
in assessing the commission
because we have social,
economic,
environmental,
and governmental impacts.
What are the effects
when you re-use the data,
if someone did something,
or what he did,
a social, environmental,
or economic effect,
it would help us a lot
to know about these examples.
If you say,
this and that didn't happen
in Slovenia because of the data.
This feedback,
I would say,
is a threat to the data,
because someone could
give us an application,
but if it's very hostile,
where is the application,
can you leave it?
The problem is that you want
to re-experience as soon as possible,
and if you give it a chance,
I would also like to say
that there are no applications in other countries.
What you have,
where the data is,
you can do whatever you want with it.
I have to thank,
I don't know if it's enough to say,
the developers,
Marko Kudor,
from the XLAB company,
we have been working with them
for many years,
and it has always been a pleasure
to work with them.
Marko managed to realize
all our wishes very quickly,
and we are very satisfied
with the cooperation,
because everything is going
very quickly,
and we will do what we need to do.
It is also thanks to him
that the portal is in the form
it is now,
and here I would like
to call together
to publish our feedback
based on the applications
that have been created.
If there are any studies,
or documents,
you can write to us.
I will put the links in the description.
So that we know
what it is all about.
So that you know who used it,
and why.
Because it seems to me that in Slovenia
it is quite difficult to do something
on the night of a zombie attack.
At the end,
Autolock has 13,000 active devices
where Autolock
does the job of opening
the web view of the website.
Because it turned out that people
have a lot of trouble registering
those 17 digits.
Very quickly, as you can see,
a couple of these apps
have a relatively large impact in Slovenia.
A lot of them are
latent applications.
Autolock itself is there,
but what does it mean
if someone uses this data
and how does it improve the process?
I don't think we can get that feedback.
You can turn it off,
and they will probably tell you.
We had an example of that.
An anecdote for the community.
One is related to Autolock.
When a child
was driving in Aže,
they were surprised
that the data was available
on the first or second day of the month.
And if they didn't have it,
the whole drama.
Because their business models
were so normal.
They saw what the competition was doing,
and they said, we need to strengthen the company,
because you have this data.
Most of it was for daily registration,
for the numbers to be printed.
It's not about that.
You can get the data from the municipalities.
You can see how many BMWs were sold
in a municipality last month.
And how many buyers and shareholders
were there.
It's an interesting collection.
Another thing that shocked us
was the register of pharmaceutical products.
It was hard to buy.
It wasn't public.
But when it was,
Marina managed to send them
to some Excel or CSV.
And it had 300 pages.
But besides that,
if you don't get the latest version,
and if there's no product
that would sell it,
you know you can't sell it.
And it's for a small company.
In some municipalities,
it's a huge scale.
You can have 10 data in Slovenia,
and without any evidence,
which is basic for their business,
if it's not updated...
You can go to the process.
It's only for 10 data,
because it doesn't mean anything.
It's not just about them.
It's about the impact.
In some municipalities,
one small collection
of pharmaceutical products is a big deal.
But in some municipalities,
you can't sell it,
because it's not registered.
Here, the stories are interesting.
But when you have the impact,
you calculate the impact
for the app.
They give you feedback.
Then you can start hacking.
Yes, yes.
You have weird laws.
Here we have a hacker
for the network.
Then you sell the data back.
It's like you're feeding us
weird laws to bypass it.
When they changed the electricity,
the agency...
One of the requirements
was the efficiency of the data.
I think it said
that the data must be updated.
I was shocked by that.
Electro-disposal?
Yes.
One of the KPIs was
whether the data is updated or not.
In the past, it was very difficult
to talk to municipalities.
There weren't that many people.
Until we had a plan
for a smart city,
which was already unsuccessful.
But the consequence
of that plan was
that municipalities started
uploading data to the municipality.
One of the criteria
was to re-use their own collection.
There was some...
There's interest.
It's like a prototype
of a human rights model
that has a goal
to change something
for the better.
But there's a problem.
We, as Free,
work a lot.
We don't do these projects
in a financially beneficial way,
but we do them
because we can make
a big impact.
It was a very
sweet spot.
Yes, that's right.
This collaboration
and our connection
works so well
because we're all complementary
and we can give each other...
Aleš needs apps. We're working on them.
We need Aleš to help us
because we could legally get
everything.
One is on paper, the other is in practice.
And then you have people
who are actively involved with you.
It's a bit of a legal thing.
Maybe, as Mateš said,
we're all connected.
We started a project
together with OECD.
We set up a network of data stewards
in English.
In Slovenian it's called
skrbnik.
These would be individuals
at institutions who would be
in contact with each other for all the data.
Not just for the open data,
but data from the institution
and try to set up
internal procedures
such as quality control.
We haven't reached that yet.
We're working with Mateuš
on the methodology
of quality of public data.
Because it is what it is.
Now we have to take it to the next level
by raising the quality.
Because we know that data
can be excellent for one purpose,
and completely crap for another.
And the quality...
Interoperability.
That connectivity.
Someone gives you a password,
and the other one doesn't,
and then you do a matching.
We're also looking at
trying out some things,
recommendations.
To be able to connect things.
To automate them to a certain extent.
Some things, for example,
can be automated relatively easily.
To see if consistency exists,
to be able to stick it
to the same scheme.
One more thing.
If we talk to each other,
the network is like a forum.
The individual is currently represented
as a team of 30 state institutions.
As soon as you realize
that you're not the only one with these problems,
that we all have them,
then you start solving these problems
together.
I have to say
that I'm very proud of the individuals
in this group
who want to change something.
Who are promoters of good solutions.
For example, a member of the state
has a payment system
that can change data.
In the decision of the CSD
on data transfer,
the data is transferred via a payment.
Payment of data from 47 different
data centers.
They send them to the CSD
and they make a decision.
Another thing,
international driver's license.
Through the payment,
they receive data
about the condition of the vehicle.
Can you drive a car or not?
Can you transfer alcohol inside?
When the documents were on paper,
it was written
to transfer the vehicle.
When we came to plastic,
there was no such thing.
There was a problem
with the international driver's license.
Then the state took the time
to make a decision
and they confirmed that
there was no problem.
But you had to come to the CSD.
If you were late,
the CSD didn't work anymore.
Until the moment when the CSD
said it,
data was transferred via payment.
You come to the CSD
and you get the international driver's license
without any problems.
These are small use cases.
Because of the payment,
we have a lot of cases
where the state can
make these problems.
Maybe it's not political will.
I don't know if it's political.
Maybe it's misunderstanding.
The state already has all your data,
but you still fill in some spaces.
It's a very ungrateful question.
But
there is a lot of power
when you decide
or when you start
that someone will decide
to give the CSD up there
or to hire a CEO.
You have to portray people.
It's a lot of work
and energy.
People want to hear
and they will see it as additional work.
They will see it as something
that will help them.
We are trying to do that.
We are trying to do that
with Excel.
If you upload Excel on Ops,
there is a possibility
that it will be uploaded.
If I remember correctly,
we haven't used it yet.
We haven't used it yet.
It's been a year.
If I remember correctly,
the people who were hired,
there were no data stewards,
but there were data collectors
who collected the basic data.
It was like the 20th task
of someone.
It was like the 20th task of someone.
There was an attitude
of how we implemented it.
It was so broken.
You have 35 things to do,
then someone will tell you
that you will have to delete
some of the data.
Then they will come to you
and ask for the data.
You don't know how to export it.
Then they will ask you to do it again.
In the 10th year,
the attitude changed.
People started to have
one more task.
There is a legal basis
on which we have to do it.
The idea of the data stewards
was to make it full-time
where you would have a lot of data.
But the process...
I was so surprised
when we started this project.
I thought that if we would have
10 data stewards from the state,
it would be like that.
When we sent a message to the minister
to propose it to him,
he got angry and said
end number 33.
I was like wow.
The profiles are different.
It is a novelty.
Slovenia is one of the first countries
in the world that systematically
implements this function in the institution.
Estonia,
maybe Ireland,
then America.
Let's be honest.
What we are talking about now
will be something that we will need
every day in the next 10 years.
Like we are talking about some situations
where we have been working for 10 years
and we haven't sent any APIX.
I hope that we have sent them
a lot of data because of me.
If you are interested in the futuristic part,
we will get used to the luxury
of how to get this data,
what access we have,
to whom we have access,
who we can communicate with.
That is the beauty of it.
If I look at it now,
we have been working like this
for the last 10 plus years.
A lot of things have gone forward.
We have succeeded in a lot of things.
At the same time,
I, Aleš and others at the ministry
have a feeling that we are fighting
but we have succeeded in everything
and that is what we are fighting for.
Now the manager is talking shit.
We will try to get through
to the end.
I would like to ask
what is the holy grail
that you want to see in the datasets?
What is the data source
or something
that you would like to have
in the same collection
or what do you want?
Is it some IoT data
or some high frequency data?
I know.
He sent us a list.
The more data,
the more good stories
we can make out of it.
When you think about it,
if Mateuš
from the data,
which is primarily
registered vehicles,
would have done
an auto log.
Wow!
As many stories as possible,
I would like
the value
of data
to come to life.
At this point,
I would like you to welcome us
because the first week of March
is the World Data Day.
We will have a campaign
so welcome us.
Thank you.
As you mentioned the auto log,
I have the best feeling
in the world
when you take some data
and make a product
that people thought
it was impossible to do.
There is no problem
because you don't know
if you can do it.
For example,
we don't have the data.
We have one, two, three
very good ideas.
If you want to listen to them,
we will post them on the OPS portal.
If we get coffee.
We understand Aleš's position.
We have to support him
by giving him such things
and promoting them.
But at this moment,
the amount of data
we have,
is to a certain extent,
but maybe not as much
as it is
in specific industries.
There is a lot of added value
in a lot of different aspects
of the data.
The more,
the more awesome.
I would add
to that,
I will give you a chance
because I will not give up.
Good?
I think we have to do it again in 10 years.
In 10 years?
We have a few more projects,
so you have to hear more.
At this point,
I would like to thank you
for your time.
Thank you for listening.
I hope you will continue
with us this year.
Thank you to the team,
to the supporters.
Thank you.