Welcome to the third season, the third episode in Grodje, it's a little different, I kept it a little longer, it's still in Grodje,
but today there's no car here, today there's a car in the back, where are you car? We can't see you.
He's drinking beer.
That's why we have such an interesting guest with me today in this conversation, I hope we'll have a lot of conversations,
with me Ivan Popelnjak, Jan Žorš.
I've had a lot of trouble with how to introduce myself here, but if I say so, Siva Eminence.
Old fart.
Yes, here I think sometimes old, but overcast, experienced.
I'm old.
Poisoned.
Before retirement.
I wouldn't say that.
Poisoned producers.
Let's put it another way, Poisoned from Čes, and then we'll talk about what you're most poisoned with.
I'll try to introduce you quickly, and then you can add something.
Ivan, as a blogger, podcaster, creator, architect, what else did I forget?
Alright.
That's what you've been talking about lately.
Lately I've been a programmer.
That's right, we'll get to that.
Jan, as a...
Jan, yes.
Almost an evangelist.
A speaker.
I don't know, in Slovenia, the ones that know you the most are the ones that push IPv6.
I'd like to add a personal note here.
I can say that I deserve that all operators get together and talk.
Because I think that 15 or 20 years ago, there was no synergy between operators.
This culture has changed a lot.
Back then we did...
When was that?
We did it in 2006.
We did an IPv6 community, where operators came from all over the world.
I remember the first meetings we had.
They looked at each other, everyone was in their own corner.
Usually they talked to each other as guests.
Then it became a community, an internet community,
which later transformed into SINOK, the Slovenian Network Operators Group.
I think that now operators communicate with each other.
They've become friends.
I like it the most at meetings.
When I listen to that, I feel relaxed.
There were no rushes at the beginning.
I think the culture has changed a lot.
At the beginning, every country has its own knowledge,
but now they share it.
I'm glad that I can help here.
Cool.
Let's move on.
Today, I thought we would talk more about the depths of network engineering.
Is that the right term for this?
Everything that is connected to the internet,
and I don't mean the human network,
but the connection between devices,
can be seen as someone who created it all,
if I can call it that.
The internet is what it is today.
If you don't listen to it, express it,
talk to vendors...
It's something like that.
How do you call it? Internet guides?
Ideally, we are that.
I mean, complete networking, not just the internet.
It's an infrastructure that is like a guide and an electrician.
If you know that there is some kind of food.
Yes, exactly.
The other problem is that no one knows about it yet.
First of all, they thought that the laws of physics don't apply to them.
They live in a matrix and so on.
The second thing is that you have an electrical faculty.
We are talking about an electrical faculty.
Five years.
You have a fast current and a strong current.
In the past, you had both automatic and all the rest.
And there is a person who has been studying for five years
how to drive a huge amount of electricity.
At the Faculty of Computer Science, you have one year of networking.
Yes.
And people who go to the station to buy a fan
and plug it in at home,
they don't ask how the electricity came to them, right?
Of course not.
Even a person who goes to the station to buy a fan
doesn't have to ask how the electricity came to him.
But I want to say something.
For a technology that is 200 years old,
graduates are represented in a special way
at the Faculty of Electrical Engineering.
But for a technology that is really only 40 or 50 years old,
we have one year of one subject at the Faculty of Computer Science.
Both technologies are equally important for today's life.
Because if it's not for electricity, networking won't work.
If it's not for networking, then you know what will work.
Yes, little or nothing.
Nothing.
Games don't exist because you have to connect to a server
so that you can start playing straight away.
Something like that.
Well, that's a good conclusion.
But how did the two of you get in here?
What would you say is the most interesting thing in your career
and how did you start working with it?
You started it.
I've been in front of you for 10 years now.
Not 10, not 8 for sure.
You know what's crazy and interesting?
It was around the time of 8-bit processors.
Delta Partners, if anyone remembers.
And they had serial ports in the back.
It's like USB-C mobile for those who are a bit younger.
What's USB-C got today?
A lot.
We don't know.
Well, that's how we managed through our 30,000 bits per second.
And then someone came up with a brilliant idea.
If we now fake a standard, which always happens in networking,
and we connect a receiver and a transmitter to a diode,
we actually have a part of the base on which we can have more computers.
And then he had this brilliant idea.
Once he tried it, he found me and said,
now we need to do something.
And that's how the network between partners was created.
They made it into a nice product,
with higher speed and a better interface.
So in the end it worked like a dream come true.
But what is it that drives you?
The technology is what drives you, but still...
You know what's interesting?
That you manage to communicate with each other through different physical means.
You know, the main book is the main book.
It doesn't run on a computer for a long time.
How do machines communicate with each other?
For example, I remember back in the days of VAX,
maybe it was in 2002-2003,
when TCP stack was implemented.
1992-1993.
You had Multinet and Deco stack.
Those VAXs that had Multinet could communicate with Linux machines,
Deco stack could communicate with Linux machines,
but they couldn't communicate with each other.
Those were interesting times.
I know that this was with IBM's AX,
because it used a different encapsulation on the Ethernet.
I haven't heard about those two yet.
I thought it was with them.
Was the TCP stack on VMS or on Ultrex?
On VMS.
I mean, I know that Multinet sold it.
I believe so.
We sold a lot of them.
Yes.
But...
Let's go back in time.
If we take...
How do you see the Internet or the era
for today and in the future?
Where do you see the biggest revolutions that happened here?
I mean, today we have a different planet.
But the basis is still the same.
Wait, I didn't mean that.
There were no revolutions.
Today we use the same protocols as we used 50 years ago.
Exactly.
The Ethernet framing is old.
I think 50 years.
It went from 10 megabits to 400 gigabits.
800 at least.
800, 1600.
But I think 400 gigabits is already standardized.
Yes, it's already being sold in traffic.
That's right.
TCP, IP, where did the first RFCs for IP and TCP come from?
TCP hasn't really changed.
Yes, TCP got a few new bits.
Congestion avoidance is better now.
There are fewer bugs.
And IP...
IPv6 came instead.
It changed certain bugs.
Yes, it went further into the words.
It made certain things more complicated.
No, I don't think so.
Every programmer would have to go back to The Mythical Man-Month.
It's a book written by a man who was a project manager for the IBM 370 operating system.
It was for work.
It was crazy boring.
The scores were canceled, but then it got a bit more exciting.
And he explains to others that the first system you're going to make will always be for nothing.
It's just a question of whether you can add it to the website or not.
We added the website to the website, and the consequences are here.
We're still holding on to that today.
Yes, and we're still fighting spam.
Just because some idiots said,
we're all friends and we won't account for e-mails and all that nonsense.
And we're still fighting spam because we have to pay our employees.
I mean, it all comes from the premise that we were all the best people on the internet in the beginning.
It all comes from the fact that although the transport network was created as a result of a project,
the application was written on Berkeley.
Let's say.
And then you get this mythical man-month, right?
And then you finally get the budget to write this system anew.
And then comes the second system effect.
Because you've learned what you've done before, and now you're going to fix everything and it's going to be different.
And the second system is even worse than the first.
This is IPv6.
And IETF.
Yes, IETF is...
And then you have how to switch from IPv4 to IPv6.
You have transition mechanisms.
And then you realize that you have 50 of them.
Transition mechanisms.
And then someone comes and remembers that this is not right.
Let's make a transition mechanism that will fit all 50 of them.
And then we have 51 transition mechanisms.
Which is much better than all the other 50.
Exactly.
And look at the XKCD standards.
Right.
Now, I used to mess around with roses.
And then you realize that there are
10 different types,
and subtypes of roses,
which practically no one has ever seen before.
Because they are so similar.
And in the end, you come to the conclusion that
some kind of a species was created because someone needed a proof of origin.
And some kind of technology in the Internet and IETF
was created because someone needed a patent or an IETF draft.
No, in fact, it's still good for now.
They are figuring out a problem so that they can solve it.
Yes.
Now we will...
We lost some listener.
We could take a step back and explain it.
Do you want to go two kilometers back?
What is IETF, what does it represent?
Or...
Let's put it another way.
If we are talking about this child,
if we are talking about the Internet today,
who decides what?
Who decides what?
What are the rules?
This is the beauty of the Internet.
First of all,
first of all,
no one has their hands crossed.
Okay, DNA, SKIS, and so on.
But let's leave it at that.
But in fact,
Internet technologies are one of the rare standards
where the standard is created in the public.
Because we think it's good.
That's great.
That's the only truth.
In fact, all other standard organizations
dealing with telecommunications
live off the sale of paper.
And you have ITU,
which is a representative of the state.
And there, representatives of the state
vote on anything.
I think it's wonderful.
And how do they know about telecommunications?
They send their employees.
Telephone companies, really.
And X25.
And X400.
All of this is no longer for good reasons,
just for those of you who don't know what we're talking about.
There is evidence of what they are capable of doing.
I think the last cry they managed to make was ASDN,
and then it died over time.
It won't heal over time.
Now they will standardize the Internet.
Next generation Internet.
Because it's not good.
Let's all get together,
and make something new.
Something similar to telecommunications.
Should we get together,
or should we just launch something new,
and hope that everyone will migrate to something new?
I'll tell you a story from 2012.
I started working at the Internet Society,
and there was a plenipotentiary meeting in Dubai,
from ITU.
And I got lessons,
some proposals from some countries.
And I was looking at the flyer,
I think it was in Los Angeles,
and I burst into laughter.
And I think Algeria,
one of those countries,
proposed it.
And we all saw how the IPv4 languages
were divided,
that underdeveloped countries
don't have enough IPv4 languages
to build the Internet,
because they all took away
those proud developments.
Their decision was
to reclaim,
to take all IPv4 languages back
to one big pool.
That means everyone has to go back,
and deconfigure.
And then they will divide them again,
according to the country,
not according to BGP,
but according to BDP,
and according to the population,
and so on.
That's how I started thinking about
how it will work.
And then I realized
that it's a great idea.
It's a beautiful idea.
And I really hoped
that it would happen.
Do you know how fast
IPv6 would be implemented?
At the moment,
the whole world would be on IPv6.
In a few months, I think.
That's probably the part of engineering
where the deployment is very simple.
Yes.
It's not very simple,
but it's manageable.
As long as you're starting
something new,
it's fine.
It's manageable.
It's a migration management.
My next question is
is near zero time
the migration done
to divide it?
Because if it's near zero time,
does that mean
that we can do it
in a year's time?
No, no.
They have to go back
and do a study
on how to divide it.
That's how it works
in the end.
Yes.
In general,
ITU proved
how good they are.
Then we have ISO.
They did ISO 9001,
then 14001,
then 12001,
and so on.
They're not bad standards.
They're just implemented
as they are,
but that's another topic.
The problem is
that people document
the existence of the DREC
and then they're compliant.
Because they know
what they're doing.
They're doing the same DREC
as they did in 2001.
Again,
it's very opaque
in Slovenian.
It's a closed organization
that gives out some standards
that you can't get,
but you can buy.
And they change
as they change.
The results are what they are.
The whole industry
lives from it.
And thank God
that the Internet
is on the side
of any of their standards.
At least 10,000,
I don't know.
No, no, no, no,
less than 100.
Really?
Yes.
The whole ISO 9001 standard
was changed,
but it wasn't long.
Really?
Yes.
You know,
the people who cover this,
write what you're doing.
That's the standard.
And then the persuaders,
the Enlighteners,
the Wise Men,
they do it differently.
Then we have IEEE,
those are the gentlemen
who power the Internet,
the Token Ring,
the FTDI,
and all those little things.
And again,
the whole industry
is on the side
of the public,
and then someone comes out
and says,
that's it,
be happy we did something.
Then you have 3GPP.
The same,
just different manufacturers.
Those are for mobile networks.
Or ETCs.
Then you have more ETCs.
Which are ISO,
but European.
And then you talk to them
and prove it to them,
and you have a complete history
of all the scammers
you've ever told the public.
And there you can go to a meeting,
go to the microphone,
and say what you think
about everything they do there.
Then they give you a yo-yo
and send you out.
Most of them there
have long white beards.
But in the end,
are there enough
motivation?
Because I won't go
to an IETF meeting,
because it happens.
Besides,
I have a life,
and I don't know why
I would mess with it.
There you have
in one working group
100 people,
of which 98 are paid
by the manufacturers,
because they drive through
what is in the manufacturer's
complexity,
because the complexity is sold.
Since the 80s.
You know,
if we do something so simple
that everyone knows how to implement it,
and everyone knows how to install it,
and everyone knows how to do it
and sell it,
then we've shot ourselves in the foot.
Yes,
I was at some IETF meetings
when I worked
for the Internet Society.
You asked
a very smart question.
At the IETF,
there are very smart
and intelligent people.
The flower of intelligence
would be overshadowed there.
Now,
what kind of motives
do they have?
How much academic knowledge
That's huge.
How much operational knowledge
do they have?
That's a different question.
You know,
they have a lot,
but it's outdated.
There was someone
from the people who were there
in their previous life,
Operations.
Then he went to Vendoria,
where he spent 15 years.
Then he became a Distinguished Engineer.
Then he was allowed
to speak at the IETF meeting.
And the operational knowledge
he had
was overshadowed.
As much as mine.
Thank God,
I don't have to install a production box
for the next 25 years.
OK.
Let's go back
to
what you said,
to the beginning of the war.
Do you still
have
the knowledge
of a network engineer?
Do we still need it?
Do you need the one
who studies so hard?
You need three years.
But you need a curse.
I would say
it's like those good systems.
If everything works,
you don't need it.
If it doesn't work,
where do you get it?
Why don't you have three?
I remember
when Sreta and I were there.
We installed all the empty tables.
There was Tom,
Tomas,
and everyone else.
I remember when Sreta pulled me
from Novi Gorica,
from Telekom.
He said
that the first thing I see
when I look through the window
of my office
is that you are in a café
and you are drinking beer.
Because everything works.
You are the one
who drinks the most beer
in the café.
Wait a minute.
This is an operations man
who is drunk.
That's right.
It would be better
if he wasn't drunk.
Yes, that's why we automate things, so that we are consistently on the page.
I will quote you again.
Yes, yes.
That was interesting.
Pipi was at the IPv6 Summit a few years ago.
He said he came to talk about automation.
It was one of the first times when there was a big hype for automation.
Software-defined networking.
Yes, and Pipi came and said, you know, automation is basically
that we can consistently standardize our attacks across the entire network.
So, I remembered that and with that ...
I think I still have a tweet, a screenshot, somewhere in the conversation.
Yes, yes, yes.
He said, to err is human.
To deploy the error on 10,000 servers is DevOps.
Something like that, yes.
So, we need these people, but how many people actually decide to do it?
Or, let's ask another person.
What do you see in this person?
What are the skills this person must have?
Look, first of all, when we started developing the IPv6 community,
which then grew, I noticed from the very beginning
that we are missing a few generations.
We have a few generations of gaps in the city.
We were the old school.
Then you have a few generations of gaps that are not necessary.
These are the generations for whom the internet is clicked on Facebook and Google.
No, but you know what?
In Slovenia, for example,
the market size for these people is relatively fixed.
If you look at it, the Slovenian economy is not growing much.
Of course, we have the GDP growth rate of 3-5% every year.
But the population of Slovenia is 2 million, and it is relatively constant.
The company in Slovenia is what it is, and it is relatively constant.
If you want X inhabitants of Slovenia, you need a farmer,
and if you want X inhabitants of Slovenia, you need a networking engineer.
But what about the fact that we have been eating strawberries for the last 100 plus years,
and it has spread well?
While we two, Jan and everyone else,
fell into networking at about the same time,
and there are still some people who are doing something.
Some of us went a little on our own,
a little on half-pension, and a little somewhere else.
But probably 80% of the current generation is still doing something
on some kind of joint work in the city.
Which means that the next generation simply did not need
so many people that they would need excessively,
because we will not die.
That's how it is.
If you look at the Synagogue,
there are between 100 and 120 people who come to every meeting.
Which is a lot for 2 million people in Slovenia.
And they are always the same.
We are getting older.
And then it's like that,
this thing is not sexy enough,
not too much, not too little.
And is diving sexy?
Well, but,
someone might say,
and maybe the people are always diving.
Yes, everything is something like that.
You asked if it's sexy,
not profitable.
But wait, for some,
I said today,
a man, a student,
a student who is graduating,
what did we say,
in computer science,
the question is,
will I make money with it?
Yes, you will.
But, let's say,
an anecdote,
years ago,
I was at the Synagogue,
everyone comes,
students, young people,
a new generation of networkers has appeared.
You go to the application,
you click on point A,
and then you click on point B,
and then something happens,
and these two points are connected.
Someone has, my friend,
I go to the datacenter,
I see that someone has to put a router in,
then a switch, then a cable,
then configure everything,
and so on.
And now,
if we celebrate young people,
or this new generation of network engineers,
and we say that they are connected to the fact
that they don't know,
I would say,
the history of those builders in the network,
to the extent that they would face them physically,
I mean, they would be more likely to hide it
through some SD-WAN,
something that clicks on the Internet,
or on the interface,
and then something happens,
or something else?
And the fact that they are really, really interested in it,
and that things are flying,
as they say, hands-on,
these guys know,
and if they don't know,
they ask, they come to SYNOK,
we welcome them there with open arms and hearts,
and we share our knowledge with them.
Now, if you want to be a network engineer,
as they say,
on the easy way,
to get through as easily as possible,
and you know it all,
and you follow a line of the lowest resistance,
then you have a lot to learn.
You know, it's the same as mechanics.
You have those mechanics
who really know how the engine works,
and you have those mechanics
who copy the tester from the manufacturer
and burn the test,
go for a beer,
and then do what the tester tells them.
For example,
on a car,
the tester,
as they say,
my mechanic was lost,
the Renault service center was lost,
the computer was replaced twice,
because it had to be a computer,
because if the tester says it,
no one else will get it.
In the end, my mechanic went
and with that tester,
but with a diagnostic user interface,
he looked at the engine
and said,
wait a minute,
this pressure is a bit low.
And in the end,
the whole thing,
from the turbocharger to the engine,
had a hole.
And that was the first time
Renault had that in Slovenia,
and it was such a rare occurrence
that Renault didn't have a tester for that.
But if you don't understand
what Mr. Tester is,
you'll never find it.
But that brings us to the topic
of troubleshooting.
But before we go there,
you have those
hardcore network engineers,
we need a few of them.
Then you have
installers.
Someone has to patch your wireless,
someone has to know which lights
have to be lit,
someone has to describe...
Yes.
Of course, we need that.
Now they only have different connectors.
You know, we need that.
That's the thing.
But that's a middle school thing.
Then,
everyone who touches networking
for professional purposes,
all developers,
have to know
what are the properties
of what they're dealing with.
You know, it's like
when you try to design a car,
but you don't know what's the friction
and the tires.
In the first corner,
you go out and the road is wrong.
And he designed the road.
Everyone who wants to write
a web application
should have that knowledge.
Because every web application
is a distributed system,
and for every web application
you have a network.
So, programmers
who are not motivated
by the results of their work,
but by the time spent
in the workplace,
have the results I would expect.
They made a call to API, right?
Yes.
And everything works on Loopback.
Yes, absolutely.
I think the biggest thing is
that it's not just about
downloading DNS,
and then everything falls.
No, but you know what the problem is?
The problem is that they're testing on Loopback,
or they're testing on a local network.
And again, this is a problem
of the development environment,
not a problem of the programmer himself.
I mean, again, we have programmers,
but we also have software engineers.
A software engineer
would have to know
what a distributed system is.
Programmers don't care.
They get specifications,
and they make their own.
But a software engineer
would have to know.
For a programmer,
a thousand lines of code is this much.
That's right.
But the problem is that
no one ever tests
this master product
in a way that would be
similar to the real environment.
With real bandwidth
and real latency.
That's all you need.
You know,
as long as you don't test the car in the yard,
you can put it on the road.
But what if this other extreme happens,
where everything is connected to the cloud,
and then it's put into the situation?
Can I tell you a story about the cloud?
We're not there yet,
but we can.
Yes, something...
I mean, we just changed the latency.
We put everything into the cloud,
and that's it.
A multinational company decided
that the workload should be moved
to the cloud.
And private.
All right.
Very well done migration.
Everything went as planned.
Everything went as it should.
Applications were working more slowly.
Everything was running in the cloud.
Only the clients were local.
They had a database.
But what's wrong?
What has changed since the 5th of April?
The network, right?
Must be the network.
Where was the cloud?
At the other end of the world?
How do you know?
In a country
that is geographically
very close,
but outside of the EU.
That's an important information.
And the packages go through China?
No.
Of course, the network engineer knows the subject.
So the mean time to innocence
was a few weeks.
Here it's necessary to prove
that it's not the network.
Then they finally started to look
what the database is doing.
And they realized that the complete database
in the cloud,
which was 10 milliseconds away from the client,
username and password
and authentication
is called locally because GDPR.
Well done.
And every request
that you made on the database
in the country X
was sent back another request
to ask if the user
can make that request on the database X.
So latency can be important.
You know how I like to talk about the cloud.
I adore cloud storage.
I adore it from the bottom of my heart.
So far, the cloud is on my disks,
on my servers,
in my datacenter.
Well, I've been living on the cloud
for years and years
and everything is good
in the cloud.
I mean,
thank God I don't have to deal
with those eggs anymore
and that someone else starts it.
There are no real problems.
There must be some,
but it's good that they don't sell more things
than everything.
I mean, every environment
or you can say
every developer
gives you some constraints.
If you go beyond that
and you don't care about it...
That's the problem.
Because, let's say,
US East 1
fell on Amazon
and 80%
of web stories went to the cloud.
The problem is
that Amazon made it very clear
that we never
want the whole region
to go to the cloud.
And if you have a mission critical application,
you must have an application
in at least two regions.
And we have the tools to do that.
We have that load balancer,
load balancer 3, load balancer DNA.
We have Anycast, for example.
Even Amazon has Anycast.
Yes, it lasted.
Yes.
Before they buried the whole region.
No, you know what?
You don't need Anycast
if you have a good enough DNA
and an application
that works in the browser.
You need Anycast
for things that don't need
DNA.
I just built
one
this year.
Global Anycast Network.
It will finally be streamed.
And it is...
I have to admit something.
Now that I've built
Global Anycast Network,
I've learned more about BGPU
than in the last 10 years.
You've finally learned about BGPU.
Now I'm going to interrupt you.
You know,
we've gone deep
into the technology.
What are the basics?
Just a little bit about what Anycast is.
What is Anycast?
Unicast, right?
That's what most people use.
No, let's start with DNA.
Oh boy. No, DNA will be your name.
OK. You have a server on two locations.
And now the Americans
choose a location,
and the Europeans choose another location.
The first way to do that
is to have those two locations
with different names.
And the DNS server will find you
and give you one or the other name.
That's classic.
But watch out.
That breaks the DNS-RFC.
Because the DNS
in the beginning would always
have to be the same.
I'm not going there.
And it breaks the DNSSEC.
Unless you disassemble
all the keys and sign them.
But yes, in the beginning
it breaks fundamentally.
That's pure high availability.
Now let's talk about
how much
the GeoDNS feature
uses DNSSEC.
I didn't do anything to it, did I?
Wait a minute.
You don't have to sign both records.
Yes, but then you have to disassemble
all the keys.
No, wait a minute.
You have a private key,
and you sign the answer with the private key.
The client can check it
with the public key.
The truth is that you can have
different zones
with different identities,
but you don't have to sign
with your private key.
Yes, and it quickly becomes complex.
No, but you have to have
the same private key
at all locations.
Yes, and you don't want
your private key,
no matter how serious it is,
to have it at a secure location.
No, look, you can still have
the NDNS server.
Yes, and you sign more different zones,
and then you disassemble them.
Yes, and then it becomes complex very quickly.
You know what the problem is?
It's the debate we had before,
that the Socket API is broken.
Yes.
Because the application,
if you look at how,
not how a high-level API is written
for, I don't know, JavaScript,
but if you look at what
really happens in a library,
which is actually a bundle
with its own binary,
or a shared library on Linux,
or Windows, or whatever.
I think Apple is the only one.
The application
asks the operating system
how to map
this name to this title.
And then the application
says,
please give me a link
to this title.
And now,
in a normal world,
the application would say,
I need a link
to this title,
and the operating system would do the rest.
What we have today
is that the DNS returns
not one response, but
2, 4, 8,
16, however many words,
half of which is IPv4,
half of which is IPv6.
And then, of course,
the rules are made.
First, try IPv6
words, and then IPv4 words.
And in the entire operating system,
this is also implemented,
or pre-sorted, because we can't
believe that the programmer
will do it correctly.
So you have Happy Eyeballs, right?
No, Happy Eyeballs is implemented
in the application.
No, it's not on the operating system either.
On Apple.
On Apple, not on Linux.
Happy Eyeballs is,
for example,
implemented in macOS
at the operating system level,
but with another API.
For those of you who don't follow
Happy Eyeballs,
that is, that data set
over 6 that you get, which is identical...
No, no, no.
You send requests
for IPv4 and IPv6.
You try both of them right away.
Right away.
A little later.
Yes, depending on the implementation.
And then, according to the same protocol
you take it
as the primary protocol
and use it for the destination.
The problem is, of course,
that you can get it back,
it's still installed, but then the data
doesn't go through.
If I had understood
Happy Eyeballs, I would have solved that part too.
You know what, Happy Eyeballs
is what we lack, for example.
I don't.
Look, the first problem
is that the operating system
doesn't connect the data API
to the device.
It's like if I wanted
to talk to you,
and then someone would say to me,
go to 12.5.
I'd be like, I don't want to.
No, no, 12.5.
And then I come, I say,
I went out.
No,
you can't.
Try another word.
Now, you get back
to X word, and then
it depends on how smart you are as a programmer,
if you don't use some books.
What's wrong with those books?
You don't know. That's the next problem.
Because in time,
you went through that list of words,
you tried, you wrote it
with the device, and every time you waited
three minutes.
Yes, the timeout was fantastic.
Yes, and that's how
IPv6
worked on, for example, Windows
and Linux, and because of that,
nothing started to crash.
IPv6 was before IPv4.
If IPv6 was broken,
it didn't do anything, because every time
it waited three minutes before the timeout.
And that's why they made
Happy Eyeballs, but Happy Eyeballs
is implemented in the browser.
Yes.
In the application.
Every application that
wants to behave similarly,
has to implement the same code,
in the same way.
Yes, Happy Eyeballs solved
the fear of operators.
Do you know that I was in
a design group in Prague
when we designed
Happy Eyeballs with
Endro Jurčenko and Dan.
The first one.
Yes, but
it turned out that
just as Happy Eyeballs
is good and useful
and nice and lovely
and everything,
it's hard for those
who would like to disable
IPv4.
Because Happy Eyeballs
masks all the problems
on the IPv6 protocol in the network.
It's the MWD syndrome.
Everything works for me.
And then,
if someone gets on Facebook
or Google or whatever,
the user is not interested
in IPv4 or IPv6.
He doesn't care
where the electricity
comes from.
Mine is from the nuclear power plant.
That's what it says on my account.
If you trust the operators
or the distributors.
It's not like
the electronics can decide
and paint them.
On a network level,
it's possible.
Network vendors
do it because
they take the complexity into account.
It's called 5G network slicing.
Yep.
OK, sorry.
Anyway,
it masks a lot of problems
and prevents
people from actively
troubleshooting
their IPv6 network.
Now we have the same problem
with QUIC.
TCP versus QUIC.
One is TCP, the other is UDP.
Again,
the implementations
try to make both
short.
So,
if you go to a website,
you try to make it 4-series.
Oh, now we're working
on DNS over QUIC.
That'll be fun.
I can enable it
in the lab
later.
When we go
step by step,
we like encapsulation
more.
Anyone who touches
networking should
switch to RFC1925.
Yep.
What does it say?
It's about 12 rules
of networking.
One of them is
it's always something.
Yeah, it's always something.
One of them is
every old idea
will be propagated
in a new form.
With a new buzzword
in marketing.
And the other one,
what did I mean?
You can always add
another level of indirection.
And complexity.
I like the first one.
It should work.
That's the first rule of networking.
The other one is...
With sufficient trust,
pigs fly just fine.
Yeah.
If we have enough drive...
They fly well.
But maybe I'm wrong.
In a way, you want to say
that,
considering how these things stand,
every developer
would solve
the problem
on an application level.
No, that's a mistake.
No.
Let's say that...
Let's use libraries.
Yes, but...
That it will be solved on the operating system,
that the apps will be able to call...
Yes, but you have to know that laws of physics exist.
You're offloading this problem to a good library, thank God.
Because if we all use the same library,
then like OpenSSN,
we will all end up on the same bug at the same time,
and someone will come and screw it up.
And now we have 3-4 libraries on the same...
It's all the same.
The problem is that you have someone who doesn't use a library.
You take a 15-year-old book,
Python for beginners,
copy the code from there and let's go.
Yes.
That's the problem.
Copy-paste, with IP, right?
Yes, yes.
With IP, yes.
With old code.
No, I mean, that's next.
I had...
Once I had a problem with a programmer,
who didn't do anything,
he decided it was a DNS problem,
and he did a resolve,
he resolved the name of the server in the IP address,
and the IP address in the source code.
Beautiful.
He didn't put it in the configuration file.
No.
It's always DNS.
No, the assumption that
whenever you start with the IP address inside,
even if it's more dynamic,
that you go with that assumption,
it can also be 6.
Yes.
You never expect anything.
And you know what?
In the 90s, a gentleman who worked on Sun,
because Sun had this remote procedure,
which was already very developed,
he wrote some networking,
I mean distributed systems,
not even fallacies.
And every programmer would have to go and think about it.
Because, for example,
bandwidth is infinite,
latency is zero,
the network is secure,
there is a single administrator.
And three more like that.
Latency, you have zero to localhost.
To loopback, yes.
Yes.
Hey, but if, for example,
now I'm a bit monotonous,
and I say,
and now you,
someone asks you,
and we go to the same...
No, no, no.
That's a great idea.
It's great.
Try it now.
What do you see as Don's biggest problems,
with which, for example,
I don't know,
we started with cloud,
let's say that cloud providers
are the biggest consumers of the network,
on the one hand,
and you probably have the biggest administration.
What do you see as their biggest challenges,
with which they are dealing today?
And I'll tell you the opposite,
because you probably have more access
to work for operators.
What are Don's biggest challenges for operators?
Because, for example,
I don't know,
20 years ago,
there were,
I don't know,
how to have a large enough uplink,
and how to get the bandwidth to the end user.
What are Don's challenges,
with which...
You know how it is,
what are the challenges of cloud providers?
We don't even know the answer to that.
Even that secret sauce.
Because, in fact,
everything they do is a secret sauce,
and everything they do is a recruitment drive.
Every time you have someone
from Google at a RIPE meeting
who says how phenomenal Google OSDN is,
or how phenomenal their datacenter Fabric is,
it's purely a recruitment drive.
Because you never...
For example,
there's a crazy difference
between Cloudflare on one side,
and Google and Amazon on the other.
Amazon shouldn't be there.
Fair.
Yes.
They do their own thing.
Every now and then,
they tell you a little bit
about what's going on
at one level under the API,
so that you understand
how to properly use the API.
They tell you the same details as...
Here.
The region has more zones,
the zone is a failure domain,
the zones are...
We guarantee that these two zones
are two different datacenters,
but if you want redundancy,
there are two regions,
but what's inside?
An awkward silence,
and Amazon is madly silent.
As you said,
my friend works at Amazon,
he falls into a black hole,
dies for Event Horizon,
and you don't hear his silence anymore.
Google only boasts.
At conferences,
they boast how good they are,
and smart,
and omnipotent,
and I don't know what,
but when you look at their article,
there's always that interesting 10% deficit.
And then everyone falls for it.
Google does it,
we have to do it too.
Then there's GIPHY,
or Google Infrastructure for Everyone Else,
and that's the biggest tech
we've seen in the world,
including Kubernetes.
Then you have smaller players,
like Cloudflare,
where I actually choose their engineering blog
with great pleasure,
because they dive into details
I've never dived into in my life.
For example,
how does a patch in Linux Kernel
cause your latency to inevitably increase by X,
and split to zero?
At the end,
they always write,
guys, if you're interested in such problems,
are you interested in WeAreHiring?
Look, that's fair.
Classic, yeah.
That's fair.
You gave something from yourself,
of course,
you'll say you'll take something back
if someone is interested.
Cool.
I asked nicely.
More of that.
But what kind of problems do these people have?
We have no idea.
Because it's like,
I don't know,
the three of us are working on this bicycle,
and we're talking about what kind of problems
Falcon has with the mask.
Or that we have unmodelled rockets,
you know.
It's just another planet.
In terms of their speed,
in terms of their size,
in terms of how quickly they change,
it's another planet.
And you probably don't have anything
that would have an overview,
because there are so many employees,
that everything is really small.
Well, that too,
but nothing comes out.
My assumption is,
with some kind of engineering,
they've come up with their proprietary protocol,
which they solve.
Everyone has it.
And their proprietary hardware,
do they solve some problems?
Or keep it simple,
and let's just...
No.
You know what the problem is?
First of all,
they have problems that no one else has.
Definitely.
Because of the size.
And because of that,
you don't get hardware
that would solve their problems.
On the other hand,
if you look at it,
the big cloud providers
are probably 20-30% of the networking market.
Yes.
In fact,
Whitebox switches were the second largest vendor
for Cisco,
and I don't know who the third one is.
And that goes to the big cloud providers.
And you know what I have a feeling about cloud providers?
Every time they solve their problem,
they try to solve it with their proprietary hardware,
they generate 5-6 new ones.
And then,
at the same size,
and with how fast they run,
and how much bandwidth they have.
But those are proprietary solutions.
Yes.
But look,
no one else in the world,
not only is not interested in it,
but you know how much work you have to do
if you want to give something that you have developed
in a state that will still be usable for someone else?
Oh,
that's huge.
Yes.
That's why we now have Kubernetes
in the state it is in.
Well,
Kubernetes is Google's attack,
because if I manage to make sure
that this API is correct,
then I will be able to sell my cloud
because I don't have to sell anything
because I don't have a support.
No,
I see that this is the silver bullet
with which we will solve all the problems.
Yes,
OpenStack was there too.
but it didn't sell that well.
Yes,
because it was sold by networking vendors,
not by Google.
No.
But when I developed OpenStack,
the last version I developed
was a beta version.
I was a beta version too, right?
No.
I mean,
now it was practically unusable.
OpenStack was
the way networking,
I mean,
networking compute storage vendors
made their complexity into a market.
Yes,
and this is as close as possible
to the API of Amazon.
Yes,
I tried to install OpenStack.
I wanted to install it,
but if I wanted to get something useful out of it,
I think I would need to study it for a year,
what they had in mind there,
completely against some logic
that we have been following for 20-30 years.
Yes.
But you can still upgrade Kubernetes.
Kubernetes is nothing better, right?
Yes.
It's nothing better.
Well,
in general,
we don't know what problems they have.
What we know,
what we see,
is what kind of chips
Broadcom puts on the market.
Because Broadcom puts chips on the market
that will be bought by cloud providers.
And now Broadcom bought VMware,
and we all won.
Oh,
you are...
Do you remember CIA?
Where?
Computer Associates.
Yes.
Where the old software goes to die.
Broadcom is the same.
Yes.
For Broadcom,
VMware is just cash,
like they will...
Didn't they buy Brocade in their time?
I think so, yes.
You know,
they bought Brocade
because of the installed
Fibre Channel base,
and then they took the cow from it
while it was dying of old age,
and now they bought the next cow
which they will milk
until it dies of old age.
I heard from Brocade
that they were
highly dependent on
those high frequency traders
on the stock market.
No.
They still work there.
Not for long.
What did they replace?
Well,
they did everything
just for a microsecond.
You know,
there was,
I don't know,
16 GB
Fibre Channel,
and on the other side
100 or 200 GB
Ethernet.
Yes.
The end.
Goodbye.
They...
They work for nanoseconds.
Yes, yes.
ISP.
With which...
What are their biggest challenges?
Well,
as we said at the beginning...
ARPU.
The base hasn't changed
since the 90s.
Still,
instead of these two
we have Optico.
The main operator is BGP.
Now there is RPKI.
They play a little
with the BGP community.
DNS is still
more or less the same
as it used to be
with DNSSEC.
We are not all good
at the Internet,
but you also have
different players.
So,
practically...
You have an estimation
of how much DNSSEC
is used now.
For all of you
who are listening,
what does it mean
that requests
and those
that go to DNSSEC
are signed,
so that you can say
that...
Not only answers
are signed.
Answers are signed.
Requests are not signed.
Of course.
Answers are signed
so that you believe
that those
that went back
are used.
Yes.
You can check
on the VEA website.
Now,
the problem
of the operators
that are currently
there
is that
the amount
of traffic
that flows
through their network
started to increase
exponentially
because of
those over-the-top
servers
that were offered
by various
Google
and other
companies.
So,
there are
a lot of
servers
that are
running
on Netflix
and other
Google
and so on.
Netflix.
Let's say
Netflix,
yes.
And so on.
Then,
there was
an idea
at the level
of some
European
association
that
the operators
would start
to charge
those
people
for their
services
and the
traffic
that flows
through their
network.
So,
the first
question
that
the operators
would ask
was
whether
they should
charge
their users
for that bandwidth.
If you
offer
1 gigabit
per second
for optics
for me
at home,
I somehow
pay for it.
Why would
I have to
pay for
the other
one for you?
But,
look,
this is
a different
problem
when it comes
to China.
Yes.
Maybe
Google
deserves
1 euro
per month
for you.
Almost
80%
of your
bandwidth.
Telekom
or
even
Slovenia
deserves
30-50
euros
per month
for you.
What will
20%
of that
1 euro
be?
It will
be
a
bit
more
expensive
than
a
brick
house.
Yes,
yes,
yes.
The Germans
are already
sanding
their business
into the ground.
The difficulty
in the
operators,
I'm not
talking about
Slovenians
only,
but when
they started
to
make
connections
to the
internet,
but
then the
TV came,
the internet,
the telephone.
No,
no,
give me
some
understanding.
All
European
operators
started
as
state
monopolists.
And
those were
the golden
years
when they
made
telephones,
they
made
them
in
some
road
stations,
it's
expensive
as
pork.
And
three times
before the
telephone
they
took us
away
with that
and lived
well
from that
and had
high
profits
and three
times
more
profits
than
they
had
in
the
internet.
And
all of
them
knew
that
they
had
to go
there
and
they
jumped
on the
internet,
but
here
you only
compete
with the
price.
The
only
thing
that
you
can
do
with
the
internet
is
that
you
can
use
the
internet
as
much
you
can
use
the
internet
as
much
you
can
use
the
internet
as
much
you
can
use
the
internet
as
much
you
can
use
the
internet
as
much
you
can
use
the
internet
as
much
you
can
use
the
internet
so
much
more
as
long
you
can
use
the
internet
as
much
you
can
use
the
internet
as
much
you
can
use
the
internet
as
much
much
you
can
use
the
internet
as
much
much
much
you
can
use
it
as much
internet
as much
as much
much
much
you
can
use
it
as much
as much
much
you
can
need
it
to
be
useful
to
you
and
to
others.
This
is
our
goal.
We
want to
make
this
happen.
We
want to
do
everything
we can
to make
this
possible.
We
want to
make
this
possible.
We
want to
make
this
possible.
This
is
our
goal.
We
want to
make
this
possible.
This
is our
goal.
With
this
goal,
we
can
do
everything
possible
right now.
We
want to
make
this
possible.
Let
us
start
with
our
goal.
We
want to
make
this
possible.
We
want to
make
this
possible.
Let
us
start
with
our
goal.
We
want to
make
this
possible.
Let
us
start
with
our
goal.
We
want to
make
this
possible.
Let
us
start
with
our
goal.
We
want to
make
this
possible.
Let
us
start
with
our
goal.
Let
us
start
with
our
goal.
We
want to
make
this
possible.
Let
us
start
with
our
goal.
Let
us
start
with
our
goal.
Let
us
start
with
our
goal.
Let
us
start
with
our
goal.
Let
us
start
with
our
goal.
Let
us
start
with
our
goal.
Let
us
start
with
our
goal.
Let
us
start
with
our
I asked them if it is possible to change it, if they have something in mind,
and they said that they have something in mind.
No, I don't know, I only know how they built the local copper fence.
And that, if you look at it from the side, it was honoured,
because the copper network in Slovenia was built during the time of the monopolists,
from my ass.
You didn't have a competitive copper network?
No, but for good reason.
Yes, yes, yes, you were right.
Now it seems that they also developed optics.
Yes, I asked the director if I could have a beer,
and I said to him, what would you do?
That's better.
I said, why would you try to separate these two,
first of all, they are not state-owned,
and second of all, we realized that for them,
as it was before, the mines are owned by one person,
the cables are owned by another person,
the connectors are owned by a third person,
the rivers are owned by a fourth person.
They forgot that they are a bit too low-dug,
and because of that, their cables are not drawn on the wall,
because they shouldn't be.
Oh, do you want to hear an anecdote from Rwanda,
where it was said that the mines are too low-dug?
There, in rural Rwanda, they put an optical cable
through the connection to another country,
and they didn't dig deep enough.
The result was that the locals went there,
took that cable out, and cut it off.
First, they thought it was optics,
and then they cut it off a few times.
I have the same story from South Africa.
Wait, wait.
This reminds me of Liquid Telecom,
when they started it.
They hired a security service
to keep an eye on that cable,
to see if it was leaking.
And it didn't go very well,
because they still cut that cable.
And then one of them remembered,
and said, let's call a local shaman.
They gave him $100,
and he cut the cable,
and put those symbols on the cable.
However, the shaman didn't touch that cable anymore.
But now they have other problems.
They go to the parties and say,
can you please not send our product
through the cable?
So, with too little digging,
such things can be solved quickly.
But we don't have shamans here.
No, you know what the problem is?
As Baba Chula Baba said,
the problem is that other people
who dig don't know that those cables
are there because they are not torn.
And then they take the cable out,
and look for the cable in the middle of the tunnel.
We are still waiting for that here.
Once it burned here,
now we are waiting for the other one.
You can say that here is the railway bridge
over the Danube.
Do you know why a real network engineer
likes to go to the mountains?
Do you have an optical patch cable with you?
No.
You can always have a couple of meters
of optical cable with you.
If you kill the cable,
you bury it in the ground
and before you know it,
a bugger will come and plug it in.
A life-saving device.
Let's go back to Slovenian operators.
Congratulations to all of them.
The internet we have in Slovenia
is in accordance with the law
of the most developed world.
I didn't even realize
that I was on IPv6.
Let's summarize.
IPv6.
Don's is a new organization.
If they want their own PI space,
they only have IPv6.
Everything else they have to buy
at the white market, black market.
Last week I was in Montenegro.
I helped to establish their leg.
Montenegro is not the only country
in the Balkans that has a network operator.
Congratulations Montenegrins.
Why are there so many cows?
Montenegro.
It was great.
We had a great time.
A friend from Karsolinka came with me.
Karsolinka is an operator
that was established in 2018-2019.
It was after IPv4.
It was a car company.
He told me about his experience
of how to become an ISP
after your question.
They hired 2-4 ISPs
for IPv4.
Then they got into the queue
at the top of the queue.
Was there a shortage of ISPs?
There were 22.
Now you get 24.
You have to queue up.
There was a shortage of ISPs.
If you become an ISP today,
you get ISN and IPv6 resources.
How often do you queue up?
You have to queue up.
At the last RIPE meeting,
Sander, Gerd and I went to queue up.
It was not a boundary.
It is easier to queue up.
They started with IPv4.
They soon realized
that there is no point in queueing up.
They started thinking about IPv6
and how to implement it.
Now they have IPv6 enabled network
and queue it up to all parties.
They are very concerned
that parties would not enable it on their side.
In Italy, the law is a bit different.
It is not that everyone should bring
all sorts of routers that are available.
In our case,
all the IPv6 resources are provided
by the operator.
You mean the one that terminates
on the Ethernet.
I have a router connected to my PC
and I still have PPP OSI
connected to my brother's CIO.
I work with Mikrotik.
Their CPE
is used as a media converter.
They realized
that you can't develop
your business
only on IPv4.
If the whole world is on IPv6,
why wouldn't they go?
The network is not that big yet.
What stops us?
First of all,
we are stopped by people
who are too old
to understand IPv4.
They don't want to think about IPv6.
What stops us is
that it is not a business case for IPv6.
For example,
I don't know what NLB has.
I'm sorry, XLB.
XLB has a million problems.
IPv6 is not one of them.
They have 10 internally.
All people are connected.
On Zuni
they have a website on IPv4.
No operator can guarantee
that IPv4 won't support them.
You don't have to do anything for them.
Everything works a little better,
but if you look at the replications
they give you on mobile phones...
For example,
I was asked
if I could make a presentation on IPv6.
I said no,
it's an old topic.
I made a new presentation
on a slightly higher level.
I simply gave the operators an idea
of what content providers do.
The big ones go to the IPv6 only data center.
Then you have an IPv4 translator on the edge.
You don't.
All the big content providers
have a web server on the edge.
You have a Zunani interface,
dual-stack.
They all have a proxy server.
Yes, they use SIIT,
and in the other direction something else.
But the point is...
Aha, you mean you don't have a dual-stack.
Yes, I've talked about it a lot
on Facebook, Google, etc.
When a meeting ends...
At a beer.
I told them how things work.
Then I said,
this is a modern content provider.
And a translator on the edge.
If we look at the other side
of an operator,
where you have IPv4, CGN,
and NAT on CPI,
let's put it all together.
You have NNAT, CGN,
and a translator on the content provider
before you get to the person.
Now let's put IPv6.
If you implement IPv6,
it goes directly,
without any additional points,
without any additional translations, etc.
Do you know what was the response of the operators?
Wow, we've never thought about it like that.
Of course, because they think about their own money.
You know what else?
With their dual-stack,
all video traffic goes to IPv6.
Do you know how much you save on CGN licenses?
You only save on licenses.
If you only have CGN,
you don't have an exit strategy.
More and more traffic will go to CGN.
CGN is a carrier-grade NAT.
If we say NAT is evil,
it's a carrier-grade evil.
The operators built it,
because they didn't have enough IPv6 space.
They made an additional translation,
because they used internal IPs.
Internal IPs between their cores,
and between your CPUs,
when it changes to another internal IP,
or the same one.
Then you have a problem.
Like you said,
the operator gives me one word,
while I have 30 computers at home,
and I'm fighting for that one word.
But because the operator was too late,
and doesn't have one word for me,
there's one more layer of shit
before we get to global internet.
Then you have people
who are network engineers,
or network architects.
The first idea is,
as long as it works,
as long as it doesn't extend anywhere.
No, I have a lot of other work.
Yes.
But the difficulty is,
because the world is changing,
and the other end, the operator,
is one end of the communication.
For every communication,
you need two ends.
And the other end changes,
because it's cheaper to use IPv6.
No, the other end changes,
when most of the content is on IPv6.
And most of the content is on IPv6.
Yes.
Then you have the long tail of everyone else.
99.99% of the domains in the world
are on IPv4,
because no one cares that they're only on IPv4.
Unless you're on Cloudflare,
then you're automatically on IPv6.
I think Amazon is already calculating IPv4,
so it's IPv4 for service.
Yes, of course.
You know what the problem is?
Amazon will collect the next $2 billion,
I'll get $12 or $15 a year.
I'm sorry, but I'm not going to configure IPv6 for that.
Yes.
Where's the pain point?
I'm sorry, but I'm not going to configure IPv6 for that.
All I need is for you to sign up
so that you can start signing up there.
No, you know what?
Then I have to change it on Cloudflare,
then I have to change the access list.
We're a bit lazy.
No, not for $15 a year.
At some point, they'll tell you
No, they're not going to tell you,
they're calculating the pain.
But look, real experience,
I've talked to a lot of small operators,
who implemented dual stack,
today, at the moment,
if you're not an IPv6 user,
on dual stack,
about 50-60% of IPv6 traffic goes like this.
That's for fixed IPv6 traffic.
For mobile IPv6 traffic,
it's 80-90%,
because there's only Google and Facebook.
I don't know if it's still the same for mobile IPv6 traffic.
For dual stack, you need 2 SI.
Yes, PDPv6 and PDPv4.
No, you also have dual stack PDP.
Yes, but you need newer software
for the whole network,
which almost no one has.
And you have to pay a license for one user,
for two users, because you have 2 SI.
That's why T-Mobile USA went to IPv6 only.
And that's why Lorenzo added Android.
And what else?
464XLAT.
The first representative of 464XLAT
was in Paris,
where I gave Lorenzo a Slovenian SIM card
that had IPv6 only.
And I gave him 15 minutes of my slot,
so that Lorenzo came to Oder
and we showed 464XLAT on Android for the first time.
IPv6 came from France to Slovenia
and then to the rest of the world.
That was interesting.
What does IPv6 mean in the end?
If, for example,
the ideal conditions in the apartment
were to switch to IPv6 only,
what would fail?
Where would our current use of the Internet fail?
One of the best approaches
to implementing IPv6,
as I saw them, was Telekom Slovenija.
They implemented IPv6 on all dual-stack devices,
and instead of enabling it
on all users at once,
they went like this.
No, first they had close users.
And when we fixed that,
they went like this.
Today, if you enable all users
and you get 60% traffic on IPv6,
you have no experience with troubleshooting.
The learning curve is very slow.
They went like this.
From now on, every new user gets IPv6 by default.
Anyone who changes something
in the self-care portal
and goes through the same procedure
to install something,
automatically gets IPv6.
Or if you go to the portal
and you want to have IPv6,
the learning curve was somewhat positive.
And above all,
it was manageable.
At the same time,
we wrote the RIPE document
called IPv6 Troubleshooting
for Residential Help Desk.
We did complete procedures
on how help desks test IPv6,
do a dual stack,
what to do if the user calls
and has problems with any of the protocols.
My question was,
what would be the biggest problem
if we were to block IPv6 right now?
If you're talking about blocking IPv4
there are still a lot of problems
with IPv4.
Either you won't get to those problems,
or someone will have to do a translation.
What about some applications?
In the beginning, Skype 6 was a pain.
It's still a pain.
I mean, it's still working.
Skype is still working.
The hack is,
that you have a fake IPv4 interface
on every host.
That's why Skype connects to it.
But because it's a local TCP stack,
you can change the TCP size
to 6.
On the other hand,
you have a translator that changes it back to 4.
Why couldn't T-Mobile
fit a 6-only network?
It was exactly because of Skype.
Because everything else was working.
Until 4.6.4.x came out.
After 4.6.4.x came out on Android,
they were able to fit a 6-only network.
I think there were 26 million users
on IPv6 only.
They called me and said
that they had more calls
that people wanted to order pizza
than IPv6 calls.
Things are still working.
Now it's great that Apple
finally laid the groundwork
and said,
that you won't come to the App Store
if you don't work on a 6-only network.
That's awesome.
And now,
all the big content providers
that have an IPv6-only network
and data centers,
have found that the happy eyeballs
were the best during the week.
And to make it even better,
they decided that more traffic
would go through IPv6.
And they started adding jitters
and delays to IPv4 translators
on their Edge.
Now, if you're an IPv4-only user
and you have a 6-only ISP,
your user experience will always be worse.
But they don't care.
They would rather have a network.
And those operators
that don't think about IPv6 implementation,
it would be easier to do it 10 years ago,
when there was no content yet.
At that time,
the flow of everything would be
somewhat balanced
and all the difficulties would be solved.
If you're not an IPv6-only user today,
you can get into a disaster.
You need people who have already started it
and have experience in doing it.
Then it's not a problem.
In fact, we are on the right track.
Operators are covering it well enough.
Yes.
According to global statistics,
in certain countries,
IPv6 traffic is more than half.
Google measures traffic
on all their devices.
And I think that we are now
about 50% of traffic on Google
comes through IPv6.
So it's not a joke anymore.
Without practice and experience
from the world of enterprise
and security,
IPv6 will disappear.
If I'm honest and direct,
a certain generation will be able
to get a pension
before we can implement IPv6.
It's the same.
In theory, one step forward at a time.
Yes, exactly.
Let's wrap it up.
We have the last 10 minutes.
How much time do we have?
We are already past 90 minutes.
I thought we had 20 minutes.
You've lost 5 hours.
They've limited us.
Let's try to understand
what kind of future
is waiting for us.
What can we see?
It's a very broad question.
Is it true that
IoT, Smart City,
will all get their IPs
and we will be left with a clusterfuck?
That's already a meme.
Next hype.
The problem was that
when they hyped 5G,
they had to find a hype application
to convince all operators
why they need 5G.
IoT!
Self-driving cars.
Wait, wasn't it the same for all four?
Same, of course it was.
What did we say before?
Every crash will happen again.
You need a new frequency,
you have to pay for it.
You need a new equipment,
that's really it.
The state chooses frequencies,
that's fringe benefits.
It's not interesting to vendors,
vendors live on new equipment.
If you look at it,
until the augmented reality,
or virtual reality,
really comes to life.
Everything will always go faster,
always more, always this,
always that.
But I've had the same speed
of an internet connection
at home for 10 years.
And I don't need anything more.
I went to look at the statistics,
how much I use,
and it's sad altogether.
Yes, I have 100 megabytes,
and I don't need more.
I mean, I wanted to sell 100 megabytes
symmetrically, and I said,
I don't need more, thank you.
It's a traceable thing,
you have a bluetooth toothbrush,
that generates a lot of traffic.
You were better, you were a liar.
Wait, I don't understand,
why would I need 1 gigabit per second
symmetrically on my phone?
No, that would be a problem
for the phone.
Another problem,
I don't want to say it,
but we all know it,
the phone works by air.
And air is a shared spectrum.
And you won't get
1 gigabit on your phone
until you stand alone
under a tree,
so that the zombies and everything else
will eat you,
and the operator is still alive
because the internet is still working.
I remember, we were in Serbia
a year ago, the IGF meeting,
the Internet Governance Forum,
and there were debates about the development
of the internet, and there was
a woman from the European Commission
who came down and said
wireless, wireless, wireless,
R, R, R.
And I said,
air has its own physical laws,
it's a shared media.
We won't be able to
push it forward,
and blow it up,
and smoke it,
and you know what I said?
Look, the solution is
to take Bulgaria and start digging.
And she looked at me in a strange way.
Yes, but the direction of the European Union
is, as soon as
Bulgaria is in our hands,
Bulgaria,
and if you are in the country,
then optically.
Because in the current optics,
sometimes you do it this way,
with air, but sometimes you can't do it anymore,
because you need a higher frequency,
and a higher frequency doesn't go through the window,
doesn't go around the wall.
How much more will we want to blow up people?
Well, it's not a problem to blow it up,
it's a matter of
keeping the power relatively low.
Not at once.
The problem is that it's a line of sight.
The problem is that high frequencies
can't go into the eye anymore.
Oh, run, run.
Look, they're giving it to you.
We have a radio material.
We will present this
for a beer later.
Do you have any final thoughts?
Yes, I would say
about the development of the Internet,
as far as operators are concerned,
I would say
that we should let them
deal with new complexities
that are intensified by
suppliers of equipment and vendors,
such as SRV6 and so on.
Don't curse them.
Yes, sorry.
I have to say it once.
SRV6, okay.
Twice.
And to actively devote
to the implementation
of IPv6
and the development
of transport routes
and capacity.
So that they are connected.
Automation, right?
Yes.
Actually, what I wanted to mention
on this topic before,
when Deutsche Telekom launched
its project called TerraStream.
TerraStream, yes.
Actually, at all the local
RIPE meetings,
they did a business analysis
and concluded that in a few years
all their equipment will be lost.
Meaning, no more cows.
Have you heard about Peter Lodberg?
No.
No, another one.
Peter Lodberg was the father of the project.
It was his grandson, I think.
Yes, and probably he was in Sweden.
In English.
Anyway.
The main point is that the margin is not more.
Focus on how you will
reduce the cost of the equipment.
Because only then will you survive.
If you don't reduce the cost of the equipment,
there will be another one.
Cool.
The second point for developers is
that the laws of physics remain unchanged.
Latency is not a book.
Bandwidth is not infinite.
Even if it's a simple file,
you think that's it.
We referred to the RFC,
and we'll talk about it later.
If not, we'll talk about physics.
We'll talk about SD cards.
Laws of physics also work for us.
If I add,
as I said before,
for developers,
the beating will continue
until the morale improves.
So, you watched and listened
to Ogrodje.
With me, Jan Žorš,
Ivan Poplnjak.
Thank you very much.
Did I say anything smart?
No.
Maybe we should repeat it more often.
I would also like to thank the team
behind the camera,
Patreon,
3FSA, Human Frog,
and
see you next time.