A few words about the new episode of Ogrodije
and about the new season of Make It.
Greetings to all of you in the new episode of Ogrodije
and greetings to all of you at the Make It conference.
Today we are filming this episode of Ogrodije in front of the live audience,
but it won't be anything less interesting and technically advanced.
Today we have an interesting topic,
which we have named Slovenian 3.0.
This topic has become very relevant in the last few years.
We are in the third phase of language technologies,
and we hope that we have debunked it.
When we started with Slovenian,
Slovenian was called a written word, a spoken word,
and we recorded some points.
Then we tried to digitize it with technology,
we have dictionaries, translators and so on.
Now we are working with technologies
that were based on large language models
in the third stage of Slovenian,
and we have also taken our word for it.
Today we are joined by Prof. Dr. Marko Bajec from FRIA,
who is involved in various laboratories and projects
with modern language technologies.
I hope that we will explore this area together,
and that we will go not only superficially,
but also a little deeper into these concepts.
I forgot something, Draž, before...
We have agreed that we will talk,
so it won't be strange to anyone.
We are the same age.
Yes, we are the same age as engineers.
I would ask you to introduce yourself,
so that we can properly introduce ourselves.
Thank you. First of all, hello to everyone in the audience.
I am Marko Bajec from the Faculty of Journalism and Informatics.
I teach subjects in the field of data databases,
which of course also includes me from the previous conference.
I also develop information systems and technologies
that are connected to speech and language.
I lead a laboratory for data technologies,
and in recent years we have been dealing a lot
with speech and language technologies.
We are trying to bring Slovenia to a level
where there is no digitalization,
to a point where in the future
we would know a lot more.
Today we know that we expect
that most of the communication between humans
will be on the right speech.
If we don't take care of our language,
even in the digital sense,
it can happen to us very quickly
that we will be very disappointed
to see what solutions others have,
and that is why I am very happy
to be able to share these things.
Great. I wanted to start this debate
with a powerful question.
How far are we technologically
when we can,
I said technology,
I will ask the question again,
tell our medical symptoms
in Slovenia,
and we will get back a diagnosis
that we can trust.
Is this too powerful a question?
The question is fine,
but it depends on how I will answer it.
First of all,
I belong to a more conservative group
of researchers and scientists,
so I am not particularly
technologically inspired.
But given the fact that most of you
have technical background,
I don't think I need to gather words.
That is why I will say
what I see in reality,
but I don't want to give everyone the same answer.
I think that we are already very far
and the solutions that big language models have
are already a very good assistant.
We work in tandem
if we trust them to decide for themselves.
The same is true in the field of medicine.
I think that the solutions
that the health care provider consults
can be very useful,
because they have in themselves
and in other language models
a huge amount of knowledge,
which the health care provider
can't even process.
They can be helpful,
but the final decision and interpretation
must be made by a human being.
In your question,
such solutions already exist.
If you check them,
you will see that they are mostly
in the direction of the health care provider,
because it is unified.
One of the difficulties in big language models
is that we met them
through chatbots,
where people started to see
that they can be asked and answered.
How do you hide the fact
that there is a lot of knowledge encoded in them?
Is this preparation of knowledge,
cleaning of knowledge,
is it a good description
of these technologies?
Especially since most people
receive big language models
through chatbots,
such as chatGPT,
which today are much more
than just a language model.
It is true that the language model
is the backbone,
but even if you have studied
how they were taught,
only the first four or five phases
were dedicated to the language model.
When we approach people in this way,
we think that all language models
are capable of this.
Then there is a great disappointment
when an open source model comes
and does not know how to answer all the questions.
If you ask chatGPT,
it will know how to answer anything,
so it seems quite sensible.
It will also know how to answer questions.
For this part,
chatGPT took a lot of time
and included 10,000 engineers
who helped with supervised learning
and used techniques
such as sub-combat learning,
which is not part of the learning
of the language model at the beginning.
Let's go even deeper.
As engineers,
we often use apps
that are available to us,
such as international corporations
and large companies.
I am not interested in this.
I have no feeling
if there is such a model
in Slovakia.
I have no feeling
if we know chatGPT,
we can make an app
and call it in Slovakia,
but exclusively in Slovakia.
I can't imagine where we are.
My only experience
was a medical examination
and a call
where the model wrote what it heard.
The patient's wish
would be to automatically write
a diagnosis in such a structure
that he would not need it.
There is an additional possibility
to enable a language model.
If I go back to what I said,
I have heard many times
whether we should be afraid
to give birth to Slavs.
They will eat us anyway.
Slavs are not interested
in the market.
We all know this,
but we don't want to stay.
I think they will eat us
Let's take chatGPT,
which was named Trojko.
As you probably guessed,
because it is a public data,
its model has 175 billion parameters.
If we look at how many buildings
are needed for such a model,
there was a lot of research on this topic,
how many tokens,
are needed for one parameter.
There are measurements from 2 to 200.
For example, from 2 tokens to 200 tokens
are needed for one parameter.
If we take 10,
it means that we need
1750 billion tokens
for such a model.
A book typically has
50,000 to 100,000 words.
To explain the difference
between words and tokens,
big language models are not taught.
Their vocabulary is not just words,
but also part words.
In this way, they can cover words
that do not yet exist in the vocabulary.
New names and so on
typically have 50,000 to 100,000 tokens.
20% to 30% of them are words,
but they are the thickest words.
If we took a book and tokenized it,
it would be easy to show that
50% to 70% is tokenized with words,
and the rest with parts.
If we calculate this,
we will come to 1.5-1.6 tokens per word.
If we take 50,000 to 100,000 words,
we get 80,000 words,
multiplied by 1.6 or 1.5,
we get about 130,000 words.
If we divide these parameters,
1,370,000,
we get about 10 million books.
Slovenia produces 5,000 books every year.
We will produce books for 3,000 years
and we will have this many books.
This is just for the sake of feeling
what large quantities mean.
In the case of LMA,
books accounted for 20% of the population,
at least.
I don't know for sure,
but if we want diversity,
we have to include a lot of other buildings,
and where in Slovenia to get it.
What we are offered now
by larger language models,
because they also know Slovenian,
is what can be taken from the Internet.
Projects that crawl from the Internet
are mass-produced,
and as much as Slovenian is included,
it is included.
There is nothing controlled.
In the end, the first models
were really taught by a group of masses.
Now it is clear that in addition to the mass,
there is also an important quality.
A very good language model
for the field of medicine
is Google's MatPalm 2.
I think it has passed the tests
of all medical institutions in the US
to get a license.
They had 60% and with this model
they got 87% of the correct answers.
It is very important
what beliefs are.
Beliefs are completely superstitious.
We are talking about larger language models
where some Slovenian is accidentally included.
Then the question is
if they are superstitious.
It doesn't matter that we do something in Slovenian.
If you delve into how language models work,
then you will realize
that it is very important
what we give at the source.
Large language models were taught by the masses.
Grammar, syntax,
pragmatics, semantics,
extremely large linguistic values
that we don't even know how to name.
They are included in neural networks.
But they are included from a large mass
and a variety of constructions.
If we translate it correctly,
we will get an extremely poor language.
Subsequently, the model will not evolve.
I think that the only way
if we want to take care of Slovenia
is to make sure that as many people as possible love us.
Not only for Slovenia,
but for the whole family of Slavic languages.
They are all somewhat similar
and the model can be learned from common properties.
And that these people love us as much as possible.
We are doing our best
and we are conducting a project
at the Faculty of Criminology
which is intended to track
how the most wanted person
comes to the data
in these special categories
in order to make a model
that can be used in the public good
and does not reveal more of the data
because we have very tight deadlines here.
Just two years ago,
I think that AMZS and Zvezda Potrošniko
encouraged the State Assembly
to do something
because the vehicles we buy in Slovenia
do not speak Slovenian.
We do not have to talk to them in Slovenian.
Why not?
When we turned to VW
and so on,
we finally came to Germany
and they said,
OK, give us the data.
Which data can we give now?
During the preparation of the episode,
we talked and you mentioned
that we will change the legislation
in order to attract more believers.
Will this be an initiative on a European level
or a Slovenian one?
Will it be necessary to change the legislation
in order to attract more believers?
The law on risk activities has already changed
but it allows different interpretations.
I can give you an example from our project.
We invited people to the database
where a lot of information is recorded
and then they are transcribed.
This is a great educational tool
and it is gaining a lot of popularity.
For example, it is gaining popularity
every year.
But we did not receive this data
because according to the law
we have a priority.
But on the other hand,
the owner or the data manager
cannot force so much work
that it does not benefit
what we will do.
I understand the answer of some people
who have archived this data
in a very different way
and did not spend much money
but I want to say that the legislation
is moving in this direction
and it gives us more opportunities
but it is still difficult to get the data.
We can ask the RTV for the data
but we will not get them again
because they are copyrighted.
What I would like to say
is that the minority of Slovenia
is a bit more innovative
and a bit more open.
For all of us who need it.
A big part of the language technologies
are the corpuses.
Can you tell us
what are the corpuses
and how are they prepared
and if they are still used
in the future?
The corpuses are very different things
and that is a question for the linguist.
But I can tell you what the corpuses are
and where we use them.
When we practice the natural language
it is very important that we know
the whole vocabulary and that we know
what each word has,
because then we can teach the system
that when they practice the natural language
they know from the data
what the literal meaning of a word is
and from that they know how to come to
the correct sentences
or to solve the tasks that we give them.
That is why we need different corpuses.
But are they also used in building LLMs?
Those are additional knowledge
that we can add to the learning of LLMs.
In the case of LLMs,
as they were in the beginning of their learning,
it is based on a huge amount of data.
LLMs are based on
generative artificial intelligence.
They try to understand
all the data
and all the linguistic values
in the words
to make the best prediction
of the next sentence
from the context they have.
Generative language models
generate the next sentence
based on the prompt you gave them,
but not all the sentences.
When we were preparing for this episode,
I was surprised
at how good
the basic data was.
Some portals
that are focused on Slovenia
have corpuses.
If someone wants to play with a ball,
they don't start with a corpus.
They start with the data
on the will,
and the portals are organized.
I was surprised
that those things exist.
Maybe some comment on that.
A lot of work has already been done,
and it is also very personal.
A lot of work on this topic has been done,
but we should know
that a lot of work has already been done.
A few days ago,
there were a lot of linguistic models.
This work was done
to digitize and preserve the language.
Our goal is not only
to digitize the language
so that we can make technical solutions,
but also to teach the language as a language.
This is the language of Slavs.
I think that a decade of research
from different departments
and universities in Slovenia
was made in the 20th century.
Unfortunately, when we talk about
large linguistic models,
the basis we have is simply too small.
It does not help us.
We have to decide
whether to build a linguistic model
or specialize it.
Today, we can specialize
a large linguistic model for a specific task,
and we can do it well for the Slavs.
But we do not have to do
anything in the field of medicine.
Until Slovenian medicine is included
in large linguistic models,
it will be even harder.
We will not learn anything from it.
Before we move on,
I would like to ask you
more about large models.
Can you present to our audience
a collection of very interesting
and useful tools that you have developed
in this segment?
Yes, of course.
The development of Slovenian digital environment
was the first big project
where we all got together
in Slovenia.
The Minister of Culture
and I were co-financiers.
We raised a lot of money.
I think it was a four-million-euro project.
The goal was to prepare such a trust.
We also raised funds
or bought the whole thing.
We had money for the purchase.
We also built solutions
in the field of natural language processing
and in the field of speech technologies.
This means recognition of Slavic speech,
translation of Slovak, English,
English-Slovak and,
which is probably also very important,
we had to prepare a thousand-hour database
of recordings of public speech,
private speech, spoken speech,
which can then be used
for recognition.
We did this in such a way
that the database was also available
for commercial use.
Based on this database,
we also created a publicly available
recognition and translation database.
In Slovenia, it had a 30% decline,
but when we did it, it fell below 10%.
I think it was 6% for some multiples,
which is much better.
And Prevajalnik was also taken to a certain area
much better than Google,
but not to a certain area.
And this is also publicly available
and companies are already using it.
I think this project was very useful,
but we may have made a mistake
in the operational understanding
of the order,
because it is part of the resource
of the Minister of Culture.
It is very good that they financed it,
but I think that on their side,
they also admit a lack of technical understanding,
and this part is perhaps a bit uncomfortable for us,
because we have to,
on various resources,
as you know, we got the government again
from the Minister of Digital Culture,
and then we don't know who to talk to anymore,
that such projects should not be stopped,
because if they are stopped,
we will remain at some point,
but I think it is a very good thing
that you did through this project
Slovenian EU,
that all these tools have a web interface
and you can use them today,
check them and try them,
and use them today,
it is very good that all the code is on GitHub
and you can download it,
because I saw that people today
open poll requests,
and today not only some research project
would be done because of a research project,
and then it is published in some academic archives,
but it seems that there is an interest from a wider audience
to help you with this,
I have such a feeling.
Hold on, I have to correct you a bit,
when we talk about misunderstanding,
a model is a model,
it is not a solver by itself.
If we make a model for the recognition of Slovenia,
someone expects to have subtitles on the TV
that are generated automatically in real time.
This means a complicated use of such a model,
or a model that is learned from it.
This problem is not a problem
that was big in the past.
We made a demonstration
on slovencina.eu portal,
where you can submit a speech
and get a transcript,
but it was limited to 5 minutes.
Why me? Because we don't have such a hardware
for the whole of Slovenia to fulfill it.
You have a model for this,
but you don't have the whole culture.
We gave so much money,
we have to understand that the application
is not the same as the model.
The model allows you to develop
very different solutions,
but it is not the final solution.
In the final phase,
I think it is a meaningful measure
between what the research community does,
which is financed by the public,
and what the private sector does.
The private sector in Slovenia will not invest
in the preparation of things that are needed
for Slovenian,
because it is too expensive.
If you want to make a synthesizer for Slovenia,
you need a professional speaker
who will record it in a professional studio
for 25 to 50 hours.
Then you have to buy the rights,
which are quite complicated,
because he will give his voice,
and the voice will appear.
With the big ones, you can buy a synthesizer
for 1 million zl for $20.
Who will do this in Slovenia?
To some extent, the state must drive
if it wants to develop solutions
that can have much more added value
than this basis.
Will you go next?
I think it is fascinating.
I am fascinated.
For the listeners,
it started to rain heavily in Zuni.
Otok will talk about our supporters.
We are already at the same moment.
A little EPP to interrupt.
In Grodje, it is possible because of our supporters
via Patreon,
who support us with monthly donations
and get exclusive access
to all the videos before the game is released.
In Grodje, there are also supporters
such as Tripodetia, Humanfrog, Trifas and Kaldi,
who are very grateful to support us
and allow us to work on this level.
You said like and subscribe.
Yes, like and subscribe,
and tell your colleagues if they don't know
to listen to one episode,
and if it is OK, to listen to another.
OK, this is an EPP. Thank you.
Let's move on to the language models.
We realized that you need a lot of volume,
we realized that the legislation is interesting,
we realized that you need filtering,
you need to pay attention to what goes inside.
We realized that the data is added approximately.
Now we are more interested in the technological aspect.
How do you get those ETL pipelines
for that volume of data?
This is a Java data conference.
Can you tell us more about
how much energy and resources
do you need to invest in preparing the technology
so that we can train these models?
I can try.
The last project we are developing is called Povejmo.
In this project, we have to create
a smaller Slovenian model
that will have 1 billion parameters
and then 10 billion.
We are working on this smaller model
to be able to make phones and so on.
We don't start from scratch.
We have taken other similar models
and we are learning them in the future.
The techniques are very different.
I have already mentioned tokenization.
Many of you who are technologists
probably understand this.
If we start from a different model,
we can protect their vocabulary.
But this will not be ideal
because Slovenian is a different language
and has a different vocabulary.
There are probably some bones
that are similar in meaning,
so we have to create a new vocabulary.
We have already done this,
but we don't want to lose everything
we have learned in the basic model.
There are some techniques
that we transfer this knowledge
from the first model to our beginner
and then we learn it with our words.
As far as building a building is concerned,
it is very different.
What we are trying to professionalize
is from this point onward
when it comes to the faculty.
This means intensive meetings
that are intensively monitored.
It is clear that the data is not lost.
The volume is large,
but the quantity in terabytes
is not that big.
It is difficult to handle this.
Then there are the resources,
the computing tools
that we need for our work.
We are targeting VEGA.
VEGA is a well-known HPC
that is installed in Maribor.
For those who understand GPU technology,
it has 64 cores and 4 A100 cards.
This is a bit outdated technology,
but it is enough for our size
and our amount of data.
We have 12 H100 cards at our faculty
that are already better.
We have installed two new data centers
in the process.
If NVIDIA really gave us GB200,
it would not be in 5 flops
with VEGA.
It would be in a water-cooled container
on the faculty roof.
It would pay for electricity,
which we have not changed yet.
I think we still have half a year
to finish the installation.
Did I answer your question?
No, I told Andraž that I would not
answer the hardware question.
No, no.
People are often critical.
They like to complain.
We were like, OK, why do we need
this HPC?
Do you think that with LLMI
we will be a bit more popular?
We need more preparation.
Of course, now we need GPUs
or something like that.
I am in a dilemma.
I personally think that we have
more than we need.
In my role as a professor at the faculty,
I think it is still too little.
We do not have to wait for others.
We want to work with the best.
We have other skills when it comes to language.
Then we have to go the same way.
No one else chooses.
The installation, what it brings us,
is a different question.
It has its own philosophical dimension.
I will not go into that.
That is the same question.
OK, we are at a Java conference.
Is it written in Python?
No?
No, it is mostly in Python.
Python is simply a data science language.
You do not have it in Java.
There is no mutual love between you and Python.
That is known.
We have to watch how we arrange programmers.
It is true that Python is meant for those things.
It is not written for enterprise software,
but it is meant for those things.
Most of the tools we use are written in Python.
But Python as a glue,
we probably have a C in the back,
for ultra-optimized tasks.
Yes, of course.
Some libraries that Python uses
make a military around a very fast core.
That is done.
If we go into that parallelism
in any architecture,
of course, it is not Python.
Do you have to rush a lot?
If you have VEGO,
do you have to rush?
Is it such a big effort?
No, it is not trivial.
Today, most young people
already know a lot about Docker and those things.
But on the server,
as a job manager in such large systems,
you hear it for the first time.
Or on Singularity and similar things
that are used on such HPC systems.
But the learning curve is not that long.
It is necessary to write concise scripts
that give a job in order and can be prepared.
We have to do everything in such a way
that there is no interaction,
that it can flow smoothly,
because the models we teach
do not have a guarantee that the task will be completed.
It can fall at any step.
It has to be done in such a way
that it is not a bad art.
But if you give me a person
who has never heard of Linux
and would like to be a data scientist
and run it on HPC machines,
it will not work.
I don't even know where to start.
Can you give an illustration
of how long these jobs last on supercomputers?
Of course.
I will give a few examples,
and then you can imagine.
For fine-tuning on LLM,
even if we take a LAM,
a larger one, let's say 10 billion,
if we work only on one era,
it can be done in a few days.
Because it is only fine-tuning.
Techniques are being developed,
such as Solora,
which we can use to make
fine-tuning of the model faster.
This can be done in a week
on extremely powerful machines.
I would say the same for synthesis
and recognition.
I think we have a week to two weeks.
When we talk about basic language models,
I think we don't even have enough hardware.
If we wanted as many as they do
for big languages,
we don't have enough of that.
When it comes to these
open-source language models,
what exactly does this open-source mean?
We are talking about open use,
what do you see in here?
Is it really open?
And where is the secret sauce?
In models, open source means
mostly that you have a model
with the right hardware.
How was this model made?
What was included?
It is not necessary to know.
But you have a model with all its hardware.
You can take it and build from it.
This is an open-source model of this type.
Commercial ones are not so open.
If you want to take GPT-3,
you can't.
Some people do more steps,
others do less.
I don't think this is fair.
Do you think that this will be the first part,
that we will want to have a whole
regulative system that will want to know
the accuracy of the data,
that we will be able to have better written
and defined training,
or is it just technical and inexplicable?
I don't know where it will go,
because we are trying to have
more and more ethics in the field of
the use of artificial intelligence,
and then a lot of different interests
arise.
I can say that
generative models
can't serve you data
from which a certain answer has come,
unless they give you all the answers
that you wanted.
This is a statistical model.
The most likely answer is 1.5.
I think we will deal much more with
informing people that these answers
are not necessarily correct.
We will learn where this technology
is really useful,
and where it is still dangerous.
This distinction will have to be made.
At the University, we made a step
not to order, but to recommend
that an ethical commission be set up,
which will check where it is going.
At the end of the day,
this is a good intention,
but the result is harmful.
As I said, we can't expect
to be serviced by trusts.
If you go and ask
what the trust will write to you,
it is because trust is not only
a linguistic model.
It will probably also write to you
with the same trust that it took
to generate it.
It can't be the same with the generation itself.
I gave him a task for a new project,
because I know he will write it very well.
I told him to write me an integration
between me, a linguist,
a state-of-the-art, a challenge,
a work package.
He said yes, but he also added
references to Motivation.
I knew I wouldn't get those references,
but I was interested in what I would get.
I tried three of them.
One of them I already invented.
They were in Serbian.
It would have been great if someone
really wrote it.
But the authors were serious,
and the article could have been
a different word.
And it wasn't Tewik who wrote it,
but it was most likely that
the article would have been sent
and it would have been generated.
I think that people don't understand
what's going on behind the scenes.
That's why it's very important
to know what we are using
and what are the potential risks.
That's why I often say
that the other sector should get
more money to speed up its pace.
We make decisions too quickly.
They come out too quickly.
If the market is not ready
for them, the society is not prepared
for them.
We are not prepared for them
in terms of regulation or ethics.
An example I often give to my students
is the autonomous vehicle.
If they find themselves in a situation
where there are only two choices,
a child or a grandmother,
they have someone coded into their model.
Isn't that morally disputable?
But such decisions already exist
and we are trying to introduce them.
That's why I say that we are in a time
where technology is great
and we find it fascinating
when we can do things that move humanity.
But I don't know if we are fully prepared
to introduce them in a smart way.
I think we need to think about that.
A year ago, we had an episode
where we talked about LLM and AI.
And now that we are talking about it,
in six months, I think they are moving
forward very quickly.
Some things seem self-evident to us.
The strategic importance of Slovenia
will rise.
I think we put forward this month
that this is important, that we need to deal with it,
that we need to be proactive,
that this is not a joke.
But these technological LLM things...
I won't say where we will be in three months,
but we are working on it,
and maybe in three months we will say
that this is normal.
I think three beers would be enough
to answer that.
To predict the future of AI
is more like going to a bar,
where a person forgives and philosophizes.
Personally, I don't feel that I am a guru
in this area,
but from everything I understand
I think that at the moment
we have a lot of solutions
that use very good models,
taught on a huge amount of data.
But for that we need a lot of time
to learn them and then use them.
We learn them, then we make inferences,
then we learn, and so on.
And this cycle is driven
by a very fast development of hardware.
It can be reduced in such a way
that in some areas
it can start in real time.
This is my additional step forward.
A few years ago we installed
VEGO in Maribor,
which is so big and spacious,
and now it is in one of the Omars.
This shows that there is still
a lot of space here,
and when it is possible
to learn the system in real time,
I think that will be a big step forward.
One more question related to this.
We are talking about 1 billion tokens,
10 billion tokens,
LAMA has 70 billion,
will we get to the point
where the addition of these tokens
has a cap?
Do we need to add 1000 billion?
Will this remain somewhere
between 1 billion and 1 billion?
Will we be able to implement
more algorithms,
or a fundamental layer?
Do you see this as a trend?
Is there a top line?
There is almost always a top line.
When you ask the question,
the top line is business-oriented,
but I also think that
business-oriented and technical
is the top line.
What we need is to learn all the hidden and well-known meanings of the language.
I personally think that there is a limit that we do not need to go beyond,
because we will somehow eat up all the features.
But the language is very large, the way of expression is very diverse,
the personality is also huge, and this limit is potentially very high.
Andras, I will not say that it is time for a beer, maybe it is time for a snack,
so you will have one last question.
Yes.
I hope to get one question from the audience.
I can try.
Let's go a little out of the comfort zone.
Who will raise their hand? Who hopes?
Exclusive opportunity.
Among the projects that are more technically advanced,
the most important question is more about the project that would inform the public
about the logical understanding of these models,
or what exactly you said, that there would be a problem with some applications,
that they would not be able to do something.
Now we have a slightly biased Slovenian,
because we have seen a new type of AI in the world,
and that's it.
Yes.
Now I will have the question again to go to Eder.
Is there a project that would educate the public about these technologies,
so that the wider public would be more prepared for these technologies?
I will be very short, so that the audience can hear.
Yes, Marcin, everything is happening.
I have already seen some of the manuscripts,
where they dealt with large language models from a non-technical aspect.
So, I expect that there are also such views.
At our faculty, we try to include interdisciplinary groups,
because we are technicians, and we can explain how it works.
But what impact does it have on society, on young people, on I don't know what.
This is not our area, which we could really understand,
because we do not deal with it, and we are looking for others.
And when I mentioned the Ethical Commission at the University,
it was set up that way.
But in the beginning it was without us, without technology.
We are now on the same level, because now we know what these things are,
because we have seen many times that many people are biased,
and they do not know what it is.
So, we are trying to do this part.
I cannot criticize the Ministry,
but I would like to see a little more proactivity from their side.
We have one last question.
We have the privilege to be listened to by Slovak speakers,
by the developers of the widest range of knowledge.
Do you have an opportunity to invite them, to help them?
Do you need help from the community,
and if so, how can you help them with all this effort?
If I can say something, I would like to say that in our surroundings,
and this is not about some private things that someone would share with us,
but it is about, I do not know, that we get funding from NTK,
that is, from our national libraries,
or we get it from RTV, or we get it from the judiciary, etc.
I think that it is very important to understand that Slovakia
is on the wrong path, and that it will stay on the wrong path.
I work for a health care provider,
because of my knowledge of the language and so on,
and they say, I was in America,
and a health care provider goes there for a visit,
and when he comes back, he has a record of what he talked to the patient.
I understand, but we do not have to help each other,
we do not have to record the conversation between the patient and the health care provider,
but we need to be able to come to an agreement.
The only way to understand a little better what needs to be done,
and where we need to forgive some mistakes,
is to do it ourselves.
Otherwise, it simply does not work.
I already told you that we have set up a thousand hours for language recognition.
The best models are made in 500,000 hours.
I already told you that.
Ok, I agree.
I will take this opportunity to tell my colleagues a little about the problems,
so that this conversation expands a little.
I would like to thank everyone for your attention,
both in the audience and those who are listening to us in the car.
It seems to me that attention is a rare goodness,
for which we are very grateful.
Thank you very much for your presence and for your many questions.
Thank you from my perspective, thank you to the team,
thank you to the supporters and thank you for being with us.
See you next time. Good luck!