Welcome to Split Horses Maribor. Today we have a wonderful team of podcasters from Grodno.
Welcome to Split Horses Maribor. Welcome to the first… Today we have a lot of firsts.
Today we have the first Split Horses in a wonderful KGB club, mostly in the underground square with microphones and lights in Maribor.
Today is also the first recording of a podcast about Grodno live.
For example. We have already tried it. Qualifying in such clothes and with such colors.
We didn't go that big.
Oh, you didn't go that big.
Let's say the first recording of a podcast episode this summer.
Absolutely.
That's right.
And the first recording of a podcast live on Split Horses. I already mentioned that.
I didn't.
So, yes.
Quickly, for those of you who are the first in Split Horses, because I always say that as a moderator of Split Horses.
Split Horses are events about technology, the world and everything in between.
Once a month we get together in our favorite city of Maribor.
We used to get together more often, but look, now we've grown up and we all have an adult life.
We don't have to go somewhere for two weeks, because it already looks so strange.
But yes, I talk a lot, so maybe it would be cool if Andraža could join us.
No, no. I mean, first of all, the fact that we are all in this new merch, and maybe even that.
I would like to thank Erne Gračner, who is also...
Not only does he help us to make the city look as professional as it looks,
he is also one of those who are very deserving that Split Horses has been around for 13 years.
So, also for that, Erne, thank you for that.
Thank you for working hard.
Do I have to hold this?
No, no. You know what, I'll just tell you about the technical briefing.
We have some more points.
One is that it is satisfactory, it is not regrettable.
Great.
We will try to convey this live.
Now, Kadar, we talk to each other.
Sometimes I ask very stupid questions.
Not because we don't know, but because we are stupid.
He is simulating the audience.
I am not stupid, so you don't have to ask.
To bring the audience closer.
That's what I heard.
We have such a high level of audience that...
Yeah.
That's how it is.
Audience in Grodno.
I don't know. Do you have a structure?
At first, I wanted to start with some kind of a rant.
How everything went in Tri Krasne after Covid.
But I said no, we are not there yet.
You will continue.
Yes, definitely.
I don't want to...
No, no.
Not from the start.
A little.
Slowly, but surely.
So they don't run away.
No, no.
They don't.
Where to run?
Up the hill.
No, no, no.
It won't turn out like that.
For all the listeners, viewers, podcasters in Grodno,
I would like to give you a little background
about the connected streets in Maribor.
All of you who live in Ljubljana,
you are probably very happy,
because a lot is happening in Ljubljana,
when it comes to technological events.
There is not enough of them in Maribor.
But there are connected streets here.
We are here as a connected member
of the technological community in general.
These are not just topics of pure software development,
but also topics of design,
project, product management.
And yes, the players,
who are hiding in the back,
are already writing.
They are 13 years old,
and they are already working.
As if they don't see it.
But yes, a lot of volunteer work,
and we are very enthusiastic about it.
I also like to make shoes,
so I am front-facing.
If you would like to,
you would move to Ljubljana,
to the connected streets.
You survived.
We survived, yes.
And what about the connected streets?
They started in Ljubljana, right?
Yes, yes.
And is the connected street brand still there?
As far as I know,
it is a connected side.
I don't know if there are still events.
There was a revival a few years ago,
in 2014 or 2014,
I can't remember.
I am interested in the community.
How does a community develop,
how does a community sustain itself?
What is this thing?
How did the garden develop?
Why did the garden sustain itself?
How it sustains itself,
we will talk about that later.
But how it develops,
we already talked about it.
Then you grow up,
there are other priorities.
Do you succeed as a young person,
or as a connected member,
that will pull you forward?
If not, everything ends at some point.
And then you conclude.
Do you conclude?
OK.
We are talking about the community as a whole,
or specifically?
In Grodje,
I will talk about Grodje,
but I think we are somewhat similar.
In Grodje,
we somehow agreed that
if you want to do something in Sibinje,
it is good to have your own audience,
to know your target audience well,
to know who they are,
to understand their ambitions,
to understand their problems,
what they are facing,
what they are thinking about,
what works, what doesn't,
what language they speak,
to get to know the people
for whom you are doing this.
We tried to make a pool
through which we can now
celebrate this audience,
so that we can gather as many people
as possible on one channel,
so that we can get this feedback
as soon as possible,
so that we know who we are working for,
so that people tell us
whether we did a good job or not,
and so that they grow together with us.
This helps us a lot,
also in the selection in Sibinje,
in the promotion in Sibinje,
and in everything else.
We are working on the pool
for two purposes.
One is that we are doing it for ourselves,
and the other is that we are doing it
for this audience,
which I hope we understand
and which I hope will grow together with us.
Can we go on?
There is more.
This thing with this audience
is always interesting to me.
In my relatively short career,
I have done a lot of different things,
but I always deal with people again,
although a little more in the technical sense,
but also with people
who are not purely technical.
And I always deal with how to translate
an idea into something else,
so that everyone can understand it.
What we did very well,
in my opinion,
haters, you don't have to vote now,
but what we did very well
in all these years,
is that we managed to bring together
complex or perhaps technically demanding
concepts in a much broader way.
This is what we are doing now.
We are trying to bring together
some concepts in a much broader population,
even those who don't need
a technical background.
I have said it many times,
and I will probably say it again,
but I have been dealing with URIC
throughout my career.
If it were not for URIC
and other events in Maribor,
I would not know what Ruby on Rails is,
and I would not have published
a book about URIC.
On the other hand,
if it were not for URIC,
I would not have been in a cage,
and I would probably have been
in a more fancy place.
I can give you an answer to that.
We are moving to Odense.
We have learned that
doing too many accessible things
does not work.
We have learned that
everything we do in ourselves,
if you have a full-time employee,
for example, you are a full-time employee now,
coffee, is that a keyword?
I am definitely a full-time employee.
I am not a coffeemaker.
OK, I got carried away.
If I ask you something serious
or if you are going to start for a long time,
it will be really hard to explain.
On the other hand,
if people are interested in this,
they will find a lot of other content
that is specifically made for this purpose.
They will find more faith,
it will be better explained,
it will be explained better,
especially for you,
maybe with someone else in front of you.
So far we have learned
that we are not that intelligent,
but simplification does not work
for our example.
We then prepared,
maybe this can be a bit
for the younger ones,
we then prepared that,
for example,
we need a certain format
in the space for individuals,
for beginners.
We will make a series of individuals
under the banner of Zagon,
which is also created and run by our Sarah.
These individuals are made for beginners
and try to be individuals for beginners
who know how to find themselves
in this space,
but still with a local note,
how to prepare CVs,
how to pay,
how to connect and pay developers,
which is something we will investigate.
And this local note for beginners,
how to learn to program,
what does a programmer do,
these are topics that people are looking for
and I also see that the response is very good
and it works.
This is probably a bit different
for our use case.
Also community,
on this note,
on Discord we have
a channel called Zagon,
where more and more beginners
are being recruited
who experiment,
listen,
and need feedback or help.
Since so many people are already
helping each other,
it is also very interesting.
I think this is the thing.
If you take,
let's say,
the word community,
I would say that
a large majority of people
are regular visitors,
or through the fact
that they came or left,
maybe got drunk,
met new friends,
came to help,
as you said,
to careers,
or to some opportunities
that have opened up here.
That is what a community is.
In fact, it is not only
that you share a personality
but also that a community
of individuals is growing
where everyone starts
to create and work together.
So, I don't know,
in Grodno,
it is also important
that there is Discord.
It is probably
a physical space
and presence,
not only that people listen
to a lecture and ask questions,
but also that a debate
can develop there.
That is what is needed,
and that is probably
what Corona fucked up so well.
What we forgot
is the community.
Online,
I can't say that
in Grodno we notice
that
the younger generation
is doing it easier.
I don't know,
I am from the generation
of Šenoklet,
and people
needed to come there.
That was
the added value.
Not that a certain personality
was created there,
but that people
were actually
hanging out there.
One question here,
because the microphone
is a bit higher.
Is it better now?
Yes, it is a bit better,
isn't it?
One thing that interests me
at this point,
is that
Grodno is a community
that is a hybrid community,
if I may say so.
It is partly live,
through the conversations
you have,
every so often.
At the moment,
Grodno is not organized
in the form of meetups
or events like that.
Simply put,
at the end of the day,
we have other things,
but that is not our ambition.
I think that
Grodno should be exactly that,
Grodno.
There should be a framework
on which we can build things,
there should be a foundation,
there should be media and community,
and a channel of audience.
And then we have to
fully empower
the event organizers,
who organize meetings,
Open Blend,
Sektoke, B-sites,
and everything else.
Andras will tell you
the story of all those events,
there is always someone
who says, fuck, I know it better.
And he is right.
And then Slovenia...
Slovenian, I know it better.
I did it myself.
And then there are meetings,
and then we come to the point
where they say, hey,
Otto, what if you did a gift
and collected all the dates
so that we wouldn't organize the event
on the same day,
because that is already happening
in Ljubljana,
that you have very big, powerful events
on the same day.
I think that in Slovenia,
the space is for everything,
and if you look at it,
those scales are still small.
There is a gap
in how much these things can grow,
and that gap is not very big.
And I think
what we are aiming for
and what we are doing this year
is that we have
a couple of events
where we are connected with the organizers,
and they have events
that we publish on our channels,
and in this way we present it to our audience,
and it is a win-win situation
for the organizers and for our audience,
because we know that they are interested
in these things,
and it is logical that people come.
Also, for example,
I have a sponsor here, 3FSE,
they organize a Kubernetes meetup,
we promoted it,
and I think that tomorrow
about 18 people will come.
I think that is our role.
Last year we also partnered
with Dragonhack,
ADA,
and many other events.
We want to create
a community
and create a channel
for these events.
We are also present
at these events,
we also broadcast,
and we will come back,
because this is where
the offline happens,
as Andras said.
Do you think
that maybe
there is an expansion
and contraction of these events
and meetups?
For example, in Maribor,
I remember that a few years ago
we had a huge meetup.
It was this meetup,
and then at one point
people lost their way,
and they didn't have time,
and there were children,
and other services,
and then
people lost their way,
which is often the case
in our industry.
What can we do
to make it
as sustainable as possible?
I think that
the most you can do is
to go and see
who organizes it.
If you are an expert
in a topic,
if you go as a teacher,
it means a lot to people.
People organize,
and the more events,
the better.
People learn
how to organize.
It looks very simple on the surface,
but when you have three guys
with three microphones,
how much communication
is needed to happen?
I think we have to
move forward,
but it's better
if they are powerful,
because if people come together...
That's what I wanted to say.
It's more about
lack of cooperation.
If there was more
cooperation,
and I will say
that because of the fence
there is more cooperation,
but I see that
there is more cooperation.
If there was more cooperation,
there would be
more meetups,
and the community
would grow more.
There would be less burnout.
On the other hand,
when a meetup
starts,
maybe
the ego goes away.
I can do it,
I believe I can,
but we have seen
that if you do it once or twice,
you don't succeed.
It's more about
how to motivate
other people to help you.
How do you
motivate
someone
to help you?
It may not be perfect,
but it's
a learning process.
Let's start with Asano.
No, Asano is not for me.
I get a flashback
to Asano.
I'm glad you mentioned it,
because it's one thing
that we encounter
at meetups.
Maribor is not
a huge city.
Maribor has a tech community,
but it's not
as developed
as Ljubljana
or any other city.
I don't think
that's a problem.
If you think
that people will come to you
and ask for sponsorship,
it's hard.
There were times
when we had 4 sponsors
and everyone was fighting
who will get pizza, cookies,
caps, everything.
It was a way
to get
to that kind of people
and to support them
with business interests.
But now
everyone is fighting
and it's a crisis.
It's hard
to find someone
and a sponsor.
You can be disappointed.
We don't have a sponsor,
but we have supporters.
If you want
some organizational freedom,
and you want
to choose a topic yourself,
or if you will invite
some partners,
you can be careful
that they won't influence
the choice of guests,
so HR won't take
your event and
recruit you.
We witnessed that
many times.
There's no free money.
People who come
to events
don't have to pay
for a beer.
It's hard
to get funding
in Slovenia.
I think people are
more responsible than
in the past.
I agree.
It's a cycle of ups and downs.
There are times
when it's easier
to make a name for yourself,
or when it's already
done.
Then it's easier.
But then
you think you're
behind the wheel,
and next year
you're not
a part of it anymore.
The same people
don't give you money anymore.
It's interesting to me
that many events
from the 80s
to the 90s
were based on two principles.
Either it was purely
punk DIY,
where everyone gets
a beer every other Thursday
and we talk about
some topics,
or we go to
a formal structure,
an organization, etc.
Splitnavice is an example
of a punk DIY.
You say that,
but I didn't say no.
We are structured.
Yes, we are structured.
But that's punk.
We were very lucky
to have
very good friends
and supporters
in Kibla,
the National House.
They were always there
for us,
they promoted ZDV,
and for two weeks
we organized events.
It was insane.
The Splitnavice team
is here right now.
It was
machinery.
People went to Maribor
constantly,
everyone could see everything.
From specific events
like
coffee,
blockchain,
to some simple
topics,
I don't have to use the word
simple, because nothing is simple,
to some general topics
like how to find
your first job in IT,
or design topics.
Design topics are
very important.
for some reason, underrepresented
in general,
project, product management.
When we started
developing these tasks,
and when we started developing this program,
the DIY mindset,
the punk mindset,
got us to this point.
We had
low operating costs,
which were practically nothing,
a lot of people didn't get paid
or anything, so we hid
and it went through
for a long time.
Then came the corona,
then we all locked ourselves in our rooms.
But you had some
kind of flow as well.
It was very visible,
when Slovenia was closing down.
At the same time,
there were rare cases,
which were published daily,
you came, there was a channel, stream, talk,
very proper level.
Where are you at the same time?
There is also an archive in Spetni Hurice,
at the same time.
It's very interesting.
There are a lot of things.
But all of this takes a long time,
especially for people.
We took a break one day,
then we called him back,
and he was gone for a month.
And that was it?
That was it.
No, poor genetics.
Spetni Hurice.
But yes,
events like ours,
the basis is that
it's live,
with people in front of the audience.
And live events have their own dimension,
their own challenges,
and their own specifics.
Correct me if I'm wrong,
or I'm interested in your opinion,
what do you see as an advantage
of live events?
I see it like this.
What I've noticed in those meetups,
is that 40%
is a person,
60% is the audience.
And from the perspective of someone
who organizes the event,
you have to focus.
I see the guests,
everything has to be perfect.
Then the other 60%,
when the lights go out,
you have to find out who will
help organize the event,
who will speak,
who will delegate.
You have to work very actively
so that the next event
will happen while you're there.
He's laughing now.
Andras, can you tell us about
Sektok?
I can tell you,
I don't know how it is in CyberPipa,
but I have to
imagine
that CyberPipa
produced
only three events
a week.
That's a lot.
These are three events a week.
There were four,
so four days a week
were events.
And in one month
you had to know exactly what will happen
because the flyers were printed.
There was no internet.
How sick is that?
You could have
a salesperson,
you could have known
that you can print flyers
for the next month.
Andras, what are flyers?
I mean,
in an analog form,
a sheet of paper
on which the program
for the next month was written.
A flyer.
I was
actively
leading
these events.
What did I do
to make it possible?
I don't know.
I'm trying to put one meetup
a month in the hallway
and it really needs to be
postponed.
What is it?
I don't know.
The audience here
looks very simple.
They send e-mails.
The meetup will be there.
It's not that simple.
Even the copy
that needs to be printed
with 3-4 flyers
will take
one hour.
Then the image,
and so on.
You lose
some time.
It's not that simple.
I agree with what
the author said.
You probably
haven't noticed
but the idea is
that people are there.
What do you do with these people?
I'm from the generation
that says
that the video stream
kills the event.
In CyberPipa,
we were in a phase
where the stream was fine.
If someone had an idea,
how to stream
and the stream appeared,
but somehow
people got mad.
They were like,
how come there's no stream today?
It happened once
that we stopped people
on the street
and asked them
when the last stream will be.
It wasn't in Kibla
or in Kamesov Pisarnik
where we have events now.
I was working on something
and I was like,
sorry.
Streams are great
but there's one more level of complexity.
Especially that we set up
everything here.
At this point,
we wouldn't sell the audience
here.
But with the garden
and with the story
that Andras is telling,
it's very simple
to add features
and complexity
to the events
and to increase
the expectations
of the audience
and the people
who attend the events.
It's easier
to add lights
and cameras
when at some point
you say,
let's go back.
Now we had streaming
and we won't have it anymore.
Don't you have to
force yourself to go back
or do you have a feeling
that the audience won't
notice it?
What can we do
to make it a new standard
and to bring it back?
Because then you start thinking
that
it's at this level.
You have to realize
that we do this
to a large extent
because we like it.
We like it so much
that we do it freely.
In such a mindset,
people can be easily
exploited.
The whole music industry
works on this concept.
People are passionate
and are ready to commit
to anything.
This leads to
excitement,
to expectations
that you don't have to keep.
As you said,
we have a live event
in Grodno.
It would be an additional
part of everything
we have to do.
If we find someone
to delegate it,
we can't replace
or compensate for it.
What do you mean?
I mean,
it could be a shout-out.
If someone is interested
in experimenting
and would like to
get involved
and stream live,
we won't.
Will you complain?
What if there were...
You see, that's where it starts.
You know what you could do?
That's pure Maribor.
You could switch to Turkish.
Those who don't visit you
and don't listen to you
always tell you that.
They didn't follow you,
but they suggest what to do.
You could have headphones,
even better microphones,
you could stream,
you could...
You know Patreon?
Oh, you know,
I have a low salary in Switzerland.
Some of those initiatives,
like Grodno,
Spletna Urica,
various meet-ups,
are only for those
who come from common enthusiasm
and common interest.
It grows.
It grows a lot.
I would say that everything
comes from one individual
who is crazy enough
to do it.
Yeah, definitely.
Andras Raga.
Those social activities
are forming a lot
and we are finding them now.
You still need some space
to organize an event,
you need a way
to communicate with people.
I would go back a bit.
I often use
this Slovenian proverb
and it goes like this.
A good farmer
finds a good heir.
It's a very deep
thought.
We are not good at that.
We are still working on that.
That's a theory
about the Slovenian proverb.
We are not good at that.
If we want
Grodno to survive
5-10 years,
we need to
structure it in such a way
that it will be resilient.
If I am sick today,
or Andras is sick,
we need to rotate
and take care of him.
We need to think
about that.
We are also working on
how to
mix different parts,
so the torch
will be
thrown forward.
But it's not like
here are the keys.
You need to somehow...
I would say yes.
That's a nice
proverb.
I would add
that I allow
anyone to take
the torch
and turn it
in a different direction.
I mean,
whether it's a wedding
or a meet-up,
whether it's in Grodno,
those who
carry it forward,
they carry it with their vision.
They keep the skeleton
and decide
whether to change
specific content
or just change the torch.
That's something
that is a bit
purely Slovenian.
I remembered it,
it's my project,
and the successor would like
it a bit differently,
so I won't let it go.
We need to leave the ego aside.
Someone calmed down,
someone thought
to turn it in a different direction.
It sounds much simpler,
but to build
a climate
where
you can screw up.
We'll do something
we'll screw up,
it'll be a disaster,
but we'll learn
and turn it in a different direction.
Yes, but here's the problem.
If you screw up and learn...
Are you talking about me?
Maybe, maybe.
Then it becomes
that no matter how much
you learn,
we've learned something.
A person has to go through
the same mistakes
and learn something new
again.
Yes, that's why
in Grodno we don't have
a recording studio.
We've organized a recording
in a cafe.
You learn from some things.
Maybe that's also
important,
if we've ever organized
anything like that,
the reflection after the event
is very important.
When we record,
we talk about what was good,
what wasn't.
Maybe it's not like that,
but we've learned
what suits us.
That reflection,
retro,
is very important
because you need a point
to say,
is this what we're fighting for?
If you have those points,
it's less likely
that you'll lose
what you're fighting for.
I like that, because
it could be applied
to everything.
We do everything
based on what we've already done.
What did Loki do in CyberPip?
What did the players do in Design?
What did we do?
And then we learn a lot.
Certain things can be re-recorded,
certain things
don't exist anymore
in 2020,
but you have to try different things.
That's true.
I see that
even when there are live events,
we have to try
to keep people on their toes
and to develop the debate.
A few years ago,
it was something normal.
I had this forum
at Pipini Expert
where we know
that the Slovenian audience
didn't stop asking questions.
There was a good flow of people
who invested a lot of time
and in the end,
zero questions.
Or there's always
one person who asks
the most fucking questions
and the most discussion in the world.
That's what I did.
I had a lot of questions
and I provoked
the audience and someone
so that in the end
I put a lot of questions
in front of the audience
because they said
that they would ask me
the same questions.
Just because I provoked
the audience to start asking
questions.
A little trick of a great master.
Are we going to include
questions from the audience?
We will.
You know what,
we could tell our sponsors
and supporters.
Is that you?
No, that's your part.
Here we have in Grodno
we thank the 3FSE
and Human Frog
who support us
in this story.
We thank all the Patreons
who support us.
Patreonite, besides
getting a person before
also got a merch
which was also made by Mr. Gračan.
Thank you for your support.
EPP.
Now we have
a few more questions.
It would be cool to include them.
Are you ready?
Did he choose me?
Ok.
Did you choose the first question?
Why don't we have a 8K
video podcast?
Jan,
are you going to start
We don't have a disk.
We don't have a storage disk.
Yes, that's a problem.
Yes, those SD cards.
We are fully limited,
so it's better to have episodes
after 20 minutes.
If we would do it in 8K,
if I'm right,
Jan's answer is that
there would be an episode
of 100 GB.
I think that would be
too much.
A lot of people are using the internet,
so they don't have a problem with 100 GB.
I already have
a portable SSD disk
M-tera for 90 euros.
You can put it in your pocket
and save it.
I think there are
some other technical issues.
Jan said that
if you are interested in why we don't have a 8K
in the back,
the audience is waiting for you.
We will discuss the details of that in a bit.
Video production
costs $1 and $1.00 per hour.
To make it look
and sound proper
is absolutely one thing.
Thank you, Jan, for everything.
It also means that we can
get along with everyone else.
Tomaš should also join us,
because Lightning is also important.
Yes.
Tomaš Zaman is the bringer of light.
Tomaš Zaman is the bringer of light
from Kobilje.
We thank him a lot.
He is the real YouTuber
from all of us.
A random interlude.
If any of you
are involved in event organization,
you know that the person
who forms the light
usually sits behind the table and watches.
Those who are involved in event organization
are like,
oh no, there is a photo,
and physicists are jumping around.
Shall we move on?
Yes, let's move on.
Because people could go crazy.
They can go.
We still have some problems.
We have to deal with them.
You can go crazy,
but technically speaking,
they are recording everything.
How long does it take you
post-production or video editing?
How do you publish a new video
on all platforms? Do you have your app
or do you use a third party app?
This is a really interesting question.
How long does it take us
video editing?
We will record this,
I have it all on a disk,
and I will bring it home,
and when I have time, I will edit it.
It usually takes 7 days.
It depends on how busy you are.
We don't press any buttons.
It is an artistic work.
We send it, and then we publish it.
You said that it is fully post-production.
Post-production is...
Post-production is
just putting in
this audio program, normalizing it
to minus 3 decibels.
No, no, no. Hired.
Hired?
We have already learned
that this doesn't work.
We have Jan, who knows this.
Once we had AI tools.
You put this in, and then AI tools.
Then you say, now it will be a perfect sound.
No.
I would say, everything is fine.
He said, no.
A YouTube commenter once said,
when you put it in AI tools,
it doesn't work.
Jan looked at it and said,
fans, before you put it in AI tools,
you should worry about stereo recording,
not mono.
Why do you publish it?
OK, the publisher of the podcast
is Fordhamis.
There is a platform
called Podcaster,
which was bought by Spotify.
You put a file on top,
and then it does an RSS feed.
Then we have it posted
on all the other platforms,
like Apple and Insta,
and from that RSS,
YouTube chooses.
Then you publish it on top,
and that's it.
On those two channels,
we publish the audio recordings.
We also have a developer, CMS,
technical.
You can see that this is a technological podcast,
because someone has always been developing
their own CMS.
Integrate, integrate, integrate.
That's how it started.
Maybe it sounds stupid,
but that's how it is today.
From CMS, we have a page generated,
and everything is stretched and structured,
and thumbnails can also be created.
So, stay tuned
on our GitHub and open source.
If anyone is interested in this technological aspect,
we are on Skriberi.
On the other hand,
what we are most successful at
is getting people to use it themselves.
We were at that point
where we needed a ticketing system.
And then,
Slovenia decided to write their own.
Yes, yes.
And then I said,
there are a lot of them,
but not Jira, but something else.
I get PTSD every two seconds.
Only if it's integrated.
Only if it's integrated, right?
Yes, that would interest them.
On GitHub,
we have everything written.
If anyone is interested,
if anyone wants to clone,
they can make their own podcast.
Yes, go for it.
In the community,
we touched on everything.
Questions for the older generation.
Oh, my God.
What are the current meetups,
conferences and similar events
starting better than the previous ones,
for example, 10 years ago?
What are we doing better today?
Definitely,
more omnipresent
on the Internet.
On all possible channels,
but also,
as you said,
there are all these different tools
that are being generated,
sent, etc.
What is being done worse?
That might be more interesting to me.
There is less honest contact
between people on events.
I don't know.
I mean,
if I go to our side,
we started collaborating
with Laro Kozbek this year.
If it wasn't in Portuguese,
it would probably be with us.
And now we have
a member in our team
who manages to distribute
the gifts on TikTok,
YouTube, Reels
and Instagram.
We can see that there are
a lot of audiences
and we have to be present.
It's our format,
so if you see the clips,
Laro does it all by himself
and spreads it.
We make sure that people
who don't know us see us.
Facebook is for old people
and LinkedIn is for business.
What if I say I don't have a Facebook?
You have to do it,
but if you really want
to be present
on LinkedIn and Facebook,
you will be able to do it.
You will be able to buy ads
and then come back
to it quickly.
You can do it today
as an event organizer.
In our case,
we built
all this presence
for nothing.
We never bought
new ads or anything.
Everything through our own networks
and that was enough.
How far can we go with this effect?
You definitely get to know each other before 2-8 events and after that you have a chance to get an audience.
You can try a little bit, but you have social networks, you have a lot of things,
as I said before, airplanes, press of airplanes, there was nothing else.
On the other hand, if there was RSS, it was already a step forward, there were very few aggregators,
there were no Facebooks, Myspace existed, and that was it.
In fact, this word is not a lie today.
But it's not a lie either, is it?
It's not a lie because you can work harder for the attention of those people.
It's not enough to launch something, but in some smart way you will launch it so that you will target the right people.
But I would say that this part of honest contact, or actually building a community with people who really come to the event,
to shake hands a little bit, or to get to know each other, that's what it's all about.
I see that everyone you meet at such an event and you get to onboard them by hand, stays there forever.
One of the things in our Discord is that people who came in, if we onboarded them by hand,
they are full of passion and they felt it today because they understand these issues.
So, this personal touch, communities are people, we can all have some titles, techniques, voices and everything,
but that's the touch you build with people.
And also, if you want to, I have a question here,
bring some commercial business, because you will work with people.
I think it's all the same, the level is higher or different, but you will probably be able to maintain the business,
and it's not enough to do it once and then hope that you got it all.
Ok, I have one here, who wrote this to me?
How to motivate young people who will help maintain and continue the Smiley Face community in Switzerland?
One of the debates we had last year with Blengorjev, where do you find young people?
In cafés, at basketball courts, so random that we get together in Maribor for a few years.
I prepare one thing, I work a lot with young people and I'm in some different initiatives,
I'm not a stand-up comedian, I'm not an improviser, I'm not an economist,
Ok, that's enough.
I see that a lot of young people have a desire to be part of a story, something bigger,
but they often have a problem because they don't know how to take the first step,
how to join an initiative, a lot of times there is no onboarding,
you come, you find someone, and if you are lucky, someone will take you under their wing and show you things,
and then you start to learn, you meet new people,
but a lot of times it's a problem because people don't have a structured approach.
For example, in Urec, we had a lot of students who came to help us,
they helped with filming, photographing, organizing events,
and it's not hard to start an event like that, you need a space where people will gather,
you need a topic to talk about, you need someone who will say something about that topic,
and you just need to make sure that the conditions for dissemination of information are as comfortable as possible.
Yes, there is a light, maybe a microphone, or that everything is so quiet that you can hear it, and so on.
Nobody sees all the other things that are happening.
You need to prepare tables, you need to prepare cables on the left and right,
and there is a lot of hidden work.
A lot of young people are under the impression that this is ready-made,
I come, I sit down, and suddenly things start to work on their own.
Where do I find young people who have so many desires?
It's very hard to find them, and when you do, you have to do everything in your power to keep them.
Which is a big problem, because young people, or people who have some special characteristics,
or predispositions, characteristics,
they are very curious, and they do six different things at the same time.
And you compete now for these six other interests in their lives.
Sometimes you succeed, sometimes you don't, and then people move,
then they have jobs, then they have children, and so on.
I don't know if you like to have a structured approach to looking for these young people,
great, but it takes a lot of resources.
If you don't have cash, time and energy.
If you don't have time and energy, you can supplement it with cash.
It's not a simple answer, it's a very difficult topic.
Who is this guy? I can talk to him for three hours, I don't know who he is.
If I remember correctly, at the beginning of Cyberpipa,
there was a period when the broadband wasn't very widespread.
So if you had a good ISD at home, or the beginning of some kind of XDSL, great.
But in reality, we had the most equipment available at the time.
So there was a lot of interest, people had fast internet,
and there was a lot of equipment that you don't have at home.
So you got a group of people who could hang out there.
Now the question is, how did you...
Yes, a lot of people became very motivated because of that,
and they wanted to do something.
Today we have this problem,
when generations come and say,
look, we have faster internet at home,
I have a powerbook at home,
which you don't have here.
Why would I go to you?
When there was a period,
I don't know, 3D printers,
we had a 3D printer, great.
Today you have a 3D printer at home,
why would you hang out with someone?
But this hasn't changed from...
I don't know,
before 2008.
In Ljubljana, for example,
Ljubljana Tech Hub,
events there...
Ljubljana Tech Hub, what's that?
You have old news.
It's not Ljubljana Tech Hub anymore?
I mean, that news hasn't come from Trojana yet.
No, I didn't...
You'll have more beer then.
Ah, OK.
The last time I was at an event there,
it was more equipped than the Marsekater Hall
in Prijeditven Prostor in Slovenia.
That's what we were talking about earlier.
It's very simple,
it's hard to be consistent
through time.
If you start at a high level,
you can't...
It's not sustainable.
In Grodno,
it's a third or fourth attempt
to have a technical podcast
or a tech-deo podcast
in Slovenia.
People have
even better microphones
than we have.
They're just microphones
because
you need a lot of other things
that are important
and you need continuity.
Exactly.
It's easy
to buy gear
because of the equipment.
But
if I just go forward,
it's more likely
that if you create
comfortable physical conditions
for an initiative,
you'll attract people's attention.
But it's not necessary
to attract people's attention.
I won't go too deep
into details,
but the cyberpipa
that lost its space
somehow
sank or disappeared.
People started to say
that they don't have space
or a place to start.
Then they realized
that in order to have
their own existence,
they need space.
Then they found
an unoccupied space.
But these people
didn't have a place
to start.
Then they went there
and nothing happened.
The infrastructure
was too small
and people thought
that's it.
If there is
motivation in people
or passion that these people
will find,
they will do what they need.
People said
that they wanted space
and then nothing happened.
It means
that space is not what you want.
It sounds like a cliché
but everything is important
for the team.
When you organize
events,
do you really need 350 people?
Is it enough
to have one, two, three?
For example
Ruby Meetup
has seven people
sometimes five.
Now there are more,
but these are people
who have been doing Ruby for 15 years
and they all know each other.
People organize events
for people,
don't forget that.
Now,
if CyberPipa is mentioned again...
CyberPipa is great.
CyberPipa is important
historically.
You know what's fascinating?
I will mention it again.
When people come
and say
that it was great
but I have never been there
because I was so confused.
Everyone told me
that something really started there.
It definitely made an impact.
Definitely.
There are a lot of such things.
People always talk about
how it was in the past.
Now we are working
and we don't know how long it will be.
Let's make this episode
in order.
now.
Maybe we can discuss
CyberPipa with Šanko.
Are you afraid that it will be the last one?
My attitude is always like that.
When I look at it,
it doesn't matter.
Now we have to do it.
Everything has to be done well.
You always worry that it won't be.
I always think about it.
But now you talk
as if it's a dream.
Yes, it's a dream.
We are here, in space, in time.
I don't own the field.
No.
Let's talk about it.
We have
a strategy.
It's a document.
If you go to ogrodi.si
you will get a new design.
There is a tab called strategy.
It's written there.
We have one document.
You can see it by the links in ogrodi.si.
Yes, everything is in ogrodi.si.
I don't know if people have changed it.
It's the only document
that exists in Grodno.
We have written it.
It's a manifesto.
We are keeping it.
We have updated it.
But
it's very important.
Because
it's a contract
between us.
Why do we do it?
What are the values?
Where are we together?
For whom
will we do it?
Where does it go?
Now we have to update it
because the vest is getting older.
But
it's changing.
It's growing.
If you can say
what you are proposing
it's not related to
values or strategies
that we have established.
Now we will evolve
against those values
or we will go somewhere else.
Or we will change the strategy.
But it's good
that you have the same people.
After this episode
we will record something a bit different.
A bit different?
It's easy
to do it.
It looks like
you are a Zen monster.
But
this is
a strategy.
This is a reward for doing a reward.
So this is
a Zen monster.
Next question.
Jan told me
how much time we have left.
Do we have SD cards again?
I don't know.
We have people locked in a cage.
They can order
or get married.
Ok.
This question is still in the chat
and it says
Do you think that
a community funded way of support
is possible in Slovenia?
Yes.
Are you a community funded?
Are you?
No.
We are not a community funded.
Did you think about it?
We are.
More than once.
More than once
we were locked in a cage.
Maybe more time for pressure
or that so many things happened in our lives
that we didn't take a step forward
and formalize it.
You have Patreon.
Community funded.
We needed a lot of time
for that.
We had to talk about it.
For a long time.
Struggles.
But if you are a community funded
then you can be a community funded.
Exactly.
It sounds trivial
but
then it means
that from someone
for the story you produce
you get something.
And before that
it is
very important
because it validates
that what we do today
brings so much value
that people are ready to pay for it.
From a product perspective.
You can see
that it is not so much value
but just for you to start
people are ready to support you.
Yes.
I can imagine
when people say
that they are just starting
but I will give them more.
And they are not so unprepared
but they do what they do
and I think it is a good thing.
That it brings so much value.
You have a lot of disposable income
so why not give it to them
and ask for it.
I always think
that just before I publish an episode
and before I press send, upload, publish
it would be great
if someone else did it
just for 5 euros.
If I was just
a subscriber,
someone else would do it
and I would just subscribe.
Then it would be great.
Who wouldn't?
But
I think
there are
5 of us
in this story
and if in the beginning we were minus
we were working
in our own way
and then we came a bit closer
to nothing
we are not over nothing yet.
A lot of the equipment
is disposable
we drive on our own gas
we have our own electricity
a lot of that.
So
if you want to have
equipment production
you will pay a lot
so
this production costs
we don't work for free
we don't pay for anything
even if it looks like a top sheet
that part is very expensive
especially if you don't
count the time we put in
and the energy
and the waste.
That's an interesting factor
because we know how to calculate
the time and we didn't count our own
because that's a lot of money.
The streets
work according to the same principle
we have been volunteering for 14 years
so
once a street vendor
didn't get a salary
once one of us didn't pay the salary
those burgers that you all eat at the end of the season
we cover
our own pockets
we paid a lot
for a few things
we have very nice supporters
friends
that help us
pay for the space
we have our own equipment
time and energy
are the things that
drive the initiative forward
yes,
there could be community funded
options
but it requires a lot
of administrative and bureaucratic work
especially
the mental pressure
the pressure to deliver
I know
you probably go back to
the commitment
if you eat yourself
DIY
concept
help us
what will you deliver
we will try our best
it can be a war
and if that's the expectation
that can happen
you probably don't give a fuck
we will constantly
work on that level
and if you realize
that it's the bare minimum
and you expect
that it will be constant
then it's not a problem
we already had those difficulties
when we were filming
during the pandemic
when we had Zoom calls
and then everyone
was watching
a little before the pandemic
if you remember
correct me if I'm wrong
a couple of months
5-6 months before the pandemic
we started with some
streams
and some
uploads
but it was very simple
we had one old phone
that no one used
one cheap tripod
we put it in the toilet
the toilet had
no sound
so we just
put a cable in the phone
and it was editing
and uploading
and then everyone
wanted to have
a production
and we were thinking
what if we make a company
and get some money
then we can get a better phone
or a camera
microphones
a mini setup
so we can film
it's not because
we are serving
because we haven't been serving
for 13 years
it's because we want
people who come
and take time
we want to give them
something good
a good product
to have some value
I think
it's very important
if one of those
people
if it's a passion
that interests them
to stream
for you it's 8k
if it's for you
then yes
it's not like
we'll do it
because the audience expects it
it kills
the part
that you are working on
if it's for you
it's probably for you
because you saw the shape
of the people
to continue the story
to be happy
to get some topics
and that's it
if it's for you
to have a 8k live stream
then it would be
it would be our duty
to have a live stream
I can now
for the last few questions
because we'll finish in a while
is it cool for you?
easy
sometimes I have wet wishes
and sometimes wet dreams
wet dreams and questions
for both
this question is for you
no, I'll serve it to you
warm
wet dreams and questions for you
what would you like to see in Grodje in a few years?
I don't know if it's written like that
wet dreams
here it's so clear
maybe more from myself
not from the whole team
in Grodje
but I especially see
from that
manifest
that
it's
a connection
that helps
the individuals
in Slovenia
to do something good
and write those stories
that
we can be something else
in some other year
or that year
or in some other beer
and say
10-15 years ago
it was good
I think that
it's
I never
never
in meetups and events
that I do now
I value more
quality of content
than quantity
how many people watched
how many people came to watch
it doesn't matter to me
and I think that
if it will
leave a mark
that it was
a good event
we connected
I don't know
if we connected
two people at the other end
of Slovenia
two different communities
to find
a new startup
a new company
or a new community
Thank you very much, Ilona
Yes
Same question for you, for Spletna Urica.
I thought you were going to say it for Grodje.
No, for Grodje.
Let's try it one at a time.
When I see Spletna Urica in a couple of years, 5, 10, 15, how old are we?
It says wet dreams.
Wet dreams.
It's easy even today.
I see Spletna Urica not as a physical space, but a space that gives young people opportunities.
I always ask myself, if there was no Urica and no space for a young, ambitious,
with a head full of hair, Blinder, I wouldn't have a career in IT, I wouldn't have met these people.
A lot of stories have been born before and after Shank.
To have a space, an independent space, where anyone interested in technology,
and in the world of technology, can satisfy their curiosity.
That's what I see.
In what form?
We'll see.
It's a living organism, it's constantly changing.
So, that's it.
Great.
I hope...
Do you have a tip for wet dreams?
I told you, choose a strategy from what you wrote.
Ah, that's it.
Strategies for wet dreams.
That's it.
Be this layer, this framework, so we can sustainably build these stories,
so we can pass them on,
so we can build a strong community of people with similar ambitions,
who work in this space,
and who can tell their stories,
so that someone from across the world,
from some village,
can come and work in Google,
and in your phone,
and in the whole world,
so that we have good engineering in Slovenia,
so that we know how to build products in Slovenia,
so that we are as good as anywhere else,
so that we can do this in any form,
where media is not important,
so that we can do this,
because it will be fun,
because we will be happy,
because we will have some satisfaction from this,
so that it will be good for us,
and if it doesn't,
then we will be OK.
But, yeah...
I don't know why we do this,
and why we choose ourselves,
but I always have this in my head,
I don't know,
you go to events,
and then a shy first-year student comes up to you,
and says, hey, I listened to all your episodes,
it's great, I didn't know it was growing,
and then you see,
you show them,
hey, we are the same people,
and then you see,
it's a very reliable thing,
I hope we can do it,
something like that.
I know, it's a lot of fun.
Will you have any last questions?
I don't know,
what is the last question?
Pepperoni or chili?
That came up right away.
And then there's the,
let's stay away from the wet ones.
So,
content creation
was probably
a little bit more for us,
but it's all connected.
How important is the creation
of a person, blog, video,
for an individual programmer,
or for his career?
And then we can connect it somehow.
How important is
the creation of a person today?
And content, and video,
and tutorials, and everything.
I think that
everything that
relates to content,
if you want to prosper
somewhere,
at the beginning of your career,
you already gained some knowledge,
probably because
people call you,
so you can sell yourself.
Try to sell as much as possible at conferences,
show up as much as possible,
try to transfer
that knowledge forward,
because in this way
you increase your credibility,
you learn more,
even if they tell you
that you're not good enough.
It's also a kind of learning.
Definitely,
to participate in the teaching.
And if you're so good
that you know what to write,
and have your own personal blog,
that's great.
But if you're an influencer,
and you need YouTube,
I'm afraid that young people
are lying to me,
that they are used to
being in front of the camera,
and talking to themselves.
I don't know.
Can I have a hot take on this topic?
Yes, go ahead.
I don't know,
sometimes I say something
and people look at me strangely.
I think that we collectively
brainwashed people
with the idea
that everything has to become
a content production machine.
Anyway,
as anyone who works in IT,
not just a developer,
you spend a lot of time
and brain energy
to break down complex problems
into smaller ones,
and then put them
together in a mosaic.
And now,
I think it's not fair
to expect that
you'll have your own blog
and produce a certain amount of content.
Let's collectively
not put
any pressure
on young people
who are starting on this path.
Self-pace.
Do a good project,
document it well,
and post it
so that it becomes
a constant
production for the content.
You probably have to ask yourself
what the endgame is.
What would you achieve?
Or would you just
restrain yourself?
I have the feeling
that a lot happens
when you look at bloggers,
who are huge bloggers,
until they reached
the next level.
Was it because they got a job?
I remember
a blogger
who was very popular
in Second Life.
He got a shift
in Second Life
because he wrote
the experience of Second Life,
his blog, and so on.
At the moment,
there was not much
in that blog.
His endgame was
how to get there.
If someone
was a super engineer
and wanted to
get to Google,
maybe he would write
a blog in algorithms
and try to build
his credibility
so that he could
talk to Google for a job.
I don't know.
Even if you are
a good,
top-notch programmer,
you don't need to know how to write articles.
Exactly! That's what I said earlier.
You don't need to.
Maybe
step one is to document
all your side projects.
Document
in the style
of whatever I do
on GitHub.
You work as a repository
of your projects.
That's a minimal step.
Whatever I play, whatever I experiment,
just snippet codes,
just a toy project,
just to get used
to the routine of publishing
and publishing.
Also,
if you see that someone
made a book,
if you see that
you used someone's book
and you found a bug,
just tell them
that you found a bug,
open it and report it.
That's also considered
an active thing,
I'm interested in things,
I'm ready to take the next step,
I know how to use these tools,
I'm aware of them,
and you discover
that there are other people
on the other side
of the online community.
Whatever you give,
it's better than nothing.
Most people in this space
consume,
contribute,
and if you write an article,
if you write a blog post,
if you come to a meeting,
it's much more
than anyone else did.
Then a few meetings,
a few smaller meetups,
and then you have
the experience
of how to register
for a conference,
what are the other disadvantages.
For example, people don't know
that if you register
for a bigger international conference,
they usually have
a speaker dinner,
and that means
that you are at an international conference
together with
the biggest entrepreneurs
and you get
access to a network
of top people,
and you can build
your name
over time.
You start with smaller events
to gain more experience.
What you said is true,
it can be overwhelming.
Let's start with Kodo,
with a little correction.
If I may,
Kodo is a platform
where you can
connect with people
and use it as an app.
Maribor is always open
for new teachers,
so if any of you
want to come
and say something,
just call us.
We are here.
Sometimes we are downstairs,
sometimes we are on the floor.
Don't panic.
We are big.
But we already got people
to come and say something.
Yes, yes.
Like, hey,
from the marketing department,
our boss came to say something.
It's full.
I don't know
if it will work.
I can explain why,
because we are ready
that it won't work.
It's better to have
an engineer in their team
to say something.
We are more interested in that.
But yes.
What did you do?
I don't know.
I married,
and we got closer.
Blender.
That was it.
You listened
and watched
Spletna Urica with Ogrodje
live.
3rd season,
4th episode.
That's it.
Where can they find you?
On all podcasting platforms.
And on YouTube.
That's when they can say
write it down
and tell us.
Like and subscribe.
If you are on Patreon,
you got this episode
before the others.
That's it.
I think that's it.
Exit.