Part 2
Part 3
Part 4
Part 5
Part 6
Part 7
And now we have the intro again.
No, the beginning is cut.
I will edit it a bit,
maybe for this part
when I will edit the last part.
So that the light changes.
So that you are more enlightened
in the dark phase
and then you can edit the intro.
In the last part I will just add
some background sounds of the Himalayas
and the wind
blowing in the mountains
so that people feel
like they are...
like they are falling down.
The Himalayas are not mountains,
they are mountains.
So, Jan,
in the meantime,
turn on the background noise.
I managed to change a bit today
because we have a different atmosphere.
I managed to change it
into an intro passage.
It is from the book
by Reinhold Messner,
an uber-alpinist
world-famous
from his book called Death.
There is a quote
at the beginning of the book
from a Swiss healer
who also dealt a lot with alpinism.
It is actually
a death pass. What is it?
It goes like this.
A person can still acclimatize
at an altitude of 6,000 meters,
but not more than 7,000 meters.
You can get used to it
in a short time.
Why I am losing my eyes
can not be fully compensated
at the beginning.
Maybe the acclimatization limit
could be removed a few more,
but we do not know.
At an altitude of 7,000 meters
real damage occurs.
The pain in the neck
is converted from normal
to chronic pain.
Colds are dangerous
because the body
lacks oxygen.
The heart, which is difficult
to adapt, expands,
so-called dilatation.
Insecurity is no longer
able to recover due to
lack of vital vitamins
and to protect it
from loss of flow.
The body maintains
a superior physiological level.
I wanted you to hear
what we are going to talk about
today,
what is the mission
of today's episode,
how we communicated
with the people
who went through
all those levels,
who went through those levels
where people do not exist,
where the environment
is very hostile,
because
the achievements
we talked about
should also be looked at
through this prism.
The achievements in alpinism
and in the technical sense
of what was needed
to make this story work.
I hope that
this definition of the problem
puts it in context.
But now,
let's get back
to Grodno.
We are in the heart
of the Computer Museum.
With us is
Jan Žorš,
the second in this season.
Why did we meet
today among others?
When we had that conversation,
we got a hint
of a topic we would talk about,
but it did not really
get to the point.
But when we thought about it,
when we talked about it,
we realized
that it is a big topic.
We are not only
passionate
and successful alpinists
in Slovenia.
We also described ourselves
as the first streamers
on the Internet
from the Himalayas.
Jan,
you are part of this story,
two of these stories,
and the fourth guest
on the show,
who
covered
the technical part.
So, we will talk
about the two
trips you participated
in.
How did this
happen?
We talked about
whether
it is something
that is nice to have,
that we now have
this stream there,
or is it something we can
survive,
we can forget about it,
and move on.
How did you
start with this?
Did you find in this story,
which we will talk about later,
in Slovenian media,
that it was also
a victory
for Dusežek?
So, Jan,
how?
Thank you very much
for the invitation,
both of you,
and the whole team.
It was 25 years ago.
We have already
made a few other things
at MES,
but yes,
as we were talking,
I remembered that I still have
this laptop at home.
So, I pulled it out
of the closet
and brought it with me.
How did this story
start?
It started
about a year ago,
when
this
Andrej Kmet
came to me and said,
Jan, Tomáš Humar
is going to dance
in America,
El Capitan,
and it would be nice
if we make
a cover
of his dance,
El Capitan solo.
I think
he was the first to do it,
practically
and so on.
But at that time,
we did not succeed,
because we were
so amateurish,
as you will see later,
as a PGC society.
Tomáš, Andrej and I,
when we tried to
put together some equipment,
Xenia helped us
with various satellite phones,
and so on.
For El Capitan,
we did not succeed,
because we did not have enough time.
Later, Tomáš
heard
the call from above,
when he called him in the camp.
At that time,
Andrej and I were flying
for nine people.
This IBM was
my office laptop.
At that time,
I was at CIOLO,
one of the pioneers of CIOLO.
It was my office laptop.
We said, let's see
what we can do with it.
I was not yet in the Himalayas,
I was always on the other side.
Andrej is a climber,
and a computer scientist.
We put together
the most experienced
people from each area,
and we created a system
that would survive
in the Himalayas.
The equipment was
in the base camp,
which is 5-6 thousand meters high.
Up there,
it is from very warm
to minus, I do not know how much.
The equipment had to withstand it.
We were preparing
if we could
make a stream
through a satellite.
At that time,
a company called
Real Audio
made a server
called Real Audio.
I do not know if it was already
visible at that time,
but it was there.
Actually,
we brought it
together with Andrej.
Xenia gave us
a satellite phone,
for which we
signed a contract.
I think it could
be connected to 9600.
Serial communication.
We said,
aha, we have it.
We thought
what would be
the most effective way
for two-way
communication.
Then we did it
so that there were
Windows, I do not know,
XP, 590, I do not know what it was.
You probably have
an adapter here.
If they have it,
put it in the computer.
We'll see if it still works.
About a year ago,
I put it back together
and turned it off.
It is just
a historical example.
We somehow
connected it together.
The satellite phone
went to the laptop's com port.
Then I thought
how can I get
information from
the laptop as easily as possible.
What did I put?
BBS.
I put BBS software
on the laptop,
which was
driven by Stipe Božić.
He was making pictures
with the laptop.
Tomaž was climbing up
and the day before he was in a cold sweat.
All these pictures
were assigned to one director.
Then I
from the
SIOLA space
connected to the modem
via the satellite
on the laptop.
It turned out to be Jan.
He was waiting for me
in the director's office.
I was waiting for the pictures.
I'll explain BBS for a moment.
You can imagine it as
an FTP predecessor.
No, it's more of an Internet predecessor.
Give us a crash course
on what BBS is.
Give me a seat.
These
notes
were
about the Internet
that connects to each other.
BBS was
a bulletin board system
where you had a monitor
with two lines
to which people were called.
You didn't call your provider
and then connect to the Internet,
but you called the BBS server
with a call dial-up access.
Usually,
you had to wait
in a very textual way.
You had to wait
until the next day.
Maybe
we should
step back
so that people
have an idea
of what the Internet is.
It started in 1999.
Maybe we should step back
so that people
have an idea
of what the Internet is.
There were call-ups.
ASDN was already present.
I don't remember.
I think it was 2001
when XDSL was first
brought to us.
It was the turn of the millennium
when there was
Y2K
and Scare.
People were afraid
that old Russian launchers
would drop rockets
and systems would crash.
There was no awareness
about technology yet.
It was a completely different time.
Did people at home
already have a dial-up?
Did people at home already have a dial-up?
Yes.
It was like
a two-channel
I7N
with 128 megabits.
It was like a two-channel I7N
We were talking
about this
earlier.
We were talking about this
The problem today
is that you already
have a signal at the back
and a trigger.
It's not a challenge anymore.
At that time,
not only
in terms of technology,
but also in terms of good software
that would support
this technology.
I can bring you back
to the base camp in the Himalayas.
I can bring you back to the base camp in the Himalayas.
This means that this laptop
is not fully charged.
No, no, no.
The problem is the battery.
You don't have an electric
power source
to charge it.
We had solar panels
and batteries that were charged
during the day.
In the Himalayas,
sometimes there is sun, sometimes there is not.
Power management was very important.
Did you foresee
the use of
cables?
Did you foresee the use of cables?
Everything.
All cables were
reserved.
If a climber comes down
from a tree and steps on a cable,
you have 10 days to get
to the first station.
You don't have a complete system
of cables.
Everything was double.
There was only one laptop.
I didn't have any service.
We did it like this.
A group of citizens.
You were in Ljubljana.
I was in Ljubljana.
You were in Ljubljana, in Siolo.
On the other side.
It was like this.
We had some problems
with access to the base camp.
We could not fly with a helicopter.
Tomas said
that it was a group of
private citizens.
The mobile phone supported
us in the beginning.
They went down
for their day.
Everything was
very limited.
I think that Andrej
couldn't get to the base camp.
Stipe Božič was there.
He was a photographer.
He filmed everything.
Andrej went
to the base camp the day before.
In a few days he taught him
how to do it.
From power management
to how to install a laptop,
how to connect a satellite phone
and so on.
It was interesting.
Then I realized
that when they were going
and we were doing tests,
I realized that
calling a satellite phone
was very expensive.
Then I went
to Siolo in Pisarno.
Rudi Skobe was there.
He was the marketing director.
We were doing a project.
We were trying
to cover Tomas Humer.
I would like Siolo
to support us.
He asked me what I needed.
I told him that I needed
a phone in Pisarno
so that I could call
and download
the files.
He said that he didn't have
any problem.
That's how Siolo
became one of the sponsors
and supporters of the project.
By the way,
when I was passing by
his office.
Was the stream
recorded and
uploaded?
No.
Let's talk about the pictures.
I was from Ljubljana.
I connected with a modem
to this laptop via satellite.
It was sent from BBS.
Then I learned a few things
because this line was very unremarkable.
When it fell down,
the zip file fell down
and I used Xmodem
or Zmodem, one of the protocols
that enables continuity.
I learned this very quickly.
I used this
for the transfer
because Stipe
connected all the pictures.
On the other hand,
there was
an inbox file,
where all the
emails from that day
to that moment
were sent to
Tomasathumor.com.
We learned this from Stipe
how he put the inbox file
in the client's email
and
how he practically
when Tomas was
up in the wall
with the whole Calvary.
When you are up there
and you are alone
and you are down there
and your tooth hurts
and you are sad.
When he was talking
with someone
he said
when he came back
how much it meant to him
that Stipe
every time he got
the same file from him
started to pick up
all the emails
that people sent to Tomas
through radio stations
in the wall.
He said it meant a lot to him.
He said he also answered
a couple of emails
from the middle of the wall
through radio stations.
Stipe wrote them back
and then he packed
the inbox file
and then I pulled it all down
and executed
what I sent from the email server.
The pictures were sent
and the third member
of the team
was Matej Ropred
who was in charge
of the web.
He was in charge of
the old Apache servers
and so on.
He designed
all the pictures
that I got down there
and looked at them
and so on.
These pictures
were sent to the website
and in fact
primarily
why we wanted to do this.
Tomas wanted to
expose
what happened to another climber
that he came to the top
and nobody believed him
because he didn't have pictures
from the top
or anyone else.
He had all the pictures
up to the top, but not from the top.
He said let's do this
so it can be broadcast
on the internet
so people can see
day by day where I am.
It was intended for the public.
It was intended for climbers.
Maybe I interrupt you.
For that time
when you forgot
how you had
the pictures
and when it was
ordered on the web servers
do you have any idea
how many people were there?
Was it a peak?
Do you remember anything?
I think we had
1,700,000 climbers
over 1,000,000 a day.
I could put
additional servers
especially after the media
stole it.
I am interested in that.
Do you know
what this means
for Siol?
At the same time
Siol was taken from the internet.
It was a boom.
1,000,000 hits per day.
I had big dreams.
It was like an egg
It was crazy.
Can I ask you
who came
let's put it this way
when climbers go to Everest
they have base camps.
Base camps are at different heights.
You go up the steps
to one base camp
and back to another
to go up and down
to acclimatize.
When that laptop
came to the Himalayas
it was probably
with some other equipment
that prepared it.
When you opened that case
what else was there besides the laptop?
You mentioned
cables.
There were a lot of different
power supplies.
Tell us what was in the box.
Very important were
solar panels
batteries. They were heavy.
You couldn't carry
heavy batteries in a base camp.
Then there was
a satellite phone.
Everything you needed
like here
for 9 people
most of the things were 2.
Did you have a satellite phone
there or on the other side?
No.
I had a normal phone line.
Did you call an operator?
No, just a phone number.
A satellite phone.
Fortunately,
the satellite phone was also a modem.
How stable
was that line?
Terrible.
Was it on the clock?
Was there a specific moment
when you could call?
No, it was like that.
There was a voicemail.
I called Stipe.
I said, long live Jan!
Long live Jan!
What do you have today?
He told me what was going on.
Then he said
I will prepare
a computer for you.
I put everything on top.
He put everything together
because
every atom of energy
is very important there.
Then he put it together.
Then I called the modem
and the modem answered.
Then I called so many times
and continued the download
that the whole file
fell down.
Then we distributed it here.
Then,
I called back
by voice.
The telephone
that I had on the table
I converted it so
that I got the sound
from the telephone out
and connected it to my dream.
There was a real audio encoder.
When I called her
it was a specific moment.
A few hours ago we announced on the internet when there will be a live audio stream.
And then Stipe told me that he had a connection to the radio station from his satellite phone.
So I talked to Tomaž directly when he was in Hrib.
In short, this conversation was streamed live on the internet.
So people could hear live what I was talking to Tomaž about,
what problems he had in Hrib, what was happening to him in real time.
It was just wow, unprecedented.
So you were talking about the radio station and then from the radio station through the setup.
In fact, it was done in such a way that the satellite was connected to the radio station with audio.
And in fact, every time I asked something, Stipe pressed the transmit button.
And then when he released it, I could hear Tomaž answering back,
and it went through the satellite to me.
So on that side, both me and Tomaž could hear what he was saying.
And then I heard a terrible rumbling.
So I asked Tomaž what was that, and he said that a hand had hit 2 cm away from me.
And it flew down.
But ok, I'm alive.
You are working from above.
In that setup, what was going on?
Where are all the scenarios, what did you solve?
Most of the time, the problem was the humidity.
Because if you don't know how to work with equipment at such heights and at such temperature changes,
the humidity condenses very quickly.
Especially in the equipment.
And then if you bring the laptop out of the warm tent to minus so and so,
or vice versa, things will start to condense.
Because of that, they were very, very, very predictable.
As far as that is concerned, very, very predictable.
Otherwise, there were no bad entanglements.
Probably also because there were not many people in that base camp.
Only a small part of the crew went to the base camp,
and not many people were working with that equipment.
Because in the previous base camps, which were lower,
everyone wanted to switch to electricity,
and to take their e-mails to the computer.
Here, it was practically without that.
It was also interesting how the media got that over time.
They found out, oh, look, look,
there on www.humar.com there are daily pictures of Tomas when he is dancing.
It was one media base, and then everyone else.
And they started to simply download pictures from the website,
and then send them.
Because there was a blog post every day,
saying what was happening there.
Without them knowing the truth.
And we said, wait a minute.
This is not going to work.
And we warned them a few times,
and we said, children, please do not believe.
And they did not believe.
Then we said, all right,
let's wait for the pictures until 6 o'clock in the afternoon,
when the editorial office concludes with the message,
or with whatever they had.
And then they started calling us in a panic,
where are the pictures?
That they need the pictures.
And I said, yes, the pictures are not until you tell them the truth.
And then the scout team fell in love with telling the truth.
And then we gave them those pictures.
And then they started to reveal the truth from below.
That's when I could start installing new servers.
That's when everything started to work out.
How long did you have the dry training at home?
How did you test the setup at home?
How long did you prepare?
One week.
One week?
Yes.
Andrej and I were in a big team,
and we simply made those things a bit different.
We played a bit with the software.
We did things together.
He was a computer scientist,
so everything was clear to him.
That's how you work with professionals.
How long did Andrej need for dry training?
That's a different question.
I don't know.
But here it was still,
on this side is your interaction,
and on the other side is the interaction of people.
It wasn't as sad as it is today,
when a person opens a YouTube channel
and they simply split up.
You have to take into account
that there was no other streaming software
than Real Audio.
If it wasn't for Real Audio Video,
I think they released the first beta with video.
There wasn't anything else.
There was Quick Time,
and other things came later.
Real Audio was practically the main one.
Yes, there was nothing else at that time.
The idea of having video or audio on the Internet
was a revolution.
Can you tell us more about the bandwidth,
the resolution of the images,
how did people feel about the content?
Do you mean video or audio?
Both, tell us.
The images we talked about
probably weren't 5,000 pixels at a time.
No, no, no.
If they were 1,080 times,
I don't know how good it would be.
Or 1,200 times.
I told Stipe to reduce it a bit.
Because if he would upload pictures
from a camera,
I would need more than one day.
It was 9,600 communications per satellite
from another part of the Earth.
We were able to optimize everything.
The sound I streamed,
those conversations live,
I think it was the default.
I think you had a multi-rate.
You had 32K, then 16K, then 9K.
Depending on your connection speed,
you were able to change the client and server.
It was a revolution.
It was a whole thing.
Then you had another release.
Later, right?
Yes, yes.
It was the revolution of video,
if I understood correctly.
Yes, video came first.
But that was a year later.
No, that was...
That was 2,000, right?
Yes.
That was a test.
2,000 was in Lodz.
It was a release.
Fans went to Lodz,
and Andrej went with them.
We set up a system.
We were testing there
live video streaming.
If I remember correctly,
the satellite phone was Nera.
It had 64K connection.
It was a huge upgrade.
Yes, a huge upgrade.
But that release was more sponsored.
We were able to hire Nera satellites.
We were testing there.
There was a Sony Vaio laptop.
We set up a real audio video encoder on it.
At that time,
nothing was public.
Andrej and I were testing
how things work.
What came to us later,
it was 1921 or 1922,
I don't remember exactly,
when Davo Karničar
took over Hammond Everest.
That's when we used
this newly acquired knowledge.
Of course, again,
a complete setup,
batteries,
solar panels,
the whole system.
Did you upgrade it?
Yes, we upgraded it a bit.
We got a lighter battery,
so the gods of Sherpa
didn't open it up.
That's when this happened.
We had a small camera from Canon.
I think Andrej put some duct tape
on the big lens.
This huge lens.
Somehow we managed to get a picture.
On a webcam?
No, a handheld camera.
DV.
Digital video.
Yes, digital video.
It records analog,
but writes in digital.
From this camera,
the analog form of the cable
went to the card
that took the audio and video
from the laptop.
There was an audio-video encoder.
We connected the laptop
through a neural satellite,
which was capable of
connecting 64 kilos of data.
This was then streamed from there.
Andrej went to Kalapatar,
which is 6,000 meters high.
On the opposite side,
we have Everest.
He waited there.
He had a stand with him
and a base camp.
I think all this was included
in the communication through the camera.
When he started to run,
unfortunately, the sun was shining
from the back.
But this is not something
you can influence.
At that moment.
He set it all up
at 6,000 meters.
When he started to run,
here in Slovenia,
you could practically
sit down in an armchair,
turn on the computer,
connect to the Internet
and watch the sunrise
from the top of Mount Everest
as if you were watching
a sunrise in the Kranj mountains.
It was incomprehensible.
The camera was on the other side
and with the body lens
you could catch the sunrise.
Then he took it to the top,
then down through Hilare,
then down to Pren.
On that side,
I had...
I think it was
the Sun Ultra 250,
which was a real audio video server,
but it was only for split stream.
Then I had a whole horde of Suns,
which I splitted into streams.
If I could watch a stream,
I could switch to a split server,
so I could watch a stream.
All the others,
no matter how much we added them,
were full at the moment.
It was full capacity at the moment.
Because the media took it,
the thing got bigger.
The thing got worse,
because DarwinAwards.com
put a link to the first thing.
They said, look at that Norwegian
who will be a live fan.
At that time,
you could bake eggs on those servers.
I had a few colleagues from Siola.
Let's leave that for later.
Who paid for all those servers?
Was it Siola?
Yes, Siola.
But it was through Tomas Humer.com?
No, it was Davo Karnicar.
I'm sorry, Davo Karnicar.
Was the host on your site?
No, no.
Siola was a technological partner.
Simo had it,
and one agency was running
the whole project,
from the beginning.
We had full support.
But all those servers,
I practically pulled them out.
They were spare servers on Siola,
in case other servers crashed.
I had a few colleagues from Siola
installing and configuring new servers.
Just for that project?
No, it was live.
He was the one who crashed it.
We were pulling the servers out,
and I was configuring the split stream.
Then they were added to the frontend
so that people could access the servers.
How many servers?
6-7 servers.
All of them were full.
Until the end.
Did it affect the accuracy?
No, you just didn't come to the right place.
The server was full, and that was it.
If I had 10 more servers,
I would have added 10 more.
At that time, it was D-technology
that existed.
Or do you think that it existed
to make sound and images
and distribute them to users?
That was practically the only way.
Later, there were other servers
and systems,
such as Reel,
and Puzzaboo.
At that time,
we received a lot of money.
Americans and Japanese
had the same idea
to send videos from the Himalayas
live.
But as Andrej told me,
they didn't have luck with the weather.
They were calculators,
Nepal alpinists,
in the base camp.
Everything worked at home,
but when I came,
it didn't work.
You know, the magic white smoke
when it escapes you,
it's hard to send it back.
So...
Davor Korničar had a camera
on his cell phone.
But this wasn't a live stream.
It was recorded and distributed.
We tried to convince him
to have a video add-on.
But he said,
that he had to move it up
to the top of the hill.
It wouldn't work.
Actually,
it was the first live video stream
from the Himalayas in history.
Andrej and I did it.
CNN came to interview us.
We had a 5-minute interview
on CNN about how we did it.
The Americans said
they needed a few million dollars
to make the first live video stream.
They were not surprised
that two Slovenians
with the same equipment
as it was,
managed to do it.
That's how it was.
I think they were just worried
about the impact of the humidity.
But it's not enough.
It's not enough,
but we have to overcomplicate it.
The more elements you have,
the more things can go wrong.
I think they had two problems.
Power management.
They had too little
generation of energy,
and too much use.
That's why there was no humidity in the city.
I think we need to add
a very important factor.
It's very simple to be smart.
At an altitude of 5,000-5,300 meters,
if you go higher,
the air is like breathing through a straw.
You do all these things.
Frost, humidity,
you didn't even try to test it,
but it comes through experience.
On the other hand,
you have a technical partner
who understands not only technology,
but also alpinism.
At that altitude,
as far as I understand,
the capacity of thinking
would easily lead to some smart moves.
Always.
It's like a playbook.
You work on a playbook,
and now you have to figure out
what is the best and unique task.
You are a younger generation
on the war.
At that time, it was pioneering.
We were researching sports,
we were developing sports,
we were putting together sports.
There was no playbook.
Playbook was like,
Andrej, go set it up and stream it.
That was the playbook.
Everything else was improvisation.
Improvisation.
Improvisation is to that extent.
If it doesn't work for you,
try this or that.
Of course, it can change.
On Saturdays,
if something doesn't work,
you can double it.
We had double cards for laptops,
so we could double or triple it.
On the other hand,
Andrej could jump
to 6,000 meters
on his own,
with a tent and everything he needed.
He set it all up
and started streaming.
It was a superhuman effort.
When he set it up,
he was on his own.
Yes, he was on his own.
He was a free spirit.
He dressed up,
put on his backpack,
set up the tent,
had a drink,
and went to 6,000 meters.
That's how it all started.
It wasn't that simple.
Even today,
with today's technology,
I don't know how many people
would be able to do it.
That's true,
but today we have
better technology,
and we can reach a wider audience.
I'm not saying that you can fly
certain drones,
and solve the problem that way.
Where are the drones?
I don't think the army has them yet.
I would like to tell you
to take a breath,
drink a glass of water,
and stay in that space.
We can't bring in any liquids.
We also turned off the air conditioner.
We're halfway through,
and I would like to thank
the Research Museum
for their support.
They will help us expand
this space.
I would also like to thank Caldeo,
3FSL, Human Frogs,
and everyone else who supports us
through Patreon.
Thank you all.
Join us on Patreon,
and you'll see some of the people.
That's it.
We don't have a live stream yet.
What you're watching now
is recorded, uploaded,
and you can download it.
When Elon Musk
installed Starlink,
and when he installed
the Starlink modem,
which is practically everywhere in the world,
you can find it on the Internet,
there's a link to it.
You can see the evolution of how you experienced the communication with different parts of the world.
Did the lessons you got here with those two or three experiences, did they influence your career?
Did you see that people upgraded those parts? Because it seems to me that from what we have now, I don't know,
Starlink in the Amazon rainforests, some time has passed. How do you see this evolution? Maybe a little more about that.
Yes, the development of these parts is going forward, but nothing can replace optics.
The satellite can have a wide range, but you will not be able to force physics how much time your package takes to the satellite and back.
There is a lot of latency here. I greet the satellite technology for those parts where there is no optics at the moment,
where there is no network and so on. To include those billions of people in the world who are not yet included.
But I don't know if this is a permanent solution. At a meeting we had a few years ago, a lady from the European Commission came,
because there was a lot of hype about wireless, wireless, wireless, everything must be wireless and so on, mobile, mobile.
I told her, the air has its own physical laws, it is a shared media, and we can all develop wireless to some extent,
but it has its own physical laws. She asked me what is the solution. I said, take a bugger and start digging.
Now you have optics, so you can rely on them. This is the only way we will reach the right capacity for internet transport around the world.
In fact, we can solve those really difficult areas where there is no such thing yet, but my advice is, take a bugger and start digging.
It will be difficult in the Himalayas, but OK.
You go 6,000 meters and then you wait for the optical cable and then you plug it in.
No, they already have it up there. In the base camp you already have wireless providers, I don't know, you pay $10, I don't know how much you pay for a whole week.
It's up there now, as simple as that. It wasn't even 20 years ago.
Of course.
Up there, they also promoted connectivity with energy. I don't know how they solved it.
I mean, it's true that there are lower bases than on the mountains.
Yes, yes.
Solar panels are a technology. Solar panels are being promoted, used, when you need energy, for example, with some new laptops.
Today, you can do almost anything from a phone, and all of a sudden you switch to a smaller power supply.
So, from that perspective, if you said it before, the problem is that today there are more technical solutions, or more possibilities to solve the problem.
Yes.
No, it's not possible.
Definitely.
I mean, just the fact that today you can put a lot of things in your pocket, and no longer in a backpack, so you're not up there.
Yes.
Can you tell us more about that wedge you brought up there?
Yes, that's a wedge that Tomas had. Tomas went up there, he didn't go solo.
He didn't have any crazy conversations, maybe he sang somewhere while he was resting.
Or maybe he was in a bit of a difficult situation, but he didn't go up there.
And he had, as far as I understood him, one of those wedges, for example, that he would have to abseil back down.
That is, if he had to stop the mission and go back down, he had one of those wedges and a rope.
But we calculated that it was about 400 meters, or 300 meters, how much he could go back down with those wedges.
That means that when he came across that wall, it was pointless to abseil down, because he simply didn't come to where he could go forward without warning.
And when he came back home, he gave me one of those wedges, I don't know if it was gold or what, it looked like gold up there.
It wasn't like that originally.
And he wrote up there, what did he write?
Here he gave me a engraving, Tomas Humar, Southwall of the Laguerre, 1999, and his signature.
And he gave it to me, he brought it to me, we were friends through all those projects, he said, Jan, here you will be able to remember this wedge that went over the Southwall of the Laguerre.
He said, fortunately, I needed it, I don't know if I needed it in the wall, because it looks like something new, and then he rubbed it.
I think it's polished, yes.
But it was one of the wedges that was in the wall up there.
I think it's nice.
He also brought me a book at the time, and he signed his book inside, and he wrote, dedicated, and I said, what do you have to wait for a book, he destroyed the book.
Now I'm happy, now I'm happy that he wrote to me.
And he wrote exactly what was the essence of this project in the Laguerre, as he wrote, even if we are short of wedges, the PGC society is made up of people, it remains as it is.
And that's exactly what we did at the time, from the fallen hardware and practically into the trash.
I mean, we had better hardware in Karničar, but that was practically when the three of us would look at what we had at home, on the walls, and put something together.
But I didn't look at it at home, probably not even at the hardware market.
And you had, at the time, on Siolu, for that time, Latest Greatest.
Yes.
Maybe there was an encyclopedic category, maybe even better hardware, but it was about the same, bigger and heavier.
Yes, that was for the server part.
I mean, that was my official laptop, which I said I had already lived without for a month, when we got it there at Siolu at the time.
But that was how it was.
Until then, the shipment didn't go there.
Until then, we didn't do the first tests, which Andrej set up, we all went to Kathmandu.
Then I realized that we had a problem with the price per minute.
I said, I'll call you at home.
Don't make fun of him, he has to explain this to his wife.
When the phone bill came, I think it was the military bill of a smaller African country.
At that time, at Siolu, I made sure that Siolu supported it.
And then it turned out that those minutes were covered, plus the complete use of servers and my time.
Because then Siolu saw that when the Siolu badge appeared on humor.com, and when the media grabbed it, it was a whole thing.
Then the whole PR department joined the action and did a whole thing out of it.
That's how stories are written.
Yes, but it all started with a group of citizens, as the locals say.
Now we are in the cellar of the Computer Museum.
You decided to sell this laptop to the Computer Museum.
I think, looking at the exhibits that we saw today,
everything that fits into this atmosphere,
I think they will take good care of it.
I mean, I know they will take good care of it.
I'm really curious, what message do you want to convey with this laptop?
I think it's part of the Slovenian Internet history.
I haven't heard about it for a long time.
In fact, my wife Tatjana told me about it some time ago.
She said, what are you going to do with this laptop?
I said, I have no idea.
She said, it's not for the Computer Museum.
I said, maybe it's not a bad idea.
Then I called Tomaž Humare Mlajšević, Tomaž's son.
I said, listen, let's see if they are interested in the museum.
He said, let's go one day,
I'll take it to them,
we'll take some selfies,
and then we'll go.
A message for me, of course.
I think I will take it to Tomaž.
I brought it a bit.
Are you going to add anything to that?
I'm a bit in a hurry.
In the sphere of the creation of the Slovenian Internet,
you deserve a lot of praise for your work.
If not, you deserve to be supported,
to be provided with a link,
or a server,
to be able to share your work.
Thank you very much.
Maybe some people don't even know
about your pioneering work,
how things worked in the past,
and that they worked not only artificially.
Yes, in fact,
it was very pioneering,
and without any political connotations,
it was done in a very partisan way.
We simply said,
let's try to do it.
We were young,
we had a lot of energy,
and we wanted to do it.
We went into action.
With this project,
the live streaming project,
when did you realize
who is the international leader
in some of the tasks
you are doing?
I think it's a very important question.
Did you prepare for some other project
that brought such a revolution
on the Internet,
or a continuation of it?
In fact, no.
This humorous project
led to the decision
to go to Lodz
in order to cover myself
with pictures
so that I could test
live video streaming
which then led
to Davo Karničarja,
who was really
the first person
in the world.
Then,
after a while,
it happened
that we decided
to cancel
this
Trans-Australia Foot Race.
Dušan Mravlje
was running
in this race
across Australia.
Andrej was no longer healthy,
but he went to PeeBee.
PeeBee,
the legend of Siola.
PeeBee and I went down
to Australia.
I set up
a complete system down there,
we went there,
we tested everything.
I was PeeBee's translator.
After a while,
I was down there with them
when the race started
and everything was being prepared
across Australia,
via satellite and everything.
Then I flew back
and set up the server
and everything else
that was needed
to make it work.
Then we wanted
to do streaming
from an underwater cave.
It didn't work out
because
the gear on Siola changed a bit.
They were prepared
that it would be too dangerous
because underwater
cave diving
is not among
the most dangerous sports
on this planet.
It's a coincidence
that I came here.
Yes, but the problem was different.
Tomas jumped in the cave.
Davo jumped in the Everest.
Jan would go in the cave
to dive.
Jan would go in the cave.
So Jan took care
of his life.
No, Siola took care of my life.
Jan was crazy enough to say that.
I'm a technical diver,
certified.
I was not crazy enough,
but self-assured
that I would put
all the technical equipment
on a double bottle
and additional aluminum
for decompression
and camera in my hand
and go to the cave
but then
Siola decided
that it's not necessary.
I wanted to say
that I didn't recognize it
and I wanted to say
that the equipment was cheap
and available.
Then our paths
with Siola changed.
At the same time
I went to
Select Technology
to transfer my knowledge
from Reel Audio Video
to making the first
video portal for RTV.
It was a complete system
that digitized
Reel Audio Video files
in real time
and then streamed
from the server outside
and then there was a base
where you could search
for recordings and so on.
We did it for RTV
and then RTV used it
for a while
and then
flash media came out
and so on.
Then it was split in two.
You pulled out
some archaic technology.
I don't know
but what we were talking about
and what you mentioned
was before YouTube.
Before YouTube started
Where was YouTube?
Maybe that too.
Flash.
When we were talking
about Humor
2000 and so on.
When you went to Page
there was no
Flash player.
There was
a media player
with a computer
and a program
not in a browser
I don't know if it was possible
to embed it
in Humor.
There was a plugin
for a browser
and I was not for all browsers.
Internet Explorer 4
had some value.
Netscape communicator.
The most important thing
was to click on the link
and then the real player opened
and then the player was inside
and it broadcasted everything
If you were to fly
in a submarine
from Prague
how different
would the setup be?
You don't need satellites
but what would you stream?
How would you fly?
I would fly
in a cable
that I would pull.
You could pull a cable for yourself.
Because you are connected
when you swim in a hole.
You are not connected.
You are pulling a cable.
In this case, I could have a setup
in front of me where I would
set up a hole
with a rope
that is a security rope.
I mean a safety rope
in a hole
with additional flashes
on the ground
so that I don't touch the ground
with my foot.
And yes,
I could somehow
pull this camera
underwater
and I could probably have
a whole team of people
behind me
to pull the cable
underwater
but wirelessly
because it doesn't work.
No.
Now,
if someone would pull the cable
forward
and then
it wouldn't work anymore
because you have a cable in the hole.
I see that you have already
thought a lot about it.
You probably thought about a hole,
an underwater hole.
Yes, yes.
You know I don't remember anything.
I don't remember anything.
But I think there was one
Slovenian interesting hole.
I don't know if it was Suhadolc
or I don't know where.
Underwater or live video stream.
You would like to watch that.
Yes, I don't know.
Yes, I mean...
That time?
That time definitely.
I mean, you didn't have YouTube
that time.
You didn't have Instagram,
you didn't have TikTok, Facebook.
Nothing.
Yes, you had
TV.
With teletext.
Yes, somehow.
I mean,
it's interesting because we talk about it
all the time,
in front of GoPro cameras,
in front of mobile phones,
in front of many networks.
No, there were mobile phones.
Nokia 61.
Yes, yes.
But phones were
bigger bricks.
They had the ability
to last for a year.
One week.
You will see
how in the first album.
And in mobile phones.
In the history
of Slovenian streaming.
No, I wanted
more that.
Because you
from
Internet Society and so on.
If you prepared
like that,
if the
streaming service
or streaming
at the level of the protocol,
how much
did it develop?
Or did you accidentally join
some working group
that drew something
from the protocol?
I don't know.
Multicasting and so on.
I was in some small group
on IETF.
We talked about it.
But then,
when I left IOL,
when I was on Select,
I went more
in the direction of my friend,
I would say,
IPv6.
So,
when you were streaming IPv6,
it didn't go through IPv6?
No, it didn't.
I counted.
That's provocative.
Actually,
my first
IPv6 stick
was there in 1997.
I downloaded
a patch
from Sun Playground
on IOL.
It was a tunnel to Sixbone,
which was an experimental network.
I could ping over sixes
and stuff in Sixbone.
Of course,
no DNS, no servers,
no Apache.
But I could ping
and some names answered.
My first stick was there
in 2000.
It was nice
to have ErzBouncer,
who introduced himself as IPv6.
IPv6!
He was that jack,
who had a slightly different IP
when he was on the channel.
Or if you had
reverse DNS installed.
Yes, I had my own reverse DNS.
If we're talking about IPv6,
it was something different.
So,
after I left
Select,
I started working with Dumenco.
I went
back a little
in that direction.
Then we did Go6,
a competition for IPv6 promotion
and implementation.
We pushed forward
all together.
Then we
somehow transformed
the community
we built
from 2.8 onwards
into Synog,
which is today
also a
morph.
At one point,
I realized that
anyone who has a phone
can stream
from anywhere.
It didn't
take long
for me
to realize
that this
was a
Let's talk about things that are interesting, that need some kind of help,
some kind of drive, some kind of awareness.
Here you have the example of technology, the technological challenge.
The main thing in this challenge is the content.
Did you have a content that was interesting for you?
Today, there is a network, everyone is talking to each other,
or a ping is sent. Boring.
If you have content that needs to be sent out,
and it needs to be served to a mass,
all these challenges are also technologically interesting.
Yes, but it can be special.
If we were to bring some plants from the base camp,
maybe everyone would look at it, because there was so little of it.
But I don't think it would be as interesting as Davo Karničar,
who flies from the top of Mount Everest.
What are your interesting challenges that you see now?
What are you excited about now?
I'm still working on IPv6 in the world.
It's always more operational.
Everything is happening day-to-day.
And now, for example, Google is making measurements
of all traffic to all its services.
I think that around 50% of the world's traffic
comes through IPv6.
So it's not some obscure experiment
with some scientists.
It's an operational protocol that lives in the real Internet.
Now we have more and more of this curve.
So it's a big problem for me as an operator
who hasn't implemented it yet.
What else is a challenge?
Are we talking about the implementation itself,
integrating it?
Or is it a challenge from the point of view of the protocol
and the application?
You can understand that IPv6 is a protocol
that was founded in 1996 or 1995.
It's not ideal.
It's still being improved a bit.
But it's good enough that it can follow
any moment of IPv4.
And it's already following it.
I don't know how to say it.
Until now, it was a challenge in CPE equipment.
People call it a modem.
But it's getting better.
But there's still an elephant in the room.
And it's people's disappointment
or the thought that if something is not broken,
don't touch it.
And we still need it.
We have enough of it.
It means blind spots.
I may have said too much.
But I think that some generation of networkers
will have to retire.
And the younger generation will have to come
to show some difference.
That's what I've been trying to do from the beginning.
But do you really think that today's young people
will need this strip?
Because I see it from the other end.
When we have a deal with some young systems
that mostly screw cloud services
or develop some software or SaaS products.
Very rarely I hear that I've turned on IPv6.
Or that I've touched IPv6.
I don't see it that often.
It depends on the teacher and the mentor.
For example, for the last 20 years,
I've been designing all the networks
and the architecture.
They were made for IPv6 architecture.
And then you add IPv4 at the end.
And I'm still learning.
I want to say that today all the big cloud providers
allow dual-stack or the possibility
to have IPv6 as a healthy network.
But it's up to the user to click on it.
Now certain providers will go in that direction
that IPv6 will be paid by default and IPv4 will be paid.
But it seems to me that even among young people
I haven't noticed that it's now.
Let's go to the last one.
We've talked about it.
In the final phase,
I don't mean the engineers,
but the end users,
everything is working.
The technology is hidden.
The Internet has become like electricity or water.
When you buy a fan in a store,
you come home, turn it on and it works.
When you turn on the water, it has to flow out of the pipe.
The Internet is similar.
IPv6 is not a thing of the end user.
The end user needs to be able to open Facebook, Google,
whatever he clicks on.
It's a thing of the operators.
I want to say that.
We've talked about services,
and if I'm not mistaken,
it's a live show,
because the end user will be interested in the content.
If there's a dual laptop with cables,
the end user doesn't care about that.
That's the difference between
developers, engineers,
and the general public,
who are interested in the personality.
You also have to know
if you're fully excited to watch a TV show.
If you watch a TV show...
There was a time
when you could watch a TV show
if you knew exactly what was going on.
You could quickly go to the data.
You could watch a TV show on your phone
and not have to open it in 15 days,
because maybe you didn't have that much time.
I agree with that.
But for Loki,
who graduated from high school in 2000,
or was on his way to college,
internet technology was probably new at the time.
You were more excited,
it was more interesting.
You probably didn't care about teletext,
you cared about the internet.
Our generation probably has a lot of protocols,
and they are given.
Water flows, electricity comes.
Even when they took out the phone,
everyone was excited to be able to connect it.
That's the thing.
Everyone who was stimulated
when we started to talk about technology,
was like,
I need to go back to the side.
We wanted to release some content.
Let's say it was a technological challenge.
To frame them inside.
The idea was to release some content.
You can show that to your elders,
to your friends.
You can't just configure a Linux server
and send it up.
I used to do that.
It's a rabbit hole.
Shoutout to our audience.
People are listening to us
and watching us.
We have a bigger community on our Discord.
It's very active,
it's very fun.
I think there are people
who are genuinely interested in technology.
There are people
who see it as an interesting universe
of some things,
and are looking for networking,
mobile, Linux.
I see young people are still
using it all over the place.
I think there are more offers
and choices.
We talked about Windows XP,
or maybe Linux.
Today, if I had a laptop,
I could do anything.
There are more offers and choices.
On the other hand,
we have a bigger audience.
We used to have millions of people
watching our streams.
Today, if we had good content,
there would be millions of people.
The world has become more connected
and more decisive.
Today, if you do a live stream
from a concert,
you get a special reward.
This always fascinates me.
It doesn't matter
how high-quality phones are.
Why do people record concerts?
It's their best piece,
and they record it.
Do you send it to them?
Yes, I do.
Do you post it on Instagram?
Or is it a personal choice?
I do it from time to time.
I do it to support a friend
who wants to go to a concert,
but doesn't want to.
Another reason why I do it
is if it's a band
and I'm trying to play the guitar,
and I don't know how it goes,
so I record it to see how he plays it.
Then I enlarge it at home.
That's what he likes.
I dream that in the hall
of 10,000 people,
all those 7,000 people
who record it,
I dream about it.
Can I ask you one last question?
We're talking about young people
and their successors.
I wanted to ask you
how you deal with young people.
I think you have a son
who is very popular in this world.
Yes, the youngest son, Max Jakob.
Last time you gave me his github,
I looked at it.
When he was 13,
he wrote his own programming language.
The others didn't like it.
They weren't fast enough.
It's all very Slovenian.
Yes.
He decided that he didn't like
that Python is too slow.
He didn't like that C++
is a bit clumsy with coding.
He was ready to write
his own programming language.
I told him to look at the source code
of C++, how it's done.
He said he would like to start from scratch.
He got into it.
First he wrote the syntax.
Then he prepared it.
Of course, he learned how to assemble.
Before that, he wrote a bootloader
for his operating system,
which he's writing now,
because the others aren't good enough.
I told him that he has too much hardware
in the world to support it.
I told him that I would transform
my code and syntax into assemblies.
He started to reverse-engineer
from his own needs.
Then he wrote Lexar and Parsar.
You wouldn't know what Lexar and Parsar are.
Then he implemented
different if-inputs.
He gave me a package
so that I could install everything together.
Install package, documentation, everything.
I think he was about 15 years old
when he started to work with it.
Then he started to write other things.
Then he worked with graphics cards
and some drivers.
Then he graduated.
He worked in a high school in Škofa Loka.
When he decided where to go next,
he decided to go into mathematics.
Pure mathematics.
I asked him why,
because he was a programmer.
He told me that he was already used to it
and that he lacked mathematics.
He told me that if I wanted to be a programmer,
a coder,
an encryption engineer,
you need mathematics.
He told me that I don't have any relatives here.
Now he is happily working
as a first-year mathematician
and he enjoys it to the fullest.
He enjoys it to the fullest.
He was very proud.
Yes, he was at some world olympiads.
He brought medals home.
He was a leader of a Slovenian team
that represented Slovenia
at the international...
I don't know what it's called.
The international world olympics.
He got a silver medal
which was his goal.
I think that's enough.
He left high school
and now he will surely find another competition.
I think that if we see him today,
luck will be on our side.
Fortes fortuna jovat!
At this moment,
I would like to thank the EPP
for supporting us before our mission.
I would like to thank Caldi,
3FS and Human Frog
for supporting us on Patreon.
In conclusion,
I wish that people will find
a positive thought
in this story.
That this work will be an inspiration
for all of us.
I would like to thank you
for this difficult path
that you went through.
That's my story.
I would like to add
that for this story
and all the other stories
you need content
and technique.
But in the end,
it's the people who create the content
and give the technical knowledge
and make a good story.
I mostly see the people
who produce the content.
That's why it was so interesting
for the organization
to present this story
from a different perspective.
The technical aspect
and the people.
It's not so trivial
that someone connected
to a satellite in a base camp
and a miracle happened.
You can make a series
out of this story.
When this story will be released,
we have already released
three other episodes.
They are called
Extreme Security Monsters.
You can check them out.
They are also great.
Thank you, Jan.
Thank you, Andrash.
Thank you, Nami.
Thank you.