Hello Belgrade, it's a little different, we don't know each other yet because I'm on the other side of the lens.
I'm one dollar, so here I'm filming and watching OTA sitting in my place.
Today with me are two other members of the team who are more in the back.
If I'm not mistaken, Tomas is a little more visible, our bringer of light.
Hello Tomas.
Hello.
On my right is a player who is a little more visible because of our branding, stickers, logos.
I'm not my image, is that it?
That's true.
An idea for a successor?
Yes.
Too little of your image.
Okay, so for 2025...
Special edition.
More image.
Trend for 2025.
Cool.
Today we talked a little.
He gave me the car for his replacement.
I don't know exactly why, but I see that they are preparing in the back if the cameras are recording.
So I hope they have something to mount.
Yes, I thought that maybe we should first introduce ourselves as a team from the back,
so that we are a little more noticed, if that was the idea.
So maybe Tomas would start.
I would introduce you...
I think I would thank you a lot.
Seeing that you are everything from a YouTuber to a product developer,
now you are competing with me in photography and video and everything.
How would you...
Do you have a word for what you are?
Are you a creator?
You know what?
With women, sometimes in this topic, it is said that they don't know...
For example, my wife, when she goes to a friend's party,
or to a prayer meeting, she asks me,
how does your husband actually start?
And there is always this dilemma.
It is very difficult to put into a box my beginnings or all those interests.
Why am I like this?
I have no idea.
The man decides at some point that he wants to know something,
and then I go back to it for a month, a year, or just three minutes,
and I make sure it doesn't take and I go on with my life.
So where do I start?
I mean, in the context of Ogrodje...
We will come back to Ogrodje.
For the listeners, I would say that they know me the best,
I will say publicly, probably on my YouTube channel.
Although it is not a big one, and also not that old,
but somehow in September, October I decided to share my knowledge,
because I always wanted...
For example, a fun fact about me,
in high school I wanted to be a professor of English.
That is an interesting fun fact.
I don't know, for me it is.
For me too.
Then I wanted to be a professor of physics and technology,
but somehow I didn't keep up with the homework,
and all those experiments, so I failed,
so yes, I always liked the aspect of sharing knowledge.
I will also say that when I was with my partner Per,
when we established the company,
we went to Open Source,
because the community aspect was always very close to me.
Although, yes, YouTube, on the one hand,
you talk a lot, there is no back debate,
although I try to respond to as many comments as possible,
but if a video is good,
thousands of comments are made very quickly.
Do you still follow those comments?
Yes, yes, yes.
Still?
Yes, yes, yes, I still try.
I mean, one is like that,
but when you start, I will say,
look, when you start, you create a filter
with which you pay to engage completely,
because not every comment is worth engagement.
Do you filter trolls?
Or you don't have them yet?
Trolls, I will say,
sometimes it's okay,
they find everything,
you know, I talked to a colleague recently,
it's interesting that you always get angry
at those comments,
the most toxic, for some reason.
If he pokes you in the right place.
Yes, yes, yes.
You get, I don't know, 100 comments,
out of which 99 are so madly positive,
and then he pokes you somewhere,
and then he pulls you out,
and then you go to sleep,
and you think about the same thing,
which is absolutely not worth your attention.
You can't do without it,
because you invest so much time,
and energy, and your creativity,
and you want it to be well received,
and it could be really clean,
to know how to deal with it,
but in my opinion it's hard.
Yes, it's hard, I mean,
I can understand, because you're in public,
and everyone sees you,
and I'm a very open person,
it's hard for me to talk about
good and bad things,
about my own, I would say,
good and bad qualities,
but yes, I have some feelings,
and I have them,
and they quickly accept them.
Now, when you said,
something else about yourself,
yes, what did you say,
for example, photographer,
audio, well, not audio,
I mean, I enjoy those things,
those are topics I'm really interested in,
and I could go on.
I would have two hitters
who would debate about that,
about equipment, audio, video, production.
I would go to a coffee shop,
and you would come with me to the end,
and I would come back.
I would like to do something like that,
because we will still,
I mean, I hope we will come
to this field a bit more,
if we can get a bit closer to Tomas,
if he stands by that.
Tell us a bit more about you,
what do you do?
I won't say that you are a graphic designer,
a disc golfer,
but we know that you are.
Yes, we can say that,
we don't know that.
Everything is almost professional.
I mean, it says on the card
Professional Amateur, so.
Yes, that's it, you have the card.
I have the card, yes.
But yes, when it comes to work,
I am a designer-illustrator,
or a mix of
bigger things.
We already mentioned that,
a pastor of some brands.
It means that you work
from logos
to marketing material,
to video editing,
I'm exaggerating a bit, sorry.
I know, I know.
Everything that comes,
which I really like
in this freelance field,
and what's nice is that
I have a lot of fixed pages,
that I don't have everything
new, and that there's not
a lot of debating
what to do, but the page
comes if I need it,
I know what to do,
and it's produced.
You do everything.
Yes, everything.
I have a question on that point.
How creatively
do you work
or do you challenge yourself?
And maybe this question is
correct in this way.
Why do I ask you this?
Sometimes you have an idea,
or sometimes you have a problem.
If I look at it from a more
engineering point of view,
it's easy to assess problems
and solutions.
By the book, as I said.
But when it seems to me that creative work
can be like that,
and you know,
it's easy to say
that you're making a logo
for someone,
and they say,
it's too simple,
I don't know,
and you'll say,
you're not going to
rush me for that.
I mean,
I know it doesn't work like that,
but a lot of people don't know
how much you value
your work.
I mean, from a financial point of view.
Ah, from a financial point of view.
We're almost there.
No, no, no.
How do you approach such things?
For example, if I told you,
look, I need a logo for my brand,
how would you value it?
And above all,
what price would you change
so that it wouldn't be known?
Because now that it's known,
I know you'd be like,
wing it.
Yeah, I think
a lot of people
over the years,
when you hire them,
you almost know how much
they value you,
so that you can value
internally,
how much time it takes,
how many resources you need,
and then on the basis of that,
I have some packages,
where the prices start.
I don't know if anyone noticed,
but in the beginning,
there was a lot of...
Let's be honest,
I worked a lot with start-ups,
and there was always a problem with them.
Not financially,
and then you try to compensate.
Maybe you start lower,
but if you can,
you change for longer.
But, as you said,
a standard of quality,
you probably keep it,
regardless of the budget.
All in?
Anyway,
if you want to do the best you can.
So, it doesn't look like
if you get less money,
maybe
in the end it turns out
that if you have less time,
you change the topic,
or maybe you give them less iterations,
it can lead to something unclean
in the final phase.
But if you try to do
the best you can
and then
I personally think
that brands live through it,
and when you do something,
you can't say that it's fixed,
but it still grows
through the years,
or months, or whatever,
and other things develop,
because you don't just have a logo,
you also have other assets,
or materials.
If we're talking about that,
I was thinking a bit later
about the topic of the garden
and our collaboration with the garden,
but let's go a bit
to our
new brand,
our new logo type, the garden.
How did you
get to that?
So, let's say
it's a no-budget option,
like most
other productions, and so on.
That's crazy,
yeah.
It all started when I saw
what Otto chose as the original logo
for the garden, and
I think I was the number one
hater of
that logo
from the very beginning, especially
when he told me he had 300 of them,
and that he chose
exactly that, and I bet
there were 10
better ones, one of all those 300.
Is that the same original one?
Yeah, that one,
the orange one.
But that one really touched my heart,
that new logo type.
That's the problem
with those brands,
you look at the brand and you think,
beep,
if I screw up something,
how am I going to fix it,
because people are used to it.
We found that through our jingle.
I mean, we all wanted
to change the jingle, so we both
worked on it, we gave it to the whole team,
you were absolutely
in favor of changing the jingle,
but somehow we didn't find
a better one.
It's always the same with the jingle,
with the music, I think we're all on the same page,
when you have to choose a music for a video,
it's not just a rabbit hole.
It's a special project.
Yeah, it's a special project.
Because everyone wants to have
their own character in the music,
and if you don't, then...
I mean, there are so many sites
that already have it, and you've heard it a dozen times.
Someone can comment,
do we have a good jingle or not?
I don't know.
Maybe we'll change it someday.
This one says no.
The one in the back.
We're open to suggestions,
listeners.
Yeah, maybe I'll try the logo.
Yeah, the logo.
The guy in the back asked a question,
if you didn't hear it,
because he has to say more about the logo.
Basically, yeah, I had quite simple hands
when it comes to
doing something
that was better.
Then, when you have simple hands,
on the one hand,
it can be a big problem
when you don't have any skills,
what and how to do it.
And then I experimented a bit
with different typographies,
and I wanted to
take the nature of the geeks
into the logo,
and then, through some iterations,
various elements
appeared.
And then, as I imagined,
specific
product information
were determined,
which were in place,
and we tried to
work through some cycles
My idea was that
even though it's a podcast,
and you need some merch,
some stickers,
that the logo
is placed so well,
or the whole brand,
that you can develop some graphics,
some banners,
and that when you look at something,
you know, aha, this is it.
Because it has some element
from the outside.
I think you did quite well.
I don't know what to say.
I really liked it.
And also our merch,
and everything that you can see
behind all those cables.
I think it's nice to wear
such merch.
It's not just
a logo
from some company.
It's more like a home.
That's the thing about
these logos.
You have an open illustrator,
and you have a bunch of vectors,
and you play around with them,
and you create a gradient,
and it spreads out nicely,
and you're like, wait,
this will be a bit lonely,
and when you have it,
it looks cool,
you put it on a mock-up,
and you're like, ok,
it's something.
And when you print it,
you see that it looks so good.
I wanted to ask you
if you work with an illustrator.
With Adobe.
Yes.
I know it is,
but is it enough?
I started boycotting
Adobe
in particular.
I started...
I don't think...
I think it's a bit of a dream
to have thousands of subscribers.
I don't know.
At some point,
in my previous company,
we did...
I'm not saying this just for Adobe,
but in general,
you make a subscription,
I don't know,
once in January,
I did all the subscription calculations
for the whole company.
I mean,
we agreed with a partner
that at the end of the year
we would save
30,000 euros.
So I started
being more careful
with all the subscriptions.
I haven't cancelled one yet,
because I was...
I have to say this,
it's a bit off topic,
but Manscaped.
I got it as a gift,
but the woman who gave it to me
could register
my e-mail there.
And now they sell me
12, 15 or whatever euros
for sending me
a deodorant for
the Nether region.
I thought you were going to say
it was sponsored for your YouTube channel.
But that's why
I haven't cancelled it yet.
If there's more software,
how do you get the license
for the same version
to arrive and be finished?
I'm just joining in here,
because I've been
on the Adobe suite
for about 10 years.
I don't know if
it was a one-week transition
to alternatives.
I don't mean that the functionality
is exactly the same.
When it comes to video equipment,
I'd say they're a bit better,
but maybe it's just a matter
of graphics.
I think Adobe is still adding
AI tools.
There's a lot of support
for Photoshop, 3D,
for example.
If you're not working
in a fixed software,
it connects to
Illustrator and Vector.
If you want to do it in Photoshop,
Raster or After Effects
to animate,
I think it's much more connected
to Hit Trigger and its workflow.
As far as that's concerned.
I don't know.
You'll tell me later.
For me,
it's OK.
Everyone is trying to learn
not just Adobe or Figma,
but all the smaller apps
for video editing
or anything else.
And when you do it,
you draw a line.
I hope our listeners
know what we're talking about.
I feel like an outsider
when it comes to
the tech sector.
But I'm short-sighted
when it comes to
all these projects.
I don't know.
For example,
you come to
these programs,
more graphically oriented
to your various projects
with hardware.
You go to Illustrator
or to use
Illustrator or Photoshop
or something like that.
I started my career
with web design.
I'm not a designer.
I don't have...
But in my 20 years,
it was like that.
If you wanted a website,
you had to be a web designer.
I learned Photoshop pretty well.
I still know it pretty well today.
But I'm talking about Photoshop
not as a form of photography,
but as a form of interface design.
So you cut it out.
Yes.
And then I wrote CSS.
Those were my beginnings.
HTML and CSS.
But it first appeared
in Dreamweaver.
Do you still remember,
comrades?
I remember.
But now,
I went back to
the back-end scene
and I was a programmer
and a system architect,
if I may say so.
Now,
when I took photography more seriously,
it's still my hobby,
so I won't bother you,
but I'm really working on it.
I looked for
the most effective way
to get a picture
from a camera
to a place
where someone will see it.
Social media,
Sprint, whatever.
What's the fastest path?
For me,
personally,
I really like the iPad.
I have a mini studio
and I'm ready for
a direct shooting.
The iPad is directly
embedded in the camera
and I can take a picture
through the iPad,
and it goes directly
into a software called Capture One.
I'm ready for a full...
Again, I'm not a professional photographer,
so I don't know.
A professional would say
that I'm just playing.
In the beginning,
you can hear the standard workflow.
I don't know how professionals
deal with this,
but I like to record
in Capture One,
then I do initial culling,
and you get 500 pictures
in 30 minutes.
So, it's a basic filter.
Yes, but I do all of this
on the iPad until the evening,
on the couch,
and I like it because
it's soft,
and you're on the computer all day.
If possible, I also try
to put a chair in the desk.
And I'm ready
to come back
to this.
I put filters,
basic colors,
light corrections,
everything on the iPad.
If I really need to edit the picture,
I put it on the iPad,
and I like this Affinity Photo
which I also have on the computer,
and I also have Capture One,
the Mac version,
if I need to.
But for me,
I've already edited a picture
and I put it to print the next day.
I also put it on Dropbox
and I sent it to a retoucher
online.
You get the same pictures for 5 euros.
It's really tasty,
it's not overdone,
and the pictures are
very satisfactory.
If we're talking about mobile
tasks,
I know that
illustrating on the iPad
is probably the right thing
to do,
but
I mean,
the workflow,
the iPad?
Yes, I think
buying an iPad was one of the better
things I could do.
Even before,
when I was a designer
on the Windows system,
now when I switched
to the full
Mac OS,
the connectivity is even better,
but the iPad is great
for making some ideas
on paper,
for daily work, illustrations,
when you're writing, for example,
before the iPad I had a tablet,
especially when you have to write down,
and you look up,
and you need some time
to get used to it,
to write,
just a little bit.
So, yes,
I think the iPad is great.
Procreate is an app
that you can use,
for example,
this app is great,
because once you buy it,
and you have a license,
for example,
with others,
it's great,
and it works great.
Now that I have it, I connect it
to Photoshop.
I can make an iPad as a tablet and I can solve it without any problems.
So I think it's a very good investment.
I also see a lot of such solutions for video,
with the iPad,
our cameras would also be able to do it,
but somehow I got into this workflow where the files,
this raw video,
is a bit heavy for the iPad to be able to do it,
if not because of the price,
because we have,
we've already talked about it,
about 600 to 800 GB per episode,
from two cameras.
I don't know what storage the iPad has.
You need a disk for all these tasks,
you need an additional disk.
As far as that is concerned,
my new iPad would also know.
I think it could,
but for me it's spatial,
I don't have a tablet.
A little less real estate,
a little editing, I think.
I mean, you still have DaVinci Resolve for the iPad,
but the timeline you see on,
I don't know,
on such a small format,
the question is how productive you can be on it.
I really don't think so.
You don't?
No.
If anything, you have,
I mean,
in addition to DaVinci,
as you mentioned,
it's just great for smaller screens.
The difference between an iPad 12-inch
and a 25-plus-inch monitor.
I would just say,
while only standard editing is being done,
while only cuts are being made,
nothing special.
Now you would have a similar workflow
when you have to edit it,
but if it's your first edit,
you can just click on the timeline
and that's it.
I think,
I don't know,
it would be possible to edit on an iPad in December as well.
I can't imagine YouTube,
because you have to focus a little more.
No,
I can't,
but the retention,
editing,
no.
But you probably work with more layers,
so you can do more interesting things.
Yes.
It's not a lot of cross-cutting.
That's right.
And when you edit,
for example,
lines are inserted,
you know,
things like that,
because on YouTube,
people have a lot of attention,
a lot of gold bars,
and,
look,
if you don't do something,
and now,
if you make a talking head video,
then the camera that shoots you
is finished.
And now,
you have to do that,
in addition to performing in front of the camera,
to be a little more lively,
you can also edit.
And I,
for example,
I don't know,
I have 32 ultrawide monitors,
and I have another special 4K monitor above it,
for tools and assets,
and I have a timeline on that big monitor,
and a preview,
and those two,
you know,
what you're doing,
video,
and that preview of those assets,
and above I have those assets,
power bins,
and all that.
OK, yes.
I think for all those who don't know,
he was talking about power,
about DaVinci Resolve,
for video editing software.
Yes,
very powerful software.
For Stone,
for some reason.
or then,
yes,
the license,
or the hardware,
if we compare it to the time,
it's one time.
I can only cry when I start, right?
Yes,
actually.
I think I came to terms with,
I don't know,
I think DaVinci was 16,
now it will be 19,
during beta.
At that time,
all the updates are for Stone.
Yes.
Fully professional,
it accepts,
absolutely,
I think,
the flow,
as you said,
the integration from one program to another.
It's all in one program.
You don't have,
I mean,
you don't have a vector,
I'm not talking about DaVinci,
it's a combination of Adobe Premiere
and After Effects, right?
After Effects and Audition.
And Audition,
of course.
And maybe a little more.
I was talking about graphic programs.
Yes,
I know,
graphics,
if I'm not mistaken.
But,
for me,
DaVinci convinced me the most,
because I don't have to,
for everything,
open a program on my own.
And I also remember,
at that time,
it had all the Adobe Premiere,
it had full,
basic,
when it comes to color correction.
I know you needed some plugins,
to make it work better.
DaVinci was already all over the place.
In addition,
it had a full license on the camera.
Yes,
that's great.
I mean,
if you buy it,
I don't know,
it's 300 euros,
300 dollars,
something like that.
If you buy anything from them,
then the price comes down.
Yes.
Now,
there are a few minor additions,
but still,
you can buy
a little more expensive stuff.
Yes,
but also,
I mean,
if you buy it,
you will.
Yes,
anyway.
I mean,
I haven't bought a license yet,
because,
simply,
in the paid version,
there is absolutely nothing,
that would,
ruin the movie.
You know,
I'm not a filmmaker,
so,
I don't care about those tools.
For a YouTuber,
it's just good enough.
You know.
I don't care.
I came to this,
not just because of,
some noise reduction,
or something like that,
but,
the first project,
that was,
you had to delete something,
from a phone,
or something like that.
Yes.
And,
it doesn't allow for that.
it's just a tool,
that I needed,
and I was like,
ok,
at this point,
it's already the first thing,
right?
Yes.
But, yes,
definitely,
everything can be done,
for free.
You're filming,
and you're recording,
on camera,
B-RAW.
Yes,
so,
Blackmagic's RAW codec,
although,
for those long recordings,
in,
let's say,
the lowest quality,
because,
it has some,
possibility of compression,
also RAW,
format,
because,
if it's not,
really RAW,
in the video,
then,
yes,
actually,
this is being recorded,
in RAW.
I'm recording RAW,
mostly,
because,
because the workflow,
is completely,
already,
working with Davinci,
right?
Because Davinci,
for those who don't know,
is the same company,
Blackmagic Design,
they work in hardware,
and software,
and,
this,
this works together,
clean,
clean and smooth.
A lot of my work,
I have,
with post-production,
from which,
I made friends,
mostly,
with filesize,
and,
I work in RAW.
Because,
I'm recording,
I'm recording a program,
the program,
is already set up,
to work with,
Blackmagic RAW footage,
and,
I don't need,
those,
how to say,
from flat profile,
I hope you know,
what I'm talking about,
from flat profile,
to,
to non-flat,
or,
how to say,
not,
not only,
conversion,
because,
it's,
practically,
everything works,
one,
two,
three.
Yes,
because,
I have to,
have fun here,
and,
I'm recording,
at home,
my video,
on Sony,
this,
S-Log3,
logarithmic,
format,
so to speak,
and,
it's,
so,
so you have,
full hitter,
overexposed,
and underexposed,
you can,
even RAW,
because it's,
RAW,
which is,
H264,
to be precise,
and it's,
so,
overexposed,
and if it's overexposed,
you can't,
pull it back,
because you lose,
I don't know,
you know,
if you have a light,
on your forehead,
and your forehead,
shines a little there,
and you lose,
the data,
you know,
and it's,
so,
too,
too.
Let's,
let's know,
what is,
overexposed,
or underexposed.
So,
if you,
when you,
set,
the frame,
on your camera,
it's,
you can,
overexposed means,
that the light points,
are brighter,
than those sensors,
can,
I don't know,
tolerate,
somehow,
I would say,
it's,
overexposed,
and there,
after that,
the sensor sees only white.
But,
that means,
that,
that white is,
pure white,
I mean,
pure,
real white,
there is no important,
decorations,
inside,
what else,
can be,
but it's,
white.
Finished,
right?
And,
under expose,
is on the other side,
I mean,
if we have black light,
and you have the sensor,
that is not too sensitive,
and there is a shadow,
and then there is black light,
and sensor doesn't know,
what is there,
and it's not possible,
to move,
then lower.
And now,
when we are photographing,
in photos,
that data,
I don't know,
it's huge,
I can almost see,
with black light,
I'm photographing,
and I will always,
put it in software,
and because,
16 bit,
so much data,
can be,
on pixel,
that there will always be,
a lot of difference,
and from that,
enough information,
to get,
details,
in post-production.
While,
when recording,
there are those files,
I mean,
when photographing,
for example,
I don't know,
you are photographing JPEG,
if we go back,
if we stay on photographing,
you have JPEG,
it's a picture,
I don't know,
4K, whatever,
it doesn't matter,
it's 2 megabytes,
while RAW,
has so much data,
that it's 100 megabytes,
so,
it's 50 times bigger picture,
and video is identical,
and now,
if you are on camera,
which is intended primarily,
I mean,
photographic camera,
but hybrid,
so to speak,
that's what I mean,
if you are photographing,
I mean,
if you are recording,
or,
I want to say,
those cameras,
are not so intended,
in video production,
which means,
that they don't have,
the possibility of RAW,
at all,
I mean,
the bit,
or as we would say,
I mean,
on frame,
or,
the amount of data,
on pixel,
is 10 bits,
max,
and you are fully limited,
then it's like,
it would be JPEG video,
I mean,
again,
you don't have some,
more detailed details,
while RAW,
for example,
you can,
because you have so much,
but the files,
are so much bigger,
because of that,
right?
Yes,
I mean,
I don't know,
did you understand,
what I was talking about?
Yes,
yes,
I understand,
I understand.
I know,
that you are recording,
slowly,
as needed,
or,
I get,
those videos,
which I can edit,
I get,
from iPhone,
recorded,
and,
it's fun,
it's a lot of fun.
Plus,
it's not RAW.
No,
We have already tried,
recording in those,
Apple's,
let's say,
you know,
who wrote,
application,
which everyone uses,
for recording,
Apple's app,
Blackmagic.
Aha,
OK.
You have a camera,
Blackmagic camera,
I think,
that's how it's called.
Yes,
yes,
they are the only ones,
who use it.
And that's,
Apple,
in that event,
recorded on,
iPhone 15,
with Blackmagic camera app,
in Apple's app.
I hope,
that Tomas and I,
won't go too far,
in Da Vinci,
and Blackmagic,
so,
let's go a little,
to our,
some,
some planned projects,
because I think,
that,
we could talk,
in Grodno,
in software,
in photography,
in everything,
and,
now Tomas,
Tomas is already,
the second day here,
or are you the third?
Second.
Second,
right?
Yes,
I'm the first guest.
So maybe,
what projects,
are,
in your field,
if you just said,
that your field,
is really,
very wide,
or more like,
without names,
so,
you make graphics,
you make pages,
you make,
let's say,
a plug,
for a project.
Projects are,
what to start with,
some,
I mean,
most of the projects,
are those,
because,
let's say,
what I wanted to do before,
video,
illustration,
that is inside of that,
then,
fixed,
the tasks are done.
Okay.
The main project,
in which I am,
outside of,
tech,
I mean,
outside of that,
is more about,
creativity,
from a human point of view,
and,
some growth,
and that creativity,
in young people,
in old people,
and,
and there,
then we work,
and,
materials for,
for,
networking,
video,
editing,
making shorts for,
Pinterest,
YouTube,
Instagram,
then another,
another project.
But you don't have,
you don't have for,
video,
things.
Look,
I mean,
those videos are,
I shoot them,
and then I try,
somehow,
from those,
when they are,
very,
improvised,
but,
co-founder,
he has,
in that area,
he is very powerful,
and,
when he starts to explain,
he can,
talk about anything,
for a long time,
and then,
the problem of that,
retention,
editing,
that you can,
try to cut it as much as possible,
and maybe cut a lot of things.
So,
that's one project.
With the other,
I then,
actually,
in,
in one start-up,
I greeted,
there it's the same,
first,
you need,
then,
on the logo,
split page,
illustrations,
and then,
those illustrations,
are great,
and you can send them,
then,
to all slides,
to all other materials,
and then,
in the end,
we decided,
that,
actually,
I also work,
only product,
which is called,
back-end,
dashboard,
for,
for what they do.
Ok.
It started,
purely,
yeah,
we make logo,
that's it.
Was it also,
like,
I have similar experience,
so,
sometimes,
we had that,
you know,
someone from,
some business school,
or business school,
or whatever,
they came to you,
and then,
like,
hey,
I have a great business idea,
but,
actually,
I don't have to pay you,
to be,
you know,
co-founder,
or something like that.
Did it come from that,
or?
No,
it was purely,
paid,
paid for work.
Ah,
yeah,
but,
it's a,
between these,
projects.
And,
I also have one more project,
that is,
is actually,
it's quite,
which connects,
We'll know each other,
the business,
the design,
and the business.
They called it,
D&B,
which is,
local,
Slovenia,
and it tries,
to connect,
designer,
with business world.
There,
more than not,
like I said earlier,
a Pasteur brand,
you know,
all materials are,
on-brand,
whatever needs to be prepared,
goes through me,
either I prepare it,
or someone else,
prepares it quickly,
and I'm like,
OK,
I'll burn it,
so that it's done,
and it always,
has to be like that.
Now,
maybe,
in response,
considering that,
there was a previous episode,
actually,
for Gon,
where they talked a little more,
in tears,
and about business.
That's all,
actually,
freelance,
so,
you don't have,
or,
do you have,
part-time jobs,
like,
some jobs,
or?
No,
those are all freelance,
freelance projects,
yes.
OK.
Now,
I'll tell you about a project,
that you saw,
that fascinated me so much,
and you mentioned it before,
and,
so,
Jan comes,
or,
he sends a message,
Hey Tomas,
we're across the sea,
come on,
let's go for a coffee,
or a drink,
or whatever,
and I'm like,
yeah,
cool,
where are you?
And he's like,
what?
Yeah,
Disc Golf,
what?
But now tell,
now tell,
please,
to the listeners,
because,
I'm not the only one,
who saw it for the first time,
so,
tell us,
what is Disc Golf,
please.
That's something you have to do,
yes,
for Disc Golf,
but you're doing it again.
Yeah,
again,
so,
to get into the subject of this episode,
now,
I'm relatively
on a full break,
or,
I wouldn't like to be on a break,
but,
sometimes,
Disc Golf,
tournaments,
and everything,
during my work,
so,
give me,
give me one,
very,
very short,
what is,
what is Disc Golf?
It's a sport,
very similar to golf,
where,
instead of,
fingers and thumbs,
you use discs,
and you aim,
or frisbees,
yes,
and you try to catch them,
and shoot them,
to the basket,
in which,
you can score,
and that's it.
It sounds,
very simple,
but,
when you try,
you see,
it's not.
Now,
very,
I mean,
I'm sorry,
but we both fell,
now,
into Disc Golf,
but,
what is,
what is guess worth?
No,
it's certainly not game,
what is,
what is.
What can one do?
Well,
I would say that
there are many
technical problems
that you can fall into
and you get lost
because each
disk can be
in four different
layers
that relate
differently.
The wind is ideal,
the altitude
is ideal,
and the shape
of the disk
is ideal,
how you drive,
how your
engine is
ideal,
and then
at the end
there is
such a problem
that is
different,
but not
different.
And this
9 skillset
disgolfing
is very
far from
tech skills
and everything
related,
for example.
So,
maybe
a little
explanation
of this
is that
when I listen
to how
my field
sees
this rule,
I am
sometimes
in this
field
totally
unknown
and unskilled.
The most
I know
how to
put it,
this is
the highlight
of my
tech skill.
So,
maybe
somehow
in reverse,
so,
I
for myself
think that
everything I
start,
that I don't
lack
some
programming
knowledge.
I don't
mean that
I don't see
options and
possibilities
that would
suit me,
but I
do see
that
so,
it's
right
if you have
both tech
knowledge and
maybe creative
knowledge.
How much
is this
width
useful
if we
compare?
Yes.
For me,
personally,
at the beginning,
I am,
for example,
a little
against what
Tomas said,
he started
in web design
and then
at the beginning
he wanted to
be a programmer,
so,
of course,
my brain wanted
to work a little
differently,
and I went
into design,
but I also
worked a lot
in web design,
HTML,
CSS,
and at the
same time
when CSS
appeared,
I fell
in and
it was
funny.
And there
was Internet
Explorer 6.
Internet Explorer
6,
yes,
and I
gradually
went out
of it,
that I also
worked in
the front-end
part of the
design,
I think
it helped
me a lot
in the design
itself.
I think
we always
changed
a lot easier
for developers,
and maybe
I prepared
some tasks
beforehand
when I
knew that
they could
be done,
that I
wasn't
afraid
of
doing
them.
So,
I think
it helped
me a lot
in the design
part.
And
especially
in the
communication
part.
Yes,
if you know
what's
waiting for
you,
I understand
that.
Now,
I don't
know,
you went
a little
more into
hardware
design,
but
I'm
curious
about
how
you,
I don't
know,
your printer
and router,
and everything
in general,
where do
you work
the most?
Because
you work
creatively
and
technically,
but
what are
those
skills?
Look,
I'll put it
this way,
regarding
design,
I have
a lot
of
basic
shapes,
but
there,
I had
those
purely
from scratch
design
products.
So,
purely
manual
skills.
So,
I have
a lot
of
basic
shapes,
but
I have
a lot
of
mechanical
skills,
electrical
electronic
limitations
and
regulations,
I don't
know,
how the
matrix
works,
so you
get to
know the
basics of
how the
printer works
but
the rest
is relatively
fine.
And
everything,
for example,
how I
print connections,
so it
is
very
simple.
And
I
have
a lot
of
mechanical
skills,
so
I
have
a lot
of
mechanical
limitations
and
regulations
so
it
is
relatively
fine.
And
the
rest
is
relatively
Usually, most of the time, not in the buildings we have in the mansion, but
yes, it is for protection and for you and for the layers below, for bakers.
But I want to say something else, I wanted the layer to be visible,
that if someone would like to learn again, if I return to my desire to sell knowledge,
that they can take the connection from my printer and look at the traces.
Slobo will give you a brief overview of this, I know that we will open source it completely,
the whole printer, so if anyone wants to look, they will have step files, they will have gerbers,
these are all files, if you want to make a part yourself, you send it to someone who knows how to make a printed version.
So you give all the information, but what about the printer?
How does someone come to your printer?
Yes, they come to my printer at monominuskeyboards.com,
they can buy it, I sell them, but I will say that this project,
I don't have it as a commercial failure, I still sell them and sell them,
but not enough to be presented as a basic source of income.
So from a commercial point of view, from an artistic point of view,
I would say that this is a very successful project, because I liked it the whole time,
everything I learned and everything I am now applying to the development of the router,
when I started working on it, but it is not the same now,
to be able to develop a company, so to speak.
So far, I haven't even reached zero, for example, with the printer,
but look, no regrets, thank God.
Yes, you gave it your all, it gave you back what it gave you.
That's right, a lot of knowledge, for example, so now that I work on a router,
things are flying differently, so I don't repeat those mistakes,
and I'm not afraid that the same thing will happen.
And here, I think that the same difficulties have arisen,
here I also managed to get some risky capital,
so the company was established in Delaware from March last month,
so from March 2024, and we already got, here I am today,
the first offers are coming for foreign investors,
so now we will be flying more seriously,
and here I really got all the knowledge I needed to finish it.
Even if we go back a bit, you probably can do a bit more here,
I mean, you are not from scratch, you can design everything.
Are you talking about the router?
Yes.
No, again from scratch.
Yes, you can look, for example, I mean, yes, from scratch,
I mean, I don't have to make the processor myself,
I don't have the knowledge, I don't have the skills, I don't have the money,
but you can look, for example, at the market,
I mean, it's called embedded,
because embedded means that the processor itself is part of the connection,
because in conventional computers, the processor is special,
when you plug it into the connection, for example,
and embedded, the routers are embedded,
or the phones, or the ones that burn everything,
so it's like gold or gold or whatever.
It's really hard for me when you don't speak Slovenian,
because usually you burn soldered, or soldered,
the third American, and then you say gold,
so it sounds weird, I don't know why.
It's also for a lot of people.
Yes, yes, that's how it is.
Anyway, and here again, you can look,
where are those who sell processors
in terms of network capacity,
because the router is a network device,
and you know which processors are more
a network protocol, or used in network devices.
Okay, I understand that,
but you look for the most optimal,
what suits you best for the need.
Yes.
Now, but in my opinion,
I always look at the fact that I'm preparing
your YouTube late.
Thank you.
I'm trying harder, but I'm not that much on YouTube.
And also the printers, right?
It seems to me that you are more
aiming for aesthetics.
Yes, this is very important to me.
This is why, I will say,
of all my visual hobbies,
it is very important to me.
You see, it's the same as the printing box.
Yes, you know, that's why I'm a big fan,
as I said before,
that they send it to Apple.
That's why I like Apple so much.
Okay, fanboy is perhaps too powerful a word,
but I really have their iPads, iPhones,
wife's iPhone, child's iPhone,
at iMac, not at iMac,
at MacStudio, I work,
I'm really into their system,
because, first of all, they really work.
You know, at the time there was still that fame,
you buy an Apple laptop or MacBook,
and everyone, oh, it's so expensive,
but today, if you look at, I don't know,
an average MacBook, or an average Dell,
or Samsung, or Asus, or whatever,
it's all the same.
You're on the same level.
It's not like, oh, Apple is much more expensive.
It's not like that.
Yes, you can always compare it
with a Windows laptop for Yuri,
but you wouldn't compare it
with an apple or a pear.
But what I want to say is that
Apple is still, you know,
I can bring something,
I want to clean it up,
and I put it back on the table.
It's very simple.
But if I open a terminal,
you can still, I don't know,
compare it with a Unix system
from the bottom, and you can
come to all the files,
you can do whatever you want,
and you only have a terminal,
practically, without any
graphic tool.
It's aesthetically perfect,
and that's the layer that
combines those things,
so that the thing looks good,
and if you need it, it's really powerful,
and it's really like that.
But the whole experience
is top-notch.
I experienced that, for example,
when we were still parking,
when we hired Mitya Mousari,
he was at the time,
I think he's still with us,
but I don't think he's so active anymore,
he was a user and an expert.
Wait, my mic is down,
let me put it back.
Technical difficulties.
Yes, technical difficulties.
Anyway, Mitya hired
a couple of people,
they were in front of me,
so we developed a product,
they used our product,
and he was the first person
who came in and used our application,
he got a script, a fake script,
you can feel that.
And you saw a person,
and you saw how he had no idea,
and you thought,
what's wrong with you?
And then he somehow clicked to his goal,
and you thanked him, and he left.
And another person came in,
and he struggled again, and so on.
And with everyone else,
you realized that nothing was wrong with them,
that something is wrong with you,
because you got used to things.
That's why I say that I really liked
the evangelist UX over the years,
that it really means a lot to me,
and now about routers,
we also have a team
that specializes exclusively in industrial design,
and that's the team CITO Design,
shout out, here in Ljubljana,
and they will help me,
they are really...
we had a lot of meetings,
even, I don't know, a simple thing,
for example, a beam on a router.
We had a meeting about a beam,
or a beam.
What color was it?
That's a legitimate question,
because, for example,
look at yourself at home,
how many times do you look at a router?
Many times.
But at the beginning,
never.
How many beams does it have?
How many of them are there,
because you never look at them?
And that's purely practical,
but also cost-effective.
Now imagine,
you have a beam that costs 5 cents,
but now you have 5 beams,
I'm talking about diodes,
but now you have 5 diodes on top,
and now you make 100,000 routers,
I'm imagining,
and RedZap,
and in the end,
cost-effectiveness,
visually, everything,
and you see,
I don't have to say anything.
It's worth it.
I was wondering
if I should add a little to my work.
Now I have one more question for him,
about connections.
You're in one area,
but you go to another,
how much does it benefit you?
How did you get this knowledge?
You weren't in hardware from the start,
so you didn't know.
What can you do
so that this knowledge doesn't limit you
in terms of what you can do,
for example, against coins,
or did you go for a bluff inside
and then against it?
Jan will answer that.
No, no, no, no.
Aha.
Our condition.
I mean,
yes,
it's very informative,
and you can focus
very strongly
on hours of googling
about a topic that will interest you for two days,
and then maybe nothing more.
I think that's
the best description for
the problem.
No, I mean,
that's how our brain works.
You get stuck in something,
and it just interests you.
If it interests you, for example...
You have to know everything,
not just a little.
You can't stop.
You don't know how to help yourself to stop.
One woman came to me,
Toma shook her,
and then she turned blue.
I have to google this to the end.
It goes to extremes,
but on the other hand,
if I'm not interested,
I can procrastinate for a month.
She sent me,
and it already happened to me,
and I'm not ashamed.
For example,
you get a bill to pay,
but it's a convoluted way
of paying.
Based on a true story.
If I didn't want to pay
on that bill,
which was never a problem
in finance,
I could pay it somewhere,
but it wasn't enough
to pay it at home.
It was such a pain to get stuck,
so much pain,
that I had to go to the court,
and they took my cash,
and I had to pay the court,
and in the end it cost me 80 euros,
instead of the original 20.
I think it's called ADHD tax.
I think it's called that.
You just can't do it.
You can't talk about it.
And then you have to do it on YouTube.
Yes, but on YouTube,
it's a lot of work.
It's a lot of work.
Especially in the late hours.
You have an idea,
and then you have a deep dive,
and then you start doing it.
It's a lot of work.
You go into a rabbit hole,
and then you see
what you're going to get.
But you always have something left.
Something left, yes.
It's not easy,
because you have a wide range of things
that you can use
later on.
Let's say, Jan,
I'll give you a programming challenge,
or maybe this is it,
something is growing,
and you'll be like,
we'll get it in three years.
I was thinking
about a specific language,
or just a concept.
I think it's a great idea.
I don't care about that.
I don't care about the name,
or anything like that.
I don't care.
I think it could be
a program.
I don't want to be too loud,
but maybe you can give me
something easy.
Really.
Thank you so much
that I know how to google.
Because I think
it's not...
Jan, I'll give you a challenge.
Modern programmers
are like
Fax.
I would learn Fax.
We all learned
Stack Overflow,
I learned PHP,
it was linda.com.
Linda is a big name.
I pirated half of Linda.
That was a year ago.
And in my defense,
dear Linda and viewers,
I was full-led.
I didn't use them
because I brought notes.
But that's how I learned
to program.
I'm a mechanical engineer,
and a failed forestry engineer.
Great.
I think the only problem
is that I didn't have enough time
to edit the short video
in Grodno or some other video project.
Programming is a very
long thing
because
I see hours and hours
that I need.
Maybe it's too much,
but I think the beginning
is a bit too much.
You need to find something
to connect with what you're doing.
You had the same project
with the pictures.
Do you do something like that?
Or do you just solve everything?
It all depends on the problem.
You need to add something
in the program
that's not in the user interface.
Then I google different codes
and commands.
You need to go that far
to find a solution
to make it more programmable.
But to know
where to start,
I don't know.
I wouldn't know how to start
such a project.
People are getting closer
to learn how to start.
I think you always
have to start from the problem.
The one I don't have.
That's my problem.
The problem you don't have.
If you have a task
and you listen to it...
No, it won't be OK.
You don't need someone else.
I know what you mean.
We can give ideas.
Where are the ideas?
We'll find an idea
to learn how to program in Ruby.
I have an idea.
The first google is
What is Ruby?
I'm very interested
I was born in Zraven,
which is one of the places
where I was introduced to Oto.
We didn't have a camera yet.
But I see
how outside of this field
I'm still
on the other side
of technology.
It would be
a segway
to some AI talks.
I think
there's a bit too much AI
with this.
For all of us.
AI as
a tool
would probably help me
with such tasks
and such problems.
For example,
the animation of the logo
that happened at the beginning.
At the intro in the garden.
We wrote a script
in After Effects
which is 4300
squares
that were put on a piece of paper
and changed into
a slow pixel animation
to look nice
on the surface.
And then they die.
You didn't mention
how many versions
you gave me
to mount on my hands.
We came to the point
where we could help you.
We had an idea.
I think we used
the whole first episode
of this season.
We didn't find
my part.
I really liked your
squares and all that.
Let's talk
about AI.
Many people ask me
as a photographer
if I'm afraid that AI
will replace me.
Because it's full of
generative stuff.
Everyone looks at my work
because I do more events
and more in-person stuff.
I think that
I won't be replaced so soon.
Or if I'm a bit worried
that we're all in the Balkans
a bit behind.
I'm still a bit behind.
What would you say?
Do you see a threat
of AI?
An opportunity?
What do you think?
Are we going to generate
rewards instead of taking pictures?
No. I don't have much experience
with AI.
I don't have much to say
about it.
I treat it as a tool
and I don't need it
anywhere.
I don't even
proofread it.
I don't proofread
my YouTube videos.
I don't.
That's who I am.
That's the whole point.
If it's AI, it will be AI.
And
I take everything
out of AI.
What do I want to say?
It's a threat.
It's generic.
There are influencers on Instagram
who are already AI.
But they don't change anything.
Why? Because they're generic.
You look at 5% of influencers
and they're the same.
It's a repetition.
It's like robots.
Why are robots in factories?
Because they're repetitive
shit.
We take shit from people
and I think they can
enable creativity
so that more people find out
that they want to outsource creativity.
That's what I think.
What?
I think
that
there's a panic
because AI will
replace everything
visually.
I think we're in
that bubble.
But if you see
those debates...
But if creatives change
how will it change?
Everyone is trying
and generating something nice.
Everything is nice, everything is fast.
I think that
creativity is overrated
by the whole population.
So,
I like to hear
that one day
instead of watching Netflix
they'll generate a series.
My idea
of what I'd like to watch
is good enough
to watch Netflix.
If you know what I mean.
Because sometimes you know how to write good scripts
and you have an interesting plot.
That's logical.
I agree.
People think
that they'll keep
a never-ending cycle.
A cycle.
I don't know.
Maybe you're...
I think that your field
in terms of illustrations
has grown a lot.
Yes, yes.
It's just
because of some copyrights
and some agreement
they reached.
It's always interesting.
Every week
there's a new existing
software with its
AI prompting
integration.
And the first question is
where did you get the data
from?
And then there's a comment
that it looks really good.
Thank you for the comment.
It's a little...
It's a little sus.
Yes, because of that
and with the power of Adobe
you have the AI
inside and you can prompt.
I think that on the one hand
you look at it yourself
and you're like
as an illustrator,
as a designer
you're going to do something,
you're not going to prompt
even if it's just for a generation
of ideas.
I think that sometimes
you can't do anything
out of them.
As far as I know,
I've been doing this for a long time
and I think I'd lose too much time
if I were to teach
or explain what exactly I want
because I know exactly
what I want, what it looks like.
I've tried with the videos
that in English
you have more options
to make content
from other content,
the final content.
It looks better if I find
a generated graphic
that I need,
what kind of text
to start with, even if it's
going to look better in a year or a month.
It all looks cheap.
I would say
now it's like
in five years
I'll know everything.
But the problem
can't be solved.
If you have a creative vision
you can't look
into the brain.
Look, AI is
a mix.
It's always a mix of what you learn.
A person can have a creative idea
originally
that AI will never have.
In my opinion, no.
And here
we're always one step ahead.
A very optimistic discussion
about AI.
You know what I'll tell you?
When you look at our sphere
we all think
that we're in
these waters.
You don't have to work
as hard as you can,
but there are
90-100 people asking
what you think about AI.
90% of people
won't know
what you're talking about.
I don't think
it's as easy as it seems.
That's what you said,
creativity.
I see a lot of creativity
being outsourced
to big corporations.
I think it's sad
for humanity.
On the one hand,
why would the process
of creating
art
be built
when you're creating an idea,
when you're drawing something,
when you fall into a flow
and an idea comes out.
Why would it be built
with a stake?
And that's it.
It's like a sheet
without feeling,
of growth.
You're making a picture
where you can
capture your feelings
and thoughts.
I think it's
from a legal point of view
that it's possible
and it has to be possible,
because if it's not,
you can't produce
tons and tons of something.
When it comes to
legal thoughts
and all that,
I'm on the author's side.
If they took
or learned
that AI systems
would have to be credited.
Or someone has to go there.
And from that point of view,
I'm a bit on the side of those who are now spreading some insults.
That's also very nice, yes.
I think that's very good.
You want a cat to be generated, and a car will be generated.
Or something like that.
The picture has some information inside the picture.
Like a leather model.
I've heard that before.
Yes, like AI scrapes new data.
And then you publish the picture.
You've just called it Nightshade.
Nightshade, something like that.
That's what I've heard for the first time.
Yes.
And over time, AI learns it by heart.
But when you look at the same picture, it looks normal.
But in one pixel, there's some information that takes it over time.
And over time, it goes out to patch results.
So if a cat is pre-generated, a dog is generated over time.
Okay, whatever.
There's no antidote for that.
Okay.
It's not that simple.
I'll tell you where I'd like to have AI.
And where Dejansko has it.
I did a study on this topic.
I'm a passionate gamer.
For example, I don't watch TV.
Every night, my colleagues and I get together and shoot each other in virtual worlds.
But Dejansko has a lot of cash in here.
And Dejansko has a lot of cheaters inside.
And some algorithms are developing.
Or some AI-powered detection.
That would be your gaming fingerprint, for example.
That is, if you read...
To learn this model, what cheaters do, how you read.
Because all cheaters do the same.
For example, I don't know.
That is, if you have a measure on something.
And then a head appears and the cheater finds out.
The measure goes directly to the head.
Because it's a faster headshot.
That's auto-aim.
Auto-aim, yes.
But, for example, if you're holding a mouse.
You can have insanely good reflexes.
But your hand will never go through the bi-pixel line on the headshot.
That is, to find this model.
And to find the cheater.
And then, as I would say, your fingerprint.
And if you read the most, in one game there would be an AI repository.
Where you would log out of another game.
Or if you made a new account.
I mean, here I see...
Recognize a sample of your gameplay.
And then comes the blockchain.
We're there.
Yes, that's it.
In the blockchain, the cheaters are involved.
And it's forever.
But here I see...
Because it's not frustrating at all.
My colleague and I invest a lot of time in gaming.
And you have some...
I'm an amateur, so it won't help.
But a lot of time and you're good.
And then you lose against a cheater.
It doesn't seem cool to you.
Bad UX.
Yes, bad UX.
That's it.
OK.
I would like to go to some of our more common projects.
To go back to our dear garden.
At this point, if we're close to the end,
I would like to thank our partners and supporters.
3FSO, Human Frog and again Kaldi.
Don't forget about our Patreons.
I hope we'll start doing more special things for Patreons.
But at the moment we don't have the capacity.
There won't be much.
Yes?
I agree.
We all support you.
Let's talk a bit about the garden.
What are we going to talk about?
I don't know...
Tell me why you work in the garden.
Why do I work in the garden?
That's a good question.
Why does anyone work in the garden?
Not why anyone, why do you work in the garden.
I know, I know.
It was so spontaneous in the beginning.
Because it seemed like there would be less work.
I connected with Oto.
Because Oto is just a recorder.
He recorded in the lowest quality possible.
And there was nowhere to make a podcast out of it.
Or something like Work Your Magic.
And then it started.
And then there was your episode,
where we put the cameras on the side.
And it was just me trying out the episode,
or two, or three.
And then the whole season was recorded.
Somehow it became my project too.
I had a bit too much time.
You could hear it.
You were fixing the audio.
Wait, you were on the side before Jan?
I wasn't on the side.
But Oto was...
We know each other from Oto.
And I saw that what they produced was just a bit...
That they needed help.
To be able to improve.
Politically correct.
I was like, maybe Jan would be interested in that.
I was like, Jan, me, Oto, Oto, me, Jan.
And then...
Then we met in Maribor at a coffee.
He told me how they do it.
I was a bit surprised.
I got the footage.
They weren't the best.
But yeah, those first few episodes were brutal.
I mean, you couldn't do anything with them.
Without AI you couldn't help them.
Nothing could help.
Then came the same amount of videos.
Then came the microphones.
And everything...
It's just a bit better.
I would change everything.
I think I would change a lot of things.
It's good that you light up.
I don't have a flashlight that would light us up.
But we would have a great camera.
Yeah, Pixis.
Dear sponsors...
We're also preparing hardware.
Yeah, Blackmagic will be on the market soon.
New cameras that cost only 3000 euros per body.
We're pretty modest, we'd only need three.
And a healthy lens.
Those lenses would be interesting.
Yeah, there will be more.
So it won't be just me.
I have a flashlight.
But we don't have them.
Last night I was talking to Domna.
The director of Human Frog.
And we were debating about branding.
Where do all these frogs go?
We have some stickers.
They're pretty cheap.
We'll put a commode on the camera.
If not, the sponsors will...
10 stickers.
Yeah, all their stickers will be all over.
Just in front of the lenses.
Not to be seen in the frame.
Maybe Blackmagic will make a custom one.
An additional attachment.
You can screw it on.
It's fixed.
Like a frog.
We hope that Domna will call us.
She's a big supporter.
Sometimes she comes to watch an episode with us.
The rest of you are great.
If anyone wants to come live,
we haven't done it yet.
The community is great.
Write to us.
We'll change the commode if we can.
Last time we were in Maribor,
how was it?
I think it was a question.
If we're doing a meet-up.
Not yet, right?
This is our meet-up.
How did you come to Grodno?
Someone called me.
Was it you or Oto?
Definitely not me.
We met here.
Oto said he'd come.
Oto introduced me as a guest.
But at the time he said
if I remember correctly,
it's been a year and a half now,
he was thinking about
making the first episode.
The first episode
with me.
It was the only episode
with three cameras.
There were three cameras.
What?
Two Sony cameras and a Blackmagic camera.
I had two of my own cameras.
For my needs.
I needed a conversation.
Every conversation was about
a new gear purchase.
So I bought this flashlight
that illuminates us today.
And a lamp.
And a stand.
I came here for a hobby.
Rub it in my face.
I came here as a video guy.
He came here for a hobby.
At the time,
I contacted
Oto.
He was the best.
At the time, Oto said
if I wanted to be healthy again,
I'd do it with my hobby.
I was totally the best.
I'll tell you why I'm healthy.
Because I always get to know
the guests.
The guests are always phenomenal.
It's one of those activities
where you grow up.
In a personal way.
I always say,
when I'm alone for two hours,
I need to eat,
recharge,
and spend a lot of time at home.
Why did we end up in Ljubljana?
We're all from the east,
like here.
We're from Maribor.
Oto is also from Maribor.
But everyone says
this is the second episode
for today.
Yes, that's right.
A woman
never asks
why.
She sees that I come home
with a smile,
that I come home because I love it.
Most of the time, I work from home.
I have
very few advantages.
But loneliness
is not one of them.
You can meet people
with similar thoughts,
with an overlap of interests,
but knowing, thinking
is priceless.
With the biggest laugh
I go across the sea
to film in Grodno,
and with a big laugh
I come home,
meet a new guest,
see friends.
I have a similar experience.
I'm an outsider.
It's interesting to see
people in the tech sector.
That's where I get
that feeling.
When Oto took me
to a Make It conference
this year,
I think
people get to know each other
much better than
at our meetups.
Which meetups?
Like videography meetups?
I don't know.
With Facebook groups.
I chat with more people
in a global Blackmagic group.
Couldn't you do something
for Blackmagic fans?
I could.
No, no.
Not here.
Blackmagic fans.
I don't know if it's too little.
They showed their hardware.
It's too little.
No, I don't think so.
If you did that,
it would be interesting.
It would be possible.
Could you make a movie about
Phil?
I don't know what it's called.
You have a lot of movies.
NAB in Slovenia.
I don't think so.
Probably Broadcasters.
Canon, Nikon, Neve.
I saw that.
Blackmagic, Neve, not yet.
It's a business opportunity.
Yes.
Send me an e-mail.
I will represent Europe.
We let you down a bit.
You came to Grodno
because you couldn't watch
the old logo.
Yes, that's it.
I think I heard
that you should change
the logo.
What did you watch
this summer?
Everything was good.
We changed it
from time to time.
Then you need
to find a moment
when you can devote yourself to it.
I came here because
I've known Otto
for almost 20 years.
And you made him laugh.
Yes, I made him laugh.
It was a cool idea.
It's similar to
what we do in Maribor.
The community,
the knowledge,
the connection
of all actors
seemed very important to me.
In this format.
It was interesting
to see how it can be done.
How fast it grows.
It grows very fast.
Now that you mentioned
the meeting hours,
I don't know.
It was a coincidence.
You have two microphones.
It's very convenient.
You can bring the camera
by yourself.
If I don't sit there,
I have to do something.
The photos are very quiet.
Not like my old Canon
where the glass
would make some noise.
It hurts me when I see your photos
because I know
how much your old camera
costs.
I know how much my camera
I don't see such a difference.
I don't like
purchases.
But yes,
meeting hours are cool.
Now that you mentioned
overspending for the game.
Do you think you overspend for the game?
Or what kind of conversation
do you have about overspending for the game?
I try to overspend
for the game
that I will need.
I make sure that
I have everything on the way.
If I have too much
of everything.
I like to be compact.
Basically, all the equipment
for this setup
can be carried alone
in one.
For the podcast.
When I buy something,
it means two trips to the car
or home.
It makes
a lot of sense to
overspend for an old camera
that worked great.
But then you see that it's there
and you have to replace it
and clean it.
That's my blockade.
I do a lot of different
projects
outside of work
and elsewhere.
I don't know
what kind of construction
I would build
instead of getting
boards and wood for the garage
and now I need beams.
And it doesn't have to be
just one beam.
You need a lot.
You can do it.
What do you
overspend?
I bought
a new Apple which was
expensive.
But I think that
when I started working on it
which was done without
Macbook A16
which was
done, I think
that's the price
and I don't overspend
on equipment.
I have an iPad
which is 7 years old
and it's still working.
We both dropped the same thing
on a bag.
Yes, the same thing.
Books
and flour
for baking bread.
Flour?
Yes.
It's never too much.
Wait, how much do you overspend
on flour?
Classic flour
or exotic flour?
I don't know how exotic
you can go
on a fresh summer.
You could buy
your own flour and live
and hang out.
I think we went a bit too far.
If you have
a final thought
because we are
being chased.
As you would say,
it's a bit noisy
and we are 90 minutes
away from the demo.
We have an hour and a half
left on the disc.
Let me tell you
how it went.
I'm still choosing
who to talk about it with.
I hope you will.
You tell me, it's cool.
What do you mean?
How do you feel
about the first episodes?
I could have prepared
a bit more.
I went a bit crazy
because we all know each other
and he is a local.
I don't see who will listen
and watch it.
I'm OK with it.
It would be nice
if we recorded
the first episode first.
But yeah,
it's been a long day.
As far as I'm concerned,
you are a top leader.
Thank you.
You are a great guest.
You complement me a bit.
I hope we didn't lose
anyone from the listeners.
I don't think so.
No one will hear the final plug
and like and subscribe.
Do you have a plug?
Where is it?
On YouTube.
It's youtube.com
slash Tomas Zaman.
I'm posting shit on Twitter
without the listeners.
Also Tomas Zaman.
That's all the social media I use.
That's it.
I only post shit
on Twitter.
On Instagram
I write and
rely on AI.
Handle.
Yes.
Brits.
I don't have a plug.
That's it.
Thank you for listening
and watching
our
very friendly
conversations.
Thanks to the supporters
Human Frog, 3FSO and Kaldi.
And of course to Patreon.
Come here.
With joy
I'm waiting
for the comments
to see if we have any trolls.
We don't.
I'm waiting for trolls.
There's a comment
saying we don't have effective trolls.
I think we haven't managed
to troll in the city.
We haven't managed
if we don't have good trolls.
Too few haters, too few trolls.
I think the city is full
of...
I don't know.
What do you think?
Thanks for listening.
Bye.