Welcome to the 5th episode of the 3rd season of the podcast in Grodje, in Zagon.
Today we will talk about payments and other types of compensation in this sector in Slovenia.
Nika Anžel and Miha Medven are with me today. Welcome.
Thank you.
As we thought about the topics that are constantly appearing, we realized that we do not have to go beyond payments.
I must admit that the response to the previous episodes surprised me a lot.
It is incredible how many questions we got.
As I said at the beginning, we will not be able to cover all of them, because there are a lot of them.
We will touch on this in the next episodes.
Today we will talk more specifically about payments.
We will focus on the technical area in Slovenia, but we will also talk about the international space.
Why am I inviting Nika and Miha today?
Nika Anžel has been helping in the Slovenian community for the last 5 years.
She also helps with the search for personnel, especially technical personnel.
She comes from the Agency for the Search and Selection of Personnel.
Welcome, Nika. Would you like to add something?
I would not.
As I said, for the last 5 years, we have been working together.
Especially in the positions where the IT market has opened up due to the coronavirus.
We have been working on tattoos, especially for the Slovenian sector.
Great. Miha, you are a very visible member of the Slovenian technical community.
You come across your name either on the Slovenian developers or through your content on YouTube for freelancers.
This has also contributed a lot to this part of the Slovenian technical community.
You have worked a lot in start-ups.
Now you are also in the first international company with a much larger business.
I am currently involved there.
Would you like to add something?
Or I have to add something.
And of course, first of all, why are you here today?
I paid for your survey.
On behalf of the whole of Slovenia, thank you for your time.
And that every year you really take time for this.
I think we all see a lot of added value from this.
But of course, we will talk about this a little later.
I would like to start on your behalf.
The post-COVID period was very interesting.
I mean, the COVID period was very interesting.
I think it changed the whole industry a lot.
But in this sector in general, I think there was a big shift.
Now we are four years later.
How did you experience this time, but also in general?
What trends did you notice at that time?
I think one thing is when we think about trends and the current situation.
As a person, you always go back to when you started your career.
And then you base all your experiences on it.
So I started at 22 years old after a big financial crisis.
And at that time it was very, very, very bad.
And anything after that is very good.
So people who started in the time of Corona and after Corona in the IT sector
experienced the biggest boom in their lives.
Because the market share of the IT sector was so high
that almost every month we had a budget of 500 to 1,000 euros more for the same job.
And that was, on the one hand, very nice to see.
On the other hand, I expected that it would slowly go down.
The market returns to normal levels.
And we have a feeling that there is the greatest stagnation and recession.
Despite the fact that our sector still lives very well today.
The salaries are still very high.
A lot of companies are working very hard for us.
Not every day there are 10 new employees, but only one.
It has calmed down a bit after Corona.
It was logical that it could not be sustained.
So now I see a healthy, calm environment.
Trends have slowed down a bit, or are slowly returning to normal.
I hope that most of the layoffs are over.
You never know, but now I feel that it has calmed down a bit.
We'll see how it will be in six months.
What I have learned in the last three years is that the next 14 days are not crucial.
They change very quickly for you.
So that's my take on the last four years.
I lost a lot of voice.
I made some mistakes, but it was fine.
You can see all the trends in the polls.
We went from a non-remote company to a very remote company.
Salaries went up.
A lot of employees were replaced.
Some of you met in the dark four years ago.
As you said in the introduction,
there was an explosion of inquiries about engineers.
You were there as well.
How do you see the last four years?
I saw that you were moving, but I also saw that you were moving away a bit.
Yes, that's true.
I think the whole corona has grown.
A lot of inquiries, too few employees.
Everyone turned to IT.
At the end of 2022, I still experience layoffs.
They started because of Google and Facebook layoffs in the US.
American companies in Slovenia started because of that.
A lot of companies went into layoffs because they lost their projects.
A lot of them went into layoffs because they were afraid of the economic situation.
They said, we've grown too much.
We've gone crazy.
Now we're going to cool down a bit.
Maybe we weren't together or didn't perform well.
We were preparing for a crisis.
It didn't come to this.
I hope it won't come.
Last month, there was a story.
Less than 40% of people went into layoffs because of the lack of projects.
I don't know how long it lasted.
I still accept these stories from time to time.
As Miha said, the market is still shrinking.
There's still a shortage.
There are positions, but maybe not that many.
As far as pay is concerned, I'd say they're growing.
Not as abnormally as before.
But the conditions are much more demanding for candidates.
They don't give everyone a good salary.
They choose who they're going to hire.
In an ordinary profile, it looks like a big difference.
I remember four years ago, you were voting for some juniors for some contests.
You asked yourself, are you really ready to pay so much for such a cadre?
Did it change a bit?
Did the company become more demanding?
They don't hire us for juniors anymore.
We're looking for specialists, mid-to-seniors.
I think they've learned that it's not good to hire someone just because you need him.
You have to look at the individual fit,
and that the person contributes to the company for the money you give him.
I'm aware of that.
It was different a year ago.
Today, I think it's a bit more understandable.
There are more offers for juniors now.
It takes a year, a year and a half for people to know
that they can start with a junior position.
At the beginning of the pandemic, a lot of people started looking for IT jobs.
Now we have a lot of juniors, but there are no jobs for them.
I have a feeling that it's much harder to find the first jobs,
because the criteria are much higher.
You can show a lot more, more references, a portfolio,
than maybe before or after the pandemic.
There are a lot more offers for juniors now.
As a junior, is it easy to pay off your debt today?
Is the market today like, thank you, you've come to the service,
or is it a market where you also pay off your debt as a junior
and you also get involved in that part of the service life?
I think you always have to pay off your debt.
As a junior, you have a very, very small position.
It's still a matter of compensation.
It's still a matter of debate.
I know that the word is paying off, but it's a dialogue
between the employer and the employee.
If you tell someone else that you want to have a job tonight,
or something like that,
as a junior, I also want to fulfill my wish.
I don't know, a research conference, an education budget,
similar tasks.
As a junior, I don't think there will be any intention
if we start doing these tasks.
It's not a lot of space, but they are different tasks.
That's my opinion.
You also know how much you can show as a junior.
As a junior, you can get out of the fax,
you don't have to work as hard as you did on the fax.
As a junior, you have a lot of private projects,
you are interested in a lot of things.
For example, you work as a student.
If you can show something,
I think you can always pay off your debt.
Does this entry-level salary and this entry-level profile
make such a difference?
Does it also increase the amount of compensation?
I think it increases everything.
I don't know if there was a bigger advantage for this entry-level.
Every year it goes up.
How much it goes up depends on the year and the profile,
but it increases.
As we have a higher minimum and average salary every year,
these salaries also increase.
I don't think there is such a drastic difference.
Criteria change.
Now a junior has to show more than two years ago.
If you only had a desire for programming,
and then you started programming again,
and then you could start a good job,
today it is no longer the case.
Paying is the best thing, but it takes a lot.
As a reply to the question,
I would say that the salary is the most important thing.
Paying is the best thing, but it takes a lot.
As a reply to the question,
we work a lot with young people,
because we have a special program for educating young people.
Paying in vocational profiles,
in children's profiles,
has definitely increased for the entry-level.
Not only for engineering or programming.
It is simply inflation.
In the past, young people were completely unemployed,
and today they all got a job.
I think it was also related to that.
I mean, if you ask a boomer,
they don't know what to do.
They don't know what to do.
I can tell you,
when I started working with young people,
we had an entry-level.
I'm not talking about IT.
We were 3,000-4,000 people.
Today, we are 1,800-2,000 people.
Go.
Even if you go to a public place,
and you have a shop,
I don't remember how many people there are,
because there are too few people who would work full-time.
We have a record low unemployment.
There is a pressure from that side.
Because someone still has to manage that job.
Even if you don't need it as much as during the coronavirus,
people still go to work.
They change jobs.
Absolutely.
COVID has completely shaken us.
What is important to us is the value.
It seems to me that, in the end,
it has helped us a little bit
with a little more decentralization in Ljubljana.
If I'm right,
it is the call back to office.
I don't want to say that you have to work
for a week or two in the office,
but it seems to me that
it has shaken us as a society.
First, I would like to clarify
some basic concepts,
and then I would like to focus
a little more on the survey,
because you have been collecting data for some time.
But first, let's talk about wages
and salaries.
Let's clear up this brutal debate.
What are we talking about?
Salaries? Salaries? Salaries?
Salaries?
What is in the best interest of a candidate
who is talking about wages?
If I'm right, you can start.
I have a very strict opinion,
but I will start.
We have a lot of money.
I think that if you want to be a candidate for protection,
to be treated as much as you expect,
it is good to know what the difference is.
There are a lot of calculators on the Internet,
so it is not easy to look at these things.
But there is always a lot of talk about wages.
I would like to clarify
the specifics of the Slovenian market,
when we talk about wages.
We are not talking about compensation,
because there are also regressions
and the return of various expenses,
which can cause a lot of problems
at the end of the month.
I think that we are still in the middle of
understanding gross wages.
What else would you understand
as gross compensation,
which is much more expanded in the EU,
because it pays two-thirds of all other bonuses
and additional workers.
It is a very large employer.
Gross wages are the same
from the point of view of a specific person.
The distance from the company
is different at the end of the month,
but in the end,
we are talking about gross wages.
That would be one of the reasons
why I went to do this survey.
So that I could start talking about
the importance of gross wages
in the EU.
I started talking about the importance
of talking about gross wages,
and when we get used to it,
we will move on to compensation.
But Miha, I don't care
what the company pays.
I only care about my employees.
Why don't we talk about gross wages?
And then there are the SPs,
and I don't know what else.
I have a lot of these debates,
so I am a bit triggered.
I think this is the basis
for googling,
so you know what the system is.
When you get an offer from a company,
you can always ask them to prepare
the first calculation of the payment.
You can see for yourself
how much it will cost.
One of the stories I heard a lot
was that I changed my salary,
then I went to the hospital for a month,
and then back to work.
It's like you said,
you are a member of a company,
then you have a child,
and then you don't even expect it.
You work for a long time.
That's why it seems to me
that gross wages are the same,
because we are more on the same level.
We talk about the same things,
because as you said,
it depends on each individual.
It's nice for us as individuals
to be able to get gross wages.
It would be a lot easier
if we paid ourselves.
Gross wages are the basis.
It seems to me that everything
puts us on the same level
as other people.
What are the gross wages
in recent years?
I have a big problem
when it comes to gross wages.
Most of the debate is about gross wages.
Gross wages are a bit complicated.
If we have 2 euros,
then 10 euros is 4 gross wages.
We will be disappointed.
I always try to talk about the media,
which means that 50% of people
in Slovenia deserve less than that.
In the last survey,
it was between 3,000 and 3,500 gross wages.
That means that more than 50% of people
deserve less than that.
If you deserve more than 6,000 gross wages,
you are already in the top 10%.
If you don't have that salary,
if you don't get that salary,
if you get a salary of 4,000 euros,
you are in the top 1% of employees in Slovenia.
On the one hand, that is a big number,
but on the other hand,
I thought it was millions.
These are the figures that give you
a different perspective.
Gross wages are more about distribution.
Few people have a figure
of 3,000-3,500 euros.
If you deserve less than that,
you know where you are.
If you deserve more than that,
That is every two years for 500 euros.
Do you remember the first survey?
Yes, 2,500 euros.
The first survey was 6 years ago.
It was accurate, but not accurate.
People don't know exactly what it is.
I try to be accurate with 500 euros.
I looked at it,
2,000-2,500 euros was an average of 2,800 euros.
It is probably a big leap for the Slovenian industry.
Is it a leap for this industry?
It is huge.
In Slovenia, we have the SPF phenomenon.
SPFs have more income
if we equate them with employees.
The biggest characteristic
is that most of them work
for companies that are on this market.
A Slovenian employee is primarily employed
for a Slovenian company that works
on the Slovenian market.
If you work for a company that works
on this market, if it is also Slovenian,
you will get a higher salary.
If we have big Slovenian names
in our business,
they have locations in Slovenia,
they work for Europe and America,
they get a higher salary.
The work is exactly the same.
One of the biggest stereotypes
and reservations
I hear from Slovenian developers
is that if a person pays me
three times more,
what can I do for that money?
Is it really the same?
It is the same.
We have a Slovenian company
that employs Slovenes
from the wider Balkan region.
They pay them 3-5 thousand euros
which is a good salary.
They sell them as an agency
to American companies
for three times more money.
And they work side by side
with their American colleagues.
Documentation has opened up new areas
where you can learn this.
The only problem is that
the work you do can be taken over.
If you make a 10% difference
for a Slovenian company,
you earn 100 euros.
If you make a 10% difference
for an American company,
your average programmer is the same.
The elite may be different
because they have different access
to problems that can be solved.
In Slovenia, there are very few companies
that have the same scale as Google.
Some specific knowledge exists,
but there are very few people
who know what it means.
I haven't seen any difference in me.
We make the same mistakes,
we get confused because of the same problems.
We have the same problems.
You work a lot in Slovenia,
but also in the Balkans.
What is the difference?
You don't pay more,
but you work a lot.
You work a lot,
but you don't pay more.
I call him a rockstar candidate, that's why it's important.
Because they can work with big systems, with scalability and so on,
but I think that the difference is not very rare.
When you find the difference, or if you already find the difference,
it's more for smaller products.
I will connect this a little more with ESPM, because you also changed ESPM.
You started in 2010.
I remember that time, 2008, and that post-2008,
when there were no more regular services.
All the engineers could be ESPM,
you got a year for a certain time,
but more or less everything went to ESPM,
and then at one point, of course, the legislation changed,
and then it all turned upside down.
All the ESPM people started,
but if Freedom were in your position,
you would miss that.
And now you have both,
that's for both questions,
but you also have to pay attention to ESPM,
and today it is, as you said, a means for work, for income,
and in the end, how can Slovenian companies compete
with this broken ESPM,
which has a lot more data and data.
Do you want to start or should I start?
Yes, I think that certain Slovenian companies
use this practice.
Let's not talk about them.
There are a lot of them in this practice,
also because of the stability that they want,
if someone gets a job.
I also pay attention to the fact that lately,
a lot of people have been talking about
regular employment and the possibility of a loan,
and so on, some kind of special security
especially in these unstable times,
and maybe they also got caught up in some international affairs,
that they were on ESPM and then the project was cancelled.
So I won't say that now the trend is to move from ESPM
to regular employees,
but I do see some signals in the market.
I would like to add here,
because I talk a lot about ESPM,
and in my survey I have a lot of questions,
whether you work on ESPM or not,
and in fact there are 15 or 17% who are only ESPM employees.
All the other 75% are regular employees,
and 10% of these regular employees also have half-day ESPM.
Which means that this is a small number.
What I think is that this number,
which works for TOINO,
is on a higher level,
and they are talked about more,
because they are also part of some groups,
and all those guest debates that we have on Facebook,
this is perhaps also a little hidden,
as if the whole of Slovenia is on ESPM.
Well, no.
I have been studying this for 4-5 years,
and only 20% are ESPM employees.
Of course, ESPM employees deserve more money,
if we look at their income,
but I think that this is also a very good topic,
which we can discuss a little,
because there is a little bit of data optimization,
and all that stuff.
The good thing is that,
when the global market opens up,
I think that ESPM is a good alternative
for smaller companies,
that they are competitive in terms of pay,
because larger companies can offer you
as little through employment,
as a smaller legal company can through ESPM.
And now I see some added value,
that these Slovenian startups
may pay a little more for this,
because there is optimization on both sides.
Because in the end,
most people look at how much we get
at the end on the bank account,
which went to a very small amount.
So I think that's how it is.
A lot is said about ESPM,
but I don't know how serious the problems are.
Maybe it's not as serious as a problem,
it's more of a question,
and if it's a completely different league,
and we don't mess with them,
then maybe Slovenian companies
are losing out in terms of competition
because of ESPM.
On the other hand,
if you work as a contractor for an American company,
is your alternative really a local Slovenian company?
No.
You are in a different market,
you are on a different level.
I think that ESPM makes the Slovenian market
more competitive,
especially because it reduces costs.
Without that, it would be much harder for Slovenian companies.
The big ones are mostly in employment,
the small ones have good legal and accounting services.
So, I don't know.
I don't know if it depends on the community,
or the programmers, or the company,
what we want to do.
Because I remember those days
when ESPM came,
because they didn't want to have unemployed people.
They said, here's ESPM,
we'll give you 5,000 euros for two years,
make a company out of them,
and then we made a one-man band,
and 10 years later we still have them,
and we're small-scale contractors.
I remember that.
I forgot about that.
It was still 5,000 euros,
and we all went to ESPM.
If you wait another year without a job,
you get additional benefits.
We all go to ESPM,
just because we don't have unemployed people,
and 10 years later we have a small situation.
I don't know.
It's a good question.
It's more historical.
Maybe in Slovenia,
companies employ people at ESPM,
or you can work through ESPM,
and they can employ you.
There are also other solutions
for how companies can employ you.
For example, companies in Tojina
have an Employer of Records,
or an agency for employment.
Besides that,
do our companies also serve
in the market,
or what do you think?
What are the forms of employment?
If we're talking about Slovenian companies,
that would employ Tujans,
we have offered this form many times,
Employer of Records,
but it didn't work out.
Maybe they didn't know about it,
maybe it wasn't well-developed yet.
Usually, they want a B2B contract,
which means that,
if a Tujan employs a Slovenian company,
then the Slovenian company
has a lot of companies in the Balkans,
so they can employ them.
But usually, they want you
to work as an SP,
or a part of a company
that exists in the same country,
and then you sign a contract
as a B2B contractor,
according to the agreement.
We have applied to various services,
but I don't know,
I think that the Slovenian law
isn't that great yet,
it's a grey area,
and companies are a bit afraid,
as you said,
they haven't been properly
investigated yet,
and then it's easier for them
to say to the candidate
that from the company,
we will sign a B2B contract.
Can you explain a bit
what an EOR is,
for those who don't know.
It means that
you are employed
with a company
that has registered...
OK, I can't talk about
name companies now,
but there is a company
that specializes in
employing people
and then giving them
to you voluntarily
through an agreement.
They are employed
in a company
that is based in Slovenia,
so that other companies
can hire their employees,
even if they are not hired,
and then that company
does all the financial things
for those employees,
and it's like they are
employed in their own country,
and then they are employed
to you.
Then you pay an account
every month,
and they cover all the social benefits,
and all the administrative
and financial things.
So, you are employed
in a company in your country,
and you work for another company.
Which means that
you also have all the benefits,
and the laws guarantee you
your own country,
not the one you work in.
So, today,
there is only one form of employment,
an agreement in employment,
in Slovenia or in EU,
and in Slovenian legislation
you have regress,
and if your company
that employs you does not follow it,
it is in a legal violation.
Large companies cannot be opened
by employees in Slovenia,
because if you do not pay,
you do not know all the hackers.
I have also heard that
it is not possible to work
as an employee.
Employees want to have
a safe job,
so that the American state,
but also the wider society,
can trust you.
You have unemployment,
and of course,
the best is a hospital.
We optimize for different things
in life.
As you said,
you need a loan,
which looks different
in this period of life,
than some agreement
that has a two-week
repayment period.
I can tell you something very interesting.
A few of our clients
contacted us,
who have the Employee of Record service,
to help them as partners
in Slovenia,
so it looks like they are interested
in the market,
that they have a potential market,
and they support this service for us.
My experience,
from the point of view of the company,
is that if you choose
a good provider,
which has partners all over the world,
it means that you have entities
all over the world,
and you can work anywhere.
The fees are different,
depending on the location,
how complicated the legislation
is there,
but if you are
a remote provider,
it is possible
to hire
a lot of people.
There are also
gentlemen in suits,
who are happy that they are
in compliance with all the rules,
and that you have a contractor.
How do the candidates perceive this?
Do they prefer to have a contractor,
or does it suit them?
My experience is that
the market is remote,
because we do not
work with contractors,
which means
that we are completely
non-competitive in Eastern Europe.
In the whole of Eastern Europe
and the Balkans,
we have our SPs,
we are much more conservative
for such a remote company,
which can pay you internationally,
because it means that
half of the country will take you.
If you are already at this level,
you are a 100 or 200 euro engineer,
you do not have any interest
in being 70 euros per year
on the account,
because of compliance.
That was the biggest learning.
The biggest learning was
that simply
a club with a global level
of compensation
is no longer competitive,
because people could
go to meetings.
I think that
the SP is not a Slovenian thing,
but it is also Poland,
the Czech Republic, Croatia,
Serbia,
the whole of Eastern Europe,
Bulgaria, Romania.
It is easier for them
to be at the SP
than to be an employee.
I mentioned 100 or 200
engineers
per year.
One question came up
very interesting,
what is the difference
between 100 or 200 engineers?
These are really important
global compensations,
not Slovenian.
In Slovenian,
I would speak a little less.
Is it really an elite engineer?
How many do we have in Slovenia?
What is the difference?
How do you work as an engineer?
As I said,
if we look at 1%
of employees in the economy
and 4,000 net,
8,000 brut,
how much is it?
100 euros per month.
What I mean is
that these are people
who are very, very rare.
We know
at least 10 of them.
Slovenia is a small market,
so we know
who these people are.
The biggest criticism
is that their IT impact
is not programming,
but business impact.
At that time,
there could be a lot of differences.
I will say that if you are employed,
it is quite difficult to get to those numbers.
If you are an SP, a freelancer,
or something like that,
you play by the rules,
but you have more employees,
then this contribution is not so unattainable.
But then you are a subcontractor
and you have employees
and you are often the best agency
and so on and so on.
So I have a lot of debates.
I was always an SP,
a freelancer,
but I had 5-10 contractors
and because I couldn't do anything,
I hired someone else
to fix it.
And because at one point
it is no longer paying,
but it is the income of the company.
100 euros per year for the income of the company
is not such a big amount
if there are 4, 5, 6 people employed.
So I would say
to think more about the income
if you want to have those contributions.
Because if you pay too much,
it will be difficult for you to get there.
Let's be open.
I'm talking about Slovenia.
Have you sponsored any engineers
for 100 euros in Slovenia?
Not in Slovenia.
If we are talking about developers,
we are not talking about some government CTO.
No, we are not talking about VP,
VP of engineering,
individual contributor,
programmer.
No, not in Slovenia.
Do you have a goal in mind?
Can you say something like
wow, that would be cool?
I have 10 euros
per month of compensation
of Bruto SP.
10,000 euros
was for a company
that is going for
an operational role
of which there are only 50 in Slovenia
and this company
was one of the companies that did that
and it was worth it,
not the programming,
but the fact that it was able to
provide that service to its customers.
That's why it was so expensive.
I remember a similar contribution,
but it was so expensive
for a Slovenian company,
but not entirely owned by Slovenia.
So I don't have to say
that we paid in Slovenia.
But I would like to
ask you about that,
because I have a personal
foolproof way
that I think
100K engineers do.
But since we are talking
about pay and careers,
what is the world
like for someone?
How do you get to that level?
How do you start?
Here we are quite connected
also with the
stay and learn
or move and earn
debate.
How do you optimize your career
so that you can get
to that level of compensation?
If we are talking about Slovenia,
and that you are just a programmer,
we have to wait
for the inflation to come
so that we can get to 100 euros,
which I honestly think is impossible.
If we connect,
your skills are not only connected
with programming,
but also with launching
new products or opening
some verticals or horizontals
for more income.
These are a bit easier to achieve.
But then you are not just a programmer,
but you are something else.
Maybe a leadership role,
more product oriented.
What is the purpose of a career?
First you have to develop a skillset,
then you have to learn
how to sell well.
At the beginning of a career,
you have to optimize your skillset.
In the second half of your career,
you try to sell better.
What does it look like?
For me, it looks like a freelancer,
for some it looks like
they change jobs,
have their own startup projects,
go to conferences.
Then there is a grind.
Every new job
has to be 20% higher.
Or 30% higher.
If you replace 10,
it's 30 days.
30 days.
Maybe it's different
or for some other
leadership role.
I would say that
engineers and programmers
pay 12-20%
difference
than me.
But higher percentages
are more responsible
for leadership positions.
I haven't been
in the market for 10 years.
Then I moved
to a business position
and then I managed
to get a market
compensation.
It's almost
very difficult to be in the military
for 10 years and still
get a market compensation.
We had a case
and it turned out that
there is a lack of knowledge.
You can do a lot
in what you've been doing
for 10 years.
You change things.
Then you move to another company
and you are not as flexible
when it comes to technology
and products.
It wasn't enough.
You are culturally
very balanced in one field
after 10 years.
It's best 10 times in one
than once in 10.
You are in an open zone.
Of course,
there are other criteria.
You will be here for a long time.
That's good.
I see that
here you are always
building a team
or as a recruiter.
There are some differences.
There is a difference
between 7 years of experience
and 7 times in one year.
But is it possible
to have one year of experience
even better than 7 years?
It depends on the context.
I think that
one year
is extreme.
But I think that
Slovenia doesn't understand it.
That's a sign
as I hear
from my contacts
that there is something wrong with the candidate.
Absolutely.
As you said,
job hopping
I can understand it
in a candidate-driven market.
When you are interested
in a skill set
and you get a new offer
every week in an inbox.
You find a better project
and it doesn't work
on its own.
On the other hand,
you let it go.
It's a great way
to optimize for a higher salary.
If you optimize for an expert,
it's hard to work
if you only have one year.
I would like to change the perception.
I have been working
for 60-70 different companies
for 10 years.
When I applied
for a regular job,
I said that I was a freelancer
and I had my own agency.
The more contracts I have,
the lower my value.
I know how to impose
FDV.
I try to adapt my situation
to a variety of experiences.
If I write
that I was here for half a year
and here for 3 months
and here I am hiding
because I worked in 3 projects
for a short time,
I think it's also
because
in the end,
IT is a very complicated thing
where you have a portfolio
and some references.
Those who are
at the top
have a lot of unrelated
services.
They have startups,
hobby projects that can develop
or not.
And now we will have
an experience where
they value engineering
in a positive way.
That you are not a one-trick pony.
Absolutely.
When it comes to profiles,
we see hundreds
of recruiters.
Življen wrote weekly,
then also daily,
but weekly.
There are some patterns.
You see that
engineers who are
perhaps the most successful,
there is a difference
between 100 and 200 engineers,
there is a difference.
You see a lot of different things.
But it's not just
different companies,
but really different
industries, different stacks,
different products,
consultants, agencies
and product companies,
startups and big
legacy companies.
When you see more different things,
you are more
realistically T-shaped.
It seems to me that
at the beginning of your career,
in the first 10 years,
it is obvious that you change
and you see a lot of things.
I have an experience
with mentoring and people
who perform.
What you are trying to look for
is an organization or environment
in which you can grow.
There are not many of them.
I think that at the beginning
you will suffer a low salary
if you have a feeling that you are developing.
Because this development will
happen to you in some time.
The alternative is to fall
into a company that can pay well,
but then you stagnate
for years.
If you change the service so much,
you become competitive
because you have not learned
anything useful.
Because you become an expert
in your own system.
I had a situation
where I applied for a front-end developer
and I did not know JavaScript.
He told me that this person
had 4 hours of Bruto
3 years ago, before Corona,
which is a very high salary.
But there was one person in Slovenia
who is a custom CMS
developed by an agency.
I told him to stay here
because no other company
will give you this salary
for front-end developer.
And that is one of the reasons.
And I said, look, ride it out, but know that you will have a challenge if you don't know that.
And in the end, he still paid me well, he was at a certain level, but at the end of the service, it will be a little more painful.
It's a little, well, here it's a little, no, well, there is a menu, but as you said, if you find a good engineering culture,
then you will spend the next two to three years, because you can go there on that dip.
But I also face this question a lot, what is a good business, what is a good engineering culture.
I have two opinions on the recipe.
Now I don't know if you agree with me or not, but I think it's true that you always optimize,
or if you already choose and you don't have a lot of choices, you prioritize companies that make a living from selling their software.
This means that their main source of income is software and not gasoline, or I don't know, something else, but business software.
You have to approach the production of a product in a very different way.
Is engineering a profit center or a cost center?
That's right.
In my world, it's a bit like that.
Services are partners, you have to try more to know what you like.
I somehow follow this in the world, you don't really know what a good service and a bad service are if you have one.
A lot has already happened to me, I thought it was the best, then I changed it and two years later I'm preparing it.
They write that it was toxic, you didn't satisfy and I don't know what else.
But when you're in there, you have a different view of what you don't know.
After ten years and sixty accidents, I gave up.
Now I'm a bit old-fashioned.
When I'm older, I'm a bit more lost, I don't sleep well.
You get a perception when you're at the factory, you know, you're accused of a crime,
and then you realize that people work 10-12 hours a day and they're proud of it.
And you're like, okay, I've been there a hundred times, I know how it ends.
This is definitely one of the stresses of organization of work.
But I think it's very interesting.
The engineering culture or the process of development,
where the software development life cycle is as transparent as possible,
so you can really see how things start and how they go into production,
and what happens later.
That's one thing, that the software development life cycle is transparent
and that it values your brain, not your hands.
That's the best.
I'm still a bit skeptical.
Maybe I'll tell you later.
And one year? Really, not one year?
No, no, no.
Slovenian companies don't have such good onboarding systems.
No, absolutely not.
So that you can really go and start working.
Slovenian companies are not prepared to replace candidates in one year
and one year really perform fully.
I think everyone here ...
I agree completely.
If you're a junior, three years.
If you're a senior, maybe a year and a half.
And then a year if you're really out.
Yes.
I would say that if the engineering culture is bad,
change it in one year if you find a better one.
In three months.
If it's good, stay two to three years.
Absolutely.
I think it's a better digger.
For example, in the first seven to ten years,
you can replace more than five companies.
Something like that.
If you're a regular employee.
If you replace more than five companies in ten years,
it's already a bit of a red flag.
You can have a good argument why you did it.
Because they will ask you.
That's it.
I'm really not completely against it.
If you're not good, if you don't learn anything new,
change it anyway.
But I think it's an indicator.
I will not say any relationship,
but it is in existence.
You put it very well.
I would also like to share
this onboarding.
Because it seems to me that
Slovenian companies
have a chance to improve
when we talk
at a very senior level.
You want a samurai
and someone
who will really change
things in the company.
Then he comes to you
and you shake his hand.
The first thing.
You shake his hand and say,
it's okay,
here's a year of onboarding
so you can get to know each other a little.
Then it comes
the trust.
That maybe you know everything
and you're in the top
paid company.
I think these companies
know faster
what your superpower is
and you let your superpower
to them as soon as possible.
Is that just a stereotype
from my side?
Or how do you see it?
I think we have a problem
in Slovenia with the culture
when we come to a more leadership position.
Onboarding and recruiting
for juniors
and for mid-levels
is even more difficult
because there are
very few opportunities.
It's more difficult
to get that knowledge
and I would say
that when a leadership position comes
to a company,
it's usually when there's a crisis
and there are fires
and you need to do something.
That's why they hire you.
I think it's difficult
in a bad leadership culture
in general
because
we talk too little
about these things
because we have so few opportunities
in general
how the organization is set up
how it's organized
how the teams are structured
we don't talk about these things
in the sense of whether you have engineers in the team
whether you have a product team
or what is the composition
and that has a big impact
on the whole onboarding
because if you only need one year
to figure out
there's no problem in onboarding
the problem is in the food.
In my experience
I think that
in Slovenia
all companies will say
that they exist
and that they have all the necessary documents
and you go through it
and you don't know where to start.
That's my experience
I'm a bit triggered
and maybe you can see
that I've been through a couple of such stories.
You are also
starting a business
with onboarding
because there's a fee
or a guarantee
that you give to the candidate
if they pass the exam
and then you invest in onboarding.
What are the trends
from your point of view?
We are prepared
when we talk about
collaborating with companies
that have very little experience
and we had a case
that we are still recruiting for
where they hired 10 people in the last two years
and out of those 10 people
only one was hired in two years.
And then
we got
four positions
and we started to think
what's going on
what's the problem
is it the people you hired
that weren't right
or is it the problem in the way
that they didn't
work for the recruiters
because they are
not well-known in Slovenia
they are super international
they got bad reviews
and they took the ones they could
so we found them
hired people
but we were a bit scared
what if we let them go
and we decided
that we are going to
start onboarding
so we were
a bit scared
did we give them a tool
even though the first six months
were exhausting
working with people
because in any case
you are on a project
you have your priorities
how much time do you have
even if you are a mentor
and those people are juniors
at the beginning
we realized that
there are companies
that do it very well
and there are companies
that you come to
and you don't fall in the water
or you swim
we are interested
if we hire a candidate
to hold on for a long time
not only in the time
of the guarantee
which is so many months
so we recognize
that there is something missing
in smaller companies
because they don't have time
to deal with it
and they don't have tools
to help them
once you were in a company
onboarding went through
two years went by
first year
honeymoon period
everything was great
second year
you have a sexier company
and you look at your net pay
and you get your net salary
when is it easiest
to pay
and
how to
protect
a position in a company
but you have to pay
to stay competitive
do we have a world
for all those who
worked hard
but
what are the opportunities
for higher pay
once you work in a company
just like you did with a domestic tax
the day before you ask
for a higher salary
6 months ago you asked
hypothetically
if someone wanted a higher salary
what could they do
you tell your boss
you talk about some goals
and then you work
to satisfy those goals
get new competences
or whatever
and then you put
your effort into action
and you are ready
that's it
a lot of times
in my experience
why don't they give a raise
to people who are already employed
until they ask
just that simple
just ask
ok, first step
ask
and then they say
I don't have a budget
and if I don't have a budget
I won't pay new people
and then you know
if you have a budget
and you don't want to give it
you know where you are
and it's a different kind of conversation
but you always have to ask
what are your goals
most companies start
hiring once or twice a year
we will hire for inflation
we will hire for that
those are things you have to
be prepared for
and you have to talk about
that shouldn't be a topic
your compensation is part of your job
and if you are afraid to ask
I would think about it
because
if you don't ask, you won't get it
it doesn't mean
you won't get it
but it's just a step
do you pay attention to
a lot of candidates
who hire you
to get a raise
yes, it happens
quite often
for example
we give them a better opportunity
a better pay
they are not satisfied
but once they decide to go
you have to be patient
you push them a little
because you know them well
and you have to be patient
so you have to repeat
when they decide to go
you have to pay attention
so I would say
if you are
if you are satisfied
but you just have to pay
one thing is to ask
the other is
you can say
I think I have a low salary
I think I would pay a little
and again, it's enough
if you know
you have a domestic task
and the domestic task is
if you are lucky
look around
and try to get a value
you don't have to react to it
but it's an ease of mind
the service for hiring
is not a fixed time
you won't be prepared
for some options
that's it
I think
the hardest
is to know the context
and
I know
we go to recruiters
and then you go
you didn't want to go to another service
but you had to tell the boss
it's a little more serious
than we talked
it's nice when you mentioned
it's a good product
it's nice when you are prepared
for the story
what did you do
what did you learn
what did you contribute
just to say
I think I have a low salary
so I would deserve more
or he has more
you have to be careful
what you wish for
you can wish too much
can someone
say
we don't play in this league
for such compensation
we all agreed
you have a low culture fit
and
you can be worried
that if you can't
offer compensation
that you know
it's too late
too late
for the person
who will ask for more compensation
in two years
we don't have to increase
the compensation
we are prepared to invest
and risk
it's very likely
that the person will fly
it's related to a culture fit
where you try to understand
why the person is looking for a job
6 months without a job
desperate
not satisfied with our compensation
but will take it
and you will find someone else
I see it this way
you always try
to match your expectations
to what you are looking for
there are levels
there are budgets
and if you are off
hiring manager can win
we have to change the crypto
we have to change the crypto bubble
with a song
because
there are engineers
who managed
to reach a compensation
that was simply unimaginable
because it was
a lot of free crypto money
and then
there was a lot of disappointment
when you had to leave
I had a situation
when someone came and said
I want 7000 brutes per month
and the question was why
because I come from Great Britain
and it starts there
once in a lifetime opportunity
I am very happy
that you liked it
but
the reality
99% of other cases
we don't talk about those numbers
and now it is
a bad recognition
or you will go back to crypto
and try again
or you will agree
that if you earn 4000 brutes
you are a top 1% earner
that is the reality
I don't know what to say
if you are the first one to say
in a paid conversation
and it is so high
that you take away the opportunity
and it is better to wait
for your children to say
this was a question
on this topic
and it is interesting
these are just some basics
is it a stereotype
that it is very important
to be the first one to pay
and is it or not
how do you see it
my problem is
that
sometimes I exceed
most of the budget
and I won't have 6 interviews
in 4 months
and I say
thank you
but
if you don't exceed the budget
it is good
that you have a good idea
of what you want
you have to know what you want
you don't have to say it
but you have to know
what are your expectations
and if you don't have expectations
don't go crazy
because you won't know
what you want
it depends on the context
and it is important
to have a response
because it depends on the subject
on the seniority
and if you already know
what you want
it is much easier
to move forward
if not
I think
it is best to be realistic
you won't get 30%
more money
but
there are possibilities
be realistic
say what are your expectations
one principle
is to say
what do we pay now
and you expect so much more
another principle
is also
I recently received
from a professor
very interesting
MBA
what do you pay
how much do you say
first of all
you say a very high number
that means
for this position
I predict that you pay
as much as you can
psychologically
a very high amount
and then
ok
now I look at my experience
and seniority
so
you have your minimum
and maximum
and your salary is not your maximum
but it is chaos for this position
so you psychologically
give them an idea
that they give you more
than your minimum
I don't know
you can always make a domestic tax
yes
every company for the same tax
will have different budgets
and if you will
come to two different companies
you didn't make a domestic tax
you have to be interested
either through voice
what are your budgets
or you try to pay
through LinkedIn for jobs
or whatever
first of all
we don't talk about paying
we talk about paying
and these are issues
that are not a taboo
if something is recorded
or not recorded
but recorded
so let's make a domestic tax
I don't have an experience
that if a range is announced
that everyone comes
and wants the highest salary
I think it is true
that we break the stereotype
that companies have
if I write
that everyone wants the highest
and my employees will come
I don't have such experiences
on the other hand
I also have an experience
that there is always a range
after the range
as you said
everything happens
that if there is a range
for the right skillset
it is not there
what happens a lot
is that you come
to a workplace
and you think
that it would be better
for something else
that we haven't opened yet
there we can talk
and there are different interviews
and there is a new job
and a lot of times
a new job opens
because if you get
a super old guy
you won't give him
a clean slate
and a lot of times
when the right person came
everything changed
and the leaders
changed
that was my experience
it happens
but we can't say
that it is a rule
because in some cases
the politics is very strict
they look at the salary
they look at the situation
for the last night
it is different in other cases
what is the salary
in a clean workplace
is it a lot?
I would say that it is not a practice
it is not a practice
but still
there are some
roles
with a range
and it is hard
to go beyond that
but it is not
like it would be
publicly known
what is the salary
even in IT
I don't know if you know
it is too many jobs
three times
a product job
an engineer
a basic job
there can be a big difference
in salaries
between sales and IT
sales salary is very low
because it is related to
compensation
then it depends
if it is a yes or no
maybe
sales is not so much
because it can be
very good
compensation
support functions, accounting
marketing
there are standards
customer support
we all need to know
that engineering salaries
are above average
absolutely
this is also
my experience
that Slovenian engineers
are more conservative
than I said before
I have to work three times more
especially because
they get along with others
and engineering salaries
are above average
I agree
it is so rare
to get a job
in a software company
in Slovenia
we don't have much to do
we get bonuses
we get a good salary
we have a good
reputation
and a good personality
we don't complain
it is not a bad thing
it is nice
that if you work
somewhere else
you don't realize
that you are privileged
this is my intention
We are all privileged, not only IT people, but we need to maintain some kind of relativeness.
We are nearing the end, so I will only ask one last question.
It is a big one, but it will also be a guide for the next episodes.
You touched on this a little bit, so maybe we can conclude with this.
In addition to the salary, maybe there is no space, no budget for a higher salary.
Maybe this is not achievable.
What are the other things besides the salary, which can be more successful,
or which are often used by companies for, as you said, compensation, not just salary?
One thing we often forget is the allowance.
You can always say 5 more days.
If this is still your compensation, if you say for 20 more days an additional month,
which is almost 10% higher salary,
and of course some things that are not related to finance,
such as a car service or something similar,
which is more contextual, are things that you can talk about.
For companies it is easier because they have a budget for salary.
These things come from other budgets, education budget, etc.
You can always ask, you can talk.
The question is, what does it consist of?
And then they ask themselves on the basis of this,
what is the space available for me?
Some things go against you, some don't.
These are all my experiences.
In addition to bonuses and salaries,
this is not so widespread in Slovenia now, in my opinion.
Did I forget something?
Yes, maybe that.
Sometimes it is not necessary to have a high salary,
but let's say a company offers 13-14 salaries,
a reward for success,
and you have a plan at the end,
I don't know, 5 salaries can be more,
but if you don't ask, you won't know.
So it's also nice that maybe you start asking for a salary
before you increase the amount,
but what are the other benefits?
Do you see a lot of this in the Slovenian market,
that companies try to be more competitive with other things,
which benefits more than just business?
And is the candidate a business person?
I mean, has anyone ever replaced a company
because of ping-pong and good writers?
Or not at all?
It depends on how dissatisfied he was.
A lot of candidates who are very dissatisfied
will also go for less,
I think it's because of the full practice,
but it will also go for a little less,
and maybe for a little less stressful job,
maybe for a better performance,
I don't know, the benefits they will have.
So these things happen too.
I think that a lot of engineers and programmers are like that,
when they come to a level
where 500 euros more or less is not as important as
what kind of challenge they have,
what kind of team they have,
how they can develop in the future.
So different things happen.
A good indicator of these benefits
is the culture of the business,
what gives value.
I have a card for fitness, badminton,
I don't know what else.
It's not badminton,
but the card that makes the difference,
but it gives you a feeling
that they value you as a person,
in their head,
in a physical sense.
I have the feeling that a lot of companies
that can't compete with pay
compete with that culture.
Holistically.
We have, I don't know,
God,
as funny as it sounds,
businesses that have God
let you know that these are family businesses,
and if you have children in your head,
it won't be that bad.
And those who have children,
God is an indicator
that maybe you will feel better here,
because if my child is sick,
nobody will live for me,
because he has children and understands.
So I would say these are indicators,
that they have a culture,
value, and maybe something else,
because you work from 8 to 4,
as much as possible,
make money, make money,
but there are other tasks.
Or time,
that's a good shout-out.
I think that time is
extremely valuable,
and a lot of engineers
from my experience
are prepared to work
for a lot less than 4 days a week,
for example.
There are others
who only pay at the end,
but
are we already in Slovenia,
did we conquer it,
do we have a nice competitive
benefit and profit
in Slovenian businesses,
or is it still a little
connected to culture?
I think there is more to it.
When Corona came,
we had competitors,
and in one year
a lot of things happened.
Cups are no longer
rare, but we all have cups now.
So for me,
the pressure that came
from Zuni for the Slovenian frame,
some Slovenian companies
were a little scared.
So I'm not saying that it's
very good now and that everyone is there,
but I personally see a lot of progress
in the last 2-3 years.
We also let ourselves be trampled,
we know that the law has changed.
This is a big indicator
that your presence is not important,
your output or outcome is important,
and this is a big shift
in the mentality that
maybe 5-10 years
is not as widespread as it is today.
So that's my opinion.
I'm pretty happy today.
I was also here 4 years ago,
but today I'm a little happier.
I think that
when we talked about
how much the need for IT staff has increased,
all the companies could adapt a little.
Also working
on employer branding,
to hear the stories
how well they are doing.
We also have a very small company,
I don't know them at all,
but I'm worried about the employees.
Once again, I can say that
the names that are promoted
with it. So in practice,
the companies have made a lot of progress.
Thank you.
You're welcome.
It seems to me that it was
a great conversation.
I'll give you a little more time
for some closing thoughts,
if you want.
Miha, maybe
we'll start with you.
We are always a little paid.
If you work,
you always pay too much.
Let's talk.
First of all,
we won't talk about a taboo topic,
but let's talk about it
with some context and
importance, because
there is a lot of talk about it in Slovenia.
We always
talk about how much you pay.
Maybe one more reply
from my side.
Don't fall asleep.
Don't be 10 years in one company.
Look here,
what can you develop?
Tell us what
doesn't suit you.
If you think you have a change,
go talk to a recruiter.
I'm kidding.
If you can,
don't turn away.
We'll tell you in a light way.
Definitely,
don't fall asleep.
In fact, every employee is
responsible for his or her career.
If you leave it to others and
don't take care of your career,
we'll get in trouble.
We've covered it to the end.
Thank you for joining me.
For all our listeners,
you can sign up for the service
on kaldi.humanfrog.rif.se,
which is sponsored by
this podcast,
which is also
in a collection of Slovenian companies
in the IT space.
So,
thank you very much
once again for this interview.
And of course,
we invite all our viewers
and listeners
to leave us some feedback,
follow-up questions,
and we'll try
to answer them
in the next episodes.
So,
one more baby under the train
to wrap up.
Have a nice evening.
Thank you.