How did you come up with the idea of doing a podcast?
Well, at some point our jingle comes together
and then the conversation starts.
If you want to have a podcast, you have to have a jingle.
We bought it online.
I thought it was a proper podcast.
I also added lighting to make it look more proper.
The problem with my intro is that at the beginning
I completely kill the guest and then I leave.
I've been preparing and talking for half an hour
and that's why the intro is so awkward.
The idea was to greet people first.
Then I'll say hello.
Where's the camera?
It's easier for me.
I'll say hello and then I'll try to introduce myself.
Hello.
That was the most awkward intro I've ever done.
Okay, I'll try to continue.
Today we're in Maribor.
I wanted to start the break we did during the summer
with some new energy.
Let's try to have an easy conversation with senior engineers.
I've been thinking a lot about who are the top engineers
at Steyrsk, who I know and respect
and who would have something interesting to say.
I decided to talk to you.
I've known you for a long time and I know you a bit less.
At the beginning it was important to introduce myself
to the people I know.
I know you from Databox.
We've been together for about 2 years.
I don't know exactly when you came.
I was there from day one.
You worked for Databox.
Yes, I worked for Databox.
I came on a trip and they said there's a guy in Bulgaria
who works for iOS.
He has an Apple logo, he's young.
He was the poster boy of Databox.
He was the only one with a widescreen screen
so he could see the phone.
And I'm still the same.
The director always speaks nicely.
If I understood correctly, you were the one
who created the iOS app for Databox.
That was the first version.
Yes, I'd love to go into details.
Long story short, Databox was Zepelin.
The previous iOS engineer who worked for Zepelin
quit when they decided to pivot from Zepelin to Databox.
I was 19 at the time.
I was a huge iOS geek.
I was lucky to have a colleague.
My job was to develop the app from scratch.
The 1.0 version was just my job.
It was our flagship product
that kept the company going.
Can you tell us a bit about the time
when you were developing the app?
At the time, Swift wasn't out yet.
Objective-C was out.
iPhone was out.
It was August 2013.
Objective-C was out in August.
It was a milestone for us
when we switched from scale morphism to flat design.
We were using Wave,
and we had a flat UI.
It was a miracle.
I had a plan to find a geek in the summer.
I wanted to go out and do things.
It was a great challenge.
It was the most complex
and demanding project so far.
It was a great challenge
and a lot of hype.
What are you most interested in?
We'll come back to Inuta.
I know Inuta.
At some point,
someone wrote that there's a company in Slovenia
that works with Erlang.
They're trying to set up
a MySQL base
for Erlang.
There's a wizard in Maribor
who works with Erlang.
That's my first intro to Inuta.
Good intro.
Yeah, cool.
I'm from FACS.
You think about
what to do.
You have a bunch of jobs
like Java, C-Sharp, etc.
There was a company in Maribor.
A professor from FACS recommended it to me.
He gave me a code for an interview.
They told me they work with Erlang.
Wow.
It's an absurd thing
when you come from FACS and know nothing about it.
It was like
Sergey and Denis
are still experts
in Erlang.
In this environment,
you can learn about Erlang
at such a high level.
It's the most interesting language ever.
You can learn things there
that other languages can't.
I got to know Inuta
when I came to Ljubljana
for a lecture.
We talked about Erlang.
How to write programs in Erlang.
I think it was Ruby Crowd.
I know we were all like,
what the fuck?
Even now,
concepts are completely different.
Erlang's success
and the languages that are popular now,
like Golang,
are the basic concepts of building programs
that you are capable of.
They are ideal for machines,
for full processors,
so you can compete.
Do you know Erlang?
Not really.
I know the concept,
but the multi-training structure is terrible.
It's a bit like the Ektor model.
Even in Swift.
Yes, in Standard Label.
Why?
For isolation and multi-training.
Ektor isolates your access
when it comes to multi-training.
It's the same on iPhones.
Phones have full cores,
but Hyper-Trading on them
means more threads per core.
Parallelization is the only useful thing.
Objective-C sheet
had CS add-ons,
so you could manage all the threads yourself.
In Swift, in Standard Label,
you can't just fuck it up.
It's a 40-year-old concept.
Speaking of debates,
can you tell us
what's the point of doing
a quick course on Erlang?
What's the point?
Why would someone want to learn Erlang?
What are the examples?
You need a certain level of reliability,
and the expressiveness of the language
is very high.
Even if you use
a design property of the language,
and use it as you should,
to always write
in a correct flow,
and let the code fall through.
Let it crash, for example.
When computers are growing
in the number of CPUs,
and you want to use all of them,
Erlang helps a lot.
Erlang builds
a scheduler for each core of the processor,
and then it aligns the processes
inside the Erlang virtual machine.
You don't have to do anything by yourself.
Each process will take the same amount
of execution time.
The programs you write
are always hierarchical.
You have a supervisor,
who can start new processes,
and they always communicate
by sending and receiving messages,
because they have their own mailbox.
Each message can be responded to,
and a new process can be created,
or it can fall apart,
because the business logic
doesn't go through,
and let the hierarchy crash
in a higher process,
which decides what will be done.
The whole program is built
for one task.
I'll give you a practical example
of why this language was created
in the 1940s.
It was for Ericsson.
Ericsson managed
the telephone switches,
and if we have a conversation,
the conversation falls apart
and the switch can't affect
the conversation of someone else.
If you work in a CEO,
where you have a shared global memory stack,
you can have problems with that.
They built a language
from a purely practical example,
which is still extremely popular.
WhatsApp was created
for Goldman Sachs trading,
VocaLink MasterCard
for Intermediate Payment Systems.
There are huge problems with that.
This problem is,
for example, today we have
a micro-service architecture,
where you develop your app,
you have different services,
and then one service falls apart
or you replace it.
From your perspective,
is it a better Erlang model,
for example?
For people who will listen to this,
I get similar concepts from micro-services.
If you look at micro-services,
they are applications.
Then you can look at Erlang processes,
which are not system processes,
but micro-processes.
Or micro-services.
So that nothing crashes.
Everything fits together very well,
so that you can really
work with a reliable system.
We forgot that at zero.
30 minutes on the hard drive.
It's cool.
For example, if you are deploying
an Erlang in a production,
does that mean that you put
the same server on top of the Erlang VM
and then you deploy a binary
in that gross?
Or do you still communicate with the whole server?
One cool thing about Erlang
is that it was meant
to write distributed systems.
To write distributed systems
that can be distributed.
At this level,
you need more than one server
if you want reliability.
You can cluster them.
One good thing about it
is that these processes
that have names
are location-transparent.
You can send a message
to a local or geographic process
at the other end of the world,
and in Erlang cluster
you can send a message
without knowing the difference.
Looking at how much experience
you have with Erlang and the system
that is 40 years old,
what is your take on Kubernetes today?
Do you think it's a re-engineering
of some concepts?
No.
Those concepts in other languages
didn't exist yet.
You have a bunch of horizontal
Node.js applications,
but you won't be able to reach
the reliability in a different way.
I know that those parts
are extremely slow.
They're just OK.
In the first version of Erlang,
could you send a message
location-independently?
I don't know about that.
I worked on version 13,
and now I think it's 26.
It was always like that.
I have an interesting observation.
I'm not sure if you can hear me.
I think that
there are some new languages
or new technologies.
For example, that the language
is top-level.
But you also need an ecosystem,
a library,
which will contribute to the ecosystem.
One came from Swift.
Swift is compatible with Objective-C,
and Objective-C is compatible with C.
In my opinion,
Swift, Objective-C,
and a bunch of other C++ languages
are just front-end for the same compiler.
I don't know how much Swift supports.
I know you have a back-end language.
The answer to your question is
interoperability is a big deal for Swift.
You have to assemble it and combine it.
That's the whole point.
That would be my question.
What is the ecosystem of all libraries?
Do I connect the system
with a traditional Oracle,
Postgres, MySQL base,
and use the whole library?
Or does it have to be separate?
I don't know about Erlang,
but all the cryptographic tasks,
the language would be used in a different way
if you had to run those things from the inside.
It could grow into Rust or C.
I'll put it this way.
If you go to AWS
or to Google Cloud,
to the GCP,
the SDK is for 5 languages,
but Erlang is not.
No, it's not.
You can write Lambda in Erlang.
I heard you have an original package manager.
Do you have one?
Yes, I do.
Now Elixir is closer to people.
Is Elixir an abstraction of Erlang?
Yes.
It's like a derivative of the same language,
the same principles,
the same syntax.
Elixir is compiled in Erlang LST,
and that's it.
You get all the functions of the language.
You can use it in the standard library.
Since Erlang is less popular,
Elixir is probably more popular.
Ok, cool.
Let's talk a bit more about Erlang.
I have a question.
Rust and C++.
Rust would say that C++ is 20th century,
that's what Elixir sounds like.
It's hard to ask,
because I don't know enough.
I find it interesting
that when you build a standard application
in Erlang or Elixir,
it's nothing unusual
to have a couple of million processes
inside the system that communicate.
On an ordinary hardware server.
How much resource does it require?
On a 16 GB machine,
you can have 20 million processes.
Even in milliseconds,
you start a new process.
One more thing.
I can give you a parallel with Akka.
That's my intro to Actor Model.
It's Akka.
It's on top of Java.
Akka made a framework
for Actor Model in Scalia.
They made it so it can be used in Java.
Binding was supported for both languages.
I think it's still supported.
Why didn't you go directly to Erlang?
Huh? Why didn't I go to Erlang?
Because of the thing I mentioned before.
At the end of the day,
I don't want to write libraries
or have a database driver.
If I want interoperability,
if I use Akka,
I can use JVM and all the libraries
from the ecosystem.
Erlang-X has been open-sourced
for over 20 years.
There's a lot of community and libraries.
You have a lot of support.
In Actor Model,
I think the whole concept
can be viewed
as a living basis.
People model actors.
The real world tries
to model actors.
If we have a chat,
during the chat,
the messages will change
with other actors.
If we have a chat room,
there will be an Indian actor.
It's a very simple mental picture
of the real world.
For example,
Joe Armstrong used
the standard language.
Joe Armstrong is deceased
for 50 years.
He wrote that
all object languages
violate the rules of physics.
When you model programs
or architectures,
you always have to share memory.
If you want something from another object,
it has to have some properties
or values.
Erlang simulates
a different world.
If I want something from you,
I have to ask you,
you answer me,
I save the information
and I can do whatever I want with it.
You don't send a message
but you invoke it.
Same, same, but different.
When you have a concurrency,
you want to share
the same information.
Everyone tries
to get a share.
It's more time-consuming
and more complex.
An interesting challenge
for beginners
is to send a message
and you can send it back.
The problem is
when I send a message
and then I wait for you to respond.
How do you implement it?
There are a lot of situations
where you have to
trade-off later.
That's interesting
because for the new generation of programmers
there are so many concepts to understand
when you're learning.
When we were learning programming,
we had a single-core processor
and we had to try to yield
with a fork or whatever.
It was 40 years ago
but for a normal person
who started programming
we didn't have to learn multi-threading
or async.
I see that you have
some of these concepts.
When I design for a more
processor-parallel world
I will get feedback
and there are ways
how JavaScript can be used.
For example, PHP.
It's getting cold.
These are languages
that have difficulties
in a world where
more computing power is needed.
Unless we have some
PHP circuits.
what is FPM, then we will have more processes and some other collaborations around it.
In my opinion, the problem is that it was added as an afterthought.
New languages ​​appeared, which had it out of the box supported,
and since it was added in the first version, it was also thought out
and incorporated into the language in such a way that it did not bother others.
In other languages, everything was C++, and everyone is still bothered by ASYNC patterns today.
They were just added as an afterthought in more modern libraries,
and then you always have the opportunity to write in the old way,
in the wrong way, depending on some architecture that you have in mind.
In my opinion, this is a bigger problem than the fact that they did not support it, and then they did.
Now you can make a drink of water, because my next question will be a bomb.
My next question will be, how do you explain to your parents what kind of blog you are starting now?
I think the word blockchain has a negative connotation, because it is...
A mortgage?
Yes, I mean...
From one perspective, it may not be the right look at it,
but on the other hand, if you look a little more broadly at what it is,
or in which areas it is moving, it makes a lot more sense.
I see it as a system of integrity.
The world is made up of institutions that project integrity into the world,
and you use these institutions, from banks to public authorities,
because a lot of money is also used for audits to project integrity,
and you use these systems.
Blockchain in itself democratizes integrity.
It tells you, okay, here's a ledger, you can issue some programs,
you can send some transactions, whether they are monetary or just a state change.
But the integrity is in your hands.
It is in your hands in such a way that you can always join this system and say,
no, I will go from the beginning to the end, to the last block of the blockchain,
and I will see if this system really has the integrity it is talking about,
and I will process all the transactions once again.
Then you have your ledger locally, and you can guarantee that it has the integrity it is talking about.
Are you a fool, Vado?
No, but I've been working on it for so long that you have 50 or 100 interviews a month.
Not all DevOps and programmers are from the blockchain.
To be fair, if you follow me on Twitter,
on the X, sorry, if you're on the X, I'll put the hashtag in.
I'll put the link below.
Your posts are very, as Jan said, critical.
For example, when we started this podcast,
people were telling us for a while that there is no one to talk about blockchain and crypto.
At some point, it was very difficult to decide,
because now that everyone has migrated to AI, it's easier because there is less hype.
No, but I see that you are constantly with your integrity in this technology.
Capital always attracts a bunch of people who want to do good things with it,
and a bunch of people who don't drink water and don't even drink water for investment.
But generally speaking,
the consequences of all the capital in the blockchain will be good things.
From new cryptography, from systems that will be democratized,
that will be decentralized.
Do you think people believe in it?
I have so many replicas here, I'm constantly jumping from one thing to another.
I agree.
To a large extent, I agree with what you said.
But the problem is that there are two issues here.
I agree that as a source of truth, the blockchain is a good thing,
because it is also transparent, etc.
Which is one of the problems that the blockchain decided to address.
Everything else was built on top of that.
But on the other hand, it is a completely digital asset,
a book that doesn't even exist physically.
It doesn't have a real power projection in the world.
Someone will be able to enforce what is written in that book.
We have now solved the problem that we have a transparent book,
which was certainly not tampered with.
But when it comes to projecting hard power into the real world,
then an institution will stand behind it,
meaning you have a potential single point of failure.
But you still hope that the government will solve it.
I said that, at least they ask us in politics.
And maybe in half an hour.
In half an hour.
But that's what I see.
I know what you want to say,
but even today there are a lot of things that are purely digital.
Most of the money exists in a digital form,
as it exists in a paper form.
But the government is based on money, right?
Banks.
OK, but when I talked about integrity,
banks go through some stress tests, audits,
Deloitte comes in and does a lot of their processes.
And their certificates are then sent to the next institution,
which looks at those certificates and says,
OK, this new KBM has integrity and is a good bank,
and they are liquid and all that stuff.
But these are all centralized institutions,
which don't do anything that can't be calculated,
that can't be turned into a program.
And to certify that program,
or give it some cryptographic power,
they really couldn't steal their books,
because otherwise they wouldn't be able to do it.
I don't know any more people who say they have it.
So power is exactly in this democratization,
integrity, I think.
Through transparency.
Yes.
Then there are other things,
for example, the blockchain,
perhaps not directly sent,
but the consequences of it,
the cryptography that comes,
zero-knowledge cryptography,
where you participate locally
in a way that you won't leak your data
on the Internet or in the world.
You will only prove things.
For example, a very banal example
that will be very close to you,
is that you pay taxes,
and the fact that you pay an approximate amount of taxes,
you fulfill some tasks, evidence,
they have a view,
if you are a child,
they have a view of your bank account,
if you are a physical person,
they don't,
but you say you deserve it.
They can get a constant amount of data
about you and your income.
These tasks can be done in such a way
that you never give any manager
any details, your personal details,
about your income,
and you show them proof
that they can trust,
and say, OK, everything was done according to our rules.
It is a kind of layer,
a set of layers that you talked about.
In the end, you only know what the result is,
and you know that the whole process was audited,
or chained,
and you don't know in detail
how the final result came out.
Because you trust mathematicians and cryptographers.
I think this is a better connection than the problem
that blockchain is solving at the moment.
The same Peaches 2829,
or the same screenshot of the same time bank,
or another bailout.
I think this is the only problem that it is currently solving.
Most of the others that blockchain would solve at the moment
are either an institution
that will project hard power into the world,
or I just do everything.
Full disclaimer for the listeners,
I have been preparing this for 2.12 for a long time,
and I still believe in blockchain as it is.
But for me it is exploitation,
where 99.9% of the projects and things
that exist on the blockchain today,
are not used.
Yes, but that does not mean that this exploitation is stopped,
but this system is not exploitable,
it is not different from any other.
That is true.
I would describe it as a technology in captivity,
because the banks we have today
did not emerge in the 15th century,
as we now have a blockchain,
but they have developed over the centuries
to the level we need today,
and in my opinion, crypto still needs some time.
I think that banks will eventually
not be able to do anything
based on the systems
that are based on the blockchain.
Maybe they won't be able to communicate
and talk about it in the beginning?
No, it will be all present and not relevant at all.
So we have an oracle in our base,
we have a blockchain,
and it will be business as usual.
Isn't that a goal?
Yes, that is a good benefit.
But again, no matter how much you have to work,
we know that you have to.
But if there is evidence,
it will be proof that it is time to work
and it will reinforce people on the blockchain.
If you have something to take.
I agree, but that's exactly what I want to say.
I agree that writing will be more transparent
but you still have to work
and someone has to decide.
Let's talk a little bit about
the application of technology.
Technology is a business logic,
if you want,
and not everything is straight.
Somewhere there is a barrier that ends.
If you download Postgres,
you have a good base,
but you don't have business logic.
But that's a good point.
Let's go one more layer from the blockchain.
If I understand correctly,
you also do a lot with Ethereum, right?
Exclusively.
Exclusively with Ethereum.
Can you introduce it a little bit?
If we talked about Erlang VM,
Ethereum is also a virtual machine.
If I understand correctly.
It is.
And you pay for the use of this virtual machine.
Can you tell us more about it?
I don't want to ask more questions.
IBM is also a good company.
Now,
you can look at Ethereum or at the blockchain
as if you were on a fax machine
and you were doing procedures.
You learned to write procedures on a pencil.
I find this very interesting
because Ethereum roadmap has changed a bit
because they wanted to shard,
execution and so on.
Now it's really a base
and a data availability base
for all possible scalability approaches.
What is the problem with Ethereum?
Tell us what the advantage is.
Before we go to the distance.
The advantage is that
you can write a program.
The program will deploy to the chain.
It will live there
and anyone can use it.
Can you see the code?
You can see the code.
Explorer always shows bytecode.
If you verify the program
then you have the source.
This source can be complex
and then people use
some applications
that pull the enemy
and steal their money.
From this point of view,
you have to be careful
with which things you deal with.
In general, it is a transparent system
that allows you to deploy programs.
Back in the day,
you could get a Solidity contract
and find exploits.
It was full of hacks.
These simple contracts
were hacked through chatGPTN.
This is the reliability
of people who are users of Ethereum
and define these contracts.
These are mathematical errors
or logical bugs.
Division by zero.
As a programmer,
when you write another code
and you make a bug,
similar problems are here.
Transparency, which is offered by EVM,
is phenomenal.
If we were there
for a basic blockchain transaction,
you can verify the history of calls
and what happened.
There is a level of abstraction
above the blockchain,
but it doesn't threaten humanity.
If you offer functionality on EVM,
you can make a bug
and exploit it.
Since you have a copy of the chain,
you can localize it
and make a rollback
with the entire interaction
with the contract.
It depends on the input and output
of the state,
but you can see it in the beginning.
You can see everything.
Let's say we use Ethereum
as the backbone of our bank.
Everyone can see the contracts
that we will write.
Everyone sees inputs and outputs.
Before we hid everything
and later it was public.
That's why you want to be sure
that the contracts you have don't have a bug.
No, that's not the case.
The privacy of the enterprise is not.
People are aware of this
and work on it.
Exactly.
If there are zero-proof systems,
we can't do anything.
Now my question is,
what are the advantages of Ethereum?
Ethereum is a decentralized blockchain
that optimizes itself
against decentralization.
As many people as possible
can participate
in this distributed database.
Is it a data-driven database?
Yes, it is.
That's why Ethereum has four limitations.
How many transactions can be processed,
how fast are the blocks,
what size are the blocks,
because the design is designed
so that everyone can participate
on their laptop in the ecosystem
and you can be a staker
and validate the blockchain.
This is a penalty for performance.
Part of the roadmap was
sharding and execution sharding.
This turned out to be
an extremely difficult problem.
In 2018
Vitalik announced
that this roadmap would change
and that Ethereum would go
in the direction of
roll-up scaling.
This is what I mentioned before,
where Ethereum becomes
the database and data availability layer
for these roll-ups.
Roll-ups are basically
a container for Ethereum.
150 years ago
we invented a container
for this roll-up.
Now you can do
a lot of things
on the same roll-up
and unload them much faster
and the roll-up can move forward.
These are roll-ups.
Roll-ups are external systems
in Ethereum
that do not yet have
but will have
the security of Ethereum itself
with economic games
and cryptography.
Is it 2D?
Yes, it's 2D.
I'm specifically familiar
with optimistic roll-ups.
Optimistic roll-ups work
in the same way as
execution clients in Ethereum
and then they modify it a little
specifically for bedrock.
Optimistic roll-ups
give a small footprint
on the code of the execution client
and then process transactions,
batch them,
compress them
and then post them
on Ethereum as call data.
The economic part of all this
is that it enables you
to use the system
in your interest
to participate
in the network
as a validator.
The validator takes the transactions
directly from us or our roll-up
or takes them directly from Ethereum
and recomputes them.
It takes each transaction separately
and applies it to its ledger.
Then there is another component
in this roll-up called the proposer.
The proposer takes the batches
of all the batches,
and the validators do the same
and compare the Merkle hash root
that was posted on Ethereum
and their local one.
They say, hey, everything is OK
or hey, something went wrong
and then they play the dispute game.
The dispute game is where you challenge
a specific entity
for a specific transaction
and you want to prove
that you beat someone.
The economic part of all this
is that the sequencer
can stake, the challenger
can stake in ETH or USD
and play this game
or get a stake from someone else.
This is one approach.
The other approach is
zero-knowledge roll-ups
which I can talk about if you want.
Now I will calm down a bit
and I will say
if I didn't have a job
and I was one of those 50
who interviewed for positions
what would I ask?
How do you check people you interview?
What position?
I'm already dissed in blockchain.
If I wasn't dissed in blockchain
what position?
Software architect or senior engineer?
He has a lot of experience
but he is a blockchain skeptic.
One interesting thing about these roll-ups
is that in the process of development
some things are missing.
Decentralization of the roll-up is missing.
If you look at Ethereum
and the clients
who chase Ethereum
they are isolated entities
and these clients are not reliable.
Postgres, RoxDB, LevelDB
file-based storage
and the client's base reliability
is not at any entity.
but in decentralization, everyone has a copy of the data,
and that data goes through peer-to-peer,
through the entire network, and you have a copy of that ledger.
So Jan has to know Java.
Well, yes.
And then the interesting question is,
as an entity that develops a role,
and is in the process of decentralizing it,
we only have one copy of that sequencer,
how can we design that role in AWS Cloud,
and the applications we deploy,
so that their storage is fully reliable,
and that if a region in AWS goes down,
so that we don't lose that disk and then...
Oops.
Blockchain.
Yes, I mean, blockchain is not a solution because...
I mean, it's not a solution because we post things on Ethereum.
We post those things on Ethereum with a lag.
And they're still parked, or they're cut off.
Yes, you can decompress them and re-apply them.
But there's always a lag, because you're collecting...
Our direct cost as a company is all the transactions
that we post on Layer 1, that's our cost,
which is paid by the FIA to the user.
But there's always a lag.
There can be 15-20 minutes of transactions
that we collect in batches and then post them,
which are not there yet.
You have them in your local storage.
And what's the catch here?
Today, in the cloud, you know that stateless applications are designed.
And then you have those bases that allow you to replicate it
in your own design.
You don't have that here.
What can you do for a stateful application to be safe?
Yes, Jan, what do you think?
Sure.
Wait, I forgot, now I'm on a job interview.
This is such a strange place for me.
This is, for example, when we employ infrastructure people.
It's good to know such things.
But what's your stack?
Do you do it in C, C++, Go?
Execution client, Golang, Typescript.
And you can't do it in NDA?
No, everything we do is open source.
This research part that we do for zero-knowledge things.
I thought it was brilliant, technically very interesting.
But do you have a side or do you develop it with your own capital
and as some kind of research?
Or is that an approximate question?
No, it's a great question.
All these roles are actually developer platforms.
You have retail users who come to manage your Uniswap deployment,
because there is an exchange there, and they trade.
These can be purely users.
They can be an enterprise fund that comes to invest in you.
On the other hand, you have projects that are purely companies
that manage your platform because of some features you have.
But all this is permissionless.
You don't have to ask anything if you can deploy, right?
Go ahead.
Can you tell us what Layer 2 is in Ethereum?
If I could say that at the beginning, that this is Layer 2.
Are you an optimistic role? Or a zero-knowledge...
I would say the same thing.
Ethereum and blockchain, the big technical challenge of these technologies
are too late to be able to write some transactions in real time
to validate them correctly.
We need to build a technology, an abstraction layer above Ethereum,
above this basic technology, and then it's called Layer 2.
Layer 2 are applications that operate outside of Ethereum,
and then part of Ethereum...
Am I interpreting this correctly?
Yes, everything is part of Ethereum.
Physics hasn't changed here.
You start a startup with a monolithic application,
and then you set up nodes, and then you get pages.
Something needs to be changed, because it's too late now,
and then you start selling out some things, for example.
There is no approach.
I would describe it lightly,
if I remember correctly.
It's like this.
In the middle is the blockchain,
the base that provides you with the truth state, the ground state.
Ethereum EBM is a script for nodes that run on this base.
It means that you are prepared for your virtual machine to have transparency.
Then you have L2,
which can be domain-specific for nodes.
It doesn't have to be necessary just to increase their throughput.
You can take a page, sell it out,
create a high-performance app for that specific task.
For the most part, these are transactions and so on.
For example, if you want Bitcoin for Lightning and so on.
And then, when you are satisfied with your work,
on your L2, you conclude something,
and then you start processing it on L1,
that is, on EVM.
Hard.
It's more light.
Yes, that's true.
One thing that is important here is that this L1, like Ethereum,
must have some ability to execute programs,
because otherwise you can't control this security.
Otherwise, these L2 systems can't be secure.
You have nothing from the blockchain.
You can use them as storage,
but you also need a fairly powerful ability
to execute these proofs or cryptographies,
when you need to prove something,
regarding the system that is alerted.
Okay.
Now, to be time-cautious.
Jan, I still see you as an IOS, Apple superstar.
Maybe that's why you won't go to the blockchain.
Or maybe you will, but I don't know.
I mean, let's go to the blockchain.
I also wanted to talk about these contracts and so on.
I find it interesting.
We really got into this.
I will try to get this debate out of the way a bit.
We probably already lost a lot of listeners
because we skipped most of it.
Okay.
I will take this point and say that
if you find these people interesting,
if you would like us to continue
doing high-quality production of technology talks
with interesting speakers,
if you want us to be a technology company,
please support us on Patreon.
There you will also get perks as a premium subscriber to Patreon,
for example, to get pre-premium subscriptions
on all public channels,
and also, I don't know, video, audio,
and buy some perks there.
You can support us there.
It will help us a lot.
It is also possible in Grodno
because of the support of two companies.
The company Trifas and Humanfrog support us.
So thank you for that.
That's some kind of commercial aspect
that I have to add.
Look, stop.
Advertisement.
Maybe I could say at the beginning
that if you are watching this on YouTube,
go there and subscribe.
I agree that at the beginning
everyone was like 15, 15, 15, 15.
Ad block.
Let's learn.
Fun fact.
You can also buy a premium subscription on YouTube.
For VPN, you give the country to Argentina
or some third world country,
and there is a monthly subscription, like $1.
And then there is an ad,
and you can take a family package,
and you have like 5 accounts.
Life hack.
Just saying.
Damn.
Amazing.
More VPN.
I don't need them
because they are ultra-commercialized
and need full advertising.
So no.
Someone who is a little less known.
But yeah.
Sorry about that.
No, it's cool.
It's cool.
Now...
Another fun fact.
You can also...
I had a pie hole on my home network.
And you can also configure a proxy
so that YouTube, ad,
shoots out.
I mean, everyone comes to my network
and then blocks the domain.
Pie hole.
Today...
Okay.
Is this legal?
No, it's not.
It was brought in.
Yeah, okay.
Then it's not a problem.
Hey, I had here...
Fun fact.
I wrote to you.
I was watching you.
We've known each other for a while.
I wrote to you.
Fun fact.
It says...
TNT.
Autotemperature.
Yeah.
I'll put it here.
Then I have here written...
Civilian.
Maybe...
I don't know what it stands for.
But...
I might make a segway out of it.
When you were my partner in a company...
You were my boss before.
Before...
No, when I was already your boss.
There was...
Every year, at the end of...
At the beginning of December,
Advent of Code starts.
I think you'll know that.
And I challenged the team.
The one who solves Advent of Code
gets a jacket.
And...
And Jan is...
Slop trade.
And Jan replaced a December
with a jacket bottle.
Which he also got, of course.
Because he solved the whole Advent of Code.
Which language?
Which language was it?
I think it was Swift.
But I took Rust.
I'm not sure.
I worked with Rust for a year.
Will you...
First tell me what it is.
Yeah, sure.
I think it's weird
when we went ultra in-depth.
I have to fool people here.
But...
In short, yeah.
Advent of Code is...
Like Advent Calendar.
But instead of 25-day chocolates,
there are...
Programming problems.
I don't know.
There are algorithms and such
for development.
And on December 1st,
it starts on easy.
On the 25th...
I mean, on the 10th,
you don't want to run into it.
And then, yeah.
There are always more complex problems.
And that's it.
Advent of Code is actually...
It works every time.
And...
It's a little more mechanical.
Yeah, sure.
So, yeah.
I mean, for anyone,
programming is a hobby.
You like to deal with complex problems.
But the idea of Advent of Code is
that you have a page
where a problem is submitted.
And it's purely...
How would I put it?
Logically described in a way
that anyone can understand it.
But looking for a solution
is complex.
I mean,
it's not based on the fact
that you can use any language.
They give you some input.
I don't know.
A banal example
of such a very initial problem was...
We have a person
who drives a car.
And every time
one of the lines is higher,
we have an overlap.
And every time
one of the lines is lower,
we have an overlap.
And then,
they give you some input
on the line
where the person
finished the line.
And that's at the beginning.
So, basically,
you can just...
Command F,
and then look
at how many are overlapping
and how many are overlapping.
You calculate the difference.
I mean,
that's how it starts.
It doesn't depend on the language.
It doesn't depend on
your problem solver.
You can solve
any problem
any time.
And all problems
are based in this way.
And then,
it's up to you
how you're going to solve it
as quickly as possible.
Because the first 100
also get some points.
And then...
In December,
you have an Amazon interview.
Yeah,
with the fact that...
Yeah, basically, yeah.
I mean,
now...
Advent of Code,
I'll put the link below.
Now,
if you're on those
Slovenian
technical social networks,
you also have people
who become
solutions
for that.
Yeah.
And then,
you also solve
at the beginning
with a lot of enthusiasm.
And it's very...
Complexity falls.
And those who
go very far,
prepare themselves
a lot.
Yeah.
I mean,
I see it
as a hobby.
I would describe it
like this.
The first five days,
people still argue
with those
who have a faster algorithm,
those who have
more performance.
It's the same.
There,
after 10-15 days,
you're like,
yeah, I solved it,
but it took me half a day
for that.
And you're just happy.
And in practice,
it's exponential.
Yeah.
But it's like...
Because I got the feeling
that it's like this.
Something is easier,
then harder,
and a little...
Yeah, all in all...
That's what I experienced.
I mean, all in all,
I don't know if the problems
are easier,
but I don't know.
It's hard to describe.
Anyway,
every year it's a different
topic and
you don't follow the problems
exactly,
but there,
I would say,
after the tenth day,
you still have two or three
problems that are relatively
simple.
The rest,
you're still chasing
until December.
And I also see that
the problem is also...
I mean,
the problem.
For me,
there was a problem
because it opens
at 6 AM
or 5 AM
in our time.
6 AM.
Yeah,
and if I go to bed
in the morning,
then I have a family,
a job,
and everything.
And then,
I don't know,
at 10 PM
I have to solve it.
I don't know how
the fans were waiting for you.
At 6 AM?
Yeah, yeah.
Do you have to do it
until the end of the day?
No,
I mean,
I have to do my thing
until 10 AM,
and then go to sleep
on the next morning.
But I didn't have
to do it till that time.
You just have to do
it in one or two weeks,
or something like that,
then the problem opens
globally.
Yes.
And then,
the first hundred
are the ones
solving the problem
the fastest.
And then,
it doesn't depend
on where you are.
I just remember
that I woke up
at 6 AM every morning
and then the first thing
on my head changed.
Yeah, yeah.
I was just
a brain-scrambler
until 10 AM,
11 AM,
until 12 AM,
I was just doing that
and then I started
doing other things.
Ah, okay.
Yeah.
What would be
my shift?
No, no,
it wasn't like that.
No, no, it wasn't.
Sorry, it wasn't.
Please explain.
What is our output?
No, no,
it doesn't really
matter anymore.
The company
will clarify it,
probably.
I was in the same company
as back then.
I started as someone
who would be
the leader of mobile development
and would develop
a mobile application.
Which one will it be?
We'll see.
You're right,
you've seen everything.
The main thing is
that we prepared
for a while,
and maybe
we wouldn't have
a mobile application
and then
Jan started
some other things
that were exciting.
The only thing
that wasn't.
Look,
I don't know,
I don't think
you've come across
that.
I have a lot
of questions.
Everything we've
talked about,
you're a top
programmer,
I mean,
I would ask you
if you could
answer me
on how
you train,
or how
you make
sure
you're
sharp
in your
skill sets,
or you could
tell me
what
project
you have
that would
be suitable
for that.
I'll ask
you first.
How does
Ino train?
I wanted
him to
explain
to me
that
he's
a
genius,
and
he's
a
genius
in
general.
And
he would
explain
that
he's
a
genius
in
general.
And
he would
explain
that
he's
a genius
in
general.
With
all
the
problems
and
optimization.
He
would
explain
that
he's
a
genius
in
general.
With
all
the
problems
and
optimization.
He
would
explain
that
he's
a
genius
in
general.
With
all
the
problems
and
optimization.
He
would
explain
that
he's
a
genius
in
general.
With
all
the
problems
and
optimization.
He
would
explain
that
he's
a
genius
in
general.
With
all
the
problems
and
optimization.
He
would
explain
that
he's
a
genius
in
general.
With
all
the
problems
and
optimization.
He
would
explain
that
he's
a
genius
in
general.
With
all
the
problems
and
optimization.
He
would
explain
that
he's
a
genius
in
general.
With
all
the
problems
and
optimization.
He
would
explain
that
he's
a
genius
in
general.
With
all
the
problems
and
optimization.
He
would
explain
that
he's
a
genius
in
general.
With
all
the
problems
and
optimization.
He
would
explain
that
he's
a
genius
in
general.
With
all
the
problems
and
optimization.
He
would
explain
that
he's
a
genius
in
general.
With
all
the
problems
and
optimization.
He
would
explain
that
he's
a
genius
in
general.
With
all
the
problems
and
optimization.
He
would
explain
that
he's
a
genius
in
general.
With
all
the
problems
and
optimization.
He
would
explain
that
he's
a
genius
in
general.
With
all
the
problems
and
optimization.
He
would
explain
that
he's
a
genius
in
general.
With
all
the
problems
and
optimization.
He
would
explain
that
he's
a
genius
in
general.
With
all
the
problems
and
optimization.
He
would
explain
that
he's
a
genius
in
general.
With
all
the
problems
and
optimization.
He
would
explain
that
he's
a
genius
in
general.
With
all
the
problems
and
optimization.
He
would
explain
that
he's
a
genius
in
general.
With
all
the
problems
and
optimization.
He
would
explain
that
he's
a
genius
in
general.
With
all
the
problems
and
optimization.
He
would
explain
that
he's
a
genius
in
general.
With
all
the
problems
and
optimization.
He
would
explain
that
he's
a
genius
in
general.
With
all
the
problems
and
optimization.
He
would
explain
that
he's
a
genius
in
general.
With
all
the
problems
and
optimization.
He
would
explain
that
he's
a
genius
in
general.
With
all
the
problems
and
optimization.
He
would
explain
that
he's
a
genius
in
general.
With
all
the
problems
and
optimization.
He
would
explain
that
he's
a
genius
in
general.
With
all
the
problems
and
optimization.
He
would
explain
that
he's
a
genius
in
general.
With
all
the
problems
and
optimization.
He
would
explain
that
he's
a
genius
in
general.
With
all
the
problems
and
optimization.
He
would
explain
that
he's
a
genius
in
general.
With
all
the
problems
and
optimization.
He
would
explain
that
he's
a
genius
in
general.
With
all
the
problems
and
optimization.
He
would
explain
that
he's
a
genius
in
general.
With
all
the
problems
and
optimization.
He
would
explain
that
he's
a
genius
in
general.
With
all
the
problems
and
optimization.
He
would
explain
that
he's
a
genius
It's not a trivial question.
I don't think there's a reason why, if we were children, we wouldn't learn how to program.
I think it gives you a logical capacity, which is useful and can be very fun.
I agree.
I wouldn't have to spend time with my children in that way. Perfect. I think it's great.
Even if you're an AI engineer, your job is to solve problems.
Programming is one way of solving problems.
If you want someone to be a mechanic, you have to learn how to solve problems.
You don't know what an AI job will look like in 10 years.
The best thing you can give him is to learn the tools that exist today,
so that he has a mindset that he won't ask for a GPT, but that he will know how to solve problems himself.
That's how I would quantify it.
I agree completely.
I saw a very interesting system of how people integrate and solve problems with GPTMs.
GPTN.
Thank you for reminding me.
You build a pipeline, you write a code locally,
you build an input, you send the input to it,
you say, for example, this is my base structure.
The base structure will act as a language model.
Then you get the answer, and then the local layer on your side does the data production,
and then sends it back to the interpreter to do the production.
Pipelines and integrations are something that we see as a next level,
because I see that a lot is happening now.
A lot of people started building layers around GPT.
They don't know that we actually use it,
but it's hidden behind and generated in a query or something.
It's similar to L2 for IBM, which we talked about earlier.
You use a product where you don't know that the blockchain is below,
but it's not important in the end.
It's a new vector to solve problems in some way,
if I understand you correctly.
A fun fact, a more mindfuck application,
AI, for example, is a company called Lightmass,
I don't know if you're Slovenians,
where they found out that you can encode 3D spaces in a neural network.
They imagined a video game where you could have a gigabyte of textures,
objects, and so on, which were rendered on a computer screen.
Now you have an AI that is encoded in the whole level,
and you feed it the position, very logically,
and then 3D pictures of what the space looks like in that area,
and there are much smaller levels, if you know what I mean.
It's like an alternative to compression.
The levels are big, I don't know what it's called,
20 gigs for 1 gig, and the performance is absurd,
and so on, it's a very interesting thing.
So AI is like that.
I think that as a back-end, you use a lot of GPT,
and you limit yourself.
It's a hot topic now,
it's where you get money, where you cut cash and so on,
but it's still not a silver bullet for all the problems.
I still have a file on my disk,
where you once made a self-driving car.
I remember that demo.
You took a video, and then...
I recorded a video.
You recorded a video and made a self-driving car.
What happened to that project?
It was a hobby.
It was a time when you could program.
Long story short,
I made a car that had radar cruise control.
It was interesting,
and then I wanted to understand how these problems work.
At the time, there was no AI in it.
It was all heuristics, math, and similar problems.
Why did this happen?
Nothing.
I developed a proof-of-concept,
and it stayed there.
If you're smart, I'll share it with you.
That was the performance.
I'll have to say it now.
You have a lot of confidence in your abilities,
in your car.
I just don't know how to drive it.
Well, maybe.
I got a recording,
where you detect the lines,
you fix it, and you drive it.
So...
It worked.
I still have it there as...
Jesus Christ.
But yeah.
Nope.
In the meantime,
we could wrap up our conversation,
because the fans are filming us,
and they're helping me with the lighting.
Maybe the last topic would be...
Community.
Or let's say...
GitHub, for example.
All these experiments,
all these codes,
production for the things you do,
you publish it.
And everything you publish
is hosted on GitHub.
GitHub has become a community,
a hub.
What does GitHub represent to you?
Has it become the spot
where you can hang out
and talk to other developers?
Or is it still you,
just as a layout of the code?
Maybe a bit of reputation building,
or something else.
I used Stack Overflow here.
Isn't it a full pad?
GitHub or Stack Overflow?
Stack Overflow.
I mean, yeah, it's a full pad,
but if you want to call it
code reputation building,
whatever, it's different.
Reputation building.
I mean, you don't have
a chat on GitHub, right?
You can see when someone starts, right?
Isn't there a chat on GitHub?
It's like a tweet, for example.
I mean, people talk
in pull requests and comments,
but it's not a real-time collaboration,
but it's a collaboration around work
for those who want to work.
If you want to work with someone,
you'll look at their profile
to see what they do,
but I don't know about that.
Let's say a person told you,
for example,
now that you have badges and so on,
when they're a bit
gamification and so on.
For me, GitHub,
for example, in interviews,
is quite important
if I see that something is there.
Then I can go and look,
okay,
you did this and that,
and this and that,
and you worked,
and I see how you communicated
with others.
Even if not,
I actually have
excellent programmers in the team
who had GitHub empty
until then.
They had others.
Okay.
Good job.
Can I ask one last question?
I'll give it to TNT.
It could have been at the beginning,
but I...
For all those
who have been waiting.
In the intro video,
I said something
that I didn't quite understand.
I said it like a geek.
Before that,
I was in programming,
I was in electronics,
then I competed in robotics.
Before that,
I was in electronics,
I was in chemistry.
And that was in primary school.
Then we mixed explosives at home.
I still have all the recipes,
if anyone needs them.
I can tell you.
Mainly,
my task was acetone peroxide,
which is very easy to make.
Acetone 3 peroxide
has 80% TNT power.
A very dangerous task.
You feel it
when you look at it closely.
The difference between
TNT and acetone is
that you have to cool it.
It's easiest to do
in a family refrigerator.
Because my mom
always locks the door
in front of the garden.
She's always in front of the grave
with the refrigerator,
and so on.
And the whole refrigerator
smells of acetone.
Fun times.
When you started talking
about these things,
we were watching it
with our neighbors.
Then we left
when one of my colleagues
took three fingers away.
We left at that time.
I'm looking if anyone is interested.
I like to talk about all this.
I mean, not specifically
about the day
when you lose a finger,
but that's a long story short again.
As the saying goes,
BOMBS AWAY!
I'm going to drink a beer.
So at this moment,
I would like to thank
the whole team in Grodno
for their hard work and sacrifice.
Thank you for supporting us
as much as you should.
And a special thank you
to Jan and Ino
for this conversation and chat.
We will talk a little bit with you.
Share this video,
subscribe,
and if you have any feedback,
we will be very happy
if you give it to us.
I also like to talk
with people in general.
If anyone is interested,
we can go out for a beer
or whatever.
Thank you for watching.
Thank you for the call.
Thank you.