Okay, so let's start this thing. So welcome everybody to our very
first battle that's that we're gonna do in in our podcast. And
we're gonna try to record this in a in front of live audience
here. And we're gonna try to record this, hopefully, in a way
that you guys will all feel comfortable talking about the
frameworks that you guys use on a daily basis. And we're gonna
try to also show the world that this conference that we're now
attending, can bring together experts in the field of Java and
the ecosystem around it. We're recording this session, it's
make it conference in Porto Roche. The make it conference
this year is divided into two parts. One is more Oracle
technologies. And one is what we call open blend with jaycon,
which is more Java and other technologies around it. So
welcome everybody to this panel. We're going to try to talk today
about three Java frameworks, web frameworks. There are other
Java frameworks that we talked about this conference. Also,
sadly, we are limited by number of microphones here. But next,
next year, we might shuffle a bit. So sorry for everybody
that's that use other frameworks. Let's, let's, let's,
let's put that constraint here. And let me first start by
introducing our guests today. So here we have Roman, Roman
neglig. He's, he's independent contract and senior software
engineer at a company called object computing, Inc. Welcome.
We then have 18 Rozenik from a company sport rather, he's gonna
he's head of MBS shared services at sport rather. I'm not sure
what exactly that means. But I think you're an engineer, right?
Okay, check. And then on my left side, we have Gavin King. He is
his senior distinguished engineer at IBM, and did a lot of stuff
also from Red Hat, I imagine. Yeah, okay. So that's why we put
the IBM and Red Hat together there as well. And you're also
very known in the world of Java as a creator of hibernate ORM
framework as well. Welcome, everybody to this panel. Feel
relaxed, although there's a lot of people in the room. My very
first question is this gonna be very hard, but still try to try
to put yourself together to answer. So my first question to
you guys will be if you can tell us a bit about yourself, the
company you represent. And if you can tell us a bit, what kind
of challenges do you guys solve with your company, so that we
can like understand what are you doing? I would start with Roman
first.
Okay, my name is Roman Naglich. As I already mentioned, working
in software development for almost 20 years. I can say that
I have a few points in my career where I really accelerate my
knowledge about it. First one was 1990s, where I joined a
select technology company, which does not exist anymore.
And we were working on the next and open step computers, which
are still considered one of the best object oriented ecosystem.
Then another another boost was that when I when I joined the
Oracle company working as a middle tier consultant, or
working on the project across Europe, see a lot of stack
trace, see a lot of troubles, and learn a lot. Then the third
one was when I joined Micronauts. Actually, I used
Micronauts before already before. But I go deeply into the
Micronauts when I joined the object computing. So I'm not
actually a developer of the framework, but have a user. So I
have constantly contact with the developers of the framework. And
we're actually solving business problems and working on a
business problem with Micronauts.
So you use Micronauts on daily basis?
Daily business.
Okay, thank you. Aytin, can I ask you the same question?
Yeah, of course. My name is Aytin. And yes, I'm a software
engineer. I've been in the software development world for
about 10 years, give it or take. And for the last seven years,
I've been a part of Sportradar. Over the years, I jumped over a
few positions within the company. And with my latest role
as the head of MB Azure services, I'm helping out
engineers by providing various tooling, internet tranquil
solutions, but I also teach engineers about frameworks, and
other similar things. So over the years, I've been in touch
with quite a lot of technologies and open source solutions. And
as such, I learned a lot of things. And that really helps me
out from day to day.
Can I also ask you, you're going to represent Springboot today
because you also use it at the company you work for?
We're mostly a Springboot company. But we also use a
couple of other frameworks, including Quarkus.
Okay, thank you very much. And Aytin, can you?
Yeah, so I guess I have a pretty different kind of experience in
the industry. I've been working in essentially the same role for
20 years now. And unlike a lot of folks in the industry, I have
little experience of building applications and deploying
applications. My workmates joke that I've never, never deployed
an application in my life. And it's close to true. So I've been
doing, you know, tooling, framework, language, library
development for, you know, product development for my whole
career. And it's interesting, really, when you talk to people,
it's been interesting recently to really realize how kind of
different that is. There's a lot of things which I'm sure
everybody in this room, you know, kind of lives and breathes
and has lots of experience with. And if you ask me about it, I'm
blankly, I don't know anything about what you're talking about.
Because the reality of product development is getting very deep
in, you know, one, you know, kind of specific problem over the
space of years and kind of losing touch with the rest of the
industry a little bit.
Specialist in one.
Yeah, I mean, you know, the lifecycle of developing a product
is, you know, decade or more. And, you know, that's longer
than the lifecycle of a typical kind of project, you know. And
in that time, that's plenty of time to lose touch completely
with what the industry is doing.
Okay, so I do have like, a couple of questions about trendy
stuff. So hopefully, hopefully, we'll get through that.
Hopefully, I can cover up my ignorance.
Okay. Let's go into more now, the content of this, this
episode, right. So we'll start with Roman. And we'll talk more
about my first question is going to be about Micronaut. You
presented today Micronaut. And from other presentations
regarding other frameworks, what stand out, at least to me is
that Micronaut tries to be polyglot framework, meaning that
it supports several languages. But you also go very far in
sense that you demonstrated, for example, in your talk today,
that matrix for all the documentation that you have. So
all the languages that you guys actually support, there are docs
written in detail for everything.
Correct, correct. We are very proud of that.
And it's impressive. You also need a generator to generate the
scaffolding of the tool because of the nature of that, right? So
my question there would be, why would you build the framework
that is polyglot? What's the advantage?
The first reason was that actually, the origin of this
framework and the authors of the framework comes from the
Grails. So Grails was a framework, it's still framework
based on Spring Boot, but implemented in the GUI. So that
was the first reason why GUI was supported. And they have some
problems with the framework, and they want to solve those
problems. And they decided they will do, they will challenge
those weaknesses of the framework, and implement it on
different ways. So GUI was there. So what language could
be better to start with than Java? It was in that time. Then
Kotlin comes and then it's normal transition to support
Kotlin as well, because it's so compatible with between Java and
Kotlin is quite easy to achieve. So that's the main reason.
There are three languages.
Three languages, GUI, Kotlin and Java.
Okay, okay. Yeah, that's what, thank you for that. Okay, I'm
gonna go now to, to Parkos and Gavin. So that's a question for
you. So some may say that like, traditional stack, like having
big monoliths, one application server that serves a lot of
traffic that these times are kind of like, not suitable in
this cloud environment where you have very dynamic loads,
where you go into per request serving, all that stuff. We're
moving more into this serverless ecosystem where you want to have
small functions that spin up and scale down, all that stuff. So
that's my hypothesis. Do you feel that that's still?
Yeah. So I mean, look, I think, you know, the whole, you know,
cloud deployments have clearly been extremely successful, you
know, to a greater extent than I had expected. You know, surely
there's still, you know, some organizations who want to run
their cloud internally or want to, you know, or, you know,
have, you know, software that works on a, you know, what
you're calling a traditional stack, I guess, by which I take
it you mean like a cluster of services, HTTP, and then a
relational database behind it, something like that. I was
joking last night that I've written code in Fortran for VMS.
So, you know, but so traditional is kind of new in a way. It's
not that old. Okay. So that's been very, very, very, very
successful. And, you know, and Java has been perhaps not is
perhaps, it was perhaps initially not a perfect match to
that, to that architecture, because of the initial resource
requirements of just spinning up a JVM and the latency involved
in spinning up a JVM. And so, and so, you know, I don't want
to get too far on down that path right now. You know, when you're
talking about serverless and stuff, I'm not really sure what
that word means. I cannot try to ask you folks yesterday what
that means. And they were kind of like, well, you know, and
they give me a textbook definition of what a server is.
And then, you know, but apparently the thing is, well,
yeah, it's infinitely scalable, and all that. And I just want to,
you know, kind of look, I don't know, you know, I'm talking out
of my area of knowledge here. But I just want to caution a bit
when we start talking about infinite scalability, there's
this, there's this thing that happens in our industry, like,
we're kind of every five years or so, somebody discovers that
stateless services are really scalable. Right? And, you know,
yeah, right. And that's great. You know, that's great that
you're stateless service scales. And that's really great until
you have a program and you want your program to have an effect
upon the world. Right. And so when you're talking about
stateless services, you're talking about pushing the limits
to scalability somewhere else. Okay. So as soon as you need to
access a database, as soon as you need to cache some data, as
soon as you need to have divide up a workload into various parts
which share some intermediate state between them or have some
dependencies upon upon how the computation needs to proceed, or,
you know, or more exotic things, you need to run a part of your
algorithm on a quantum device, you know, there's something
like, I don't know, 10 to the four qubits in the world at the
moment, right? Or, I don't know, you're running a shared world,
and you have players who need to who need to interact. Suddenly,
I don't care how stateless your service is, you know, it's not
infinitely scalable. Okay. So I, you know, I just, you know, I
know, it's just picking on a word there. But, you know, like,
I'm always a bit, you know, like, like, I feel like sometimes
we focus too much upon that stateless service without and
when we should all, you know, we should be talking a lot more
about state and how to manage state. And in this cloud, you
know, one of the things really exciting about these cloud
environments is the extent to which is the advances which have
been made in terms of scaling data, right? And, and workloads,
which I wouldn't have thought would be natural for the cloud,
things in machine learning and stuff like that, like, like,
naively, I would not have thought would be very natural,
like, like this, like are moving to to this kind of cloud things.
I think I think, yeah, I'll stop there.
No, it's fine. It's fine. My question was more like, correct.
I completely understand. But it's, you have a feeling that
Quarkus, the development of Quarkus is focused around being
ready for this environment, being ready for, you know, there
is, you feel that it's tight to GraalVM, to native images. We
can talk more for other frameworks in this.
Yeah, well, I didn't want to, like, cut into their time. So
yeah, that's right. Do you want me to answer that question?
Yeah, please do.
Okay. Okay. So like, so we always want to, you know, it's a
difficult messaging job on our part. Okay, first of all,
Quarkus is not only a framework for GraalVM. Okay, or for a
native compilation. Okay. It is the next generation of what was
our server Java E technology, okay, reinvented for the modern
era. Okay. One of the things it does extremely well, and
obviously, a big focus of development is that is the need
to be able to, you know, spin up instances extremely fast in a
cloud environment. And that is enabled not just by native
compilation. But more importantly, actually, most of
the work is not just on being able to compile with GraalVM.
But in terms of being able to compile, interpret and compile a
bunch of metadata into the image that is deployed. So that if you
start up Hibernate or something like that, you're doing that
work at compilation time as part of the build step, rather than
doing it at runtime. I'm going to cut myself short.
Yeah, cool. Etienne, you ready for the next one?
Yeah. Okay.
My question is going to be regarding Spring. So Spring, you
kind of feel that it has transcended the world framework.
So it's more like the whole ecosystem of tools and services
and libraries and cloud offerings. And there's a lot of
stuff regarding Spring. So can you, like, from beginner
perspective, explain to us the difference between Spring Boot
and Spring Framework? Like, what's in the whole ecosystem
that you're more excited about? And can you tell us a bit more
about that?
Yeah, while the long answer would be very, very accurate, I
would probably still forget quite a lot of things because as
you said, it is really a long list of features that the Spring
Framework offers. So if we just sum it up, we can say that the
Spring Framework has those functionality available and you
can use them, but there is a lot of boilerplate configuration
which you have to do. Whereas with the Spring Boot solution,
a lot of that boilerplate gets done to the auto-configuration
functionalities. So what that brings to developers is that
developers can start doing their business logic way sooner than
with the Spring Framework.
There's a Micronaut Quarkus. I think they promote themselves
that they're AOT ready, meaning that you compile all these
things in advance and that helps build native images and all
that. Is that still the case also with Spring Boot? Do you
use these technologies also there? I'm not sure if it's...
Well, to be honest, in the last year or so, I didn't give it a
go with the Spring Boot AOT compilation. But last year when
I did the analysis, I was comparing Quarkus against
Spring Boot. Spring Boot just wasn't there. But I know that
since then there was a lot of work done within the Spring Boot
ecosystem on this. And the bottom line one year ago was
that Quarkus is the clear winner for ahead of time compilation.
And that was mostly because Spring Boot dependencies just
weren't there up yet, at least for the stack that I was looking
for. Because I had a particular solution in mind that I needed
to deploy in a serverless environment and I wanted to do
native compilations for the quicker bootstrap times. But
yeah, as I said, that list of dependencies that are now being
supported by Spring Boot is being constantly updated. And I
would suggest to developers when they're starting to think about
going the Spring Boot AOT path, well, just check up that list
and see if that list fits your needs and you have all the
dependencies ready. Because otherwise, you're going to have
to do a lot of manual work and configurations. So enable AOT.
Okay, thank you for that. You guys all comfortable? You can
also drink water, so relax a bit.
I want a coffee, man.
Coffee.
Water stuff.
I'm going to go now into next section of questions. And I'm
going to go to Roman, to you. My question is going to be, you
know, modern systems now going more towards, you know,
event-driven architecture, microservices, and we need to
then somehow connect these services together, etc. And my
question is, or like an open ended question is, can you give
us some pointers, like how hard it is to use Micronaut in
microservices way? And like, how hard it is to couple these
things together with some broker like Kafka or something? Is this
part of the framework or do I need to reinvent things around
it? Can you tell us a bit more?
Actually, Micronaut fully supports declarative clients for
the Kafka and other messaging systems. So it's very easy to
implement, for example, just define interfaces, annotate with
topics which you are using, which you are wanted to receive,
for example, as a listener, and you will get messages from the
Kafka and put into the configuration a few lines where
this Kafka server is located. And that's it. That's all what
you need to be able to receive messages. The same situation is
with producers. So we also support declarative producers
and you just call it. Thankfully for the IoT compilation,
when you build your application, all this code is generated for
you. So you don't need to do anything about that. There is
a question if the event-driven architecture is the right
solution for coupling microservices, because it brings
some other challenges, how to handle all this, how to handle
transaction, what to do with this, that. Actually, I prefer
there are other event architectures as well. For
example, event sourcing is one of them. Event sourcing, I think
when you have one source of true and just save events, save
events which happened in the past, and then recreate the
state of the object from that event. And that's perhaps a
more appropriate approach how to handle event-driven
architecture.
Okay. Thank you. It feels like...
Maybe just one comment.
It feels too easy.
But maybe one just comment about framework and IoT
compilation. Maybe all this is absolute, because Amazon, I
think, has this crack functionality. When you just
create an image from the Java process, and you just recreate
it instantly. It doesn't matter if it runs Quarkus,
Micronauts, Spring Boot.
But what happens with...
Actually, theoretically, it's very good. I don't know
practically, because I didn't...
What happens with... If we go back to what Gavin said, what
happens with states? For example, you have a snapshot of
current time.
Yeah. Actually, a state is preserved, so you get the last
state when you finish with your application. I don't know if
that's good or not. That depends on the situation, but it
looks promising.
So my colleagues who've reviewed this quite carefully say
not.
Really? Okay. I read about that. I never use it.
I'm passing on that item of information, but they...
Sure, sure.
Right, Aleš? Yeah. They say not.
It's an experimental world. Thank you for your answer. I'll
go back to Gavin now. So Hibernate is now 20 plus years
old. Thanks for all the very hard work on that as well to
you and your colleagues. My question is still going to be
related to Quarkus more a bit. So is it today still a good
idea to mix Quarkus and Hibernate together? Do you guys
put a lot of effort into making it as easy as possible? How
does this chemistry work?
I mean, it's a great question. When I got the call to work on
Quarkus, really the thing that stood out for me and why I'm not
really doing data development on Quarkus, but really came back
to Hibernate was really the realization that Hibernate and
ORM was still super important to our developers on our platform.
And the other realization was that this project was 20 years
old and had been very stable, and that meant a lot of craft,
right? So, you know, really, I mean, that was the question you
just asked me, was a question I asked myself three years ago,
was, you know, is this something that we can really now, you
know, it had been kind of like in a maintenance phase as part
of why, you know, as an underlying implementation of JPA
and, you know, Wildfly. And that was a question. And really,
you know, we had to sit down and look at it and go, okay, you
know, we need to reinvent this because this is actually
critical to what we're doing with Quarkus. It's actually
really important. And the other side of this was that Quarkus,
you know, we're kind of late to the game a bit with Reactive,
but, you know, Reactive was, you know, an important thing they
wanted to be able to support in Quarkus. And, you know, nobody
had ever heard of a Reactive ORM, right? So we had to, you
know, make Hibernate Reactive. It was quite hard with such a
big code base, big old code base, but we did it. And so
that was a very, very interesting project. I mean,
kind of an glamorous project going through and trying to
figure out how you can clean up all these APIs and fix all this
craft and kind of bug-like behaviors that had developed
over time and that, you know, without breaking everything,
you know, every single program. Anyway.
So, no, no, it's fine. I'm going to do a follow-up on this
question. And
In this conference, we heard talks about this Project Loom, like you go to, I went to a
Scala conference, give a talk there, and there was like, you know, people in Scala world
are excited about Project Loom.
So everywhere to every conference you go, green threads coming in Java, it's a revolution.
And it's going to radically simplify, possibly even eliminate the use of reactive patterns
in the code basis.
That I think is going to be challenging on its own for Harbinate, for Quarkus as well,
right?
Are you guys excited about it or scared?
No, I mean, I guess I got to agree with the Scala guys then.
It's very exciting.
It's very interesting.
Again, we need to be careful about the hype, you know, I was just looking at a website
which was saying, oh, this is going to mean your server can scale to millions of threads,
right?
Yeah.
And once again, you know, I want to hammer on this fact that, you know, be realistic
here.
One of the things we've run into with reactive is users coming on and saying, oh, everything
runs on a single thread.
So I can fork my reactive stream and hit the database in 20 different threads and it's
going to be faster.
And no, you can't do that, right?
Reactive streams are a kind of thread, okay?
Loom virtual threads are a kind of thread, all right?
If you have shared mutable state that is shared between threads, it doesn't matter what kind
of thread they are, okay?
Thread doesn't mean native OS thread.
It didn't mean that when the word thread was coined, okay?
And it shouldn't mean that now, all right?
So if you have a multithreaded program, multiple reactive streams, multiple virtual threads,
whatever they are, and you share a state between them, then you need to synchronize access
to that state.
You need semaphores.
You need whatever it is, whatever concurrency management pattern you have, all right?
And that means, you know, the idea, oh, you know, before I was limited to running a thousand
threads and now I'm just going to run a million and I'm going to get that for free is, I would
argue, not right.
You're going to have to think carefully about what the programming models are.
We've seen that people immediately start abusing reactive streams in terms of data access,
okay?
That's something, that's like this crash between these two, my world and the world of people
who are thinking about stateless services, and immediately they started abusing the model
and not understanding that, no, not everything is stateless, particularly, you know, data
access is not stateless by nature.
So with Loom, there's lots of interesting questions, you know, does it mean that Reactive
is over?
Unclear.
I don't know the answer to that, and we don't know the answer to that.
We're talking about a lot, you know, some of my colleagues think that the JDBC drivers,
for example, will catch up really quickly and then we're good, all right?
Some of my colleagues say, well, maybe not, right?
And so, you know, maybe there's still a place for these replacement, for the Vertex, Reactive
database clients and stuff in all this, right?
You know, perhaps we'll be using Loom, but then we'll switch over to Reactive at some
point.
I'm not going to, I don't want to go too far and start saying stuff that we're thinking
about, right?
So it's really interesting and there's a lot of opportunities for us there, but we have
to like really, really do a lot of testing and think hard about programming models and
it's very interesting, super interesting.
Just a question, you guys, your frameworks, do they depend on Netty or not?
Can you...
You can make them depend on Netty.
You can make them depend, but...
Actually not.
We can choose the engine, the web engine, so we can run it on the Tomcat.
We can even deploy it to the web project server or something like that, so it's the same for
us, SpringBoot.
I tested with SpringBoot, it works.
Yeah, I think we're done, by the way.
Yeah, okay, cool.
So the Netty is still the framework underneath the frameworks that you guys use on a daily
basis?
It's the fastest way to...
Still, okay.
Cool.
That was an easy question.
Okay, I have the next round of more questions to focus more towards like bringing these
frameworks to the hands of, let's say, newcomers or beginners, or how to make these things
more accessible to the new generation of the engineers, if you want.
And I'll start with Roman with a question for you.
For example, Micronaut comes out of the box with OpenAPI, Swagger support, AOT compilation,
aspect-oriented API.
Yeah, just these are words that I got from the webpage.
And it's a polyglot, et cetera.
But the question here I have is like, how hard it is to go from, for example, the demo
that you had on today on your presentation to actual production environment?
Can you like, you have to do a lot more work than just like, does it help the framework?
Actually no.
Gradle plugin, which comes with Micronaut supports all kinds of building deployment
images.
So you can build native image, you can produce Fedjar, you can deploy, prepare Docker, you
can deploy this Docker to the registry.
So everything is actually quite easy to achieve.
Then the problem, how to go to the production is more, I think, what is your process?
How your code is testing, from what stages to what stages this goes, you know?
That's more important than how to prepare just binary.
Binary is easy.
Let's just run the script and that's it.
But you also offer support for like different ways of injecting configuration, flags, et
cetera, as well.
Correct.
You put a lot of effort into that.
At least that's how I feel.
With simple definition of Micronaut environments, you said, for example, test whole different
stack of configuration, application configuration can be used.
So it's easy to set, for example, even it was deducted from the environment.
So when you deploy to the GCP, it automatically, if it exists, application-gcp is used.
So now I think in the new version, it's not that anymore.
And you have to specifically define in what environment it will run.
So from that, from technical perspective, it's easy.
I said, what I mean is more hard is how to define the deploying process.
Okay.
A question for you, Etienne, then.
Spring Boot has a very active community and you also have courses, certification, academies
also written on the page.
There is a lot of resources around Spring.
And would you recommend people doing any of that?
Did you try it?
You said that you also work with people, you try to introduce them to frameworks with juniors.
Do you use any of these resources?
Do you contribute to these resources?
Is that the best way to learn or YouTube videos or something?
Learning is a core skill that every developer should really work on it.
Because learning on how to learn new things is something that you master through your
whole life.
And every person has different requirements on how to learn new things.
For some, it might be YouTube videos.
For some, it might be reading a book.
For some, might be attending a seminar or two in real life.
Now whereas the Spring Boot Academy, no, I didn't give it a go.
And yes, I suggest people to use online courses and YouTube videos or similar things to get
a kickstart on their knowledge.
So they at least get acquainted with the system, what is going on, a few concepts, the terminology.
But that is only a baseline knowledge.
From there, engineers have to build on.
They have to get their hands on code or the keyboard.
And they have to start writing code so they get a feeling about the framework, maybe write
a unit test, an integration test, and really understand what are they doing.
And not copy things just from ChatGPT or similar stuff.
Because while that might get them through a few problems, at the end of the day, they
are engineers and they have to build ChatGPT and not use it.
Thank you.
You prepared for this answer, right?
You can sense it in your voice.
I have a question then for Gary now.
Your question is more like how to work with the community, I guess, but how can engineers
contribute to a framework such as Quarkus or Quarkus specifically if you want?
And can you give us a few practical tips where you think that people can contribute the most
and how can engineers that, for example, now use Quarkus be useful to Quarkus developers
or engineers?
Yeah, I don't know how to answer this question because it's something I've often wrestled
with.
What kind of help would help you?
Yeah, I mean, like, you know, and this, I guess, because the thing is, like, the thing
that would really help is if the people who are core developing the framework, whatever
it is, the library, had time to focus their energies on strategically important functionality
and weren't absolutely overcome by a parade of small, minor bugs, right?
So really, you know, if you want to, you know, if you're a contributor and you want to, like,
help this framework advance, like, the kind of work that would most help is completely
unglamorous bug fixing, right?
The truth is that for obvious reasons, very few developers are really that motivated to
contribute unglamorous bug fixes.
And so instead, what happens is that people come along and they want to contribute some
major piece of functionality.
And that, at times, is great, all right?
But, you know, a framework, a library has a vision, a philosophy behind it, even if
that sometimes is not necessarily that obvious to, you know, there is always a set of belief
and ideology behind it.
That was the word I was looking for.
And so very often we have people come in and rather than posing a problem, they propose
a solution, right?
And the solution goes against the ideology, okay?
And it is very hard for me, as, you know, someone, you know, leading or whatever an
open source project, it is very hard for maintaining, I think that's the right word, it is very
hard for me to not just kind of knock that on the head as, no, that's wrong for all these
reasons.
I mean, you do have to try and explain to people why that's not going to fly, not what
we're going to do.
And that rarely goes over well, right?
You know, so what I try to, you know, what I often try to do is kind of explore, okay,
what is it, you know, what was the actual real problem you were trying to solve?
The number of times, you know, in my life as a software developer that people come to
me with a solution instead of coming to me with a problem, you know, and I have to kind
of drill down and by the time I actually get and discover what their actual problem
was, like, they've had it with me because I've challenged all their ideas and they're
upset with me, right?
You know, and so, you know, like, I often feel like, you know, what I want to know is
what are your actual problems, you know, like, instead of, you know, like, you know, understand
your problem better and then come and, you know, and then talk to us about the problem
and you'll find when you come to us with problems, we're like super interested to know about
new problems if we didn't know the problem before.
And then, you know, maybe we can work with you to design a solution which is coherent
with the ideology and which fits with the other features and which, you know, can elegantly
integrate with other things.
Okay.
I'll stop talking.
So, no, that's nice.
So people should bring problems to you and they should fix bugs, essentially.
That's the...
I mean, fixing bugs would be great, like you laugh, but like, that's actually what your
average open source project needs is people doing unglamorous, fixing shitty little bugs,
right?
Like, I'm sorry.
Yeah.
That's...
What would help most.
That's how they would also learn the framework and understand.
Yes.
And learn how...
Right.
And learn the ideology.
Learn that, yeah.
Solving bugs is hard.
Yes.
So people get out of them quite a lot.
People should also like try to put more effort into reporting bugs, like put more context
into it.
Yes.
Be friendly.
Yeah.
Respect people's time.
People on the other side are sometimes paid, sometimes not paid to.
Yeah.
The quality of how you report the issue which you're facing makes an enormous difference
to how quickly you will have a solution.
And really folks, probably not you guys in this room, but the typical quality of a bug
report I typically receive is abysmal, all right?
Abysmal.
Wait, what is that?
Bad.
Well, these are more or less my...
These are the questions that I prepared for you guys more or less, but I still have like
the last round of questions for you.
My question is like, can you name one of the features that excites you the most in Java
ecosystem and such, right?
So what are you really looking forward in Java now and in the future, right?
What excites you?
Please, Roman.
This is a tough question.
What excites me?
As I said, I really love domain-driven design and so environment, event sourcing and that
kind of things, actually I'm working on to provide the component for the event sourcing
to be part of the framework.
But I'm in the middle of the work, so still.
So that's my actually exciting idea.
Absolutely.
Can I ask you a question, Sam?
Yeah, but we already touched my favorite thing of Java in the upcoming years, months, and
that is Project Loom.
I'm hoping that this will at least severely decrease the complexity that we have to do
today with the current trading model in JVMs.
Okay.
And Gavin, can I ask you the same question?
What's the question?
What excites you about Project Valhalla?
What excites me about Project Valhalla?
Valhalla.
That's a tricky question.
Valhalla is very tight.
Sorry.
Yeah.
Oh, well, that's pretty cool.
I don't really like how they, I don't look, I haven't looked at the most recent proposals.
There were some things that I didn't like about the proposal from years and years ago,
but Valhalla.
Yeah.
It's a crazy...
Like the...
I don't know.
I'm a Scala engineer.
I don't know what you're doing these days, but...
Yeah, no, no.
I mean, it's good.
I mean, yeah.
No, no.
I mean, I think it's different, right?
The names are really catchy.
Valhalla, Loom, Growl.
Like, the name is cool.
It's absolutely true that one of the critical things that limits your options with respect
to implementing some kinds of algorithms on Java is that every object requires garbage
collection, right?
So, I mean, I think value types are super important, but I haven't looked at the spec
for probably years and years and years.
Okay.
That was a tricky question.
Not good for my site.
But still, what are you most excited about the Java in the next couple of years?
What excites you?
What excites me in Java?
Not by...
Look, man, you realize I'm going to be turning 50, and it's pretty hard for a 50-year-old
man to be excited.
I did that.
I definitely did that to myself.
Well, we're now kind of like ending our slot here and our time.
So I'm going to do the closing remarks now.
So I would really like to thank, first, MakeIT organizers and sponsors, and then I would
like to also thank the sponsors and Patreons and supporters of our podcast, Grodje.
And I would like to thank you, Gavin.
I would like to thank you, Roman, and I would like to thank you, Etienne, for your time.
We're going to put links to your profiles in the notes.
But yeah, thanks, everybody, for listening, and thanks for being nice citizens.
And thank you.
Thank you for having us.
Thank you.