Welcome to Ugrodje Framework, or Ugrodje in Slovenian.
We have a new episode of Borderless.
So Borderless, we host international speakers.
We speak in English.
Ugrodje is a Slovenian tech dev podcast.
I hope you know that by now.
And today we have a special guest, Nick Jackson, Principal Developer Advocate at HashiCorp.
Welcome to Ugrodje.
Thank you very much.
And you should mention where we are sitting right now, because this is not our usual place
where we record.
So today you won't hear any trains that you usually do, or every emergency vehicles driving
by.
We are here at Devs Days Ljubljana, we are at FRI, so the Faculty of Informatics and
Computer Science.
So yeah, it's a great venue.
We decided not to close ourselves into a room super quietly, so you can enjoy some noise
in the background.
Yeah, but if you listened to the previous episode, we had like similar situations.
So like this is like the new setting right now.
Yeah.
Our technicians are actually amazing.
They're doing some black magic, no fun intended.
And they're basically just erasing every noisy thing in the background, or at least as much
as they can do.
Nice.
Yeah.
How are you doing, Nick?
I'm very well.
And you both well as well, I hope?
Yeah.
So today we are both, our team from Ugrodje is Andras, and I'm also Andras.
We have a bunch of folks here.
And if somebody is missing Otto, he's there.
Yeah.
Our producer with a nice smile.
Should we jump in?
So now we're here at DevOps Days Ljubljana.
And so today's episode is going to be more of discussing the DevOps culture, the hype.
Are we still in the hype phase?
And everything related to whether this is like culture, whether these are tooling that
is sort of a byproduct that eventually happened.
And I don't know where should start, maybe giving you, leaving you the hard question.
I'm assuming that this is not your first DevOps Days in general, that you've been with your
professional career, also with HashiCorp, supporting this kind of events and so on.
So how do you see like maybe, I don't know, 10 years ago, and compare it to where we stand
now?
With regard to, well, so this is actually my first DevOps Days.
I can't believe it.
But I've been doing this role for nearly seven years.
I've never spoken at a DevOps Days, and I don't know why, but I've just never done it.
So I'm actually really excited to be here.
I think DevOps is growing from strength to strength as a kind of a first thing.
So like when I first came across the term, which was probably around 10 years or so,
yeah, around about maybe a little more, but I think DevOps at the time was about trying
to drive that shift from just sort of system administration, but trying to get more involvement.
And I think we're slowly getting there.
I mean, it's taken a long time, but I look at my background.
So my background, I'm an application developer.
I've run engineering teams.
I am literally the sort of person that you would not want anywhere near a server, because
I will do things in a very specific developer's way, which is root credentials for everything
and chmod 777, right?
But I think the thing for me is that, and I hope I'm the perfect example of this, is
that I see the benefit hugely in the DevOps culture, because I've seen the benefits firsthand.
And for me, I was always interested in the sort of system admin side and what's going
on with the infrastructure, because I wanted to help to get that to move forward, because
I want my applications to get into production.
I want my production environment to be running smoothly, because nobody likes getting up.
So by taking an interest in the kind of the operational side of things, then I think that
really helps.
And then you look at it from the other side as well.
So from an operations person, by an operational side of things, taking an interest in the
application development, understanding some of the constraints and the technical limitations
of the application, it helps you to build better infrastructure.
And that kind of mesh and that sort of culture, I think is really, really, really, really
helping us.
So I'm pleased to see that things are moving along.
I have a worry, and I have a worry that what we've seen, I think, emerging in the last
12 months is I hear a lot of platform engineering.
And I hear this is a lot of, you know, in terminology.
Now, I appreciate why platform engineering as a thing exists, because people are increasingly
needing these complicated systems.
So therefore, we're kind of rather than kind of each individual silo building their own
systems, they're trying to kind of centralize that as a capability.
The thing that I worry about platform engineering is that the developers who had been getting
really good at integrating with an operational side of things, getting involved with provisioning
infrastructure, deploying their own code, is now going to go back to the way that they
were 10 years ago and start thinking, not my job anymore, not my problem.
And I think that is a worry for me.
I don't know if that's happening.
I don't know if it will happen, but it feels, I think labels are very powerful and in some
ways dangerous, dangerous thing.
I don't know what you guys think about that.
I've seen like in last decade, I see similar to the point that this is sort of become nice
to have, let's talk about it, let's like break all the silos and work together.
But in the end, we are still struggling with similar things as before.
And yeah, like there still are labels and sort of like, this is not my job at the end
of the day.
So I'm sort of also worried whether, are we still like preaching this sort of a cult
or we are making actual like improvement in, let's say development on operation stuff.
So I should also stand with this like more worried side, no matter that I'm no longer
so much involved in this culture.
Maybe Andras could like fill me in his perspective that like what he sees.
Yeah, I would say it this way, like it's, everybody wants to be as good as the big
boys, right?
And if you want to be as good as big companies, even if you're maybe smaller or a startup,
you want to do things proper.
And once you want to do the things proper, you need to specialize in technologies.
And the thing that I'm seeing is there's, for example, when it comes to Kubernetes,
it's a great framework and a tool, but you need a super dedicated person to manage that.
If we are talking about intermediate level of people that are maybe five years in their
career, so it's not, Kubernetes is just another technology.
They need to focus on that.
And then you are starting to lose this contact when it comes just to, hey, we want to provide
business value.
Let's just create a simple, I don't know, Ansible pipeline that will do the job and
everybody will understand.
Which I think it's manageable by the whole team or just by developers.
But when it comes to the technologies that really the big companies are using, and it
might be a bit complex for the most of the team, then you're having basically this disconnect
because somebody really specialized or something, and it's hard to deploy.
And then you get this gap.
I think that basically people have this fear of missing out or looking at social media,
what is fancy, and it might be super overcomplicated for them.
I don't know if you share the same thoughts.
Yeah.
I mean, I remember the Kelsey Hightower when he kind of did his own meme where he was like,
you know, hey, I'm going to deploy my blog to Kubernetes.
And I think that's a sort of an appreciable problem.
I think in general, Kubernetes sort of solves a problem that we have, which is that we need
to run these smaller instances of applications across a distributed environment.
And with anything like that, it comes complexity.
I kind of think as well, to your point around sort of people learning, it can actually be
really difficult.
So when I started out my career, nearly, well, I graduated nearly 30 years ago, but my first
real job when I was working in the internet, and I built a website for Formula One.
And at the time, that website for the global Formula One was running on two servers.
We had an Apache front-end server, which was running PHP, and we had an Oracle server,
which was serving as the database, two Sun Solaris boxes.
And okay, there was like three people on the internet at the time, so it wasn't a thing.
But in terms of the complexity of what you need to learn as an app dev, I needed to learn
a little bit of Linux.
I needed to learn roughly, like the rough edges of how Apache works, like what is the
configuration to sort of deploy an application, and to configure things like the plugin for
PHP.
And I needed to understand PHP and some SQL, nothing too heavy.
And nowadays, I need to understand, let's assume I'm still working in PHP.
I need to understand my PHP.
I need to understand Kubernetes, because I need to understand how the application is
going to be deployed.
I need to understand the underlying structure of what's going on in the kube cluster, because
well, if I understand how the nodes are being scheduled, or if they're in auto-scale groups,
and how that affects load balancing, and how that affects the applications coming and going,
and I need to understand how to deploy it.
So I need something like Terraform, or Ansible, or Chef, or Insert, probably all of those
tools here.
And then I need to understand sort of functional testing, and half a dozen different databases.
It's pretty complex.
I mean, the world is definitely getting more and more complex, but like at the same time,
it's pretty interesting.
And so I suppose like this is maybe where we're guilty, right?
We look at these new technologies and we're like, oh my God, that's something else that's
really interesting.
We kind of get captivated by something.
So you think we, in a way, over-complex everything by pushing too much new technologies or like
new things into our stacks?
Because the last time I was like reading how the infrastructure of Stack Overflow is looking,
and it's simple.
They still keep it very simple for the things that they need.
And if you compare this to somebody else who would start doing the architecture design
would say, no, no, no.
We need something that's like Kubernetes, we need load balancer here.
And in the end, like what Andras mentioned, like maybe that's not like, but like understanding
the business, we are like more focusing on the nice technology, nice to have maybe all
the features that will never be used.
But it's like having this, it's sort of something to brag about in the end.
I don't know if it's, I think it's, so I think firstly, the sort of software architecture
is difficult.
And I think getting, architecting a system for the correct scale is also very, very difficult.
And then you've got complexity of application.
So something like, I don't want to play down Stack Overflow, but if you have like a sort
of a website, which is a kind of a forum, then the number of components are somewhat
smaller or constrained than say you have a global banking system, or take something like
sort of Netflix, which is like, what about like 40% of all internet traffic or something
like that.
So then I think what happens is we sort of learn a lot and we're reading a lot and we're
looking at these solutions.
So we're building our startup and we're going to grow as big as Netflix, that's our goal,
but we're not there yet.
But what we're doing is maybe architecting the solution at the wrong level at the wrong
point.
So instead of starting out with something which is a little bit simpler and then progressing
outwards, you know, to give you an example, like containerization is still a great thing.
It enables a great developer workflow.
So I would always recommend containerization at any scale, but you don't need to start
with Kubernetes.
You could start with Cloud Run or like ECS is actually really, really quite accessible
or like, you know, pretty much every sort of cloud provider has a run a container as
an instance.
And then you can scale it out from there.
So then as you add more services, you maybe add another Cloud Run instance.
And then maybe you can like, okay, we're going to start managing these with infrastructure
as code and building some pipelines.
And then you're going to get to a point where it's like, okay, we're at a point now where
the application needs multiple instances or having issues with deployment.
Then you start to look for the architectural solutions.
I think if anything, what we're guilty of is we'll kind of read something on an article
and think, that'd be amazing.
I'd love to implement that.
And then you implement it without actually thinking, well, do you really need it?
But at the same time, like, I don't think people do that deliberately.
I think it's just really hard to kind of, there's so much information, so much complexity.
It's like, where do you even begin?
And with hindsight, if you've got a bunch of years experience building various systems
of sizes, you kind of get to learn which is the right solution.
But if you kind of don't, and all you're doing is like, well, how do I deploy my application
to the cloud?
If you Google that, you're probably going to come across like, oh, here's an article
on how to do it with Terraform and Kubernetes.
And if you don't know it any better, that's your kind of your starting point when it's
not necessarily the appropriate solution for.
So yeah, I think it's hard, but at the same time, I'm a magpie like anybody else.
I find it super interesting.
I'm all about the new technology.
Yeah, it's hard to balance our excitement with some boring technology from the past
that might be a bit more practical or, well, depends on the use case.
But yeah, it's super tricky.
So recent years, we are seeing that HR departments or companies are basically posting job titles
like DevOps engineer.
What does that mean for you?
Well, I mean, when I kind of look at those things and I like, I see, first and foremost,
I think DevOps is a culture and it's, well, it is what it is.
It's Dev and it's Ops.
But at the same time, it's also a methodology.
So you can't just say it's a culture.
It's about, in my mind as well, if you say, well, what is DevOps?
It's about performing an operational function, but using maybe a development process.
So we're using infrastructure as code where we're building tooling to help us.
So a lot of DevOps engineers are writing sort of pretty complex scripts and their own tools
using Python or Go or Rust or whatever.
So it is kind of a meld of the two.
I know a lot of people kind of get upset with the whole DevOps when they say it as a title.
I'm like, well, I don't.
I don't have a problem with that.
I think it's just embodying that kind of attitude, if you would, and if it helps as well, like
if having a label helps promote a methodology or promote a culture, like that's not a bad
thing, is it?
I don't know.
What do you?
You asked the question.
I'm going to ask you the question.
What do you think?
I always find it tricky, right?
Whenever I go to my customer, I try to figure out what do they want?
And I know that that sounds a bit funny, but you really can't assume anything, especially
in DevOps related stuff, right?
Because sometimes people just want me to help them from end to end and maybe just like lift
up the knowledge of the whole team and the whole process.
And that might be from development to delivery.
Sometimes they're super focused just on CIC deep pipelines, so I need to basically figure
out what they want there.
But the main thing, at least the main challenge for me is when I started gaining years and
years of experience, I go to the customer and I say, look, we have, I don't know, there
are four zones of technology that we can pick.
And I recommend that we pick something that everybody can learn something and that we
don't go full crazy.
So that it's actually that the business folks or the main company, so that they are happy
that the engineer just didn't close the door and now they are geeking out, right?
But I also want to, depends on the level of the folks working there or my customers.
I also want to share whatever I know.
And I say, look, there is no need to use Docker.
We can totally use package managers that are purely functional and we just use Nix and
we can figure everything out, but that might be ultra overkill, right?
And I never do that suggestion also, but I've done some consulting in that.
And sometimes I'm just like, and I know that this will sound super wrong.
If you have, if you have two guys and they don't have any founding, they have a bootstrap
company and they commit their secrets into the repo and the repo is private.
I'm like, look, it's fine, right?
Because this company might not exist in three weeks, right?
But I will tell you all the technologies and maybe we can agree that you maybe should
do a small step and for example, take Mozilla SOPs.
If you can implement that in your thinking and how you deploy stuff, it's still in GitHub,
it's just simple executable that will help manage this.
And I can help you set up those things up.
If you are willing to spend or pay me actually two hours of my work, is that a price performance
for you and, or if they say no, then I'm saying, look, then just put them at one place so that
at one point, if you succeed, you will know where to rotate, right?
And basic things, things like that.
So for me, when I go somewhere and I usually don't apply to job postings, right?
But yeah, the main challenge for me is I need to shift or bend the jobs engineer posting.
I need to bend that inquiry to something that makes sense for my customer and for me.
And I think that is a problem, I suppose, but it was a problem, but it's such a broad
spectrum.
Yeah.
And I think that's the key thing.
It's about ultimately what we want to do is just move the bar.
It's about just incremental progression.
That's what everybody should be trying to do.
But I definitely enjoy working in a world which has DevOps a lot more than the previous,
you know, the sort of where, where you had a dedicated sysadmin who was grumpy and would
basically answer your request.
Maybe if you were lucky, certainly not on a Friday because you've probably been drinking
since lunchtime because, well, you know, dealing with developers all week, I would too.
So this methodology is not for grumpy people.
So grumpy people are not in DevOps, right?
I think in tech, we're pretty good at being grumpy.
Yeah.
No, no.
I agree.
Adding to your question, whether like DevOps, I see DevOps as like right now overhyped,
like using Kubernetes.
I see like it's maybe too much stress saying, well, this is a DevOps job.
Well, come on.
We're like using this culture, like culture norm, understanding each like each unit or
from, from, from, from management to business perspective, to development perspective and
operation perspective and be like transparent to like be everybody involved.
I rather see this like to be this like open process and you can call it DevOps.
And then like whether not, not having title DevOps, it makes far more sense.
Like, like Google introduced the SREs, far, far, far more fancy, fancy title.
But nevertheless, I'm, I'm just fine saying that he's a sys, a sys admin.
But practicing this good cultural practices of communication, open transparency and, and,
and wanting to, to, like you said, moving things forward and not saying, well, it's
not my job here.
Like my responsibility ends and, and not willing to maybe help the, the, the, the other party
to, to move things forward.
Yeah.
And I, so I think as well, I've had a thought that maybe what we're, what, what kind of
what suppose a problem that we have in, in the industry as well as you are basically
paid by what you know.
So the, the amount of stuff that's in your head, the, the more tools and knowledge you
have and obviously experience of developing systems is, is pretty much kind of, you know,
linked, directly linked to the amount of salary that you get.
So therefore, if you want to get more salary, you need to know more stuff.
So therefore I think there's, there's also like a, you know, a demand that we want to
keep learning, but then you want to kind of implement.
what you've learned and practiced.
So maybe that also is kind of a driver on why we're using in some cases
inappropriate use of technology.
And maybe we need to like flip this as a business.
And then, you know, the reality is it shouldn't be about what you know.
It should be about the efficiency that you can drive within the organization.
Now, actually having a broad spectrum of knowledge helps you to understand that
maybe the most complex tool is not the right tool and actually the best solution
for the business, which derives the best value and efficiency is the simplest tool.
And avoiding the Kubernetes and going for just the, you know, we just need a VM.
So let's just create a VM.
So maybe, maybe we need to kind of think about, I think about that as well.
But, but I certainly think, like, you know, this yourselves, like if you, if
you saw a role and it was high tech, you might be more attracted to go for that.
It's probably higher salary as well, as opposed to if it was a high salary, but
low tech role, you know, so, so maybe we're on, we're our own worst enemies.
Yeah.
But on, on the other hand, you could, you could see like, especially, but what I
saw in, in, in last decade were like those, those jobs that have this fancy
descriptions, what kind of technology you'll be using, but in the end you're
like stuck with some legacy, like they maybe have something in a roadmap.
We want to be there, but you will need the working process, how to get there.
But you're basically stuck with some legacy technology.
I find those kinds of things the most interesting, like for me, I think the,
I'm really interested in, in that how to get from point A to point B.
So if somebody comes along and says, we have this rails application, it's a
monolith, it's just a rails app with a Postgres database, we have an aspiration
to grow the business, to add technology, which will ultimately lead to
developing all of these new services.
I think that's actually really interesting because then you sort of
think, well, how do you decompose this?
How do you start extracting components out of this?
What is the appropriate way to run this new architecture?
And you see it grow and you see it involve and hopefully with it, you see
the business grow and I think that's always been a focus that we shouldn't
forget that we were employed to help provide a sort of a service to provide
a value for an organization and so yeah, so maybe basically we just need more
businesses to like start giving us money based on if they're more successful,
they should pay us more, right?
That sounds fair, right?
I'm all for more money.
So less hype driven hiring.
Yeah, but I think in general, right?
Like I think if you look at DevOps and if you've spoken to certain business
leaders, they will use the term and they haven't really got an understanding
of what's going on, but they don't really get it, but even if that term is a
leverage to be able to drive a conversation in finance, to be able to drive a
conversation with a C-level somewhere, which increases funding for technology
or for whatever that the organization then needs to help it push forward,
then that's a good thing.
Like I've got no problem at all with that if somebody's kind of using that,
but because we all win in the end.
Yeah.
Do you think that maybe in the next few years we will, in the recent years,
there had been a lot of tooling regarding delivery and how to ship something to
production, and I would say that back in the 2000s, there were, including me, a
lot of sysadmins that were happy with just like simple best scripts and we didn't
really care much with coding back then.
Of course, at least I was less experienced, so you need to grow that skill of coding.
And now we are in a renaissance where there's a lot of new tools popping up.
And I compare that, and I know it's a weird comparison, a bit to the front end
world, when there was a period that there had been a lot of frameworks, but now we
are basically settled on the three major ones, kind of.
Of course, there are newer ones, but there's React, Vue.js, and Angular, and
they seem to be the options that big companies pick.
Do you think that maybe we will agree on some tooling in some departments so we
will be able to be more rational and then think back how to provide more value and
just not hack on new things?
I think it's a good question.
And I think until we get to a situation when the tooling is really suitable for
what we need in order to do our jobs, we're going to, I think, still have evolution.
I think there is a slow sort of standardization around certain tools,
which I think is a good thing because then you have a sort of a, you know, the
knowledge sharing is kind of more focused, which is always good.
But I'm still not convinced that where we are right now, that the
tools deliver exactly what we need.
And that's why we need to continually build things.
And again, this is why I think that every organization has a platform
engineering team, because there isn't something that we can just pick up off
the shelf and that we can use.
And so I think there will be a consolidation.
I think it will kind of happen, but it seems like certainly over the last sort
of five years, you know, from an architectural standpoint where we're not
slowing down, but we seem to be organizing our thought around the two
predominant patterns of like either the serverless pattern or the kind of the
Kubernetes or scheduler based pattern, that doesn't seem to be, there's certainly
nobody's come up with a new, well, having said that, and I'm like, well, we're all
going to be probably writing serverless WASM functions running on Kubernetes,
obviously, in the next five years.
So maybe we are about to shift again, but it does feel like we're starting to
consolidate our infrastructure patterns.
And then I think because of that, the tooling will then become standardized.
So I think it'll happen.
But I think there's always, whilst we're all building our own platforms, there's
always going to be custom tooling required because what I build is not
necessarily going to be useful for you and or you or.
Yeah, but like we can simply like basically your employer, so HashiCorp,
so basically was solving some of their own issues and create tools to figure
out those tools get benefit to wide range of customers.
Yeah.
And I'm excited about that.
And like, so I don't know if any of the listeners haven't kind of got a full
background on that, but when Mitchell and Armand basically were working in a role
as DevOps engineers and they were deploying systems and they realized that
kind of the forefront of cloud, that the tooling was, there was something missing
basically.
Now this is just after Vagrant.
So they started to kind of think about this and started to build the tooling.
And then they realized that actually, hang on a minute, if this tooling is
useful for us, then it's probably useful for the wider market.
And then that was when they founded HashiCorp to actually start working on
that full time.
And back then you were looking at sort of Vagrant and Terraform and Packer.
And then HashiCorp built the first version of Terraform Cloud, which was then
called Atlas.
And we needed a secrets manager.
So there wasn't a secrets manager.
Internally, they were like, well, we need to build this secret service.
So they built Vault.
And then after Vault had been built, which was specifically designed just for the
first version of Terraform Cloud, somebody was like, hang on a minute,
that's actually really useful.
We should make that a tool for other people to use.
And I think having that ethos has been really, really useful.
So I hope that we'll see a lot more companies that do exactly the same thing.
You know, it might be some engineers who are working for an organization and they
built a really useful tool.
Then they go and they set up a startup and they can build that tool and work on it
and allow, you know, it solves the problem for everyone else.
I think that's a really nice way of developing software, rather than, you
know, the kind of the just sitting around thinking about what should we build.
When you've got an actual need, which is based on knowledge of the problem,
I think you create really, really good software.
And I think I'm hopeful we'll see a lot more of that.
But we saw this sort of good practices in the past, like the company, like out of my
mind, top of my mind right now is maybe like Netflix, open source, their Chaos
Monkey project and so on.
So basically, each company is sort of a development in its own tooling for
suiting their needs and figure out, well, maybe somebody else is having similar
problems.
Let's work on this.
And I see a lot of nice open source software or tools came out of that and sort
of a community growth out of that.
And people contributed to this.
So it seems like a lot's been going on in that sense.
Yeah, I mean, I think like in general, that whole sort of change in the way that
we share information has been like huge from, I remember when I was at university
and I was studying at university, I needed Linux.
And back in the day, you didn't have much of a modem, right?
But I had to, I bought a book, a textbook from a bookstore, and it came with a CD
of, I think it was Suze.
And that was how I got access to Linux.
If I needed some software, I would generally have to pay for it.
So like I needed, I remember working on an application and the application needed to
do some very basic image manipulation.
Like I'm talking cropping and now I could have wrote that myself, but at the same
time, the internet didn't exist.
So like determining what is the specification of a JPEG, right?
What is the JPEG specification?
What's the file format?
The actual software frameworks at the time, certainly like ASP.NET didn't
have that capability built in.
So it would be a huge amount of effort to try and even do something very, very
simple, like create a JPEG resizer.
And there was no free software to do this.
So you had to go and buy a library, which was great for the folks who
were selling the libraries, but it meant that everything just went really quite
slow, you know, you didn't have the ability to accumulate knowledge.
And then of course, when organizations, I think, started to get and realize
that we've got this learning, we've consumed some learning from other people.
So let's put back into the industry and share our learning and creating
a sort of an open software model.
It's just benefiting absolutely everywhere because now we've
got the access to the knowledge.
We obviously have access to the tools and to the organizations like Netflix.
Like for Netflix to publish their Chaos Monkey is of zero competitive
disadvantage to them as a video platform.
And I think a lot of organizations are kind of recognizing that same thing.
I think we're all benefiting hugely, hugely from that.
Yeah.
Yeah, I agree.
Like one thing that I really value about HashiCorp is whatever product was
released, it was super well engineered and designed, and I think that a lot of
solutions were also solving problems in the most smooth way that you could solve it.
I remember, maybe we should just mention a few products because when I was a
youngster, I didn't realize that Vagrant was a HashiCorp product.
And then when there was the era where we were building gold images for a virtual
machines in the cloud, there was this Packer.
And then after a while I started focusing, you know, if there is a great director
that you see a movie and then you're like, okay, that's a great movie.
And then you see another movie and you're like, okay, that's also a great movie.
And then you're like, oh, but the director is the same.
Right?
Right.
And then I started being more focused on the company and whatever products they
offer.
And for example, I was always confused.
I know that Nomad is here for a while.
It was here before containers arrived, I think.
Around about the same.
Yeah.
So both Nomad and Kubernetes were probably started around about exactly the same time.
So it was just post-Docker.
And when we were kind of starting to consume like Mesos, which was the most popular
scheduler at the time, and kind of wondering if there were other options, certainly
that was where Mitchell and Armon were thinking when they decided to create Nomad.
And I'm pretty sure that's where like Joe Bader and all were thinking when they
started to think about Kubernetes.
Do you maybe have an idea why Nomad was not picked as as much as maybe some
different products from HashiCorp?
I think it's...
Is it too simple?
No, I don't think so.
Like, I think it's an interesting one.
I mean, I suppose, I think one of the...
Well, so if we look at it in terms of timelines, I remember way back and we were
talking about replacing Mesos.
Yeah.
And we wanted to adopt something else.
Now, the first time I ever saw Armon, I was speaking at a conference in London and
he was speaking there talking about Nomad.
And so I went to, I was a HashiCorp fan.
We were using a lot of their tools at Not On The High Street.
So I went to see this talk because I wanted to know what this new scheduler was.
And at the time it was just the initial alpha release.
It looked really interesting.
And Kubernetes at the time was, there was this whole thing about, oh, you
shouldn't be running it in production.
It's not ready for production.
And there were rough edges as there always are with software.
I think the thing that maybe HashiCorp had against it, in terms of like, if you
want to look at that as a race of some sort, was that the team at HashiCorp
that were working on Nomad probably back then were probably about two or three
people.
And then you have the entire organization and the weight of Google.
But I think the key thing around those two things is that folks gravitated to
one solution, then you have sort of an ecosystem that spins up around that.
And then that accelerates that sort of drive.
I think Nomad never really got too much in that.
I still think it's a fabulous scheduler and it would probably be my primary
choice because I love the fact that it's so versatile.
And it is, I wouldn't say, in some ways it's easier to use, in some ways it's
more complex.
I think there's pros and cons to everything.
But I think it was literally just a thing that people just sort of said, look, I
just want to run containers, then Kubernetes, and then all of the, if you
Google how to run a container, you're going to get Kubernetes.
It's just a snowball.
I don't think Nomad is done by any real odds though.
I think Nomad's been there for probably about seven years now.
And I think keep your eyes on it because I think we're kind of working on some
really, really cool stuff and the versatility of having the capability to
schedule multiple different things, VMs, ECS tasks, if you want, Docker
containers, raw binaries.
Jar files.
Jar files, of course.
Right.
If you're running Java, if you're like, do you really need to containerize
your Java applications?
Well, if you're running Kube, the answer is yes.
But the thing is you don't.
And yeah, so I think that versatility could actually be really interesting for
when we look at the post-container generation, which I don't think is very
far away.
So, but yeah, I think it was literally just the, you know, it was appetite in
the community.
People gravitated towards a particular product.
Still a lot of users use Nomad.
Don't get me wrong, but of course it's not as big as the sort of Kubernetes, but
they do different things in different ways.
I suppose it, whatever, whatever your choices.
Is it like based on what you're seeing, is there like the product of HashiCorp
that is like far more popular or saying, well, this is our most popular or most
used product?
I know all of them are in the whole.
I mean, without a shadow of a doubt, Terraform.
I mean, I think literally without a shadow, I mean, even if you look at the
simplest of metrics around GitHub stars, it's far out, out sort of ways, any of
the other tools.
I mean, I don't, like I was asking somebody for numbers on this the other
day because I've heard some things.
It's definitely in millions.
Like I've heard quotes of the 10 millions.
I think we had, we've had a, they just had a billion downloads of the, the
Terraform AWS provider, which is pretty, pretty crazy.
And you don't have to go too far.
It gets mentioned a lot.
I mean, when people are talking about things like provisioning infrastructure,
creating infrastructure, even deploying applications, it comes up a lot.
So it's, it's, it's definitely very, very popular.
And I like it as a tool as well.
I mean, I'm slightly biased of course, but yeah, probably that.
In terms of like, what's the second most popular, I mean, you know, console is
still powering huge, huge, huge, huge, huge part of the internet.
There are some large, large numbers of console clusters running.
And at one point I, and please don't quote me on this, but I'm sure I read a
statistic that it was one of the most deployed applications to things like AWS,
because it was like a core part of people's microservices state, where that
goes with, with Kubernetes, because obviously Kube has etcd built into it.
Will we see a shift?
Possibly, but at the same time, console has, has shifted, you know, console
has additional capabilities around sort of macro segmentation service mesh
capabilities to bring it into the new world.
So it's, it's not, it's not gone.
And then there's Vault and Vault is, I think, I don't want to say like it's
becoming a sort of a, an industry standard for secrets management, but it's, it's
certainly one of the, the more mentioned tools when, when people are looking
for a secrets management solution.
I can add that you basically set some goals or some standards regarding Vault
because like I personally tried different or let's say alternative products.
And in the end they try to like have the same API or say API calls as you guys did.
So to have this, this transparency and being able to switch to something different.
Interesting.
I was thinking like, I'm surprised that, that Vagrant is not among first three
because I, whenever I, I joined any, any developer teams, I saw that like Vagrant
is there, maybe they, they didn't know about it, but somehow something, some
things are basically running, running in Vagrant.
I would, you know, I'm going to look up the numbers on this, but I know that
Vagrant is still wildly popular.
So in, and as well for me, Vagrant was the first HashiCorp tool that I ever used.
At the time I was working at a UK supermarket and we were, we were wanting
to run functional tests for our iOS application and our Android applications.
And this needed massive parallelization and we needed the capability of
running a clean room environment.
We didn't want to be installing software on top of software.
Now, specifically for, for Apple, and this is, you know, we're
going back nearly 10 years now.
There was no way to kind of just virtualize an OS X instance.
You, you could spin up OS X on an OS X, I'm sorry, on an Apple machine using VMware.
So what we did was we, we integrated, we used Vagrant to basically spin up
and these virtual machines on Apple hardware, which was pre-configured.
Then we could run, use this to execute our functional tests.
And we were kind of orchestrating all of that with Jenkins.
And, and it worked great.
Like, you know, long before any, any of the sort of the, there was any
sort of CI based platforms to do this.
And that was my introduction to Vagrant.
So then I started to use it for building development machines, but, but at the
same time, I also discovered things like Docker and, and for me, like the, if I
just needed a post-grade database, which I mostly did for my, my development
work or something along those lines.
Spinning that up in Docker was incredibly fast.
But Vagrant is hugely, hugely popular.
When I joined HashiCorp nearly seven years ago, and we were talking about my
role as a, as a kind of an advocate and the tooling that, and I remember the sort
of, Arman was kind of saying, well, look, you know, Vagrant is not really something
as we talk about as developer advocates, because the community is just so vast
that it kind of is self, self-fulfilling, which was just incredible.
I mean, it's absolutely amazing.
So yeah, Vagrant, Vagrant is still pretty big.
Like, I don't know on the numbers, I don't know, but you're probably right.
There's, there's a huge amount of Vagrant still going on, on around there.
I think if you don't use Docker for stuff, you're probably using Vagrant.
Before we go to the next question or next topic, I would like to thank our
supporters on Patreon that help us produce this.
So there is some cost with production of this podcast from audio to video.
So I would like to thank our Patreons and our two sponsors, two companies
are sponsoring this, or are our supporters, and that's 3FS and Human Frog.
So thank you for that.
Um, yeah, my question would be, I was, I was having a presentation earlier
today, um, at the conference and I was so surprised how Terraform really
got popular in our region, um, and how many people know of it and how many
people now use it at work.
Um, and I think that that really changed in the last two years.
Um, because when I was picking it up, I was more of a lonely rider, super
excited, uh, so that I can, um, basically spare some bugs when I go to lunch,
because I can destroy the whole deployment and then reapply it.
And my lean notes, uh, invoices were coming on 50 pages, uh, built for every
minute, two cents, and then just pages and pages of, of VMs.
Uh, and each, each line was just like two cents, two cents, two cents,
because I was creating and destroying, creating, applying and destroying.
Um, but I would still like you to explain to more junior folks what
Terraform is, and maybe I guess there are also some folks listening that
are not super into, um, infrastructure.
Uh, what is this tool?
So I think it, it basically allows you to define infrastructure in a declarative way.
So you can create a text file, which defines what a piece of infrastructure
might look like, a load balancer, a virtual machine, a network security
group, those types of things.
And you do that in, in a language, HCL, the HashiCorp configuration language,
which is, is kind of a, I always think of it as if, if, if Jason and YAML had
got together and had a child, HCL would be that child.
But it's a beautiful child.
It's a very, it's a very pretty child.
Yeah.
It's like, um, I'm trying to think of like, you know, Brad Pitt and who else?
Anyway, but, but by doing that, what, what you get is the
ability to define infrastructure.
Now, what I think is important about Terraform is, is not so much the
declaration, I think the declaration has been done before, but I think what's,
what's clever about Terraform is the fact that it uses a graph, so it's graph based.
So you can basically say that the, the output, for example, from a virtual
machine, which might have the output of a, uh, a private IP address can be
the input into another resource.
So for example, a load balancer.
And because of that graph base, what it means is that when you do your,
your sort of your Terraform apply, Terraform works out the order in
which it needs to create resources.
So it knows that it can't create the load balancer until the
private IP is available, which means it needs to create the virtual machine first.
So it like, that actually helps a lot because it means that you no longer need
to kind of have those exceptions or, um, or things the, the other benefit is where
you can parallelize things to say you're creating 30 virtual machines.
You don't need to do them in sequential order.
Terraform can basically go, well, I'm going to create 30 at once,
which, which reduces the time.
So I think those are the, for me, those things that were like brilliant
when I started using it, I think where I appreciate it moving forward as well
is the feedback loop that Terraform gives me.
So it will tell me what has changed.
And I think that, that again is, is kind of the difference of when they
were building the tool out, they think, right, okay, things needed to be
graph-based because we needed this, this dependency, but we also need to
give feedback because we want to understand what has changed.
I don't want to just wipe out my infrastructure every time I do an apply.
I don't want to kind of do this additive update.
I want to, I want to be very prescriptive on, on, um, those changes, what's changed
and understanding what's changed, which, which helps you to not make mistakes,
which is always a, a benefit.
And I think for those reasons is why it's been very, very popular for, for me as
well, like, I think it's the accessibility.
So like I, Terraform is the tool that led me to apply for a job at HashiCorp.
Even though I was using Vagrant, I was using console at the
time, uh, and some Packer, I think.
But I was working as a developer and I wanted to deploy an application service.
So I went to see our DevOps team and I'm like, look, I want to deploy this, this
service, it was actually a Lambda and the team were like, well, we know nothing
about Lambda, but we had a good DevOps culture, so they're like, look, if, if
you can figure this out and you can help us understand what's going on here and
you can do it in a way that kind of adheres to our principles, which is
everything must be version control and CICG driven, then we will support
you on, on, on whatever you want to do.
And I thought, that's brilliant.
Right.
So I went away and I looked at a number of different tools.
They were using Ansible.
I couldn't figure out Ansible.
I mean, it, um, you know, I was, I'm kind of looking at a very, I'd used
Chef before and I kind of got Chef, but at the same time, when I'm doing my
research, I came across this thing called Terraform and, and I'm like, immediately
Terraform had the capability for me to deploy this Lambda.
And I figured it out literally in a, um, in an evening when I was just sitting on
the sofa, working, uh, watching TV with my wife and that was, you know, it just
resonated.
So then I took that back to, to the team and they're like, well, we don't use
Terraform, we use Ansible.
But again, we had this agreement.
It was like, well, if it's simple enough, we can understand it and you understand
it and you're happy, then we can come to a compromise.
And that, that for me, when I was actually looking through that Terraform
documentation and working through that role, and at the time I was, I wasn't so
happy in my current role.
It was, there were organizational challenges, which, which was like sad
because I loved the team and I loved the work, but there was a little link at the
bottom of the Terraform documentation, which is like, come work at HashiCorp.
And I remember sitting and complaining to my wife and she said, look, why don't
you just go find a new job?
And I saw this link at the bottom of the Terraform documentation because I've
been working on how to deploy my Lambda and I clicked on it and there was a role
for a developer advocate based in the US.
So I filled in the form and I sent off an email and I said, Hey, look, I live in
London, but I can move to the US or can you possibly move the rule to, to London?
Well, seven years later, I'm still there.
So I'm very fond of Terraform.
Yeah.
Maybe I can add a bit like, I knew about Terraform and then I tried it
out and I don't know that was, yeah, a few years back and I really upped my game.
So I would say like, if you're interested in infrastructure,
you really need to learn it.
And for me as a independent consultant, I need to try out a lot of stuff.
So I don't move somewhere and I don't, I don't get super familiarized into AWS,
into specific services that a company might use.
So I want to maintain a broad knowledge of everything that is there, but I also
want to dive in so much that I can deliver.
And for me having, so Terraform comes with providers which implement different
cloud providers and the documentation of all the resources in Terraform are kind
of documented in a standard way because they just document the resources
themselves and for me nowadays, it's so much easier to try out different
clouds, just like move around, just like use DigitalOcean, use Vultr, use
Linode for my smaller companies and then all the three big clouds for other
customers and it really, really helped me out.
And I also didn't have this bad feeling, you know, when I came to the office and
then I click around the dashboard the whole day, right.
And then I was like, cool, this is well, kind of expensive, right?
It will cost me probably, I don't know, 40 euros a day, but I don't want to delete
everything right now because tomorrow morning I will have to do the same drill.
Right.
And if you're clicking through a UI to do that, then you might
not be able to reproduce it.
And I think this is a key thing as well, like when people are saying like, well,
why should we bother using infrastructure as code?
I can click a button to create my Kubernetes cluster or I can click some
more buttons to set up the load balancer and the security rules and stuff like that.
And that's great.
But what if somebody comes in and deletes your project?
And it was like to my buddy, Eric and I, we did a, we were doing a talk on
Terraform for DigitalOcean a few years back and the premise was all about using
Terraform to provision DigitalOcean clusters.
And so we're setting all of this up and we built everything up in Terraform and
Eric said, Hey, can you, we had a couple of clusters.
He's like, can you delete this cluster?
So I went into the UI and I just clicked a button and I just, I deleted the wrong
cluster, so I actually wiped out our main infrastructure cluster and like, and I'm
like, um, yeah, Eric, I've just deleted the production infrastructure and he's
like, well, that was stupid and I'm like, well, yeah, well, what do you expect?
Anyway, but this was kind of going into the talk and then I'm like, but hang on
we've already defined this with Terraform, so Terraform apply five minutes later,
it was all back up, you know, and, and this was, it was kind of in some ways
like, you know, we're doing this talk about why you should use infrastructure
as code and I'd actually proven the point by doing the thing that I was
trying to say you shouldn't ever do.
Yeah.
And, um, and that was, that was amazing.
Like the ability to basically always reproduce what you've, you've created
just by running this, this, um, this one command, this Terraform apply, or tear
it down again, being able to remove everything so you can save money because
it's not just production infrastructure that we've got, we've got test
environments, thousands of dev environments, thousands of test
environments, prod, pre-prod, like depending on the size of the
organization, a lot of, a lot of things.
If you can define that declaratively and you can be a hundred percent
certain, nigh on a hundred percent certain that when you do Terraform
apply, you get exactly what you had the last time, then with safety, you
can tear stuff down and you can start saving, saving money and saving
resources, but it also helps with experimentation.
And I think this is like core to the ethos of where Hashcorp are thinking
with things like Terraform and things like Packer about the, you might've
heard the term cattle, not pets.
I, um, I think it's, it's core, right?
It's like, so rather than having this additive process where you'll install
software on top of software, what you do is you create something brand new,
which has that combination stack and you throw the old stuff away.
And the reason for that is that it's reproducible.
It's not always reproducible to recreate the layers.
Um, if, if you've done that as in a sort of a layered approach, because
software packages change, um, software packages may be unavailable.
There may be an outage.
Like what happens if there's an outage on apt and you don't have like a, you
know, a, a sort of a cache when you're trying to draw, deploy some production
infrastructure in the middle of an outage or you're in trouble, but, but if
you take the kind of the declarative approach with Packer and you've got
these baked images, then it doesn't remove the risk.
It reduces the, the kind of the risk and increases, um, speed as well.
So I think it's a great tool.
Like I'm, uh, I, I completely agree.
And I'll ask the, like for the audience or the, the, the, the, the, let's say
CIS admins who are the companies that are not yet using Terraform or not yet
trying to define their infrastructure as code, uh, there's this question
of how to introduce Terraform.
Once you already have something deployed, so once like the
production is already there.
So this is like the most common use case.
What to do, because Terraform is great for greenfield deployment for deploying
something new for starting from scratch.
Awesome.
Yeah.
What to do in cases when like there's so much legacy in production.
Well, how to introduce, you have any, any bits and tricks, how
to, how to, um, do this kind of shift?
Yeah.
So it, I mean, it's always been possible to Terraformify.
Is that, I probably created a thing like if marketing are watching, I'm sorry.
Um, but Terraformify is now a thing.
Um, it's always been possible to, to turn existing infrastructure into
Terraform because there's always been the, the import command.
The problem that's always been with the import command is it
would just bring in the state.
So for folks who are not familiar with Terraform, you've got this concept
of state, which defines what exists and then your Terraform
configuration is what will be.
Now, when you've got an existing resource, you need
configuration and you need state.
So the import command would just create the state, which meant you
then had to go and write the, you know, you had to go and write the, the
HCL for each of those things, which matched the state and it was, I mean,
it was possible, I mean, you could automate it in some aspects, but it
was, it was time consuming.
It was a bit of a, it was a bit of a chore and there was tooling.
Um, I think it was Terraform, it was maybe like a Google project, which,
which could, can do some of this stuff.
But what we did in the last release of, um, Terraform, which just came
out this summer is we've updated the import command, so now you can
actually define an import stanza, point it to an existing resource in your
cloud and what Terraform will do is it will both import the state and
it will generate the HCL for you.
So you, you know, you can take even large existing pieces of infrastructure
and start kind of pulling them in.
So you can start managing them with, with Terraform, which, which
I think is a good step forward.
And again, this isn't an early stage feature.
It was only, only this summer.
And there's a lot more to do with that.
And, and of course people like to modularize things.
So it, it's not going to figure all of that out for you, but it, it's
definitely better than having to like hand, hand roll all of this stuff.
So I think you can do it.
Um, and I think there's, I think it's worth doing, but, but I think
like, should you, should you do everything?
I mean, as an exercise that could be expensive.
So maybe what you've got to look at is what is changing all of the time?
Like, so if for example, you've got 20 servers and only one of them changes,
maybe just the important thing is just to Terraform that one, that one server.
Uh, it doesn't have to be an exercise where it's all or nothing, but, but I
definitely think there is a benefit that wherever there is change that you, if you
manage that change with Terraform, you are reducing your, your risk, um, because
of the, the, the knowledge you get from the, the change diffs, um, but again,
that, that reproducibility, that consistency, the, the ability to recreate
something, if somebody goes into your production and clicks the big red button
and then just blindly copies the delete thing into the box and then realizes
that that was actually the wrong account that they've done it in, and they've
just deleted the production.
That's a great disaster recovery exercise.
That's how we learn.
I mean, right.
Yeah.
If, if, if you did your homework right and, uh, the, the, the Terraform, uh,
like it's, it's written correctly.
Like this is one way to, to actually test it.
Yeah.
And I think that's the nice thing, right?
Like, so when you, you, you have this common workflow, the there's, so I mean,
Terraform will work with multiple clouds.
It doesn't like, if you can know how to, the resource standards for
defining a virtual machine in AWS is different to the one in GCP and in
Azure and in DigitalOcean, subtle differences because each of those
clouds have got different features and capabilities.
But the thing is around the workflow, if you understand the workflow, if you
understand how Terraform plan, how it apply works, how destroy works, how you
define resources and you can create variables and modularization and, and
then the, the, the kind of the workflow of automating that, so using Terraform
within multiple environments, um, and doing automated deploys, when you get
good at that, what it means is that you can, your disaster recovery is
potentially getting tested every time you do a build.
So if you do a build to dev, you're also kind of testing the, the Terraform code,
which is going to deploy your products.
And so you'll, you'll catch things that maybe I'm using a, an out of date schema
or maybe there's a configuration problem.
Um, so I think it, it just massively reduces the, your risk and gives you
this, this, this great capability to, to recover in the incident that something
does happen, um, which, which has got to be a good thing.
Yeah.
You're right.
Um, recently there have been a lot of news about Terraform and a license change.
Yeah.
Um, and yeah, we just want to ask you what's the fuss all about?
I mean, I think, I think folks are, so there's been the change.
The change has been that we've, we've, we've relicensed Terraform core to a BSL
license so that that BSL license has certain restrictions on use.
Now the, without kind of going right into the terms of the, the kind of the legal
side of things that the terms of, of kind of the restrictions are that for 99.999999%
of people who were using Terraform, they can continue to do so.
And they continue to use it for free without any implications on the license.
What the, the license change was, was kind of is really where it really starts
restriction is if, for example, say you're building a Terraform cloud, then that,
that the, the license then starts coming into a force.
So because you're in, you're creating a service using Terraform, which is in
competition to one of, one of HashiCorp's services.
Now, again, I just want to kind of say that that's not necessarily a, a sort
of a, a pure black or white thing, because we do have the capabilities
around license exemption.
So if you're, you know, say for example, you're just, you've got an internal
platform, which is using Terraform and your, maybe there's a gray area of it.
You're in a competing business with HashiCorp.
Can you still use Terraform?
I mean, I think the answer is probably yes, but in the, the, the licensing
folks will, will, will sort of, will, will help you out, clarify that.
So I think a lot of folks were like, well, why did we do it?
Is this not mega evil corp?
Are we, are we kind of like, you know, are we, are we going against
the spirit of, of, of open source?
And, and I think the key thing is that the code is still open now.
So it is technically always going to be open.
If you want, you can fork Terraform and prior to the sort of the BSL license
change, you can do what you want with, with that code, it's still the, I think
it was MPL or whatever, so that, and the, the future code will always be publicly
available, obviously with the, the BSL license.
So as we add new features to Terraform, that code will be completely transparent
and available inside of the, the, the public repo.
And again, I just want to add as well, it is sort of Vault, Nomad, console, et cetera.
Now, what we haven't changed on a licensing perspective are things like the
providers, because the, the providers are in most instances, not, not actually our
code, so, so for example, the folks at DigitalOcean build their own provider,
Google contribute to their own providers, as do Microsoft, as do sort of Amazon.
That, that license hasn't, hasn't changed.
Like, why did we do it?
I think that's the key thing.
Like, why would you do this?
I mean, the, the thing is that with, HashiCorp invests and has invested over
the sort of the last sort of 10 years, quite a large amount of money into, into
Terraform, obviously Terraform would nowhere near be as, as, as popular as it
is if it hadn't been for, for wonderful sort of community contribution, but we
have a huge number of sort of engineers and product engineers, you know, a huge
amount of support that goes into that, which way that we made money from
Terraform as a, as an entity, I mean, we're, you know, we're a company that
was through Terraform, Terraform cloud.
And the, the kind of, I think that the drive around the change is to kind of
protect that investment, because if we can do that, what it means is we can keep
those engineers because we don't, you know, we want to keep the engineers and
we want to keep innovating on Terraform.
We want to keep putting that knowledge in.
We want to keep it as a, as an amazing tool that most of the
community can use, use for free.
And, and I think that was kind of the, you know, that's the, the, the primary
sort of motive behind the change.
It's, it's not that we're kind of moving this as a precursor to one
day, it's just going to be like, Hey, we're going to stop using Terraform.
And everybody's been like hoodwinked and you're now going to have
to pay us mega dollars to rebuild.
No, no, no, no, not in the slightest.
It's, it's literally just, we're just trying to protect that investment.
99.999999% of people you have, nothing's changed.
Um, and the, the main argument that I like saw from the community is like,
this is so widely defined that like, it's, it's not black and white.
Yeah.
And it's hard to say.
Uh, and I think this is the, the, why, why everybody in everybody active in,
in, in communities is, is, is sort of a saying now that like
HashiCorp is now the evil corp.
Yeah.
I mean, I think, you know, we, I, I, I'll be honest with you.
I think we, you know, we weren't the first people to, to do this.
Um, there's been a number of companies who've relicensed open
source to protect their investments.
And I probably won't be the last either.
I think if, if anything, if there's criticism that we've, we've maybe not
managed the, the information on, on the change, then, you know, we'll, we'll
take that and, and see if we can do a better job around that.
I think it is complex because it is quite a, like, I mean, even if you
read something like the NPL or a GPL license, they are, for me, I'm not a
legal person, it's, it's a, it's a complicated document, so maybe that is,
um, that, that can be confusing that you look at this wall of text, but, but
ultimately the, let's say the key thing is that if you're not in an organization,
which is directly competing against any of HashiCorp services, you're unaffected.
If you're unsure, then I think it's licensing at hashicorp.com.
You can sort of get you in touch with, with somebody, or if you're coming
to HashiConf, we're going to have, um, folks there who will be able to help
with licensing queries and things like that.
We're more than happy to, to sort of clarify those.
And I would like to bet that like most of the time it's going to be, you know, you're fine.
Um, and, and it's certainly nothing we wanted to do deliberately.
You know, we, we, we didn't want to cause any upset.
It wasn't, um, and, and I, uh, any, anything sort of
malicious or anything like that.
We.
We're really just trying to protect the investment so that we can keep
investing and keep, um, keep, keep, keep expanding Terraform's capabilities
and, and, um, make it a even better and better product and something we can
use for the next decade as well.
Um, I know if you can maybe like comment now that the community now
opened, uh, open TF or open TOFU.
Uh, so basically it's a, it's a, it's a fork of, of previous, previous
version of, of, of Terraform.
Um, I don't know.
Yeah.
What, what could we expect?
Because we, we definitely saw this in, in, in the past.
Yeah.
Um, and, uh, in the end, this kind of fighting, it's not like, it's not good.
No, of course it doesn't bring any, any, any
progress.
No, I mean, so I think, I mean, that was, that was perfectly a legitimate thing.
And, um, so open TOFU exists.
Um, it was created by, uh, a few organizations who were obviously
affected by the license, but who also felt strongly about the license change
and wanted to, to keep things on a, uh, an MPL license.
Now what that they're, they're obviously doing there, they've created the fork.
They will then create a distribution, um, and a registry and all of those
sorts of things, which, um, are in line with, with the sort of the license.
I don't know what the future will hold.
It, um, it's, it's difficult to kind of, to say like, will one win out?
Will we end up with, with the sort of the, like Jenkins Hudson or something
along those lines, I just don't know.
Like all I can say is that as an organization, HashiCorp is 1000%
committed to creating Terraform as the best tool that we can offer the industry
to be able to create the best support and services, um, around it.
And, and that we're going to sort of continue to do that.
Does it mean that sort of, um, providers will kind of dry up and disappear then?
You know, I mean, very possibly, right.
Some, some, some, some people might determine that they're no longer wants
to, to create a provider for Terraform.
Some people might say they don't want to create a provider for OpenTofu.
Some people might end up creating both and having to support the two.
So it's, um, I guess, you know, we just, it's, it's early days.
Like, I mean, we, we just have to wait and see, wait and see how
things, um, wait and things pan out.
But as I say, all I can say is as a HashiCorp representative, we are
committed to keeping Terraform free for, for the vast majority of people
were committed to creating the best tool that it can be and, um, yeah,
like we, you know, we genuinely love the community and everything that
they've done to support that.
And, um, if anybody feels aggrieved by the things that we've done and I, you
know, I can apologize personally from that, but, but it is, you know, it's,
it's a thing we want to, we want to keep things to be able to protect.
And so we can keep it pushed forward.
I don't know what else I can say around those things.
I think it's, yeah, I couldn't, I can understand that.
Like even company needs to do some trade-offs and, and, and, and like it
can't be like win for everyone.
Yeah.
Um, but in that sense, I completely understand you.
Um, and, um, I can also imagine like the, the fuss on the other side, but, but still.
Yeah.
And I, and I, I understand that as well.
I mean, I'm, I am an open source user as well, but like for me and, and I, and I'll
be honest with you, like, and I'm talking on a personal level here, not, um, sort
of ignore the H on my shirt, but when, when we made this sort of change and I
sat down and I'm sort of in my head trying to rationalize, well, what does
open source actually mean, mean to me?
And, and I thought about this and like, and to be honest, I started looking
and I'm like, I very rarely actually look at the license.
The key thing for me was the ability to benefit from somebody else's learning.
The, the ability to, to not have to reinvent the wheel.
I mean, back to my JPEG example, like not having to do that every time.
As a, as somebody who has an open source project, spend a large amount of
my own personal time working on, I mean, we've been sort of thinking, well, you
know, is, is the NPL license really, is it, is it, is it work for me as an individual?
Um, but, but in general, like the, the thing for me that's most important is
that the, the source code still exists.
I can still see what's going on.
I can still learn from it.
Um, and I can still consume something, uh, which was always being intended
that we wanted to create something which was, uh, you know, free, free to use,
which benefits the community as a whole.
So, yeah, I don't know what, like, what do you think?
I mean, you have opinions.
What, what?
I'm, I'm, I'm sort of, uh, looking like looking from the distance because yeah,
like I said, we saw that with like Mongo, we saw that with Elasticsearch.
Um, and I was never in a way affected.
So like me as a, as a, as a consultant or me as a working for, for a company,
but again, it, it really, again, in the end difference, whether this company
is actually like selling this, this product or what, what's building,
like reselling this, um, forward.
Um, and yeah, we saw that like, I, I, in a way I understand both sides.
Like the way you explain it now, I completely get it.
Um, it, and I also understand the other side saying that like things are not
like defined, um, the way that's like, there could be like exceptions or like,
and so on.
And, and I, yeah.
And I think that's like, if, if I've got criticism around that, then I
criticize the lawyers and I think it's, I think it's, you know, I think it's
fair to, to be, to, to have a kind of a, an inherent hatred of lawyers.
I think that they're generally kind of, if we want, we all want to kind
of agree on one thing, but no, I mean, the, the legal document, uh, and it
is a kind of a legal documents.
It's obviously a contractor license is, is difficult and it's, it, what we've
tried to do is make sure that the, the vast majority can continue as normal
using Terraform as they always have, but have that clause in there, which, which
kind of, um, stops, uh, stops folks from kind of like leveraging all of that
hard work for, and which, which again, affects us to, to kind of invest in
Terraform and with always, when you end up with that sort of thing, it, it,
it always becomes complex.
It's not, cause it's difficult to say who is a competitor, who isn't, you
can't really define that in the license, but again, to kind of reiterate those
things, like, I think if, if you think that you, you're not sure, if you're not
sure that you're competing with HashiCorp, I think realistically you're probably
not, and licensing at HashiCorp will, will be able to clarify that for you.
And I think they'll sort of, you can give you sort of written, um, confirmation
that you're, there's no sort of, uh, infringement of licensing.
Um, so I, um, and I hope that as I say, there's time, it's only been what, a
month or so that we'll, we'll get a little bit more sort of, um, used to, to
kind of dealing with things, but, um, yeah, like honestly, if you, if there's
anybody who has any, any sort of concerns, reach out to me, I'm more than happy to,
to, to, to chat, to, to kind of, um, put you in touch with people.
If you want to speak to, uh, some, some of the sort of, or get a sort of legal
answer from, from HashiCorp's team, then we can arrange all of those sorts of things.
Awesome.
Uh, let's go to more relaxed topics.
What do you do like to disconnect from all the technology?
Do you have like any hobbies?
Yeah.
So I, I like, well, so firstly I, I do like sport.
So I, um, I swim ultra, um, uh, well, marathon distance and
ultra marathon distance swimming.
So basically anything, well, marathon distance in swimming is 10 K and above.
Um, so I'll, I do, I do a lot of that, which is, I find very meditative.
I mean, if you've, um, I don't know if anybody swims or if you've, if you've
ever swum sort of lap swimming, it's, it's very, you know, meditative, especially
when, uh, if you're swimming front crawl and you've just kind of face in the water.
I find that, um, when you're swimming like between what could be four to six,
seven hours, um, it's very, very relaxing.
So I, and I enjoy floating around in water as well.
So there's, um, I do that.
I do like video games.
Um, I've, I kind of started falling into the slippery slope of sim racing
recently, um, which I started playing Gran Turismo 7, uh, in VR too.
And I enjoyed that very much.
And then all of a sudden the steering wheel appeals in my house.
And then before you know it, there's a, a, a seat and, uh, yeah,
that's, that's been a slippery slope.
And recently I've been getting into iRacing, uh, which I'm, I'm quite enjoying.
But, uh, I also like, you know, other video games.
Um, I've been playing Starfield, Baldur's Gate 3, um, yeah.
And, well, and then of course I, I do a lot of writing, so I'm still
working on my, my second book, which I'll hopefully get finished soon.
Uh, I'm going to start a new, uh, YouTube channel with, uh, Ivan, who's
hosting here today at DevOps Days, it'll be an honor, called, uh, doing
DevOps where we, we want to kind of get some education, uh, put some
education back, uh, so the concept is that, that Ivan, uh, has, has
learned a lot across his career.
And we want to be able to kind of put that back into, to helping people
who were in the same position as he was when he, when he first began.
And it's always, I enjoy doing stuff like that as well.
It's fun.
I enjoy helping people.
So yeah, pretty much, pretty much I walk my dog.
Um, I'm trying to think, eating ice cream.
There are some nice ice cream shops in the center of Ljubljana.
I can give you a list.
I'm hoping, yeah, later on today we'll maybe check something out.
Uh, awesome.
But, but since you, since you, since you started like, um, passing on like
to, to, to, to, to, to, to newbies, uh, into this world.
So for our audience, since there are a lot of like, um, engineers who are now
at the beginning of their career.
So I don't know, what would be your advice where to start if they are interested
in, in exploring the, the, the DevOps culture and so on, what, what to, what
would be the, the, the tools to start learning the, the, the, the, the, the
things that, that, that should they focus on?
Well, I mean, I think you, you absolutely can't go wrong with Terraform and whether
you kind of, um, you know, you look at that as Terraform, OpenTofu, whatever,
like there is a, as a tool and as a methodology, I think it's something
as a, that's, that's kind of here to stay, I hope.
Um, so I think that's definitely something to look at.
I think learning cloud is really hard.
Like I, I have, um, I spend a lot of time working between a number of different
sort of clouds, depending on what I'm trying to sort of show.
So I think having, doing say like your, your GCP AWS or Azure kind of
certification is always worthwhile because you can get a lot of value out
of how best to sort of leverage, leverage cloud.
Um, I think folks like DigitalOcean are exceptional as well, like, because
it's very, it's very accessible and you don't always need this huge amount
of complexity and DO does, um, a very good cloud at a very good price.
Um, so I think, you know, looking at something like that, one thing I will
say is that I think one of the things that helped me the most when I was
learning was that by teaching that helped me accelerate my own learning.
And, and I will always say to people that, you know, you, you may not
know as much as the expert, but I can guarantee you that if you know
something, you know, more than somebody else.
So by passing that back and by, by kind of having this culture of, of sharing
your knowledge, you're reinforcing that knowledge, but you're also kind of
helping, helping others who they can then can turn, can, can help you.
And then that, that, that really helps drive things.
So folks like yourself, I'm always incredibly appreciative of, and, um,
thank you so much for, for running the podcast and helping get information out
there.
Um, YouTube is incredible.
I mean, I, gosh, I wish it existed when, when I was starting the paper books,
right?
Oh yeah.
Like, I mean, I, you know, I, yeah, but I have, I have like issues with like
YouTube, like I was sort of, uh, like getting knowledge from, from books or
web pages, like you can like scan to the point where, where you need it, the,
the, the information because scanning to the video is, is, is problematic.
Yeah.
I'm, I'm, you know, I'm with you there.
So I think now video seems to be the de facto standard around how information
is, is produced.
And so for example, I'm going to, so I'm going to give you a lightning talk
later on today.
And one of the things around the lightning talk is a slide every 15 seconds.
There's a capability in Google slides where you can set it to auto
advance every 15 seconds.
I could not figure out where this was.
So I Googled it and there was a video and it was a three minute video, which
told me to click on three options.
So I think video is maybe not always the most, um, appropriate source.
As I say, like I'm, um, I've, I've written one book, which published about
five years ago, I'm working on my second one.
Um, I do like video.
I enjoy creating video and I quite enjoy watching video.
Um, but I, I do worry at the same time that we're not writing enough blog posts
and the, the advantage of something like a blog post is it's very easy to index.
So it's, it's very immediate.
If you want to look for a very specific thing, if that can be indexable through,
through the Google search and just pop up in the search box, you can achieve
something very, very quickly.
Whereas if you get a video, which has that information somewhere inside it,
it can be a little bit slower.
So, but some people hate reading, like, you know, some people have difficulties
with, um, with, with, with sort of following, um, printed text.
So having a, the, the medium of video is also very accessible at the same time,
which I think is, it's also a very good thing.
It's like, oh, I think maybe we've got pros and cons.
Awesome.
Uh, I think it's time for us to wrap up.
Yeah.
Uh, Nick, thank you very much for your time.
Thank you for visiting Ljubljana.
I'm excited.
It's a beautiful place.
Yeah.
Um, I would like to thank, uh, the organizer of organizers of Delves days.
I would like to thank Andras.
Thanks.
I would like to thank the whole team in the, at the back, uh,
Otto, Tomas and Rok.
Uh, thank you very much.
And I would like to thank our Patreons and, uh, the two companies that sponsor
our production, 3FS and Humanfrog.
Uh, have a nice day and see you soon.
Or we, you will listen to us soon.
Thank you.