Well, everybody, welcome to our show.
Welcome to Ogrodje, which should be translated to a framework in English.
Welcome to our very first episode that we're going to try to do in English today.
This is something that we want to experiment with, because so far we were all Slovenian
podcast.
And primarily, when we were preparing for this talk show, we waited for a while to get
a speaker that would kind of like transcend our local space and who would be fluent in
English.
And luckily we found such a guest.
The wrong one.
But we'll discuss that why you're the wrong one, but equally, like if our English is so
bad and we need a fallback, you're also fluent in Slovenian, so we can go.
We can also fall back with that.
You took some Slovenian courses, right?
Yes.
So see, you can do bilingual.
You can say at least hello to everybody.
Yeah, here we go.
And what else should we say?
You forgot to mention that this episode is part of the borderless.
Oh yeah, yeah, yeah.
We should definitely tell people that.
So we're going to prefix all the content that's in English with borderless tag or name, which
should hint that we are transcending our borders of our little country, trying to, again, speak
to international guests.
That's the intro for today.
We're going to talk about security, a lot of things around security, but still we'll
try to be more aware about security that's related to developers, I guess, which is your
specialty.
And you're going to be the host today, right?
I'll try.
So yeah, this episode, in a way, it's an honor to have you here, Petra, to sort of
do the connection, how and why.
We met, what, it was the first B-Sides, and I think you were one of the first submissions,
you submitted to the call for papers for B-Sides, and I was sort of cheering.
Come on, we have somebody from Australia that's willing to speak at B-Sides.
How come?
And the funny thing is, like, it's sort of what we joke about.
You mentioned that, like, for that request, you said you want to see Kremschnitta.
And I was like, there's an Australian guy who wants Kremschnitta also there.
So yeah, long story short.
So you're married to Slovene, living in Australia, you're working in security industry, so information
security.
Maybe a good question.
What's sexier, cyber security or information security?
What do you prefer?
I'll go with the former.
So information security.
So we're like skipping the cyber security.
Cool.
So...
Or whatever.
You're trying to find the word.
You're now sort of a regular guest on a yearly basis coming here.
And sort of, in a way, I could basically call you a friend.
Like this friendship, whenever you're around, well, you, in a way, also, like, helping the
local security community here.
So, and for example, like yesterday, you had a great sort of a workshop on Python meetup.
So that's why, like, you're working with developers or like this knowledge.
So in cyber security.
You got me there.
He did a poll on Twitter and he's still, and I think it was 50-50 or something.
Yeah.
It was 50-50.
It depends.
We lost the bat.
Let's just use what...
Depends who you ask.
And if you ask chatGTPA, you have like, it's always referring to cyber security.
So it seems that the buzzword, but okay, we'll stick to information security.
So like this short introduction, who are you?
Like it's sort of like, because in a way, in the intro, we said like, we're going to
host a great hacker.
So are you feeling like this title should suit you?
Like you feel like you...
I mean, hacker has different meanings, right?
Someone who changed something.
It depends.
Or someone to break into things, right?
Or like explore or like wanting to learn, wanting to figure out how things are working.
I think definitely curiosity is part of it, right?
And hacker, I don't know, just kind of, I feel that curiosity more represent the person
who like is into security because kind of you, you want to use the functionality for
the purposes that the engineer who built that or the team that have built that maybe never
thought about it or finding that beautiful edge case that can make this program do something
differently.
Now, obviously, if it impacts people's life or businesses, that become a security issue.
But I think that sense of curiosity, I would say, yeah.
One of the biggest critiques of our podcast is that our guests, our listeners sometimes
need to Google our guests to find out who they are.
So formally, my understanding is that you have a PhD in security and you taught at the
university in Australia.
I'm not sure if you still teach, but you teach...
What did you teach or like?
Can you tell us a bit more about it?
So, I mean, the hardest thing for me is bio, right?
Yeah.
So currently, I'm a lecturer at a university in Down Under.
And well, I teach a master course in, well, I should say cybersecurity related as a technical
course.
But apart from that, I also teach to general developers out there in terms of secure programming.
This was just a transition I had.
I was more, as you know, more on the other side of the game, looking at how do we find
bugs?
How we can find better bugs?
And bugs, sorry, well, it's a dev podcast, so I shouldn't say vulnerabilities or issues.
So yeah.
And then kind of, it was a natural transition.
So let's maybe start in the beginning, how you sort of study this or how you start in
information security?
What made you like this?
Because you definitely did a transition from offensive security to now defensive security
and like teaching developers how to do like secure coding or best practicing in terms
of applying security, best practicing in development, but still.
So I mean, the funny thing is, I always say there is no book for security as you have
a book for PHP and Python and Java, just open it up and you finish it.
You're kind of advanced security guy.
And I think that's the beauty part of it.
I think, again, I want to go back to the sense of security.
How is this started?
Well, someone tried to hack me back in the days.
They tried to, well, we had this newsletter and for some reason that newsletter got popular
and this person had the interest or two people to, well, get some admin access on that newsletter.
And well, they were, I would say talented enough that they built their own backdoor
or Trojan file and they sent it to me and they were asking me, okay, to execute that.
Via mail.
I did execute it.
So spear phishing.
Yeah.
Because they were part of like, well, that community themself, like, okay.
And I'm like, I'm executing this, but it doesn't work.
And after, and then the other guy on the other side of it, there was a chat happening and
he tried with this command, this parameter and none of them works.
And then he keeps asking me to try this and that.
After some point, I just felt there's something fishy going on.
And then after a while, the guy actually gave me a call over the phone, like, hey, are you
sure you're running that?
I'm like, yeah.
But then he said, okay, but have you tried this?
Yeah.
Hmm.
And then the guys, I started asking, uh, but, uh, are you, I'm kind of not sure whether
you're telling me through the guy is telling me, like, why is that?
It's like, oh, because do you know what that file is?
And then I kind of got some idea like, yes, I know, I have no idea what it is.
And then he's kind of like, you are a good hacker.
Like, what is, what does that even mean?
I didn't even say anything.
So long story short, the reason that thing didn't work was not because the program was
failing was because I was using a university internet and they had proxy and the proxy
was blocking all the traffic.
Oh, okay.
And like I thought, I know it, I kind of pretend that I'm executing that file, but I was actually
not doing it.
He was, he was thinking that way.
That kind of got me kind of like, did he like, why would you run malicious software?
So we were talking, yeah, days off when we even didn't call it malware, we was talking
about viruses and AVs.
Okay.
So very early days.
Yeah, kind of early dial up internet and the old internet connections, which, you know,
you could be at programs called Trojans, you know, I don't know, some of you will remember
sub seven or things like that.
You could connect remotely, do stuff, but kind of, that kind of opens up the idea of
the, Hey, there is something more to what you see when you run a program or when you
connect to a network.
And then, yeah, there was no resources.
There was effectively a couple of like CD-ROM, like CD discs that had some hacking tools
on them.
And then you had some text files from, oh yeah, there was a magazine called Frack magazine,
which exists today.
You want to explain what Frack magazine is to young audience?
So back in the early days, that was like, it was like monthly, monthly.
And then when it got like older, it became annually.
But concept was like from like PBSs.
So when like people were interesting in-
This was online or you had to order via mail or something?
They were like also later on the printed copies, but usually the PBSs had like, and they were
like short TXT files with a good description of sort of exploiting or like getting familiar
with, I don't know, technology or concept.
And I'm like from programming or how to, I don't know, program some special computers
or how the, I don't know, the ATM networks work or how the ISPs communicate.
Like they were like, in a way, resourceful manuals, how to get know about some technologies.
So these were like snippets without long explanations?
It got into real details.
So they were like, basically back then, the really good sources where you like understand
how like new technology works.
Yeah.
Pretty technical.
I think one section which I liked the most was phone hacking.
Because we had a really high bill for our internet connection because I was looking
for a way that, hey, can we switch to maybe neighbors?
Yeah.
And those freaking, freaking was like very, very popular.
And like basically everything grew out of that kind of community.
Yeah.
But there's a big gap between, you know, 2023 and the dial-up, what did you do in between
as well?
I mean, that's kind of interest growed in, right?
And then I think, then we are talking about the days that, you know, web apps start to
emerge in CGI bin folders and there's lots of interesting things there.
And then PHP become a thing, right?
And you could almost touch every website and there is like XSS and SQL injection there.
And because they are starting to evolve, we are talking about very early version of MySQL.
And again, it was more like understanding how, I think the way I end up finding some,
actually I have some CVs, goes back to 2005.
You kind of, I actually learned it from a programming way, like I actually learned how
you can build a web app.
And then how you can communicate the database.
Then when someone said, hey, you know, we have this variable here or PHP just gets everything
in the request and dump it in a query.
Well, ah, okay.
So I know that kind of what kind of query will make what, it was not just like, just
go there, put a typical Wikipedia example of a SQL injection.
One equals to one.
It was more like you could think a little bit more further than that.
Okay.
This query does that.
So one equals one will not work, but this other one will work.
So I kind of, it was almost more like a, and I should say there were like forums, like
discussion boards of really, um, enthusiasts that they really want to help, like want to
like help you when you are trying to find an issue or kind of, you are really close
to exploitation.
You could ask question and they will just answer it.
I think that kind of engraved in me that this is like really also nice that you also share
this knowledge.
And I think from beginning was this idea of ethics was always there.
I think it's kind of, kind of, it was not cool that you find this issue and not telling
vendor about it.
But at the time, you know, we are not talking about, you know, these days, majority of the
good businesses, they have these, well, they, they understand there could be a time someone
report a security issue to them.
And there's normally, there is a unwritten rule of responsible disclosure policy.
But back in, back in those days, maybe it wasn't, it was not that clear.
And normally when you report a security bug, often you want some attribution back.
I remember when we were reporting some security bugs to some vendors, we were like, okay,
the only thing we want from you is just mention my name in your next newsletter.
I'll go there.
I'll do it.
Yeah.
Okay.
And you, you started as a, as a, I don't know, researcher or somebody who was like, uh,
chasing, chasing those, those back, exploring on their own or how, how you like?
Uh, well, I mean, it actually started first by like building networks.
I remember like the first thing you do, you know, when I bring up a Windows NT and you
know, set up a network and then you move to Linux, you're like, huh, it's not that easy
even just bringing up a DHCP server needs that much config file.
And there is no sample file out there, like just Google for it, you know, you need to
figure out what each configuration does.
I think they started there, like learning really the, the foundations, learning really
what's how things work from physical layer all the way up to application layer.
And kind of that's, that's how I feel is, and the more you know about how things work,
the more you can kind of challenge these, these assumptions we have to between different
layers, which I always mention it, like the more, you know, how things will translate
into, well, in a different layer of the network, the more you can find that, okay.
Like if this thing doesn't have this specific format, well, guess what?
It could result into a security bot.
I think, I don't think there's any shortcut there to know it.
So this is like, basically through this learning experience, exploring like new technology,
like you mentioned Linux and so on, you basically reach, like migrate to, to, to information
security and like getting all, all that knowledge gives, gave you the, the foundations on, on,
on top.
You could like, I don't know, have a career in, in, in information security.
Yeah, exactly.
I actually, when I, when I was, when I graduated from my, my doctoral degree, I actually didn't
know there is even a job exists that they pay you to find security bugs.
Like I didn't even know there is such a thing even exists because always it was a hobby.
It was always the sysadmin type guy that maybe care about what, how long the password
should be.
And then maybe put some restriction there or to harden their SSH endpoint.
It wasn't really a thing that you could feel, well, someone really would be interested that
you go and ethically review their system and they will pay for it.
I remember I was actually looking for more like a research engineering type positions.
I actually came across all of a sudden with this position that talks about, are you familiar
with your application security issues?
Do you have any experience finding security was on the wall?
It seems like interesting and yeah, and, and working there as a effectively as a consultant,
a penetration tester.
And that's, yeah, getting familiar with the whole story of, you know, yeah, okay, nowadays
you need to do vulnerability scan.
Then you, you report that to your customer, you need to explain, explain that and yada,
yada, yada.
Started there.
Yeah.
But like with, with like in, in, in this process, like you could, we could already say that
you're a veteran in, in, in, in the field.
And like you said, the, the basically jobs in information security back then were like
not known or like not like wanted that, that much.
But now like you have kids finishing college that specialized in, in, in security.
And like you have this new generation of, of, of, of people already very eager to,
to work in, in, in information security field.
And maybe you can like share like how you see this new generation of, of, of, you know,
I don't not necessarily agree with the, whether the colleagues, colleges, or even universities
produce skilled people, but definitely eagerness, not eagerness was there also back then.
Yeah.
Like maybe it was not in a sense of web application hacking or, or cloud hacking, but it was also,
if you remember, we had the whole area of cracking, cracking files, cracking games and
all these things.
And the whole concept of reverse engineering a game to figure out how it works, or you
can just, you know, it's, I remember we were trying to crack the, there was old Prince
of Persia type game, or how can I jump to last level?
And that was my exposure to Hex editor and the things that, Oh, things behind the scene
looks like Hex.
And I thought actually Hex is what machine will understand.
And then I realized, no, actually, no, there is something more layer behind it.
It was more, more those things.
So even those days, there were people who were looking to do this thing, viruses and
things were, was the area that a lot of people wanted to figure, figure things out.
You know, that there are things can go wrong with the system, but, and I don't necessarily
know if there was any college degree, you know, doing it, but okay, coming back to what
was the question?
They were the new generation.
Yeah.
The new generation.
So basically you, from your transition on how you like ended up in, in, in, in this
field or gain this kind of expertise, we can like definitely see the new generation,
like in a way it's sexy to work in information security or, or work as a, as a penetration
tester or a security researcher.
But from, from my perspective, what I see is like this, this young generation or people
not having enough knowledge, fundamental knowledge of understanding, I don't know how a TCP API
networking works or understanding how operation system works.
And, and they just want to like do the sexy stuff in terms of, of hacking and breaking
stuff, but not really understanding what are they like breaking and what is like the layers
below running and why things are working that way.
The things that takes time, the things that you need to spend more time on.
But I'm going to challenge you guys now.
So this could turn into like old people nagging, nagging about the younger generation, right?
But what if, what if, um, the, the layers that you guys mentioned so far have been around
so long that they're so mature and so, so protected and so, you know, all the bugs have
been found and they're so stable that those layers are not with flaws.
So today they're coming from very different angle.
They are, they're approaching from top down, right?
So perhaps then in that case, you need a different kind of skills, which is a good news to hear,
right?
So that was, we haven't based our time, just still fixing the IP port, well, having said
that there was just a vulnerability identified in.
in implementation of one of the Linux distro just recently.
Ping.
Ping ICMP protocol right now, 2023, right?
So it's not that all these layers are so very secure.
I mean, you shouldn't ask me for that.
But definitely there has been a huge improvement, right?
In all those layers, right?
And kind of you assume that, you know,
one of the best things, for example,
like these days you always assume the traffic
that comes from your browser to your API is secure.
It's on a secure channel.
You never think twice, but you go back some years ago,
that was not the case.
Actually, some of the findings that you may find
in the Pentest report was always about SSL.
Oh, you're not using this certificate.
But kind of, sort of, maybe,
I don't want to give a percentage,
but that is kind of gone, which you're happy.
So kind of, we don't really need to report
on those sort of things.
We have definitely improvement
on some front-end frameworks, right?
Like some of the security issues
are really hard to get introduced,
which again, we're glad to see that.
So it's kind of by default,
some of these frameworks enforce some security controls
that if you really want to do something very bad,
there's like a function you can,
they don't limit you,
but the function is called dangerously something.
Yeah.
Something kind of gives you a hint.
You're doing something very fishy.
Which is great, but back in the days,
well, in JavaScript, you have eval.
Is eval dangerous or not?
Yeah.
I think eval should be renamed to something.
Don't call this function ever parameter.
So definitely was an improvement.
But again, coming back to that,
I feel those foundations are necessary.
If you don't know how say computer works,
what processes, how,
and then you want to quickly jump in,
like let's say, learning about Docker security,
container security,
but behind the scene is a process.
Behind the scene is a C group.
Behind the scene is a name space, right?
It's nothing different,
but without that foundation of like, let's say,
I'm not saying you need to know the Linux kernel,
but without that foundation that what are these are,
just jumping in,
running in a scanner,
trying to find a security bug in a container,
not gonna take you far.
If you want to be a thinker in this area,
perhaps one of the really good quotes
I can mention here from one professor in Australia,
he said that in our industry,
we have so many technicians in security,
we just need more engineers,
like people who can come and think.
And to be, I feel to be that engineer,
you really need to understand how things work.
What is like, in your view,
like a big difference between, I don't know,
I will use the term hacker here,
but what's the big difference between a hacker
and senior software engineer?
Is there even a big difference?
And in what way can you like elaborate on this a bit?
So I find like engineers in general
more have this builder mindset.
The mindset of getting things working,
getting things efficient,
getting, get the, you know,
solve that defined problem.
But like someone who is on,
let's say in a hacker or security side
is more like a breaker mindset.
I don't know, I often make this example,
like to build a bridge,
it takes some skillset,
but to blow up that bridge in a controlled manner,
so it doesn't touch the buildings around,
that is different set of skillset.
Whereas the original builder may not necessarily have it.
I actually found this through the workshops that I ran,
that the person,
or some of students I had back in the days
that you find a super talented guy,
he seems to really good in programming,
you know, he doesn't even need any direction.
But I really think,
oh, that person should be great for, you know,
thinking about all these edge cases that,
rare cases that can happen to a software
that can result into a security issue,
but he's just not interested.
They're like, they don't find it attractive.
They don't find it cool.
They actually like to build things.
Yeah.
And it's, that makes sense.
And like, before jumping to the next section,
in this process, like in the beginning you said,
and that's also my experience,
like this InfoSec community worldwide is pretty open.
It's pretty like this knowledge sharing is always there.
Like in a way, like the open source community,
but even more like the way I see it,
even more,
friendly in a way.
And you're also the father of SecTalks.
You're the founder, right?
Father, father, founder, father figure.
And maybe you should like explain,
because basically you build sort of a community in,
let's call it your backyard and then like outgrow
the community, right?
Yeah.
Let's call it your backyard and then like outgrow
this community to copy paste it in different,
around Australia and abroad.
What is SecTalks about?
I think it has started with the whole thing that
you like to visit like-minded people in the industry.
And, you know, security,
although maybe it's a big topic now,
it doesn't have, I don't feel it even have
such a large community of people comparing with perhaps
software development community to some extent.
So it was always good to just, you know,
sit around and just given the nature of security,
there are things that people may not necessarily
talk about it online,
but maybe in a setting, you know,
in some venue,
they may actually talk about it and you may hear
very interesting stories.
So I think, again, that was, again, a natural thing.
You kind of feel, oh, I actually like to visit.
At the time I was in Perth, in Western Australia,
there were some ad hoc events happening there.
And after a while, one of those events that we had,
that like was running for every month,
it suddenly stopped.
And then we just felt this void of, oh, actually,
you know, I want to really meet someone.
And then I was also working for a security consulting
business at the time.
And then I was like, hey, what if, you know,
we just try to run it here, ask around,
and that primarily started.
But the things I think we started from beginning,
I tried to advocate it was this whole idea
of the no bullshit.
Like, you know, you come here more than welcome.
We would love to talk to you.
You can even give a talk, but keep the bullshit.
But this is sort of like, I would say,
we, the security people, we really don't want to hear
and see bullshit.
Because basically each security community,
or it's like this kind of local community going on,
like.
But like, can we be a bit more specific?
What do you mean, bullshit?
You mean you don't want to hear, I don't know,
marketing pitches, like, you want to talk about,
I don't know, exploits, vulnerabilities,
how to protect your systems from it.
You want to have, you know, first raw access
to this kind of data.
Yeah, but to be hardcore technical.
To not like presenting the upper layer,
how this, what you built or what you're going to present
is off, is great and so on,
without discussing what is running above.
Yeah, exactly.
It's just, I think you look at when you're long enough
in security, you know, things are not secure.
Yeah.
And that's the reality of it.
You can't really say, yeah, even claim.
And we have, there are interesting stories
that CEO is going out and claiming such and such
database engine is secure.
And then there is a book is now written for that,
how to hack that database engine out there.
So you kind of, you see these things
and also as a, like a geek or a technical guy,
you know how things work and you know, okay,
under these condition and that certain assumptions,
yeah, maybe that thing is secure, but in reality it's not.
And you don't want to go somewhere,
just hear someone talking about that.
It's kind of want to attract those people
who have a genuine interest in the field,
not necessarily are opportunistic that they think,
well, I would say perhaps the time
that this whole thing started was not so much a big topic,
was more like, well, you just get together, have a chat.
So kind of trying to attract those, more those guys.
And the other thing I felt was important
is that this egoistic nature of,
when you feel you're a hacker or a security guy,
you feel you're so special that,
because, you know, you find something
that perhaps nobody in that team would ever discover it.
I kind of, you have this feeling of, okay, all right.
So, you know, I'm very important.
What kind of, I actually didn't like it either.
I'm like, if you are a great hacker,
you actually need, can you explain it to someone
who doesn't have any clue?
Well, then that means you're a really good hacker.
I can sit here and talk about the, everything is broken.
This wifi is broken and that network is broken,
but that doesn't.
It's not useful inside.
We know that it's already broken.
Yeah.
Yeah. Okay.
Just come and talk about it.
Yeah.
Okay.
And in like.
May I ask this question?
Yeah, sure.
You come up as a really humble in this conversation,
but there's a Sektalks around the world.
There's around 10,000 members in this community
or something like that.
So in all major cities, these Sektalk events appear
on a monthly basis, if I understand correctly.
So audience out there, if you're interested,
make sure you find it out.
We'll put some links there.
Right?
Can I do that?
Yeah, but it's interesting
because this is one of those meetups
that it's not recorded, if I understand correctly.
Yeah, but there were some recorded meetups during COVID.
Then.
And in general, it's true.
Generally, yeah, in person.
You know, you want to meet people in 3D.
You know, you don't want.
And like, to some extent,
like those meetups also include capture the flag?
Maybe.
Yeah, so.
Maybe it's like for the audience to explain what this is.
So you know, Perth is a city in Australia,
which I mean, 1.4 million,
but it may fill that audit.
So there's a lot of people there,
but at the time, any of you who are a meetup organizer,
you know that it's really hard to find good content.
So the idea, and yeah, we play a game in security,
which I always advocate to anyone who wants
to start security to do it is capture the flag,
which the goal is, you know,
you hack into this simulated or virtual environment
to find a flag.
And a lot of people naturally has interest in that.
But one of the things you,
I mean, I often found was missing is that, you know,
these CTFs typically run as part of a conference
and you have lead hackers.
You know, they go and break things
and find the flags and get the trophy,
but you don't really hear that how they have done it,
like how they have achieved it,
which I felt that was a knowledge missing.
But guess what?
It was like one stone, two birds.
I was like, okay, how about we run a CTF,
we limit it only to 60 minutes.
And then let the people doing it on the day.
And then in the next session,
because it's very hard to find a good speaker,
the person who hacked it can come and talk about it.
And the kind of,
we kind of have this filler of the events happening.
That worked well for,
especially for the smaller communities we had.
So it's like a good, good starter.
And hopefully we don't end up, you know,
getting any vendor talks and things to do, it's crippling.
But do you think like nowadays the Capture the Flag contest
or like online hack in the boxes
became more popular than like, I don't know,
10 years ago, 15 years ago?
Yeah, definitely.
Yeah, yeah, for sure.
It's not, my understanding is that
if this used to be like part of the conferences
organized to challenge people,
now it's becoming very competitive
and really big thing across the globe.
People are really learning
and preparing just for these things.
So as we discussed earlier,
we said that you need to learn these layers
to build your stack and learn, you know, all the things.
People are now optimizing for just these games,
if I understand correctly, right?
So they probably learn all the tricks
that are possible in these timeframes
or is there like elements
that you need to reinvent some new mechanics or?
Yeah, the way I saw like the good teams,
like they have their own tooling.
They prepared like how to like,
had some advantage on how to compete.
Prior to coming to these challenges.
Yeah, yeah.
And a lot of actually, some of the good hacking tooling
or security testing tooling actually came out
of some of these CTFs,
specifically one quite interesting security issue,
which is known as Severed Site Template Injection or SSTI.
This bug was the demonstration of how bad this bug can get
or how this vulnerability can get so bad
was through one of the, some of the CTFs
and the write up one of these players had
and the kind of that expanded that,
whoa, this thing can go really seriously bad.
So, and then yeah, publishing those tools
and as Andrei said, some of them actually
have the Python libraries even for
how to do different things so quickly.
It's a competition.
Can you give us a bit more example
what's in this toolbox that they use?
I mean, let me rephrase the question.
Can you give us example of these challenges?
Like what would be, for example, examples
a good assignment that will be part
of a capture the flag challenge?
Well, those are like the default ones of stenography,
like hiding the flag inside some kind of image.
Then like very known are like also the PCAP.
So snapshot of network traffic and then inside like that,
there's a flag.
What else?
I mean, reverse engineering.
So you have the binary file and you need to figure out
what does that do?
I mean, you have a web application type security issues
that the goal is to hack into that web app
or web API and then exploit it.
And eventually you get perhaps a root access there
and you can read the text file, which is a flag there.
It's very-
Are these things like chained together
or is this like hacking to this webpage,
get the flag and then move to the next challenge?
Or do you have to like, do you change them together?
Like get one flag here and then do something else
or is this, it really depends on-
I'd say it depends, but usually they're not chained.
Like basically you finish the puzzle
or solve the challenge, the new challenge opens.
It really depends.
Is there any help or any hints or anything like that?
Yeah, it's a penalty points for hints as well.
Penalty.
Penalty points so you get for soften to reveal the hint.
Now whether the quality of that hint will be good or not.
That's another topic, but you get some,
it's more like a competition.
So kind of you learn through the competition
and often actually it works.
Like I, back in the days, we built some CTF challenges
for some international conferences.
And I know for the fact that one of that very good CTF team
that they didn't touch cryptography type challenges.
They had no idea about different encryption
or decryption type algorithms,
but throughout that CTF period for that conference,
which normally runs two to three days,
they actually went and start learning about it,
reading articles and eventually solve that challenge,
which the guy was telling me that in a normal cases,
I wouldn't bother even to read about this.
Kind of, I was like, okay,
but now because of this sense of competition
and like actually now I know,
like there's a lot of things I can go and check out for it.
And you think like being good at CTFs,
like sort of a good starting point in security career or?
I think you can immediately test
or compare your skillset to others.
It's very hands-on like interactive.
So if you talk about like the life cycle
of like a security issue,
I mean, the first thing is you need
to find the security issue, finding a vulnerability.
Okay, there are some perhaps techniques
you can follow to find that,
but then it comes the exploitation phase,
which I typically call it is at the most closer than art
because it depends,
like often when you are engaged by a customer
to do a security assessment,
you may find an interesting security issue,
but just to turn that and prove to them
that this is really bad,
it may take you the rest of the duration of the engagement
just to demonstrate one security issue
has a really major impact on the environment.
So I think someone who,
I feel when you go through that exploitation phase,
you actually learn quite a lot
and you really understand a lot of quirks.
Like when you are a security, well, security researcher,
we don't have the luxury of having a debugger
as like a software engineers
that you can just attach to the program,
figure out what's happened.
Like there is like nothing like that.
You kind of, a lot of times,
yeah, it's a lot of trial and error.
A lot of times there's a lack of tooling
even to interface with something.
So it's a lot of complexity involved in there.
So I think.
But like experience from like a sec docs
we run in Ljubljana,
like that few CTFs that we had,
it was interesting that like on the guys
who were leading on like highest on the scoreboard
were actually developers.
So not people like dealing with security
or solving the CTFs.
There were like few guys that like really,
when the problem is presented
or the puzzle that was presented,
they start like really thinking outside of the box
because all other, let's say security people
that working security were relying on tools,
relying on, okay,
which tool should I use to extract something out
in compared to the developer who was thinking,
okay, what am I seeing here?
How can I, so.
Exactly.
There have been so many cases like that,
that people who are completely new,
let's say to security,
they come to SecDocs
and then they are taught in a ladder work.
The other things like sometimes
we had actually a specific case in Sydney
that one of the top players a few years ago,
he actually didn't even know about all these toolings
that is available,
like some of these Python libraries that are available
just to make the reversing that super easy.
He was just building everything,
thinking about it, reasoning about it.
Me.
And writing it.
I'm like that in these cases.
When he was presenting that
and then these like,
there's a lot of also students coming in.
They are looking at this kind of, wow,
like the algorithm that he built, for example,
to prove that, I don't know,
to crack the hash.
And they were telling him after the talk that,
you know, you just make a call to this library
that exactly the algorithm you have.
Yeah, if you don't know what's in the toolbox,
you can't use it.
Yeah, but on the other side,
like you also get,
like usually there are multiple ways
how to solve the puzzle.
And like it was a thing in Unix world,
like there are many ways to skin a cat.
Like whoever won present the solution,
like then you can like start comparing
whether you were thinking the same
or using the same methods or different.
So, yeah.
My observation of one of these psych talks
was like, it was very interesting
because I like, I saw a couple of guys
that were programmers
because there is no like limit
what tools you can use or not use.
Somebody is writing something in Perl.
Somebody just said,
I'm just gonna throw this code
that needs to be encrypted or decrypted
into spreadsheets or bash.
It doesn't really matter.
It's just whatever tools you use.
So that's very interesting.
I just remember there's an interesting story
how you two met, right?
Yeah.
Yeah, you remember?
I caused more problems.
Yeah.
I just remember today
and said to Otto that it's funny
because I think it's worth saying
how you two-
Obviously it's your fault, right?
So-
Yeah.
I mean, it's your fault
for solving the challenge
and revealing the secret.
I don't remember everything,
but I know that,
so we have the Slack
and you just dropped in the page
from Pedram's website.
And there's like a capture the flag
kind of a thing on his-
No, he was like hiring-
I didn't read that.
I just saw it's a capture the flag,
something with Docker.
So you didn't know what was it?
I didn't know.
There was just like this page
and Loki posted it.
And I was like,
okay, I'm gonna look, what's that?
Just play with him
because I think it was dependent on Python.
I just wanna like play with it
so that I can show off Python from him
because I know he tries to avoid programming
as much as possible.
And yeah, there was something
with the Docker container.
I can't remember what it was,
but yeah, it had some cipher in there
and some environment keys.
And I just like, like you said,
I looked into how to blow up this bridge.
Yeah, and then you wrote a blog post on your site.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
I wrote like, I didn't, yeah.
That's like-
And that's when you contacted him.
Yeah, that's yeah.
Hey, whatever, here is a writer.
Did you know what you saw? That was our career entrance.
Yeah, because what I did is like, when I was doing this, I wanted to just have a document
describing all the steps that I did.
So I wrote down everything and I was like, I needed something for my blog at the time.
I was like, okay, I'm going to write this down, right?
And then in the end, the last step was like, send email and then it was like, your email
and send the email and send the blog post attached to it.
And that was stupid and in hindsight, yeah, I know, I'm sorry for that.
I think I apologized.
Why didn't you apologize?
Then you put it public.
Yeah.
I put it public, yeah, that was a shitty thing to do.
And perhaps that could be a nice segue into discussion about hacking and ethics probably
and what you said, what's the term, disclosure.
Full disclosure.
Full disclosure, 90 days and everything, yeah.
It just made it harder for other people to apply because that's the thing, you can't
necessarily stop people to write, write up about your challenges, right?
But we'll make a better challenge, the next challenge.
So Jan, you hope that they will read that right up.
Well, I didn't get, I didn't get the job.
So the next guy must probably be better than I am.
For me, like it was interesting because it was a job ad basically.
And I saw this as a very creative job ad because you need to like solve the puzzle to actually
know what, like how to contact you.
Well, you needed to know a lot of stuff.
You needed to know, of course, you needed to know what is Caesar cipher, I think it
was there, environment variables, Docker, missing things, Python code.
There was a lot of these very things that I saw in my professional career, how these
things work.
And yeah.
So I imagine in your company, you're looking for people that have some solid engineering
background, but they also like are curious to extreme or something like, yeah.
You know, like maybe we could like cut here and enjoy the glass of water, I'll do commercials.
So Otto will now present the commercials.
So if you guys enjoy this podcast and if you want to keep enjoying it and it will really
help us if you join us and support us, there's a link below in the footnotes.
So yeah, join our Patreon supporters and it will mean a lot to us and we will be able
to make this wonderful content.
Oh, here you go.
So let's start the next section.
So what I wanted to talk about is application security.
So in terms of you now being on this defensive side where like you educate developers and
give them this knowledge of how to like apply security in, let's call it life cycle of development
life cycle.
And where to start for application security from developer's perspective.
May I like kind of like expand his question, like software development cycle means that
there are different phases in the development of software.
So you have planning, designing, implementation, testing, deployment, and then some maintenance,
right?
You have all these steps.
And traditionally what companies did is like, they went through all these steps, released
the product, and then probably perhaps also hired some pen tester because company that
was trying to buy it or something wanted some audit or something like that.
But that's not how things should be done if I understand correctly.
And is that like a good intro to this section?
I'm prepared to apply it on all of this.
Yeah.
The earlier is better.
More like you can't really, it's a non-functional requirement, right?
This is one of those that can't really have a face for it, but it's kind of applies everywhere.
I mean, I'm trying to think about the question, like, is it more, you know, I think for one
of the things I found out after working with, I mean, one of the reasons I actually started
working more on a defensive side was more, was the problems that I always have this interest
that find the root cause where the issue really is.
Like, you know, you do a code audit, a secure code audit, and you do penetration testing
and you can see a trend of security issues that just keep appearing, keep appearing.
And one approach to that is like, yeah, they don't understand that it's more approach of
us versus them.
Like, you know, they're just, I don't know, dark dumb, these guys, they don't give a shit
about security.
Okay.
Whatever.
And I'm going to just, you know, just do the same thing.
But the other approach for me, which was more interesting was like, why, like why this,
because that security issue that normally you find in a environment or a system, it's
an edge case that, well, I wish I, that, that program does.
So why it is not that interesting for those developers to, to, to, to pay attention to
it.
So this, this was a part that I, it didn't easy with me that why they don't pay attention
to this, like why they don't really go after fixing it.
And well, I started exploring their, their field even more, like what is actually happening
in the whole software engineering industry, how the software is being built, building
a software is, is one thing, but you know, keeping it online, the prod is, it's a completely
different thing, right?
So you then try to understand the, the limitation, the restrictions, and then you, sometimes
you have this understanding, Hey, a lot of those security recommendations that you give
is actually going to break the whole thing.
Like it is not applicable.
So parts of that is related to it, but parts of that is a lack of understanding and awareness.
I feel actually security need to be redefined for a lot of engineers.
Like I found a lot of times we are, they are so biased toward that.
What security is, you know, you, you will, you will talk with developers from one company.
You will find that they are security for them is dependency scanning.
And for the other ones, Oh, man in the middle, man in the middle, if it happens, it's bad.
It doesn't happen.
We are safe.
The other, or the other ones like phishing, the other one is, Oh yeah, we need to keep
our passwords long.
It's authentication.
And you kind of, you bias toward that and you feel that's the security, but versus Bell
security is old and above all those things.
I think that's where my interest kind of started kind of going, rather than being a game of
us versus them be security guys, we find bugs, you guys need to fix it.
Just trying to understand, trying to bridge this gap.
You know, one of the things I mentioned earlier, that if this is a software engineering podcast,
because in the terminology, even we use in security industry is different from often
vulnerability.
But by the end of the day, there's a bug, a defect, right?
So it can be a feature.
So if it's a design flow, then this is a feature, but it's like, one is actually opportunity.
The other is a problem kind of thing.
It's kind of redefining that, right?
So by the end of the day, in a lot of cases, if you think about security vulnerability
is a runtime exception, that kind of communicates better with engineers, but for us in security
domain, it's a vulnerability, we call it.
So I think even just bridging those gaps, trying to understand kind of the other side
of the game a little bit more, and then, well, asking them to help, because if you look at
the, if I look at the history of some security issues that was really addressed, you will
see there was an engineering team that they embed this kind of security control within
the framework.
An obvious example of it is, for example, a skill injection, right?
A skill injection kind of had gone away in majority of the cases, not because suddenly
we have an aware community of developers, but because the framework sees that you write
the code in it, it just doesn't allow you that raw access to the query.
So you're saying in a way there are, I don't know, frameworks or programming languages
that are like safer for unskilled developers to produce safe code?
Safe code, yeah.
Can you, like, is this what you're trying to say?
Or can you say, like, for instance, that there is a, I don't know, framework that is like
a bit more, like, stupidity proof?
How should I say?
Stupid proof.
I mean, there's definitely frameworks that sort of prevent someone to shoot in the legs.
Yeah.
Definitely.
There are there.
Because-
For a subset of security issues, right?
There are, I always make this example that if someone writes a PHP app and making it
secure, I will hire that guy because it means he's damn good in security as well, versus
a guy who write the same application in ASP.NET, for example, because the framework itself
does a lot of heavy lifting in terms of, like, it doesn't even just make example of, and
there isn't a, I know this is because in my team, we often, we create security challenges
for software engineers.
And then we need to convert that to multiple languages.
And often it's really hard to convert it in one framework versus, or versus one language.
It also exposes us that the maturity in a different, you know, communities of these
languages and yet some frameworks, like, we can't even introduce that security bug in
them, just because the framework just-
It means disabling so many default protection mechanisms that you really need to pay a lot
of effort into disabling all these whistles and blows and fear.
Exactly.
Yeah.
So in a way, like when, like this is sort of a, for developers, when like in this planning
phase, what stack to choose or what platform to choose or what programming language to
choose can also-
Perhaps the question is, the first question in this planning phase is like discussing
perhaps even with stakeholders and how secure should this stuff be?
Like, are you running on very personal data or is this just, you know, a random blog or,
you know, I think I would start there, right?
What does this thing need to do?
What kind of data does it store?
You know, are there any regulations or-
Usually it is the other way around.
Usually the senior engineers like choose the sexiest, the hottest framework or programming
language out there.
And because this is the something like everybody is working on and that's the pick.
That's the weapon of choice.
So we're victims of hype-driven development.
In a way.
Yeah.
I don't think you're going to get this answer.
I mean, again, all these, you know, especially if these are old established frameworks, they
have special teams, they do additional security audits regularly.
So if you have these kinds of frameworks that are out there for a long time, I think probably
people have looked at the code.
They did, you know, that part you kind of like believe that checks were done, right?
With new stuff, you know, there's always opportunity to find something there.
But equally, like if you have very old code bases, if, you know, you have software that
is written by a lot of engineers during a lot of different periods when, you know, company
was small and then became big and you have poor, and that's probably the next question,
security culture in the company, you know, people doing sloppy jobs.
It's essentially a big attack surface, I guess.
I don't know that, Otto, because I like to think that way, but then you look at some
of the trend of security ones that reported even this year in really old codes, the codes
that are open source, the code that is out there, the code that has been audited and
most likely being scanned by numerous applications, and still you find, whoa, like security issues
there.
On the other side, we actually have some people in security that they lost hope that, sorry,
we can't teach devs how to write a secure code, they just make it harder for them to
build something, at least that will eventually result into in a more secure stage, is a mix
of things that you will find, I mean, you kind of assume that the new frameworks may
have more holes, but not necessarily, it could be a security issue related to a library that
they are using and there is a security bug there and then it goes on.
But you know, today you don't use just framework, you also use third party libraries, you also
inject, I don't know, ads in your page through whatever, you know, people use, they install
a lot of different things on their devices, so there's a lot of potential to...
So you shouldn't limit yourself to only your part of the code, but the whole ecosystem,
the whole system.
But I think we still need to be like pragmatic, right, in the end of the day, developers do
need to ship something in a reasonable amount of time.
Sure.
Yeah.
The way I see it, like the simple exercise, like I think like each developer team should
do is threat modeling in terms of understanding what are the...
Please explain this to our audience.
So in a way of writing down or using a diagram way of how your application is working and
how data is going through your application, where are like possibilities of sort of risk
that could happen and how are you going to prevent this from happening and like it gives
you a way to sort of do in a way risk management.
But also this exercise is also good in a way to you figuring out what are your crown jewels.
So basically, what are you actually going to protect?
Because sometimes like there are people that are investing a lot of money in, I don't know,
web application firewalls and protecting completely like things that are not that important.
But on the other hand, they might say have the like personal data unencrypted somewhere
and they are doing like maybe the backups that are also unencrypted and that, I don't
know, shipping that to S3 bucket.
Is it enough to just write this down and make sure that everybody understands this or do
you periodically then monitor these things?
Of course.
Like in a way you want to, like the way I see it, you want to like when doing a new
features to the application or product you're developing, you again do this threat modeling
because in a way you already create one and one of the new features, you will see how
this affects the whole system.
Yeah.
I mean, threat modeling definitely, I'll actually call it a rapid threat modeling, something
that is more effective.
The problem I found is, again, it's hard to get devs to think about threats.
It kind of comes back to the old conversation we have builder and breaker mindset.
People who are good in building something does not necessarily know how things can break
and it's completely understandable.
So it's kind of also you need to kind of empower them one more level that, okay, these are
the possible things can go wrong regardless of what feature you're working on.
Think about whether this could be applicable to the things because...
Are these things like, we now have these static code analyzers that read the code and spit
out, I don't know, potential issues that are like wrong use of code or static code
analyzers check the code, but they can also...
You have similar tools to kind of like security testing as well.
Is that enough or we need to also build awareness and knowledge in developers?
Everything.
You throw everything at it.
Whatever you can do in a security, just do it.
It's such a chaotic, unfortunate environment that I personally think, and I have examples
of that, that when devs are on board with the idea of the security is important, we
should take it seriously.
You go miles away in terms of your security culture and maturity rather than if you want
the tool to tell you whether you're doing something good or not.
Because oftentimes, I mean, I'm not talking about the false positive, false negatives
and most likely you've dealt with it a lot, but it's not going to change the culture.
It's not going to change the understanding.
For me, the problem actually starts in the brain of that.
I'm going to challenge you here on this.
These organizations, responsibility starts from the top, right?
So I need to sell your service and your services to my boss as engineer or engineering lead,
right?
How do you convince people from top down that security is so important that they're
going to now invest into tools or education of their developers so that it becomes something
that the company should care about?
So how do you propagate that information from the top to the bottom?
Do you need to convince people that, you know, we're going to lose a lot of money or we're
going to have bad publicity or all of these things?
I don't know.
I don't even know someone who knows much.
I mean, in reality, still, there is a lot of security budgets are being approved because
of compliance requirement, because of some legislation.
And that's true.
You see the amount of security assessment done by organization and financial sectors.
Well, the one reason may not be so much about leaking data is because of compliance.
Of course, leaking data financial thing is a serious thing.
But I think still that has a great, you know, power to it.
Like, yeah, there was a standard.
How do you convince that guy?
I don't know.
To be honest, like security is pretty hard to sell.
Like basically, on one hand, you might choose to do sort of like those scarcity and say
how into what is like out there on the Internet and how you're going to be hacked and impounded.
I actually want to say something.
My job at the moment is not so much dealing with the people higher up.
It's actually hard to convince the developer to think about security because that's for
me is a bigger problem.
How you make security interesting and engaging for a software engineer.
Because by the end of the day, whatever security issue we have is a rare use case or edge case.
And if you look at the backlog of what this dev guy is going to do is like this feature,
that feature.
But most of it is filled with lots of other bugs.
How would you make the old security bug being something on top of that, that, hey, it needs
immediate attention?
So we're dealing with those priorities as well.
But I think that's the part for me is interesting to talk like, what are the things would make
security interesting for engineers?
Because that's all my hope here.
And what do you propose?
How do you make it interesting?
You gave me fun.
You want us to start?
No, no, no.
It's a good question.
That's a segue to the next.
Yeah.
But still, I still want to be here at Application Security and maybe start before going, how
to do this education purpose, or do this education of developers, how to explain security
to them, how to make them engage in this, like what he said, with gamification of this
or showing real examples and showing the code, or is like what usually, or let's say
usually is done, like there's external pen test, like breaking down the code and just
sending the report to R&D and saying this, everything you see on the report is broken.
You need to fix it.
What's the...
Definitely, I can say things that doesn't work is top-down approach.
Like if a manager said that, you have to do security, that's not going to work, or you
have to do this security, I mean, address that, that's not going to change anything
in that dev's mindset that security is important.
But things kind of learning more about their worldview of what they would care.
Like I found every developer is interested in problem solving.
They are interested and engaged in, well, make something better.
Well, guess what?
When you make a software secure, you have a better code quality.
You may have even better, more reliable application.
Kind of trying to highlight these angles more than it's just the edge case that, hey, no,
actually your program does more than what it should.
Well, for example, you just need to, you just make example of a calculator that needs to
take two numbers and give you a result.
You can implement that in many different ways.
When you show that a certain way of implementation of that calculator could also allow someone
to inject additional code and execute code using your calculator and kind of saying that,
but by the end of the day, you just wanted to build a calculator.
Why you just don't make your software just.
calculation. Don't worry about what else can happen, just that part. It actually makes their
software to do that things even better. So that's what I find is interesting. Of course, the whole
concept of gamification also is proven. I feel competition also, it's something that helps.
But if, stay on this, what would be, I don't know, to maintain secure hygiene inside
development lifecycle? What would be steps that...
I think it's just everyone's job. I think, first of all, start thinking about this is
that the security team should are a gatekeeper of our organization.
Sure. But what would be, I don't know, five, three top things that each company or each
business that is focusing in development should invest effort, money, what to consider?
I mean, some of the key things there is a lot of things, but
just this understanding that perhaps security is not a single team's job,
and showing them a real example of that, an incident that actually happened,
that proved the case that if security, if we're just relying on just an audit to come through,
or things like that, how many things can be missed? You can't have your junior developers
or even senior developers advocating about security, and then you have your tech leads
and software architect that pushing for features that need to be released yesterday. That doesn't
work. You need to give your team a time to think twice about the code that they write,
the design that they build, which kind of contradicts with the speed of a lot of businesses
going this way. But sorry to say that is to make a software usable is one thing,
but to make it secure is another thing. You can make a software that perfectly function,
but it isn't secure. What will take you to go there? Well, one fact is just give your team more
time. Because there are cases that I had, the team, the devs, they're really on board with the
idea that I really like to do trade modeling. I really like to follow this secure design pattern
to implement my code. But the thing is, I can't, because I'm not even given the time to do it.
So I think that's a bigger problem to solve first. And then after that, once you have that
established, then making devs more familiar with the ways that things are going to get
exploited. And kind of making them more familiar with this breaker mindset that
so they can start thinking intuitively about, well, what can go wrong? Rather than just thinking
about what program should do, they should also think about what program should not do,
which is again, the sky is the limit. I'm worried.
Some questions should, like in the process of quality assurance, should also like a security
test be part of this? I think it's okay. Isn't it already there? I don't know. Usually are not.
Usually like QA is focusing on usability and if the product is like reaching
some performance that is expected and so on. But usually the security is left out.
Well, last time I was sort of a situation like the feature went through the Q&A.
Everything was like great. And then on the bug bounty, it sort of found a huge security
flaw. And then like we sort of go back to Q&A, it wasn't that tested. And they were like, well,
that's not expected to be an input.
Why would someone do that?
Exactly. They were like questioning, why would somebody do that?
So it's not essentially the QA's job is not to do security audit or look for that kind of loops.
I mean, they can help. But again, the way that we are, again, my knowledge of it is
limited to, again, to those people who we try to train them as a QA to kind of look for
security issues. But there are two things you reach there is like their skill level.
That's one thing. And the second is the defined task of things that they have to do. Like often
they may need to use the UI interface to interact with their backend versus you may find actually,
if you remove that UI, you just directly interact with the API, you can find security issues there.
But that's not even defined in the, that's not even their job because they, one of us said,
you know, their usability is actually more highlighted there than these security edge
cases. So that's what I said, throw everything at it. It's just whatever you think is suitable
for your organization. I'm going to use this, throw everything at it. You have this beautiful
product and a service as well. I imagine it's called SecDim. So SecTalks is events,
but SecDim is your company if I understand correctly. And what you guys do is very
mix of the things that we described here, but you kind of like offer these things to companies.
That's kind of like, but I will still invite you to explain to us what SecDim is and what you guys do.
Yeah, so it pretty much started with workshops, running secure development workshops for
developers. We actually started right in the middle of COVID, the start of the COVID.
Beautiful time.
And then it kind of started with that because I felt that's like a missing part. We do need
to get more engineers involved to help us to solve some security problems. I'm not just talking
about developers to be able to put a patch here and there. I'm talking about those more like
fundamental solutions. Like can they put something in the compiler? Can they think about a popular
third-party library that won't disallow these things? So this is, I think, more
on engineering side to solve that. So that's why I kind of, I reached out more on that.
So the workshops, these are the things we regularly run for companies privately. We do
have also public workshops. The focus is effectively how to build a defensive software from
scratch. So rather than bombarding the engineers or devs with, oh, this security issue, that security
bug, that vulnerability, is there anything else we can do that you kind of, when you start writing
a software, you follow that or some of those principles and can make your software relatively
reliably secure. That's one thing. And as part of that, this platform came out, which
again was outreach to the people to, hey, you want to try to see how a security bug
well can be addressed. Now, one thing I actually found, but through experience, I found is missing
is that, so when I started, you know, we talked about capture the flag. When I started
delivering my workshops a few years ago, it was to make developers more engaged in security,
definitely I would include the CTF part that, hey, you know, it's the end of the workshop,
just do a CTF, just hack some things. And, you know, someone at the end will be,
it was engaging. It was interesting. Perhaps they would learn a new security issue,
but there was always this problem missing. By the end of the day, this person needs to go back and
fix this, but we haven't even talked about that part. This is out of a scope for security, right?
You deal with that. I told you the bug, you figure out how to fix it. And that's how I felt where
the problem is. Like we may these days talk good about some of the security issues that we have
normally in a security language, but we don't really talk so much about ways and bad ways of
fixing it. So the idea of this platform I built was, well, we have captured the black. How about
we have thing called fix the flag. So you go to school, sort of a reverse capture the flag,
reverse capture, but you, I even show you where is the security bug is,
but you only get the score if you fix it in the right way. Now, originally,
some of those, the ways that we were testing, if someone can fix the flag was too restrictive. And
to my, well, kind of, I learned that, well, no, this is a huge lack of understanding and awareness
somewhere. So we needed to kind of relax that. But now it's interesting just to see how people
actually think about a single problem, but they fix it in a completely different way. And
obviously also learning how to, well, make something or write a better patch for something
that I'm publishing. So in practical terms, you know, you log into the SegDyn website,
probably you can do this on your own or you also offer workshop. As I said, you get like a
you get like a zip file or a repository of a code that it has security vulnerability.
And then you try to fix it and then you upload it. And the tool will tell you if you actually
solved the problem or not. Right. That's the mechanics of this thing. Right.
So the idea was exactly. So kind of, you bring those security issues to the language that
developers understand. So, and the tooling that the developers, they have, like, so you have
Git, you have containers, you know, and translate to some of the security issues.
So let's just call it, I don't know, the one that I talk about new integer workflow,
not necessarily in a text or a video recording of me talking. Translate that to a test that
developers will deal with it on a daily basis. And the goal of the challenge is that can you pass
the test? Now, depending on the complexity of the challenge, you, you may be given the test
so you can clearly see what is the, what is the input? What is the expected output that as it gets
more challenging, the tests are missing because the idea is that, well, the hacker will never
give you their test. You have to figure that out yourself. Okay. That's an improvement then there.
Okay. Okay. So, but also encouraging developers in very like a implicit way that maybe you want
to think about writing these tests yourself for your program. You learn that if a program just
deal with two numbers, right? There are these usability tests that it has to always pass,
but how about these other things that can result in a security issue? So it's a kind of, they,
they learn it by, by practicing and the other, other things that are, you know, getting the score
and like getting their name on the, on the ladder board is like more like cream on the top. But
there, yeah. I had to, maybe, please, please, please let me, please. And I'll let you, I found
it very interesting. Like you don't just say, you know, this is integer overflow assignment or
something. You have these kind of like practical stories, how a company got hacked or how literally
millions or billions were lost because of this exploit, which means that there is a real world
connection of this security issue that you actually learn about. Can you tell us a bit
more, how do you design these things? Interesting you mentioned, because that happened again
throughout some of my workshops that I found in security, we are not really great in naming
something. We actually really good and naming something really complex. Like I don't know,
cross-site request forgery or server-side request. Yeah. But keep, keep in mind that lately it's,
it's, it's very popular when, when, when new like exploit of, of something is found or new bug is
found, we need to create a logo. We need to create a special site where the CVE is, is, is, is published.
So this is something that becoming popular to, to, to, to name, to name the attack or the bug.
Hard bleed. Hard bleed.
There was a changeover. It was a lot of, I mean, our industry got just lifted up and
it becomes suddenly super popular. But yeah, just coming back to that again, our goal,
my goal is to get more hopeful engineers on the security side. So whatever make them to remember
about this security issue. If I, if I tell someone, Hey, this is a server-side request forgery
bug two months from today, they're going to forget about it. But if I say, Hey, this is a bug that
happened to X, Y, Z component resulted into that. Now having this interesting story, someone after
like a few years ago, he did a, like a workshop came to me and say, Hey, you know, can you just
help me figure these things? Part of the code out. I think this, this may have that GitHub bug.
What do you mean? GitHub bug? That bug, you know, it was GitHub.
He's talking about the, there was a major vulnerability in GitHub for mass assignment.
We call it mass assignment, but that kind of tell me, okay, that seems to work.
That kind of sticks in there in their mind. Yeah. And I think.
Yeah. And like the process of, of you preparing these challenges, like you basically
tailor this to based on the company that is like, um, acquire or services and based on their stack
or so, or based on your past experience of, of you being the code reviewer of, of, uh,
auditing the, the, the, the code and seeing what are the most common mistakes the developers, uh,
do, uh, I'll create a bunch of, uh, like examples or exercises, um, for, for this kind of bugs.
What is the, how is the process of what is relevant or what, um, developers, uh, are working on.
So there's a, like a different levels of content given the maturity of that organization. So there
are kind of a group of security bugs that regardless of you writing Python or use Kubernetes,
you need to be aware of them. So we make them tailored toward that organization that, Hey, okay,
these are the things you have to follow. And then the next nice thing is that then the next step is,
uh, because the whole platform has an open SDK, they can even contribute their own type of
problems. And that will be presented in the terms of challenge. So a lot of times it happens that we
turn a security audit report into a challenge because oftentimes the security report comes in
and then you get few people, you know, dealing with that, fixing the bug and that's it.
When the whole knowledge is gone, what was it? But rather than, we kind of want to make that
more persistent for that organization. Like you have new devs coming in. Hey, do you know what we
had this bug? Well, here's an hour challenge for it. Can you try to, to solve it? And the goal is
to fix it. We are, we simulate the same bug for them and they will kind of try to do it.
Uh, that's primarily the focuses and, uh, the, the other part is more, uh, running, uh, competition
or game events for them. Like, uh, you want to dedicate time for the team to come in one day and
start exploring some of the security issues. Can't just, you know, give them a link and they'll
go and do it on your own. But yeah, they probably did that already.
Should we bring the ship to bring that ship in? Yeah. Um, yeah, I was like thinking maybe, maybe
like from how, how, how long have you like done this kind of workshop of dealing with, with
developers? So I'm thinking of, um, like the track record of, of you running the workshops perhaps
is like eight years. Okay. I was running it and, and, and in, in, in this eight years, like you
still see what are the, the top three like major flaws that developers are still like,
or was it called deadly sins in, in, in software development? What is, what is still,
still out there? And, and I don't know if you, if you, if you track a tracker, um, this at all,
I mean, it's, you can, you can see in his eyes, all the horrors that he's seen.
I mean, you mean what are the, you're talking about what's still happening? Yeah. Of course.
Like what kind of mistakes are, are, are developers still like making in terms of like,
like example, like you, you presented the, the, the challenge yesterday. Um, um, for instance,
the integer overflow that was like, like crucial in, in, in a way of understanding,
or what, what is still out there?
Well, I can say one of the, well, these quick fixes, like without really understanding what
the root cause of the problem is trying to quickly put some, if a statement around the thing,
we talked about Heartbleed, I do encourage you to go and look at the patch for the heart.
And don't be surprised to just see two, if a statement for that security bug. So kind of not
really understanding, Hey, this security bug cannot be treated like other bugs that you fix
in your program. I think that's the thing I still feel is, is missing quite a lot. Like
you can just put a couple of statements here and there just to patch things.
Um, one of the things that I'm keep talking about, it is all about,
uh, I mean, it's just so many security issues. I don't know which one I pick.
Name one, name one.
Like, I mean, like some of the, like, some of the things that is re reappearing is like
this whole concept of like, you know, front-end validation is a, is a joke. You need to do things
on back end. I thought we solved this problem, but it's kind of coming back and you still see,
well, these things that just did the validation on front-end and the QA didn't pick it up because
they use the UI to interact with the API. And modern web frameworks in the front-end
are becoming more and more popular and everything. And everything is being done in front-end and,
you know, whatever is in back. A lot of, uh, a lot of, uh, the other thing you see a lot is a lot of
information disclosure that API is just send too much information to the front-end library
because the heavy lifting is done by front-end library. And you don't actually know, actually,
if you observe just the traffic that comes in, it's just too much content.
I had one case that I could see even the password hashes of people.
And I think that the security bugs, the one that I feel companies need to go after are those ones
that are in the, their business logic, their semantic ones. They are the ones that get popped
and get attacked. I think we are kind of relatively good on a low hanging fruit,
the things that, you know, the scanners can pick up, but the ones that they are really deep inside
the code and mostly related to the semantic of the code, they are the ones that, yeah,
it's still, it's just still there. So maybe like to, to end this.
Yeah. I think maybe we need to invite bedroom to four to some Slovenian beers now, probably
Do you enjoy Slovenian beer?
Which one?
Which one? Well, we explore.
So maybe like, I don't know, words of wisdom from you.
Last few words.
Yeah. What, what would be like in, in terms, in terms of, I don't know, addressing,
addressing developers, addressing the, the, the management, running the business.
I think it's just early, get security early in, like you get benefit of cost-saving a lot.
The earliest, the better, like, so, and that's why I was really advocating for training because
that's the earliest stage you can, you can get security in when you are, when that feature
Inception or like that, a scrum meeting that you have to talk about the feature.
Actually, that's the time you can start thinking about security really early on, and you can stop
things to, to happen right there before, you know, you're implementing the code and someone
auditor comes in to do it. So I think you get security in as early as possible.
Okay. So wise words. Will you say thank you to everybody or should I?
You should do.
Well, Pedram, thank you very much for your time. We appreciate it. Andra, thank you for, for this
kind, kind words and leadership in this. And thank you, our listeners of Ugrodje and thanks to
supporters. We have so many that I can name them. So I can say thank you, Jan, Jan, Jan and Marko
for supporting us. And I hope that you guys will give us some feedback, especially given that this
is now in English. And until next time, thank you very much.
Yeah. And we promised to like, maybe do another about security because we saw that security is
quite popular, like in, in, in Discord.
Yeah, there's tons of, yeah, we need to, we need to finish now.
Thank you everybody. And thanks for sharing.
Thank you.
Bye.