Zdravstveno v Ugrodje, frameworku, Ugrodje v Sloveniji, imamo novi epizod Borderless.
Ugrodje je slovenski tehnologični podkast, se spomagajte, da ga vidite. Zdaj imamo našega prijatelja, Nika Jacksona, principalna razvojačka HashiCorp. Zdravstveno v Ugrodje.
Zdravstveno.
Če bi povedal, kje smo sedaj, ker ni to naša običajna mesta, kjer naši rekord.
Zdaj ne bodo slišali kakšne treni, ki se običajno imajo ali kakšne običaje, ki se običajno običajo. Zdaj smo tukaj v Deovske dne, v Ljubljani.
Smo v Free, fakultetu informatika in komputerske znanje. Zdaj, je to zelo dobro mesto. Poznali smo, da ne završimo se v poklicu, da lahko poživimo nekaj zvokov v okolji.
Če slišali smo, da smo imeli podobne situacije v popolnem epizodu, tako da je to znova ustvarja.
Tako je. Naši tehničništi so resnično odlični, imajo nekaj čarobnega magiče, ne srečujem. Zdaj, razmišljajo vse zvokove v okolji, ali v bistvu tako več kot morajo.
Kako si, Nick?
Zelo dobro sem. Vse dva tako dobro?
Da, da. Zdaj smo vse skupaj, naša skupina je Andraš, jaz tudi Andraš, imamo tukaj veliko ljudi.
Če je nekaj, ki je nekaj kot Koto, je tukaj.
Da, da. Naš producer, z lepim smilom. Da, moramo priti?
Zdaj smo tukaj na DevOp Days Ljubljana. Zdaj, današnji epizod bo bolj razgovarjal o kulturi DevOp.
Zdaj, prišli smo na prvi DevOp Days. V resnici, s svojo profesionalno kariero, HashiCorp in tako dalje. Kaj vidiš, ne vem, 10 let tukaj, v različnih različnih od tukaj?
Zdaj, DevOp v tem času je bil začetek od vsega sistemnega predstavljenja, ampak je bil začetek boljših vključnosti. In mislim, da smo slišno prišli tukaj. Zdaj, to je bilo dloži čas, ampak gledam na mojo obdobje.
začetek. Zdaj, gledam na mojo obdobje. Zdaj, gledam na moje obdobe. Zdaj, gledam na mojo obdobe.
Zdaj, gledam na moje obdobje.
Zdaj, gledam na moje obdobje
Zdaj, možda će Andraš napisati svoju perspektivu.
Ja bih rekao ovako.
Svaki htjele biti kao dobro kao velike ljudi.
A ako htjele biti kao dobro kao velike firme,
možda ako si mali ili start-up,
htjeli si raditi stvari poprije.
Ako htjeli si raditi stvari poprije,
trebate da se specijalizirate u tehnologijama.
I stvar koju gledam je,
kada se pomeni o Kubernetesu,
to je odličan framework i tool,
ali potrebuješ super dedikaciju ljudi
da se ovo posluži,
osim ako govorimo o intermedijalnom nivlu ljudi
koji su možda 5 godina u svojoj karijeri.
Kubernetes nije samo druga tehnologija.
Trebaju da se ovo skupaju.
I zatim začneš izgubiti ovaj kontakt
kada se pomeni,
da želimo provoditi značajnu valiju,
da ustvarimo pristopno, ne vem,
ansibolno pristopno,
ki bo delal vsega in vse bodo razumeli.
Mislim, da je to vse skupaj možno
ali samo za developerje.
Ampak ko se pomeni o tehnologijah,
ki so zelo velike predstave,
in možda bi bilo to zelo kompleksno
za večinu predstav,
tako imaš tudi tako nezgodbo,
ker se ljudje razvijajo,
ker je zelo zgodbo,
in je težko je predstaviti.
In tako imaš to skupaj.
Mislim, da ljudje imajo to občutje,
da se zgubijo ali se gledajo na socialne medije,
ko je to veliko,
in možda je to zelo prekompleksno za njih.
Ne vem, da li si podobno povzgošal.
Ja, sem se spominjal, da je Kelsi Hightower
v tem, da je ustvarjal svojo meme,
kjer je bil tako, da se predstavlja
blog za Kubernetes.
In mislim, da je to nekaj zgodbo.
Mislim, da je Kubernetes v celi
vprašanje tega,
da moramo ustvarjati
najmanje instanske vprašanje
na različnih predstavah.
In s tako vsega prihaja kompleksnost.
Mislim, da je tako tako,
kako ti pomeniš, da ljudje se učijo.
Seveda je zelo težko.
Ko sem začel svojo karieru,
sem prihajal pravih 30 let,
ampak svojo prvi resnično del,
ko sem delal v Internetu,
sem ustvarjal svojo sredino za Formijo 1.
V tem času je to sredino
za globalno Formijo 1
na dva servira.
Imeli smo Apache front-end,
ki je imel PHP,
in imeli smo Oracle server,
ki je delal databas.
Dva boxe z SunSolaris.
In v tem času so bilo tri ljudi
na Internetu,
in to ni bilo nekaj.
V tem času je bilo kompleksno,
kaj moraš naučiti kot aplikacija.
Moral sem naučiti nekaj o Linuxu.
Moral sem naučiti
nekaj o težkih okoljih,
kako se pravi Apache.
Kaj je konfiguracija,
kako se odloži v aplikacijo
in kako se konfigura
plug-in za PHP.
Moral sem razumeti PHP
in nekaj SQL.
Nikoli nekaj težkih.
Zdaj moram razumeti,
povedajmo,
da vedno delam v PHP.
Moram razumeti mojo PHP.
Moram razumeti Kubernetes,
ker moram razumeti,
kako se bo aplikacija odložila.
Moram razumeti
nadaljevanje strukture,
kaj se je delalo v Kube-klustru,
ker moram razumeti,
kako so node odložene,
če so v skupinah autoskela,
kako to povezuje z odloženjem
in kako to povezuje
z prihodnostjo aplikacije.
Moram razumeti,
kako se je odložilo.
da smo včasih
prekompleksirali vse,
ko poživljamo
zelo nove tehnologije
in nove stvari
v naših stakovah.
Prvič, ko sem gledal,
kako je
infrastruktura
stakovnega odloženja
izgledala.
Je prosto.
Včasih je zelo prosto
za stvari,
ki jo imajo potrebo.
Če se to povezujete
s nekaj inego,
ki bo začel
ustvarjati arhitekturo,
bi rekel, da imamo
nekaj, ki je
kot Kubernetes,
imamo odloženje,
in v koncu,
kot je Andraž spomenul,
možda to ni,
ampak razumemo
vse.
Počnemo
z lepimi tehnologijami,
lepo je imeti
možda vse potrebe,
ki ne bojo
poživljali,
ampak je to
nekaj,
ki se bo poživljali v koncu.
Ne znam,
prvič,
mislim, da je
stakovna arhitektura
težka.
Mislim, da je
ustvarjanje
sistema
po pravem
skladu
zelo težko.
In potem imaš
kompleksnost v aplikaciji.
Tako,
ne želim
igrati
stakovno arhitekturo,
ampak,
če imaš
nekaj, kot web,
ki je nekaj
forum,
tako je
skupina komponent
nekaj
manjši
kot,
če imaš
globalno bankiranje,
ali
imaš nekaj, kot
Netflix,
ki je
40%
vsega interneta,
ali nekaj takšnega.
Tako,
mislim,
da se počnemo
več in počnemo več,
in gledamo na te
poslušalce,
tako, da se
ustvarjamo
naša
začetka,
in bova
zelo
vzroč,
kot Netflix.
To je naš cilj.
Ampak,
nismo tudi tukaj.
še vedno
ustvarjamo
poslušalce
na zelo
zelo
naše
gracias
United States.
Moram
.
what you've learned and practiced.
So maybe that also is kind of a driver on why we're using in some cases
inappropriate use of technology.
And maybe we need to like flip this as a business.
And then, you know, the reality is it shouldn't be about what you know.
It should be about the efficiency that you can drive within the organization.
Now, actually having a broad spectrum of knowledge helps you to understand that
maybe the most complex tool is not the right tool and actually the best solution
for the business, which derives the best value and efficiency is the simplest tool.
And avoiding the Kubernetes and going for just the, you know, we just need a VM.
So let's just create a VM.
So maybe, maybe we need to kind of think about, I think about that as well.
But, but I certainly think, like, you know, this yourselves, like if you, if
you saw a role and it was high tech, you might be more attracted to go for that.
It's probably higher salary as well, as opposed to if it was a high salary, but
low tech role, you know, so, so maybe we're on, we're our own worst enemies.
Yeah.
But on, on the other hand, you could, you could see like, especially, but what I
saw in, in, in last decade were like those, those jobs that have this fancy
descriptions, what kind of technology you'll be using, but in the end you're
like stuck with some legacy, like they maybe have something in a roadmap.
We want to be there, but you will need the working process, how to get there.
But you're basically stuck with some legacy technology.
I find those kinds of things the most interesting, like for me, I think the,
I'm really interested in, in that how to get from point A to point B.
So if somebody comes along and says, we have this rails application, it's a
monolith, it's just a rails app with a Postgres database, we have an aspiration
to grow the business, to add technology, which will ultimately lead to
developing all of these new services.
I think that's actually really interesting because then you sort of
think, well, how do you decompose this?
How do you start extracting components out of this?
What is the appropriate way to run this new architecture?
And you see it grow and you see it involve and hopefully with it, you see
the business grow and I think that's always been a focus that we shouldn't
forget that we were employed to help provide a sort of a service to provide
a value for an organization and so yeah, so maybe basically we just need more
businesses to like start giving us money based on if they're more successful,
they should pay us more, right?
That sounds fair, right?
I'm all for more money.
So less hype driven hiring.
Yeah, but I think in general, right?
Like I think if you look at DevOps and if you've spoken to certain business
leaders, they will use the term and they haven't really got an understanding
of what's going on, but they don't really get it, but even if that term is a
leverage to be able to drive a conversation in finance, to be able to drive
a conversation with a C-level somewhere, which increases funding for technology
or for whatever that the organization then needs to help it push forward,
then that's a good thing.
Like I've got no problem at all with that if somebody's kind of using that,
but because we all win in the end.
Yeah.
Do you think that maybe in the next few years we will...
In the recent years, there had been a lot of tooling regarding delivery and
how to ship something to production.
And I would say that back in the 2000s, there were, including me, a lot of
sysadmins that were happy with just like simple best scripts.
And we didn't really care much with coding back then.
Of course, at least I was less experienced, so you need to grow that skill of coding.
And now we are in a renaissance where there's a lot of new tools popping up.
And I compare that, and I know it's a weird comparison, a bit to the front end
world, when there was a period that there had been a lot of frameworks, but now we
are basically settled on the three major ones, kind of.
Of course, there are newer ones, but there's React, Vue.js, and Angular, and
they seem to be the options that big companies pick.
Do you think that maybe we will agree on some tooling in some departments so we
will be able to be more rational and then think back how to provide more value and
just not hack on new things?
I think it's a good question.
And I think until we get to a situation when the tooling is really suitable for
what we need in order to do our jobs, we're going to, I think, still have evolution.
I think there is a slow sort of standardization around sort of certain
tools, which I think is a good thing because then you have a sort of a, you
know, the knowledge sharing is kind of more focused, which is always good.
But I'm still not convinced that where we are right now, that the tools deliver
exactly what we need, and that's why we need to continually build things.
And again, like this is why I think that every organization has a platform
engineering team, because there isn't something that we can just pick up off
the shelf and that we can use.
And so I think there will be a consolidation.
I think it will kind of happen, but it seems like certainly from over the last
sort of five years, you know, from an architectural standpoint where we're not
slowing down, but we seem to be organizing our thought around the two predominant
patterns of like either the serverless pattern or the kind of the Kubernetes
or scheduler-based pattern, that doesn't seem to be, there's certainly nobody's
come up with a new, well, having said that, and I'm like, well, we're all going
to be probably writing serverless WASM functions running on Kubernetes,
obviously in the next five years.
So maybe we are about to shift again, but it does feel like we're starting to
consolidate our infrastructure patterns.
And then I think because of that, the tooling will then become standardized.
So I think it'll happen.
But I think there's always, whilst we're all building our own platforms,
there's always going to be custom tooling required because what I build
is not necessarily going to be useful for you or you or...
Yeah, but like we can simply, like basically your employers, so HashiCorp,
so basically was solving some of their own issues and create tools to figure
out those tools could benefit to a wide range of customers.
And I'm excited about that.
And like, so I don't know if any of the listeners haven't kind of got a full
background on that, but when Mitchell and Armand basically were working in a role
as DevOps engineers and they were deploying systems and they realized kind
of the forefront of cloud, that the tooling was, there was something missing basically.
Now this is just after Vagrant.
So they started to kind of think about this and started to build the tooling.
And then they realized that actually, hang on a minute, if this tooling is useful
for us, then it's probably useful for the wider market.
And then that was when they founded HashiCorp to actually start working on that full time.
And back then you were looking at sort of Vagrant and Terraform and Packer.
And then HashiCorp built the first version of Terraform Cloud, which was then called Atlas.
And we needed a secrets manager.
So there wasn't a secrets manager.
Internally, they were like, well, we need to build this secrets service.
So they built Vault.
And then after Vault had been built, which was specifically designed just for the first
version of Terraform Cloud, somebody was like, hang on a minute, that's actually really useful.
We should make that a tool for other people to use.
And I think having that ethos has been really, really useful.
So I hope that we'll see a lot more companies that do exactly the same thing.
You know, it might be some engineers who are working for an organization and they built
a really useful tool.
Then they go and they set up a startup and they can build that tool and work on it and
allow, you know, it solves the problem for everyone else.
I think that's a really nice way of developing software, rather than, you know, the kind
of the just sitting around thinking about what should we build.
When you've got an actual need, which is based on knowledge of the problem, I think you create
really, really good software.
And I think I'm hopeful we'll see a lot more of that.
We saw this sort of good practices in the past, like the company, like my top of my
mind right now is maybe like Netflix, open source, their Chaos Monkey project and so
on.
So basically each company is sort of a development in its own tooling for suiting their needs
and figure out, well, maybe somebody else is having similar problems.
Yeah.
Let's work on this.
And I see a lot of nice open source software or tools came out of that and sort of a community
growth out of that and people contributed to this.
So it seems like a lot's been going on in that sense.
Yeah.
And I think like in general, that whole sort of change in the way that we share information
has been like huge from, I remember when I was at university and I was studying university,
I needed Linux.
And back in the day, you didn't have much of a modem, right?
But I had to, I bought a book, a textbook from a bookstore and it came with a CD of,
I think it was Suze.
And that was how I got access to Linux.
If I needed some software, I would generally have to pay for it.
So like I needed, I'm working on an application and the application needed to do some very
basic image manipulation.
Like I'm talking cropping and now I could have wrote that myself, but at the same time,
the internet didn't exist.
So like determining how, what is the specification of a JPEG, right?
What is the JPEG specification?
What's the file format?
The actual software frameworks at the time, certainly like ASP.net didn't have that capability
built in.
So it would be a huge amount of effort to try and even do something very, very simple,
like create a JPEG resizer.
And there was no free software to do this.
So you had to go and buy a library, which was great for the folks who were selling the
libraries, but it meant that everything just went really quite slow.
You know, you didn't have the ability to accumulate knowledge.
And then of course, when organizations, I think started to get and realize that we've
got this learning, we've consumed some learning from other people.
So let's put back into the industry and share our learning and creating a sort of an open
software model.
It's just benefiting absolutely everywhere because now we've got the access to the knowledge.
We obviously have access to the tools and to the organizations like Netflix, like for
Netflix to publish their Chaos Monkey is of zero competitive disadvantage to them as a
video platform.
And I think a lot of organizations are kind of recognizing that same thing.
And I think we're all benefiting hugely, hugely from that.
Yeah, yeah, I agree.
Like one thing that I really value about HashiCorp is whatever product was released, it was super
well engineered and designed.
And I think that a lot of solutions were also solving problems in the most smooth way that
you could solve it.
I remember maybe we should just mention a few products, because when I was a youngster,
I didn't realize that Vagrant was a HashiCorp product.
And then when there was the era where we were building gold images for virtual machines
in the cloud, there was this Packer.
And then after a while, I started focusing, you know, if there is a great director, you
see a movie and then you're like, OK, that's a great movie.
And then you see another movie and you're like, OK, that's also a great movie.
And then you're like, oh, but the director is the same, right?
Right.
And then I started being more focused on the company and whatever products they offer.
And for example, I was always confused.
I know that Nomad is here for a while.
It was here before containers arrived, I think.
Around about the same.
Yeah.
Both Nomad and Kubernetes were probably started around about exactly the same time.
So it was just post-Docker and when we were kind of starting to consume like Mesos, which
was the most popular scheduler at the time, and kind of wondering if there were other
options, certainly that was where Mitchell and Armon were thinking when they decided
to create Nomad.
And I'm pretty sure that's where like Joe Bader and all were thinking when they started
to think about Kubernetes.
Do you maybe have an idea why Nomad was not picked as much as maybe some different products
from HashiCorp?
I think it's...
Is it too simple?
No, I don't think so.
Like, I think it's an interesting one.
I mean, I suppose, I think one of the...
Well, so if we look at it in terms of timelines, I remember way back and we were talking about
replacing Mesos and we wanted to adopt something else.
Now, the first time I ever saw Armon, I was speaking at a conference in London and he
was speaking there talking about Nomad.
And so I went to...
I was a HashiCorp fan.
We were using a lot of their tools at Not On The High Street.
So I went to see this talk because I wanted to know what this new scheduler was.
And at the time it was just the initial alpha release.
It looked really interesting.
And Kubernetes at the time was...
There was this whole thing about, oh, you shouldn't be running it in production.
It's not ready for production.
And there were rough edges as there always are with software.
I think the thing that maybe HashiCorp had against it when...
And in terms of like, if you want to look at that as a race of some sort, was that the
team at HashiCorp that were working on Nomad probably back then were probably about two
or three people.
And then you have the entire organization and the weight of Google.
But I think the key thing around those two things is that folks gravitated to one solution.
Then you have sort of an ecosystem that spins up around that.
And then that accelerates that sort of drive.
I think Nomad never really got too much in that.
I still think it's a fabulous scheduler and it would probably be my primary choice because
I love the fact that it's so versatile.
And it is, I wouldn't say...
In some ways, it's easier to use.
In some ways, it's more complex.
I think there's pros and cons to everything.
But I think it was literally just a thing that people just sort of said, look, I just
want to run containers.
Then Kubernetes and then all of the...
If you Google how to run a container, you're going to get Kubernetes.
It's just a snowball.
I don't think Nomad is done by any real odds though.
I think Nomad's been there for probably about seven years now.
And I think keep your eyes on it because I think we're kind of working on some really
cool stuff and the versatility of having the capability to schedule multiple different
things, VMs, ECS tasks, if you want, Docker containers, raw binaries.
JAR files.
JAR files, of course.
I mean, if you're running Java, if you're like, do you really need to containerize your
Java applications?
Well, if you're running kube, the answer is yes.
But the thing is you don't.
And yeah, so I think that versatility could actually be really interesting for when we
look at the post-container generation, which I don't think is very far away.
So, but yeah, I think it was literally just the, you know, it was appetite in the community.
People gravitated towards a particular product.
Still a lot of users use Nomad, don't get me wrong.
But of course, it's not as big as the sort of Kubernetes, but they do different things
in different ways.
I suppose it's whatever your choice is.
Is it like, based on what you're seeing, is there like the product of HashiCorp that is
like far more popular or saying, well, this is our most popular or most used product?
I know all of them are in the whole.
I mean, without a shadow of a doubt, Terraform.
I mean, I think literally without a shadow, I mean, even if you look at the simplest of
metrics around GitHub stars, it's far out, out sort of ways, any of the other tools.
I mean, I don't, like I was asking somebody for numbers on this the other day because
I've heard some things.
It's definitely in millions.
Like I've heard quotes of the 10 millions.
I think we've had, they just had a billion downloads of the Terraform AWS provider, which
is pretty, pretty crazy.
And you don't have to go too far.
It gets mentioned a lot.
I mean, when people are talking about things like provisioning infrastructure, creating
infrastructure, even deploying applications, it comes up a lot.
So it's definitely very, very popular.
And I like it as a tool as well.
I mean, I'm slightly biased, of course, but yeah, probably that.
In terms of like, what's the second most popular?
I mean, your console is still powering huge, huge, huge, huge, huge part of the internet.
There are some large, large numbers of console clusters running.
And at one point I, and please don't quote me on this, but I'm sure I read a statistic
that it was one of the most deployed applications to things like AWS, because it was like a
core part of people's microservices state.
Where that goes with Kubernetes, because obviously Kube has etcd built into it.
Will we see a shift?
Possibly, but at the same time, console has shifted.
You know, console has additional capabilities around sort of macro segmentation service
mesh capabilities to bring it into the new world.
So it's not gone.
And then there's Vault.
And Vault is, I think, I don't want to say like it is becoming a sort of an industry
standard for secrets management, but it's certainly one of the more mentioned tools
when people are looking for a secrets management solution.
I can add that you basically set some goals or some standards regarding Vault, because
I personally tried different, or let's say alternative products.
And in the end, they tried to have the same API or say API calls as you guys did.
So to have this transparency and being able to switch to something different.
Interesting.
I was thinking, I'm surprised that Vagrant is not among first three, because whenever
I joined any developer teams, I saw that like Vagrant is there.
Maybe they didn't know about it, but somehow some things are basically running in Vagrant.
I would, you know, I'm going to look up the numbers on this, but I know that Vagrant is
still wildly popular.
So, and as well for me, Vagrant was the first HashiCorp tool that I ever used.
At the time I was working at a UK supermarket and we were wanting to run functional tests
for our iOS application and our Android applications.
And this needed massive parallelization and we needed the capability of running a clean
room environment.
We didn't want to be installing software on top of software.
Now, specifically for Apple, and this is, you know, we're going back nearly 10 years
now, there was no way to kind of just virtualize an OS X instance.
You could spin up OS X on an OS X, I'm sorry, on an Apple machine using VMware.
So what we did was we used Vagrant to basically spin up in these virtual machines on Apple
hardware, which was pre-configured.
Then we could run, use this to execute our functional tests.
And we were kind of orchestrating all of that with Jenkins.
And it worked great.
Like, you know, long before any of the sort of the, there was any sort of CI-based platforms
to do this.
And that was my introduction to Vagrant.
So then I started to use it for building development machines.
But at the same time, I also discovered things like Docker.
And for me, like the, if I just needed a post-grid database, which I mostly did for my
my development work or something along those lines, spinning that up in Docker was incredibly
fast.
But Vagrant is hugely, hugely popular.
When I joined HashiCorp nearly seven years ago, and we were talking about my role as
a kind of an advocate and the tooling that, and I remember the sort of, Armand was kind
of saying, well, look, you know, Vagrant is not really something as we talk about as developer
advocates because the community is just so vast that it kind of is self-fulfilling, which
is incredible.
I mean, it's absolutely amazing.
So yeah, Vagrant, Vagrant is still pretty big.
Like, I don't know on the numbers, I don't know, but you're probably right.
There's a huge amount of Vagrant still going on around there.
I think if you don't use Docker for stuff, you're probably using Vagrant.
Before we go to the next question or next topic, I would like to thank our supporters
on Patreon that help us produce this.
So there is some cost with production of this podcast from audio to video.
So I would like to thank our Patreons and our two sponsors, two companies are sponsoring
this, or our supporters, and that's 3FS and Human Frog.
So, thank you for that.
Um, yeah, my question would be, I was, I was having a presentation earlier
today, um, at the conference and I was so surprised how Terraform really
got popular in our region, um, and how many people know it and how many
people now use it at work.
Um, and I think that that really changed in the last two years.
Um, because when I was picking it up, I was more of a lonely rider, super
excited, uh, so that I can, um, basically spare some bugs when I go
to lunch because I can destroy the whole, uh, deployment and then reapply
and my lean notes, uh, invoices were coming on 50 pages, uh, built for
every minute, two cents, and then just pages and pages of, of VMs.
Uh, and each, each line was just like two cents, two cents, two cents,
because I was creating and destroying, creating, complying and destroying.
Um, but I would still like you to explain to more junior folks what
Terraform is, and maybe I guess there are also some folks listening that
are not super into, um, infrastructure.
Uh, what is this tool?
So I think it, it basically allows you to define infrastructure in a declarative way.
So you can create a text file, which defines what a piece of infrastructure
might look like, a load balancer, a virtual machine, a network security
group, those types of things.
And you do that in, in a language, HCL, the HashiCorp configuration language,
which is, is kind of a, I always think of it as if, if, if Jason and Yaml
had got together and had a child, HCL would be that child.
But it's a beautiful child.
It's a very, it's a very pretty child.
Yeah.
It's like, um, I'm trying to think of like, you know, Brad Pitt and who else?
Anyway, but, but by doing that, what, what you get is the
ability to define infrastructure.
Now, what I think is important about Terraform is, is not so much the
declaration, I think the declaration has been done before, but I think what's,
what's clever about Terraform is the fact that it uses a graph.
So it's graph based.
So you can basically say that the output, for example, from a virtual
machine, which might have the output of a, uh, a private IP address can
be the input into another resource.
So for example, a load balancer.
And because of that graph base, what it means is that when you do your,
your sort of your Terraform apply, Terraform works out the order in
which it needs to create resources.
So it knows that it can't create the load balancer until the
private IP is available, which means it needs to create the virtual machine first.
So it like that actually helps a lot because it means that you no longer need
to kind of have those exceptions or, um, or things the, the other benefit is where
you can parallelize things to say you're creating 30 virtual machines.
You don't need to do them in sequential order.
Terraform can basically go, well, I'm going to create 30 at once,
which, which reduces the time.
So I think those are the, for me, those things that were like
brilliant when I started using it.
I think where I appreciate it moving forward as well is the feedback
loop that Terraform gives me.
So it will tell me what has changed.
And I think that, that again is, is kind of the difference of when they
were building the tool out the thing, right?
Okay.
Things needed to be graph based because we needed this, this dependency, but
we also need to give feedback because we want to understand what has changed.
I don't want to just wipe out my infrastructure every time I do an apply.
I don't want to kind of do this additive update.
I want to, I want to be very prescriptive on, on, um, those changes, what's changed
and understanding what's changed, which, which helps you to not make mistakes,
which is always a, a benefit.
And I think for those reasons is why it's been very, very popular for me as well.
Like, I think it's the accessibility.
So like I, Terraform is the tool that led me to apply for a job at HashiCorp.
Even though I was using Vagrant, I was using console at the
time, uh, and some Packer, I think.
But I was working as a developer and I wanted to deploy an application service.
So I went to see our DevOps team and I'm like, look, I want to deploy this, this
service, it was actually a Lambda and the team were like, well, we know nothing
about Lambda, but we had a good DevOps culture, so they're like, look, if, if
you can figure this out and you can help us understand what's going on here and
you can do it in a way that kind of adheres to our principles, which is
everything must be version control and CICG driven, then we will support
you on, on, on whatever you want to do.
And I thought that's brilliant.
Right.
So I went away and I looked at a number of different tools.
They were using Ansible.
I couldn't figure out Ansible.
I mean, it, um, you know, I was, I'm kind of looking at a very, I'd used
Chef before and I kind of got Chef, but at the same time, when I'm doing my
research, I came across this thing called Terraform and, and I'm like immediately
Terraform had the capability for me to deploy this Lambda.
And I figured it out literally in a, um, in an evening when I was just sitting on
the sofa working, uh, watching TV with my wife and that was, you know, it just
resonated.
So then I took that back to, to the team and they're like, well, we don't use
Terraform, we use Ansible.
But again, we had this agreement.
It was like, well, if it's simple enough, we can understand it and you understand
it and you're happy, then we can come to a compromise.
And that, that for me, when I was actually looking through that Terraform
documentation and working through that role, and at the time I was, I wasn't so
happy in my current role.
It was, there were organizational challenges, which, which was like sad
because I loved the team and I loved the work, but there was a little link at the
bottom of the Terraform documentation, which is like, come work at HashiCorp.
And I remember sitting and complaining to my wife and she said, look, why don't
you just go find a new job?
And I saw this link at the bottom of the Terraform documentation because I've
been working on how to deploy my Lambda and I clicked on it and there was a role
for a developer advocate based in the US.
So I filled in the form and I sent off an email and I said, Hey, look, I live in
London, but I can move to the US or can you possibly move the rule to, to London?
Well, seven years later, I'm, I'm still there, but I'm very fond of Terraform.
Yeah.
Maybe I can add a bit like, I knew about Terraform and then I tried it
out and I don't know, that was yeah, a few years back and I really upped my game.
So I would say like, if you're interested in infrastructure,
you really need to learn it.
And for me as a independent consultant, I need to try out a lot of stuff.
So I don't move somewhere and I don't, I don't get super familiarized into AWS,
into specific services that a company might use.
So I want to maintain a broad knowledge of everything that is there, but I also
want to dive in so much that I can deliver.
And for me having, so Terraform comes with providers, which implement
different cloud providers, and the documentation of all the resources in
Terraform are kind of documented in a standard way because they just document
the resources themselves.
And for me nowadays, it's so much easier to try out different clouds, just like
move around, just like use DigitalOcean, use Vultr, use Linode for my smaller
companies, and then all the three big clouds for other customers.
And it really, really helped me out.
And I also didn't have this bad feeling, you know, when I came to the office and
then I click around the dashboard the whole day, right?
And then I was like, cool, this is well, kind of expensive, right?
It will cost me probably, I don't know, 40 euros a day, but I don't want to delete
everything right now because tomorrow morning I will have to do the same drill.
And if you're clicking through a UI to do that, then you might
not be able to reproduce it.
And I think this is a key thing as well.
Like when people are saying like, well, why should we bother using infrastructure
as code, I can click a button to create my Kubernetes cluster, I can click some
more buttons to set up the load balancer and the security rules and stuff like that.
And that's great.
But what if somebody comes in and deletes your project?
And it was like to my buddy, Eric and I, we did a, we were doing a talk on
Terraform for DigitalOcean a few years back, and the premise was all about using
Terraform to provision DigitalOcean clusters.
And so we're setting all of this up and we built everything up in Terraform.
And Eric said, Hey, can you, we had a couple of clusters.
He's like, can you delete this, this cluster?
So I went into the UI and I just clicked a button and I just, I deleted the wrong
cluster, so I actually wiped out our main infrastructure cluster and like, and I'm
like, um, yeah, Eric, I've just deleted the production infrastructure and he's
like, well, that was stupid.
And I'm like, well, yeah.
Well, what do you expect?
Anyway, the, but this was kind of going into the talk and then I'm like, but hang
on though, we've already defined this with Terraform, so Terraform apply.
Five minutes later, it was all back up, you know, and, and this was, it was kind
of in some ways like, you know, we were doing this talk about why you should use
infrastructure as code and I'd actually proven the point by doing the thing that
I was trying to say you shouldn't ever do.
Yeah.
And, um, and that was, that was amazing.
The ability to basically always reproduce what you've, you've created just by
running this, this, um, this one command, this Terraform apply or tear it down
again, being able to remove everything so you can save money because it's not just
production infrastructure that we've got.
We've got test environments, thousands of dev environments, thousands of test
environments, prod, pre-prod, like depending on the size of the organization,
a lot of, a lot of things.
If you can define that declaratively and you can be a hundred percent certain,
nigh on a hundred percent certain that when you do Terraform apply, you get
exactly what you had the last time.
Then with safety, you can tear stuff down and you can start saving,
saving money and saving resources.
But it also helps with experimentation.
And I think this is like core to the ethos of where HashiCorp are thinking
with things like Terraform and things like Packer about the, you might've
heard the term cattle, not pets.
I, um, I think it's, it's cool, right?
It's like, so rather than having this additive process where you install
software on top of software, what you do is you create something brand new,
which has that combination stack and you throw the old stuff away.
And the reason for that is that it's reproducible.
It's not always reproducible to recreate the layers.
Um, if, if you've done that as in a sort of a layered approach, because
software packages change, um, software packages may be unavailable.
There may be an outage.
Like what happens if there's an outage on apt and you don't have like a, you
know, a, a sort of a cache when you're trying to draw, deploy some production
infrastructure in the middle of an outage or you're in trouble.
Yeah.
But, but if you take the kind of the declarative approach with Packer and
you've got these baked images, then it doesn't remove the risk.
It reduces the, the kind of the risk and increases, um, speed as well.
So I think it's a great tool.
Like I'm, uh, I, I completely agree.
And I'll ask the, like for the audience or the, the, the, the, the, let's say
CIS admins who are the companies that are not yet using Terraform or not at, um,
trying to define their infrastructure as code.
Uh, there's this question of how to introduce Terraform once you
already have something deployed.
So once like the production is already there.
So this is like the most common use case, what to do, because Terraform
is great for greenfield deployment for deploying something new for
starting from scratch.
Awesome.
Yeah.
What to do in cases when like there's so much legacy in production.
Well, how to introduce, you have any, any bits and tricks, how to,
how to, um, do this kind of shift?
Yeah.
So it, I mean, it's always been possible to Terraformify.
Is that, I probably created a thing.
Like if marketing are watching, I'm sorry.
Um, but Terraformify is now a thing.
Um, it has always been possible to turn existing infrastructure into
Terraform because there's always been the, the import command.
The problem that's always been with the import command is it would
just bring in the state.
So for folks who are not familiar with Terraform, you've got this
concept of state, which defines what exists and then your Terraform
configuration is what will be.
Now, when you've got an existing resource, you need
configuration and you need state.
So the import command would just create the state, which meant you then had to
go and write the, you know, you had to go and write the, the HCL for each of
those things, which matched the state.
And it was, I mean, it was possible.
I mean, you could automate it in some aspects, but it was, it was time-consuming.
It was a bit of a, it was a bit of a chore and there was tooling.
Um, I think it was Terraform, it was going to be like a Google project, which,
which could kind of do with some of this stuff, but what we did in the last
release of, um, Terraform, which just came out this summer is we've
updated the, the import command.
So now you can actually define an import stanza, point it to an
existing resource in your cloud.
And what Terraform will do is it will both import the state and
it will generate the HCL for you.
So you, you know, you can take even large existing pieces of infrastructure
and start kind of pulling them in.
So you can start managing them with, with Terraform, which, which
I think is a good step forward.
And again, this isn't an early stage feature.
It was only, only this summer.
And there's a lot more to do with that.
And, and of course people like to modularize things.
So it, it's not going to figure all of that out for you, but it, it's
definitely better than having to like hand, hand roll all of this stuff.
So I think you can do it.
Um, and I think there's, I think it's worth doing, but, but I think
like, should you, should you do everything?
I mean, as an exercise that could be expensive.
So maybe what you've got to look at is what is changing all of the time?
Like, so if for example, you've got 20 servers and only one of them changes,
maybe just the important thing is just to Terraform that one, that one server.
Uh, it doesn't have to be an exercise where it's all or nothing, but, but I
definitely think there is a benefit that wherever there is change that you, if
you manage that change with Terraform, you are reducing your, your risk, um,
because of the, the, the knowledge you get from the, the change diffs.
Um, but again, that, that reproducibility, that consistency, the, the ability to
recreate something, if somebody goes into your production and clicks the big red
button and then just blindly copies the delete thing into the box, and then
realizes that that was actually the wrong account that they've done it in.
And they've just deleted the production.
That's a great disaster recovery exercise.
That's how we learn.
I mean, right.
Yeah.
If, if, if you did your homework, right.
And, uh, the, the, the Terraform, uh, like it's, it's written correctly.
Like this is one way to, to actually test it.
Yeah.
And I think that's the nice thing, right?
Like, so when you, you, you have this common workflow, the there's so many
Terraform will work with multiple clouds.
It doesn't like, if you can know how to, the resource standard for
defining virtual machine in AWS is different to the one in GCP.
And in Azure and in DigitalOcean.
Subtle differences because each of those clouds have got different
features and capabilities, but the thing is around the workflow.
If you understand the workflow, if you understand how Terraform plan, how it
apply works, how destroy works, how you define resources and you can create
variables and modularization and, and then the, the, the kind of the
workflow of automating that.
So using Terraform within multiple environments, um, and doing automated
deploys, when you get good at that, what it means is that you can, your
disaster recovery is potentially getting tested every time you do a build.
So if you do a build to dev, you're also kind of testing the Terraform code,
which is going to deploy your products.
And so you'll, you'll catch things that maybe I'm using a, an out of date
schema, or maybe there's a configuration problem.
Um, so it, I think it, it just massively reduces the, your risk and gives you
this, this, this great capability to, to recover in the incident that something
does happen, um, which, which got to be a good thing.
Yeah.
You're right.
Recently, there have been a lot of news about Terraform and a license change.
Yeah.
Um, and yeah, we just want to ask you what's the fuss all about.
I mean, I think, I think folks are, so there's been the change.
So the change has been that we've, we've, we've relicensed Terraform
core to a BSL license so that that BSL license has certain restrictions on use.
Now the, without kind of going right into the terms of the, the kind of the legal
side of things that the terms of, of kind of the restrictions are that for 99.999999%
of people who were using Terraform, they can continue to do so.
And they continue to use it for free without any implications on the license.
What the, the license change was, was kind of is really where it really starts
restriction is if, for example, say you're building a Terraform cloud, then
that, that the, the license then starts coming into a force.
So, because you're in, you're creating a service using Terraform, which is in
competition to one of, one of HashiCorp's services.
Now, again, I just want to kind of say that that's not necessarily a, a sort of
a, a pure black or white thing, because we do have the capabilities around license
exemption.
So if you're, you know, say for example, you're just, you've got an internal
platform, which is using Terraform and you're, maybe there's a gray area of it.
You're in a competing business with HashiCorp.
Can you still use Terraform?
I mean, I think the answer is probably yes, but in the, the, the licensing folks
will, will, will sort of, will help you out, clarify that.
So I think a lot of folks were like, well, why did we do it?
Is this not Megarevil Corp?
Are we, are we kind of like, you know, are we, are we going
against the spirit of, of open source?
And, and I think the key thing is that the code is still open now.
So it is technically always going to be open.
If you want, you can fork Terraform and prior to the, the sort of the BSL
license change, you can do what you want with, with that code.
It's still the, I think it was MPL or whatever.
So that, and the, the future code will always be publicly available,
obviously with the, the BSL license.
So as we add new features to Terraform, that code will be completely
transparent and available inside of the, the, the, the public repo.
And I can, I just want to add as well, it is sort of vault,
nomad, console, et cetera.
Now, what we haven't changed on a licensing perspective are
things like the providers.
Because the providers are in most instances, not, not actually our code.
So, so for example, the folks at DigitalOcean build their own provider,
Google contribute to their own providers, as do Microsoft, as do sort of Amazon.
That, that license hasn't, hasn't changed.
Like why did we do it?
I think that's the key thing.
Like, why would you do this?
I mean, the, the thing is that with, HashiCorp invests and has invested over
the sort of the last sort of 10 years, quite a large amount of money into, into
Terraform, obviously Terraform would nowhere near be as, as, as popular as it
is, if it hadn't been for, for wonderful sort of community contribution, but we
have a huge number of sort of engineers and product engineers, you know, a huge
amount of support that goes into that.
Which way that we made money from Terraform as a, as an entity, I mean,
we're, you know, we're a company that was through Terraform, Terraform cloud.
And the, the kind of, I think the drive around the change is to kind of protect
that investment, because if we can do that, what it means is we can keep those
engineers because we don't, you know, we want to keep the engineers and we want
to keep innovating on Terraform.
We want to keep putting that knowledge in, we want to keep it as a, as an amazing
tool that most of the community can use, use for free.
And, and I think that was kind of the, you know, that's the, the, the primary
sort of motive behind the change.
It's, it's not that we're kind of moving this as a precursor to one day, it's
just going to be like, Hey, we're going to stop using Terraform and everybody's
being like hoodwinked and you're now going to have to pay us mega dollars to,
to rebuild.
No, no, no, no, not in the slightest.
It's, it's literally just, we're just trying to protect that investment.
99.999999% of people you have, nothing's changed.
Um, and the main argument that I like saw from the community is like, this is so
widely defined that like, it's, it's not black and white and it's hard to say.
Uh, and I think this is the, the, why, why everybody in everybody active in, in,
in communities is, is, is sort of a safe now that like HashiCorp is now the evil
corp.
Yeah.
I mean, I think, you know, we, I, I, I'll be honest with you.
I think we, you know, we weren't the first people to, to do this.
Um, sure.
It's been a number of companies who've, who've relicensed open source to protect
their investments.
And I, we probably won't be the last either.
I think if, if anything, if there's criticism that we've, we've maybe not
managed the, the information on, on the change, then, you know, we'll, we'll take
that and, and see if we can do a better job around that.
I think it is complex because it is quite a, like, I mean, even if you read something
like the NPL or a GPL license, they are, for me, I'm not a legal person.
It's, it's a, it's a complicated document.
So maybe that is, um, that, that can be confusing that you look at this wall of
text, but, but ultimately the, the, let's say the key thing is that if you're not in
an organization, which is directly competing against any of HashiCorp
services, you're unaffected.
If you're unsure, then I think it's licensing at hashicorp.com.
You can sort of get you in touch with, with somebody, or if you're coming to
HashiConf, we're going to have, um, folks there who will be able to help with
licensing queries and things like that.
We're more than happy to, to sort of clarify those.
And I would like to bet that like most of the time it's going to be, you know, you're
fine.
Um, and, and it's certainly nothing we wanted to do deliberately.
You know, we, we, we didn't want to cause any upset.
It wasn't, um, and I, uh, any, anything sort of malicious or anything like that.
We.
We're really just trying to protect the investment so that we can keep
investing and keep, um, keep, keep, keep expanding Terraform's capabilities
and, and, um, make it a even better and better product and something we can
use for the next decade as well.
Um, I know if you can maybe like comment now that the community now
opened, uh, open TF or open TOFU.
Uh, so basically it's a, it's a, it's a fork of, of previous, previous
version of, of, of Terraform.
Um, I don't know.
Yeah.
What, what could we expect?
Because we, we definitely saw this in, in, in the past.
Yeah.
Um, and, uh, in the end, this kind of fighting, it's not like, it's not good.
No, of course it doesn't bring any, any, any
progress.
No, I mean, so I think, I mean, that was, that was perfectly a legitimate thing.
And, um, so open TOFU exists.
Um, it was created by, uh, a few organizations who were obviously
affected by the license, but who also felt strongly about the license change
and wanted to, to keep things on a, uh, an MPL license.
Now what that they're, they're obviously doing there, they've created the fork.
They will then create a distribution, um, and a registry and all of those
sorts of things, which, um, are in line with, with the sort of the license.
I don't know what the future will hold.
It, um, it's, it's difficult to kind of, to say like, will one win out?
Will we end up with, with the sort of the, like Jenkins Hudson or something
along those lines, I just don't know.
Like all I can say is that as an organization, HashiCorp is 1000%
committed to creating Terraform as the best tool that we can offer the industry
to be able to create the best support and services, um, around it.
And, and that we're going to sort of continue to do that.
Does it mean that sort of, um, providers will kind of dry up and disappear then?
You know, I mean, very possibly, right.
Some, some, some, some people might determine that they're no longer wants
to, to create a provider for Terraform.
Some people might say they don't want to create a provider for OpenTofu.
Some people might end up creating both and having to support the two.
So it's, um, I guess, you know, we just, it's, it's early days.
Like, I mean, we, we just have to wait and see, wait and see how
things, um, wait and things pan out.
But as I say, all I can say is as a HashiCorp representative, we are
committed to keeping Terraform free for, for the vast majority of people
were committed to creating the best tool that it can be and, um, yeah,
like we, you know, we genuinely love the community and everything that
they've done to support that.
And, um, if anybody feels aggrieved by the things that we've done and I, you
know, I can apologize personally from that, but, but it is, you know, it's,
it's a thing we want to, we want to keep things to be able to protect.
And so we can keep it pushed forward.
I don't know what else I can say around those things.
I think it's, yeah, I couldn't, I can understand that.
Like even company needs to do some trade-offs and, and, and, and like it
can't be like win for everyone.
Yeah.
Um, but in that sense, I completely understand you.
Um, and, um, I, I can also imagine like the, the fuss on the other side, but, but still.
Yeah.
And I, and I, I understand that as well.
I mean, I'm, I am an open source user as well, but like for me and, and I, and I'll
be honest with you, like, and I'm talking on a personal level here, not, um, sort
of ignore the H on my shirt, but when, when we made this sort of change and I sat
down and I'm sort of in my head trying to rationalize, well, what does open source
actually mean, mean to me?
And, and I thought about this and like, and to be honest, I started looking
and I'm like, I very rarely actually look at the license.
The key thing for me was the ability to benefit from somebody else's learning.
The, the ability to, to not have to reinvent the wheel.
I mean, back to my JPEG example, like not having to do that every time.
And as a, as somebody who has an open source project, spend a large amount
of my own personal time working on, I mean, we've been sort of thinking, well,
you know, is, is the NPL license really, is it, is it, is it work for me as an
individual?
Um, but, but in general, like the, the thing for me that's most important is
that the, the source code still exists.
I can still see what's going on.
I can still learn from it.
Um, and I can still consume something, uh, which was always being intended
that we wanted to create something, which was, uh, you know, free, free to
use, which benefits the community as a whole.
So, yeah, I don't know what, like, what do you think?
I mean, you got opinions.
What, what?
I'm, I'm, I'm sort of a looking like looking from the distance because yeah,
like I said, we saw that with like Mongo, we saw that with Elasticsearch.
Um, and I was never in a way affected.
So like me as a, as a, as a consultant or me as a working for, for a company,
but again, it, it really, in the end difference, whether this company is
actually like selling this, this product or what, what's building like reselling
this, um, forward, um, and yeah, we saw that like, I, I, in a way I understand
both sides, like the way you explain it now, I completely get it.
Um, it, and I also understand the other side saying that like things are not
like defined, um, the way that's like, there could be like exceptions or like,
and so on and, and, and I, yeah.
And I think that's like, if, if I've got criticism around that, then I
criticize the lawyers and I think it's, I think it's, you know, I think it's
fair to, to be, to, to have a kind of a, an inherent hatred of lawyers.
I think that they're generally kind of, if we want, we all want to
kind of agree on one thing, but no, I mean, the, the legal document is, and
it is a kind of a legal documents.
It's obviously a contractor license is, is difficult and it's, it, what we've
tried to do is make sure that the, the vast majority can continue as normal
using Terraform as they always have, but have that clause in there, which, which
kind of, um, stops, uh, stops folks from kind of like leveraging all of that
hard work for, and which, which again, affects us to, to kind of invest in
Terraform and with always, when you end up with that sort of thing, it, it, it
always becomes complex.
It's not, cause it's difficult to say who is a competitor, who isn't, you
can't really define that in the license.
But again, to kind of reiterate those things, like, I think if, if you think
that you, you're not sure, if you are not sure that you're competing with
HashiCorp, I think realistically, you're probably not.
And licensing at HashiCorp will, will be able to clarify that for you.
And I think they'll sort of, you can give you sort of written, um,
confirmation that you're, there's no sort of, uh, infringement of licensing.
Um, so I, um, and I hope that as I say, there's time, it's only been what, a
month or so that we'll, we'll get a little bit more sort of, um, used to,
to kind of dealing with things.
But, um, yeah, like honestly, if you, if there's anybody who has any, any sort
of concerns, reach out to me, I'm more than happy to, to, to, to chat, to, to
kind of, um, put you in touch with people.
If you want to speak to, uh, some, some of the sort of, or get a sort of legal
answer from, from HashiCorp's team, then we can arrange all of those sorts of things.
Awesome.
Uh, let's go to more relaxed topics.
What do you do like to disconnect from all the technology?
Do you have like any hobbies?
Yeah.
So I, I like, well, so firstly I, I do like sport.
So I, um, I swim ultra, um, uh, well, marathon distance and
ultra marathon distance swimming.
So basically anything, well, marathon distance in swimming is 10 K and above.
Um, so I'll, I do, I do a lot of that, which is, I find very meditative.
I mean, if you've, um, I don't know if anybody swims or if you've, if you've
ever swum sort of lap swimming, it's, it's very, you know, meditative, especially
when, uh, if you're swimming front crawl and you've just kind of face in the water.
I find that, um, when you're swimming like between what could be four to six,
seven hours, um, it's very, very relaxing.
So I, and I enjoy floating around in water as well.
So there's, um, I do that.
I do like video games.
Um, I've, I kind of started falling into the slippery slope of sim racing
recently, um, which I started playing Gran Turismo 7, uh, in VR too.
And I enjoyed that very much.
And then all of a sudden the steering wheel appeals in my house.
And then before you know it, there's a, a, a seat and, uh, yeah,
that's, that's been a slippery slope.
And recently I've been getting into iRacing, uh, which I'm, I'm quite enjoying.
But, uh, I also like, you know, other video games.
Um, I've been playing Starfield, Baldur's Gate 3.
Um, yeah.
And, well, and then of course I do a lot of writing, so I'm still working on my,
my second book, which I'll hopefully get finished soon.
Uh, I'm going to start a new, uh, YouTube channel with, uh, Ivan, who's
hosting here today at DevOps Days.
It'll be on a called, uh, doing DevOps where we, we want to kind of get some
education, uh, put some education back.
And so the concept is that, that Ivan, uh, has, has learned a lot across his
career and we want to be able to kind of put that back into, to helping people
who were in the same position as he was when he, when he first began.
And it's always, I enjoy doing stuff like that as well.
It's fun.
I enjoy helping people.
So yeah, pretty much, pretty much.
Walk my dog.
Um, I'm trying to think.
Eating ice cream.
There are some nice ice cream shops in the center of Ljubljana.
We can give you a list.
I'm hoping, yeah, later on today we'll maybe check something out.
Uh, awesome.
But, but since you, since you, since you started like, um, passing on like to, to,
to, to, to, to, to newbies, uh, into this world.
So for our audience, since there are a lot of like, um, engineers who are now
at the beginning of their career.
So I don't know, what would it be your advice where to start if they are interested
in, in exploring the, the, the DevOps culture and so on, what, what to, what
would be the, the, the tools to start learning the, the, the, the, the, the
things that, that, that should they focus on?
Well, I mean, I think you, you absolutely can't go wrong with Terraform and whether
you kind of, um, you know, you, you look at that as the Terraform, OpenTofu,
whatever, like there is a, as a tool and as a methodology, I think it's something
as a, that's, that's kind of here to stay, I hope.
Um, so I think that's definitely something to look at.
I think learning cloud is really hard.
Like I, I have, um, I spend a lot of time working between a number of different
sort of clouds, depending on what I'm trying to sort of show.
So I think having, doing say like your, your GCP AWS or Azure kind of
certification is always worthwhile because you can get a lot of value out
of how best to sort of leverage, leverage cloud.
Um, I think folks like DigitalOcean are exceptional as well, like, because
it's very, it's very accessible and you don't always need this huge amount of
complexity and DO does, um, a very good cloud at a very good price.
Um, so I think, you know, looking at something like that, one thing I will
say is that I think one of the things that helped me the most when I was
learning was that by teaching that helped me accelerate my own learning.
And, and I will always say to people that, you know, you, you may not know
as much as the expert, but I can guarantee you that if you know something,
you know more than somebody else.
So by passing that back and by, by kind of having this culture of, of sharing
your knowledge, you're reinforcing that knowledge, but you're also kind of
helping, helping others who they can then can turn, can, can help you.
And then that, that, that really helps drive things.
So folks like yourself, I'm always incredibly appreciative of, and, um,
thank you so much for, for running the podcast and helping get information out
there.
Um, YouTube is incredible.
I mean, I, gosh, I wish it existed when, when I was starting.
No, the paper books, right?
Oh yeah.
Like, I mean, I, you know, I, yeah, but I have, I have like issues with like
YouTube, like I was sort of, uh, like getting knowledge from, from books or
webpages, like you can like scan to the point where, where you need it, the,
the, the information because scanning to the video is, is, is problematic.
Yeah.
I'm, I'm, you know, I'm with you there.
So I think now video seems to be the de facto standard around how
information is, is produced.
And so for example, I'm going to, so I'm going to give you a lightning talk later
on today, and one of the things around the lightning talk is a slide every 15
seconds, there's a capability in Google slides where you can set it to auto
advance every 15 seconds.
I could not figure out where this was, so I Googled it and there was a video and
it was a three minute video, which told me to click on three options.
So I think video is maybe not always the most appropriate source.
As I say, like I'm, um, I've, I've written one book, which published about
five years ago, I'm working on my second one.
Um, I do like video.
I enjoy creating video and I quite enjoy watching video.
Um, but I, I do worry at the same time that we're not writing enough blog posts
anymore and the advantage of something like a blog post is it's very easy to
index, so it's, it's very immediate.
If you want to look for a very specific thing, if that can be indexable through,
through the Google search and just pop up in the search box, you can achieve
something very, very quickly.
Whereas if you get a video, which has that information somewhere inside it,
it can be a little bit slower.
So, but some people hate reading, like, you know, some people have difficulties
with, um, with, with, with sort of following, um, printed text.
So having a, the, the medium of video is also very accessible at the same time,
which I think is, it's also a very good thing.
It's like, oh, I think maybe we've got pros and cons.
Awesome.
Uh, I think it's time for us to wrap up.
Yeah.
Uh, Nick, thank you very much for your time.
Thank you for visiting Ljubljana.
I'm excited.
It's a beautiful place.
Yeah.
Um, I would like to thank, uh, the organizer of organizers of Delves days.
I would like to thank Andras.
Thanks.
I would like to thank the whole team in the, at the back, uh,
Otto, Tomas and Rok.
Uh, thank you very much.
And I would like to thank our Patreons and, uh, the two companies that
sponsor our production, 3FS and Human Frog.
Uh, have a nice day and see you soon.
Or we, you will listen to us soon.
Thank you.