We've got a message for you.
Then our glorious jingle comes out,
which we've collected from a hundred archives.
Jingle!
Janic, greetings and welcome to a new episode of Grodje.
I think it's 26 episodes, in numbers.
I have to say that it's already been a year,
and we've been on stage for a year.
We've come a long way since we started
filming this on a test set,
because we have a whole team of people behind us
who help us keep this thing on a high level.
Today we have a special guest
with whom we will try to describe where we travel as a country.
We will try to talk about the challenges on this journey,
how we will overcome these challenges,
and a lot of things we have in common that interest us.
Now we will try to keep the tone very positive,
and try to have an engineering aspect.
Parallaxed.
Parallaxed, yes.
What else can I say?
We will be hosting this time in Maribor,
at the 3FS company.
We will put a link below, so check out this company.
And I would like to thank you for hosting us.
I forgot something at the beginning.
Let me introduce you to the guest.
Today is a very special day.
Special.
Will you talk?
Yes, I will.
This fact will bring you closer.
I would also like to thank our special guest,
researcher Dr. Emili Stojmenov-Duh,
Minister of Digital Transformation.
She has a doctorate from the Faculty of Electrical Engineering
at the University of Maribor.
Before her doctorate, she worked at the company Iskrtel,
and then she started working at the Faculty of Electrical Engineering
at the University of Ljubljana.
Last year, she was a professor at the Faculty of Information
and Communication Technology.
Dr. Stojmenov-Duh is the first graduate professor
at the Faculty of Electrical Engineering.
She was also the first president of IEEE
Women in Engineering Slovenia.
In January 2024, she was appointed
Minister of Digital Transformation.
As an author and co-author,
she has signed numerous scientific and academic publications
in the field of digital transformation.
Welcome. Thank you for having us.
Thank you very much.
Can I correct something?
Yes, definitely.
I am not the first graduate professor
at the Faculty of Electrical Engineering,
but at the Faculty of Information and Communication Technology.
Thank you.
I think we already copied it.
Yes, of course, we are a bit lazy.
No, we didn't copy it from Tech Overflow,
but we did a little research,
and we didn't write it in CHPT,
so thank you for that.
Without CHPT, but we have a lot of people
who are concerned that we don't present guests well,
so we could add that aspect on our own.
We were hoping for quick fixes, but we don't like that.
The professor in me always has to look for a way to fix it.
Is that a mistake by the guests?
No, I don't think it's a mistake,
but I didn't want to make a mistake by accident.
I'll leave it to the workers.
We have a lot of topics,
so let's start with...
Quite simply.
You lead the Ministry for Digital Transformation.
What is Digital Transformation?
It's a bunch of things.
As I understand it,
it's the use of new digital technologies
to create new processes,
either through user or consumer experiences,
or through the way companies and organizations work.
On the one hand, it can be used for something new,
or to adapt existing processes
to the way we use existing technologies.
Quite simply.
We use technologies for real processes,
not just technologies.
We're not just talking about technologies,
we're also talking about processes,
we're also talking about educating people,
mindset,
culture,
resources,
and strategies.
When we were preparing for this episode,
we had a very interesting experience.
First, we asked our audience
what their difficulties are,
and what they ask us.
Now, it's a bit broader.
We asked people what they think.
They gave very interesting feedback,
perhaps in the spirit of our time.
They also talked about the lack of understanding
of the Ministry.
I went to pick up the digital strategy,
I don't know, 66 pages,
with the attachments,
with the documents.
Let's hear from you.
What is the Ministry?
What are the basic...
What is your job?
It was a soft question,
because I saw people...
People have a lot of expectations.
Some people don't understand,
because the Ministry was created anew,
the Minister of Forestry was already established,
or you already had a place in the Ministry.
But people just don't know
what to expect from the Ministry.
But as soon as you started,
you got a lot of feedback.
This shows that this area is very important
in our everyday life,
and also in our everyday work.
Digital transformation,
digital technologies
came with the new Ministry,
with the new service.
But they are part of our life.
In the past, every Ministry
dealt with this area on its own.
They dealt with the economy,
they dealt with the Ministry of Labor,
they dealt with the Ministry of Family Affairs,
they balanced certain aspects,
education,
I don't know if you know,
but the Broadband Internet for Support
was at the Ministry of Agriculture.
And everything we did
was given to an organ,
a Ministry that will look at all these things
closely, and the Ministry
is still covering them for its aspects.
Only here, our Ministry
has a close strategy,
that's why we prepared this strategy,
to show what the goal is,
what the vision of Slovenia is in this area.
And even when we finance
certain projects,
we will not prepare to finance
the same areas on agriculture,
on infrastructure,
on trade,
but somehow these things are connected.
Interoperability is also
very modern,
but what is it about?
It's about having the data
in one place, not having to bring it 20 times,
every different resource,
every different organization,
but to have it inside,
and to manage it, because it already exists.
That's why the Ministry
was created.
Ok.
I will try again,
again, I want to be
positive, but...
I prepared,
when we were preparing,
I prepared your social channels,
Instagram, Facebook,
and so on,
and tomorrow I see
a picture of you,
with the image of older people,
I think in Velenje,
and I thought, ok, great,
then in a couple of hours we will prepare
a certificate, and then it's
a shitstorm,
and then you see
all this
thunder,
is this your dignity?
Is it, I repeat,
is it still the dignity of the Ministry?
Will you
direct them through these things?
Is this a digital transformation?
I mean, this is about hygiene,
just hygiene, that you have
proper maintenance of certificates.
Before you were talking
about digital transformation, I added
a mindset, that it is necessary
to change the mindset, and just as
we have to make sure that our personal
certificate does not go wrong,
or that we properly provide
a driver's license, we also have to
properly provide a certificate.
What is our role here?
Our role is to inform
all these organizations,
to teach them,
that this is a part of basic hygiene.
It is not our fault that
the IPES certificate went wrong,
because
when we realized that this
problem had arisen, we could not
start calling IPES, our partners,
to do this job.
We saw that IPES was not the only one,
but at least some other organization.
What did we do on the basis of this?
We prepared a letter,
and we sent it to everyone,
and we will not conclude here.
We have a lot to do at our Ministry,
because we warn other organizations.
For example, another such
problem is the electronic signature.
Again, we sent a letter,
we organize meetings,
because the rest of our resource
is not only the Ministry, but also
agencies and everything that falls
from the internal sector.
We want to tell them that
the electronic signature
according to Slovenian and European
legislation is equally valuable
to the personal signature.
Our role as a Ministry is
to inform, to teach others,
and we all have to
enter the mindset of digital transformation.
And this is our role,
which we have and see.
Now we both come from
the industry,
and we are assigned to
VPM of Engineering,
CTO,
CEO,
and I am most curious about
how the Ministry is composed.
Is it for various departments,
directors, how does it all work?
I can tell you how we are organized,
if you are interested.
We have four directorates
within the Ministry.
This is the Directorate for Digital Society.
This is where the information society
is more involved, where competencies fall,
then new modern technologies,
Artificial Intelligence, block editing,
and so on.
Then we have the Directorate for Digital
and Financial Economy.
This is where you get to know
the E-governance,
then there is the electronic
personal certificate, certificates,
and the general portal
is on this directorate.
Then we have the Directorate for Infrastructure.
Here are the supervisors,
because we have the entire public administration,
the public sector, H-Com network
is in our Ministry,
and the Directorate for Supporting Users,
which is the ECC center,
we get a lot of compliments from users
that they are very satisfied.
In addition, we also have
the Service for International
and European Affairs,
we have our own Secretariat,
the Legal Service, and all the staff
that you know in the companies.
So that's how we are somehow organized.
The directorates have directors,
then there are sectors within
the individual directorate,
and that's it.
Too simple.
That's how you
logically know everything.
I just saw
that you also have
an organ in the Directorate of Inspection.
Exactly.
I wrote to you,
many of us
in the community
some time ago
received
an e-mail that
we need to go to...
To look for accessibility.
Accessibility.
And then we realized
that there is also an organ in the station.
I also saw that.
I just wanted to add that.
And it is very important
that we are proud of the organ.
I didn't want to forget it,
but because the inspectorate must be independent.
And they also warn us
when we make mistakes.
If someone does it in the directorate,
we also get a finger.
But if, for example,
we don't give an additional explanation,
the inspector calls us like that.
Why did this happen?
On the one hand,
there was a shared opinion in the public.
Some said, what do you need from us?
Do you owe us with this?
We only have an additional part.
On the other hand, we got a full compliment.
Someone finally went crazy.
Because the law exists.
But if the law exists and we don't enforce it,
we haven't done anything with it.
And I am sure that we have
to thank the main inspector.
Because our intention was not
to go to prison.
Our intention was to warn,
to see what is going on.
To talk to everyone,
to explain.
And people also understand it.
Again, it's about informing.
To know that we have to
pay attention to public access.
Because we always say that we want to be in the spotlight.
In the last episode,
it was with the
private expert from Australia.
A hacker who helps people
become more
safe in the organization.
To protect them in some way.
We asked him
a question like
how do you get
in the organization this knowledge
that something is important
and that companies strategically decide
to change certain things.
And I said
very simply.
If there are no
legal requirements
that companies
have to meet,
certain strategies
are not paid
to invest in it.
We both know
that security
is in the last place.
Accessibility does not come
when we develop
some commercial solutions.
Unless those solutions are intended
for some groups
where it is very important.
It is understandable that
we take care and the contrast
of the text on the back
or all other things is not important.
But all these standards have existed
for a long time.
I am not among the youngest,
but I graduated
from this field.
We have been talking about it for many years.
We just don't always
think about creating new
websites or new mobile applications.
We are people
who see worse
and we need to be careful.
When we publish on social networks
for someone
they don't see the personality
that we want
to share
or to come to them.
From this point of view,
exactly through the inspectorate,
through the laws,
we can get them to use
in practice.
Now we are being listened to
by engineers and engineers of the future.
Future engineers and engineers
and all the people
who are interested in these things.
I believe that
it is good to have an overflow
of knowledge and information
on a higher level,
so that you can look for this connection.
I am interested in what you expect
from engineers and engineers
to our audience.
What I would like
is
even if it is a constructive
criticism,
even if it is a warning
that we have overlooked something
or that we are working on something.
What is happening today,
I don't want to generalize,
we get a lot of
foreign engineers and engineers
of non-governmental organizations
who have proposals
to do something.
One thing is impossible
due to various reasons.
right now,
but we will start thinking about it.
The worst thing is
that we don't know
why we need the Ministry of Digital Transformation.
It was useful for us.
On the other hand,
I have to praise
the investigators in this example.
When something happened,
they sent us a message
to check what can be done
in this area.
It helped us.
We checked what we could do.
Not only investigators,
but also government organizations
and other organizations.
They were very welcome
with their proposals.
We absolutely accept criticism,
but we have to be constructive.
Now,
before we started
preparing for this episode,
the Minister of Digital Transformation
explained to us
that we have
some public services,
which will be digitized.
On the other hand,
we started thinking
and the investigators also asked
what engineers can expect
from this ministry.
One of the things
is the digitization
of the economy.
What are the things
that can be expected
from our employees
or from the Ministry?
Engineers are probably
also entrepreneurs.
What we are doing
is that we want
all the public services
to be digitally free.
You don't have to
go to different offices,
but you can do
whatever you want.
A lot of this is already free.
According to the strategy
of digital public services,
we want all the key services
connected to the enterprise
to be digitally free,
and our teams are working
in this area.
All the engineers
who develop digital solutions
probably want their employees
to know how to use them.
Our wish
is not only to use
digital services
in the public sector,
but also in the private sector.
This is not just a wish,
but a reality.
A lot of these services
are already being used
in the private sector,
for authentication,
for security authentication.
You don't have to develop
your own solutions,
but the state already offers them.
So maybe not everything
is direct,
but it can also be indirect.
For example, in five years,
if I want to go to the gym,
I won't need a gym and gymnasium,
I will have my own digital gymnasium.
I hope it will be like in five years.
I wanted to ask you
when you said
that you want more connectivity
with the employees,
even though I took the strategy
a bit to the right and a bit to the left,
a lot of these systems
are siloed information.
If you want one thing,
you have one evidence,
then you have a book,
then you have a system.
These things are distributed.
I am interested in what you do
in the real estate in this area.
How will you prepare
Interpobility in this context?
You said it today,
you posted a picture on Twitter
to choose our digital strategy,
which is great.
Otherwise, the digital strategy has 40 pages.
There are 66 pages because of the attachment.
I wanted a very short
and very specific document.
And there you probably also prepared
that we will have
ministers as a strategic witness,
in addition to representatives
of businesses,
non-governmental organizations,
talk organizations and so on.
And that means
that they will support
projects for digital transformation.
And if they sit at the same table,
then they know what is happening.
Here we are talking strategically.
On the other hand, we also have
an operational group, these are directors
of various ministries,
and when they develop solutions,
they talk to each other.
For example, last week,
we met with colleagues from the Ministry
for Internal Affairs and the Ministry
for Infrastructure on the topic
of mobile train stations.
And in this way,
they come to this transition,
because for the longest time,
they did not know who
what will start, what is developing.
And here, for example, we have a great experience
with the Ministry of Health,
now you probably noticed
that it is renewed,
and here with our colleagues
who are participating,
in this way, then
we have a lot of energy,
which we have again demonstrated
how important it is in our strategy
Digital Slovenia.
This is my favorite topic, notes.
Because you are the only one
without a note, maybe you too.
But let's go to the next question,
somehow related to the strategy
Digital Slovenia 2030.
Now I can ask
some questions,
you can introduce them to us,
you probably already know,
As I said,
it was extremely important for us
that this strategy is short
and clear document,
and that we do not go to some blablabla
talk, but to know exactly
what are the priorities,
what goals do we have,
and from this strategy then follows
the action plan, which is already being prepared,
and in the action plan we will precisely say
financial resources,
and who is responsible for what.
So here we only have a strategy,
and from this to determine responsibilities,
then we did not anticipate
how far we would go.
Some compliments,
I as a member of non-governmental
organizations, of course, choose a lot of strategies,
and one compliment
that is,
in this strategy,
I like the main
summaries,
the current situation,
then some milestone
2025,
then 2030,
and as we say at home,
we are from the company Tenso,
some KPI, which can be easily
validated and see
how we progress in this strategy.
I would always like,
we have already discussed this,
but I would always like to know
for our audience,
what are the main areas
that are now the most important
until 2030?
KPI, because I am also an engineer,
and therefore it is also
very important for me to measure
whether we have achieved something successful or not.
So the key to digital transformation
starts with infrastructure.
Gigabit infrastructure,
both fixed and mobile networks.
We want up to 20-30
gigabit infrastructure for all
businesses in the country, regardless of geographical location.
Mobile internet
equally, 5G,
so that we have everything covered,
all the places, all the support,
all the roads.
Why roads? Because of autonomous driving.
Then the next category
is digital inclusion,
and here with digital inclusion
we are not only talking about digital competencies,
but we are also talking about
that everyone can
transport that gigabit
infrastructure, even
economically.
Then they also need equipment
to be able to use those tables.
and not last but not least, digital knowledge and competences,
to enable all 80% of residents to have all basic competences,
to be able to use various devices that we have at our disposal,
both from the public sector and from the private sector.
The next category is digital transformation of the economy.
The strategy of digital transformation of the economy
was made at the Ministry of Economy before,
and given that it is a crown strategy,
here we include the main KPIs,
it is important for us that, for example,
most companies use cloud storage,
that they use one of these new technologies,
and we are aware that we cannot do everything,
but that at least some of these new technologies.
The next thing we have is a smart society,
5.0, tax economy,
which means a lot to us here,
which means open data,
re-use of data,
also foreign companies for various innovations,
and of course we cannot do without information security.
Information security is part of the strategy
that was prepared at the URSS,
that is the Council of the Republic of Slovenia for Information Security,
but here, in the crown strategy,
we take these key gifts.
I don't know where this fits in,
but you talked about the tax...
I don't know, growth of the tax...
And the economy.
The OPSI portal,
I think it also fits under your wings.
From this we saw a bunch of interesting projects,
and opportunities,
and it is a very nice project.
I wonder how you will continue with open data,
is it a European direction,
does Europe want us to have data at will,
or is it a Slovenian unit?
No, we don't have to take credit for it.
I will go back a bit,
and I will ask you this way.
Probably some European strategy
will have an impact on how you designed the strategy
Digital Slovenia 2030,
and probably Europe will also give some funds
through this strategy in this project, right?
It is about the European Digital Decade program.
And there are sources,
which are knowledge and competence,
economy, infrastructure,
digital public services,
I forgot to mention one of the categories,
and in our strategy we also looked at
the characteristics we have in our country,
we added horizontal principles,
which are extremely important for us,
open, inclusive, free internet,
democratic society,
open code solutions,
and so on,
and also, which is extremely important,
digital and green transformation.
So we draw from European documents and strategies,
and we apply them to the environment we have at home.
Why do we draw from European documents?
Because we want to go to the interstate.
Our digital declaration was already used
abroad in Europe,
it is accessible,
and even this year,
you will be able to use it in one of your neighboring countries,
I don't know, you will go to the sea in Croatia,
and you will, for example,
get an e-mail at the hospital
in the Croatian Museum of Health.
So we don't have to be alone here,
but we also have to look at
what is happening in Europe.
Now, as far as funds are concerned,
of course, just this week,
the European Commission also announced a new program,
the Digital Europe program,
which is a huge amount of money,
and one of the problems we are facing in Slovenia
is that Slovenian companies
use their opportunities too little,
they don't apply for contracts.
Today, in Maribor, we have, for example,
I don't know if I can say this,
Tico Pro, which supports companies
when applying for contracts,
but they are not the only ones,
there are others too,
and the company simply does not make the effort
to apply for a contract and receive funds,
sometimes they bring the funds we have at home,
sometimes we have them ready,
sometimes we have them in the form of a cohesion,
sometimes we also have them in the form of an account,
sometimes in the form of a draft
for protection and resistance,
but there is also a huge amount of money at will.
I mean, the companies probably don't apply
because it's an additional job
to prepare all the documentation needed,
and it's also a risk.
Are you going to sign them?
There are others who will pay hundreds
to prepare it for you, right?
Or are you investing in people
who will learn it?
From my own experience,
because I started it before at the faculty,
it really is an investment in people,
but this investment will return to you very quickly.
That means, yes,
a larger Slovenian company,
which has these lines,
but they also have to think about
having project leaders for European companies.
The question is, does it have to be a large company?
I'll tell you from experience.
It's a very demanding job.
It's a very demanding job,
let's put it that way.
But as the minister said,
from my experience,
if I, as a company,
applied for the same job,
I would probably hire a specialist
because there is a gap
between communication.
You're not a specialist.
But I believe that
if you had more human resources
or someone in the company
who would be extremely interested in it,
which is difficult in our IT companies,
it would definitely pay off.
It's not a bauble,
but it's a kind of experience.
I would also ask that.
A lot of people were asking
about the digital strategy.
These are strategies
that will take more years
to become a reality.
The previous strategy was Slovenia 2.20.
I believe that in that strategy
33-50% of the work was done.
A lot of our listeners
are interested
in whether we will survive
the politics
that is inside.
Are we really tied to it?
I don't see much difference
from what we have seen here.
I hope that we will survive
and that we will go
with some corrections.
We also have similar challenges.
Wherever we go to work,
there is a strategy
and we hope that it doesn't change
when things get better.
These strategies are not just
because we wanted to write
a strategy.
Almost all European funds
are dependent on how
the state prepares the documents.
This has nothing to do
with the current local politics.
To prevent what happened
to Digital Slovenia 2.20
to prevent what happened
and to prevent the strategic
and operational group
that will work on it
and will prepare
whether the guidelines are fulfilled
or not.
I don't worry about that.
It's very different.
Don't be afraid.
If you can,
take the document.
It's great.
It has nice graphics
and everything is highlighted.
We will now talk
about the main areas
through a conversation.
I would like to go first.
We will return to
digital strategy
through a conversation.
I would like to go first.
People are asking
people are asking
whether the user experience
in public services
is not good enough.
People are asking
whether there are
some specific problems
that some friends
that you don't like.
How can we constructively
fix this?
We thought
that we should look at
a state-approved
law and a process.
For example,
we should prepare
a beer, pay a beer market
and then what happens
we have a paper form
that we digitalize
so we make the same
document in a nice
HTML form
and then we fill in
everything and click submit.
And now
the question is
do we understand that all citizens
can't
and want to be
able to solve
the problem
digitally with certificates.
That's why we have to think
that there are also old school ways
but I'm interested
if you think that a law
should be more digital first
like in web development
we call it mobile first.
We developed a website
for mobile computers
and now we mainly design for mobile
and then we look back at
how it is on desktop.
Do you think that some steps
or suggestions
should be made
more digital
to make the law more
digital first
so that people
don't have to worry about
the fallback?
We are working on that.
Maybe we started with
digital first
which means
electronic signature
which doesn't mean
that they scan documents
and then send them to us.
Here we are talking about
digitization,
digitalization
and digital transformation.
When it comes to
changing the whole culture
or organization.
Here at the Ministry
we are working on
digital first
because we still have
50% of the population
that doesn't have basic digital skills
and we can't automatically exclude them.
But we are trying
to increase
their advantages
or whatever.
All the laws
that are adopted by the government
of the Republic of Slovenia
are usually based on
inter-resource collaboration
and our Ministry
always offers suggestions
on what should be done
in the field of digital transformation.
When are these suggestions
accepted?
Trust me, we always give them.
Just as you are excited
about the new technologies
we have the same
at the Ministry of Employment.
They are preparing trends
and we also want
what you want in the economy
we also want that in the Public Administration.
Now that we are
at the Ministry of Employment
we can have a glass of water
before we go to the Ministry of Employment.
We are in Maribor
and we will have a glass of water.
We will drink it later.
Aren't you a student here?
No, I was a student.
Phew, if you say so.
Now, we are a bit past
the Ministry of Employment
announcement
about digital transformation.
PR was concluded
but it is definitely
worth accepting.
I love accepting
when I pick up something
on the market.
Plus what technologies
are being used.
I recommend it to all listeners.
In the coming years
there are
ambitious projects ahead of you.
What kind of people are you looking for
and how will you attract them?
We already have 29 quotas
in the field of
digital transformation.
In addition,
at the Directorate for
IT
and also at the Directorate for
Digital Solutions and Tax
Economy, which is the most
hardcore of IT,
a lot of employees
will retire in the coming years.
Here we see
a big problem of how we will
get staff, especially because
in the public sector we have a paid system
and at the moment
in the private sector
the situation is as it is.
But this is not
a challenge only for
our ministry, this is a challenge
for the entire government,
the state if we can say so,
and we also talk about it at the government.
We are looking for
various solutions.
Now, how we will get
these staff, we will
try to impress young people.
Also for interesting
projects, because
it is not always the artists
who encourage you to work.
If it were so, I would never
work in the public sector.
Then
we will also
be able to get as a society
to be able to import
some staff,
because
as a state we have them, but
what do we eat if we have them?
Yes, now
as a person who was
not a governor
for a few years,
these projects
have always been
we are a state,
we all pay
with these taxes a little
and so that we can
use this money
and spend it
in a
logical way to
work on projects.
When we build something new,
it is a project.
But
often in some
information systems,
yes, we can
build it, but information systems
are a living system.
It requires maintenance,
for which we can get a job.
There are also security challenges,
because technology is changing
and every year
the security aspect is
more challenging.
And now
the question is
how to ensure
that these systems will be safe
in the future?
How do we get
a staff for a project,
which is maybe 5 years old,
to be able to maintain it?
In companies we often ask
how we will maintain the staff.
Is it more complicated
because there are projects?
There are not only projects,
because if there were projects,
we would not be able to maintain
the network and take care
of all the security aspects
within the public sector.
So with us, especially
at the Directorate for Informatics,
there is a lot of maintenance,
security, every application.
When it comes to the network,
it must be tested
to avoid problems,
as we mentioned in the past.
On the one hand,
we have regular employees,
on the other hand,
because we do not have to attract them,
we have a number of employers
with whom we cooperate.
In our case,
it is not so much about project work,
but in the area of infrastructure,
if we are talking about monitoring
and data centers,
these are not projects,
we are more concerned
with the employees.
When we were investigating,
you had 20-30 votes
for the secretary.
Undersecretary.
Undersecretary, yes.
I think there was
a certain number of votes,
up to 26-27.
That is because you were
looking at the period
when the drawings for
protection and resistance were opened,
and it is the financing period
of these projects.
But I mentioned earlier
that a lot of employees
are also retired now.
Logically, you can not be employed
more often if you are retired.
No, they should be replaced.
But you probably looked
at the time we gave
for the new project.
Because we saw
the date
26, and we wondered
why would anyone
want to commit,
if they know that
they are paying lower prices
in the industry,
and the projects will lose
these people in the industry
because of these skills.
But of course we did not know
what to do now.
It would be interesting
if we could go
to those attacks
and hacking,
what is happening now.
It is probably a consequence
of these systems
that are attacked
for protection and solution.
These systems are probably
already old.
I will make an assumption.
We probably also have
the problem that, as we said before,
people are retired.
We will probably also be able to
retire some systems and make new ones.
It is true for very different systems.
Different bodies
are responsible for different things.
For example,
URSIL has a special department
for information security.
At the Ministry of Digital Transformation
we have a department for security testing
of applications that we install
inside the Hacom network.
We have great equipment
and great technology
and we did not have
any critical attacks
in this case.
Many times it is also
a human factor.
At the Ministry of Security and Solution
the technology was not problematic
but the human factor was problematic.
It is not that obvious.
Yes, yes.
It is probably the same
challenges as we discussed before.
You also have
people who will be detained.
Logically, you have to upgrade
their knowledge.
They also have to remain digitally written
and they need time.
I certainly understand that.
As part of
this software
we received another question.
This question was
asked by Today.
Do you think
that the software
should be financed
with public money also open-source?
Open-source means
that the user gets
the source code
and the public
is also interested.
Can you give another example?
Yes, for example
a typical school example
is a software
that has
a value of
21%
and we decide to
increase or decrease
it to 20%.
If we are not the owners
of the software
code,
the former user
has a better
access position because
no one can judge
how complicated it is.
Of course, if we have
a super-trivial source code,
it is always easier
to upgrade
or change the source code.
If you are the owner,
you can choose
the source code
and you don't become
an old public orderer.
There are also
good examples of practice.
For example, in a healthy state
the application is open-source.
This is what we had
for the tracking.
This is a good example of practice.
We decided to
put the code on GitHub
because it is open-source.
I am interested in your opinion.
I think that
we should order
a software in public money
so that the state can own it.
Not only do I think about it,
but I also support it.
I am also a state secretary.
If you were aware,
we presented a computer
composition
with a novel law
called MIRO
which is a mechanism
for processing computer equipment.
The software
will be open-source.
This is
an example.
Now the order will also go
to public money.
We also talked a lot about
networking of government organizations
and we are looking for ways
to make it all open-source.
I absolutely support it.
Great.
Let's conclude.
Open-source is this.
It is easier to say more
about the state of health.
I will tell you what the example was.
Now
I will tell you
what the example was.
The German government sent
SAP and Deutsche Telekom
to develop the CoronaWarn app for Germany
as an open-source software.
Deutsche Telekom has prepared
a mobile technology,
stable management
and application management.
SAP was responsible
for the development of the app
and its core platform.
What all the
employees did
was open-source
and published.
Slovenia took the code
and made some modifications
relevant to our space.
This is an example.
This is what we were aiming for.
There are
different variations
of the term
open-source.
I will go into this.
What do we have here?
Yes.
Why are you posing like this?
This is my
home area.
Open-source means
that you get the code as a manual.
There is also a term
open-source, which means
that it is publicly available
to a wider audience.
Lately, this term is fading away.
We think that it is
publicly available.
These are the details.
For me personally,
the most important thing is
that only the ministry
which gave the order
has the code.
I am happy that
we will be able to build a bridge
where the state can
draw a bridge.
Absolutely.
I can not imagine
how it will work.
You will be
bitten by a large snake.
We are all engineers here, but it is clear to us that in Europe and in Slovenia we are good engineers, I believe in it, I think we have a lot of talent, we have a good company, but we don't have that many unicorn companies.
I don't think it is necessary now, but it is nice that there are some players with more capitalization in our region, in Europe and maybe also in Slovenia.
Unicorns are a billion-dollar company. What do you think is the main reason why we don't have more unicorns in Europe?
Again, there are many reasons. One is the fragmentation of the market. If we look at the United States, it is a much bigger market than if we look at China.
On the other hand, in Europe we have very small markets.
The second reason is, as I also had the opportunity to find out how investors function, American investors, if they see a potential opportunity for someone to succeed, invest in this company.
In our country, investment is short-lived, when someone has something to show. And here is the problem.
Another problem is the way we think. In the United States, it doesn't matter if you make a mistake a hundred times, you learned something new from it.
In our country, if you make a mistake, and I'm not just talking about Slovenia, everything is similar in Austria and Germany, if you make a mistake, then it's the end of the story and you don't dare to try again.
And this is already observed in classrooms. I see it in students. We don't go to those iterations. It doesn't matter if you don't succeed for the first time, let's try again.
I'm not that expert on unicorns. I also explain.
You have to hope. We are also recording this podcast. We are doing a lot of things in Czech. I hope we will try.
We also recorded an hour of the podcast without hitting the microphone. That's how it happens.
But now everyone will hit it. We learned something.
Actually, this question about unicorns was a more toned-down question with some additional value added.
We also saw that in your strategy. All our colleagues think that we give a high added value, but this high added value is, in fact, deductible.
We are interested if you think what to do in this space, because we got a lot of questions from entrepreneurs who have more employees.
The problem is that when people do SIN, I don't know, SP, and go to work directly for Tuino, it's a different scene if you have a bunch of employees.
I'm also interested if you are preparing any changes, if you have any plans.
Will this help us make more unicorns?
Back to the question.
I know this question. Everyone knows that it is for the Ministry of Finance and not for the Ministry of Digital Transformation.
We have our opinion and we will share it when we come to the mid-resource assembly.
It's not just about the Ministry of Finance, but it's about the decision-makers.
Why is this question important? I know it's a difficult question.
And I have to answer it politically.
Yes, but why is it important? When we talked about the staff, in the same pool, you catch the staff from the Ministry,
who catches them in the company, and then people make decisions.
In the end, you live on the same card, you put it on the account. That's why this question was important.
Maybe you will also learn from this my way of thinking, as I said before,
that motivation is not always self-paying.
But there are also other mechanisms how you can motivate a person to work somewhere or not.
OK.
You are so fucked up with the next question.
Why are you so fucked up with the next question? Have you already survived it?
No, no, not at all. I don't have such a good memory.
I mean, this next question is more about the neutral Internet.
Again, we got this question from people, because it's a real question.
Maybe you would like to go on the Internet a bit more,
and talk a bit about the toxic environment in which we work.
Maybe you can tell us something about it.
Anyway, we got this question.
We have been using the Internet for about 30 years.
We all want a neutral Internet, which means less surveillance,
we are more anonymous.
Shortly after that, we talked about e-privacy.
We would also like less online bullying, hate speech, and disinformation.
Now, big corporations, which are present in our country,
and people use them through social networks,
give a huge amount of resources, money, and human manpower
to reduce the amount of non-privileged people on the Internet.
As part of this neutral Internet, less information, disinformation,
we are most interested in seeing the role of the state,
and maybe even your ministry, in creating a safe,
acceptable, healthy Internet.
I can only react this way.
E-privacy does not threaten our anonymity.
Due to the fact that there is a certain reputation
that e-privacy will follow us far from it,
nothing changes.
It is just a means of authentication for those
who have a decent view of your data.
Let's just clear that up.
No, no, no, it's clear.
We often meet with this balance between technophobia,
when people are afraid of new things,
and when they lose everything,
and they need to be provided with benefits
provided by technology.
So, that comment is spot on.
Great.
Absolutely.
Our principle is that the Internet can be free,
open, independent.
At the same time, we have a principle that everything
that is illegal in the real world,
can also be illegal on the Internet.
If there is a breach in the Internet,
it is only on the basis of the decision of the court,
for example, when human rights are threatened,
consumer rights, when democracy is threatened,
and so on.
So, there must be an order for legislation.
And that is exactly the role of the Ministry.
To have carefully prepared legislation,
that everything that is illegal in the real world
can also be on the basis of the decision of the court.
At the moment, we are working on the transfer,
or implementation of the Act on Digital Services,
which can be implemented by the end of February 2024,
in our legal order.
Here, of course, these large platforms will also be included.
There will also be a hate speech,
or illegal, and not only illegal,
but also legal, and still harmful,
because there is a difference between them.
What is this Act, can you introduce it a little?
The Act on Digital Services deals with the fact
that everything that is illegal on the Internet
can be in the real world.
It is a European directive,
which all member states must implement
in their legal order.
The key thing is that each member state
will have a so-called national coordinator,
which must be independent.
Regardless of who is in power,
it must be independent.
And it will name so-called data-trusted flaggers.
I will not try to translate it into Slovenian now.
For example, if there is a hate speech,
or disinformation,
then these data-trusted flaggers
will communicate directly
with the Very Large Online Platform,
with 19 member states,
Facebook, Twitter, TikTok, YouTube, and so on.
And they will have to remove these personalities.
So, there will be no need,
for example, I am an old man,
to use hate speech as a punitive action.
And what can I do?
I report it to the police,
the police proceeds with the procedure,
goes to the court,
for example, I have been waiting for about a year,
and when I get it from the court,
the platform can remove this personality.
As soon as we have implemented it,
then I report it to the data-trusted flagger,
the data-trusted flagger goes to the platform,
and the platform must remove this personality.
In other words,
the technical execution of this whole investigation
will then be simplified.
I mean, one of the tasks
that we also see,
as you mentioned, with hate speech,
when we talked on those media,
and I don't know, here in the team,
we have people who are inclusive,
all together,
someone will be able to determine
whether they are bots,
whether they are real in themselves,
or, I don't know,
it seems that people think
that they are really anonymous,
and that they can say anything,
that technology enables them
some degree of anonymity,
but,
would this act somehow help
to de-anonymize, if that makes sense?
Because I see that people write everything
because they think they are anonymous, or what?
Yes, we already have this debate
within the government,
various ministries that deal with this,
we are already looking for
how to implement this question
all over the world, not just in Europe,
New Zealand and Australia
are already working on this area,
and we will try to find
an optimal solution,
because on the one hand,
it seems very simple,
if you register for an electronic personal statement,
you identify yourself, and then you don't have
this anonymity, but on the other hand,
we still don't solve it, and you will have more problems.
And we need to find a way
to protect the freedom of speech,
and at the same time,
to take care of a culture
of behavior and communication
even on social networks.
I mean, whatever,
in this area,
it has certainly come in handy.
I think that
people know too little
about what is happening on these networks,
until they are victims themselves
from various creative beginnings.
Especially among young people, I see that
they are still less aware
of what is happening,
what are the incidents,
and then there are big problems.
And maybe in this spirit,
I would continue this debate
about digital literacy,
because I think
it is somehow connected.
I mean, how to be
digitally literate
in 2023,
or in the future,
somehow that could also be
part of this curriculum,
to be aware,
to have some awareness of what you will hear
in the digital space,
so that these incidents will be there,
maybe forever,
maybe they will disappear,
maybe they will be forever,
but that they also have the characteristics
of the things you hear in the digital space,
can have real-world consequences,
in the real world.
And it seems to me that
from this perspective,
I think we assume
that young people,
because they are young,
automatically digital first,
they are already literate,
they already know the technology.
They are not literate.
That's why I will continue.
And so it is.
If we know how to use phones
and the most popular applications,
maybe that is not enough today.
If we have learned over time,
in our generation,
the word and the calculator
are not enough
for a digitally literate person.
Maybe we can turn
a little differently.
What are some of the skills
that young people could learn,
in your opinion?
Maybe we will be able to learn again,
I hope we will be able to learn
what a computer is,
also the concept of a
file system,
windows like that.
These are some things
that only we could learn,
maybe the younger generation, but not more.
Especially those who grew up with a phone.
Yes, I'm interested.
How are you?
How did you start?
Because we talked about Heatspeak,
and you started digital literacy.
I can continue.
I like it.
I have two daughters and a son.
What skills do you think
would be smart to learn
in the coming years?
How old are they?
Two and eight.
I also have eight sons.
And the best thing
we are dealing with now
is whether it is true or not,
what he sees on YouTube.
So we currently have fake news
and disinformation.
Because there was a time when he was
completely scared that there would be a world war.
Because on YouTube it says
that on October 26,
and we had
a whole mess made up
where we would hide,
and we started to learn
that not everything someone says on YouTube
also holds ideals.
Which beliefs are negligible, which are not negligible.
So that's
where we started.
And with digital literacy,
until now,
when I went to school,
we programmed.
But at that time there were no social networks,
there was no all of that.
Now, digital knowledge
and competence are exactly determined.
Information and additional literacy,
because that also falls,
either it is for fake news
or for disinformation.
Then we have the use of new technologies
for communication
and cooperation.
If we say that young digital writers
are right, how many of them,
how many students always wanted
the whole class to prepare notes
in digital tools.
Because I notice that in our ministry,
almost everyone did not know how to use
documents for joint creation of a document,
which is something else.
The next category here is
the creation of new personalities.
Also what we do today is part of digital literacy.
We don't just talk about PowerPoint,
but you can also shoot something
to present your work.
Then there is
security at the meeting
and solving problems
with new technologies,
which then comes to programming,
artificial intelligence and so on.
Now, depending on the age,
there should not be
a special subject
that we will call
digital literacy or digitization
or whatever, but you are
one of those people who can
get involved in already existing subjects.
Or rather, you have to get involved
in already existing subjects.
There are a lot of questions
that will probably be
on the learning system itself,
how we will prepare the class,
how we will teach the class
and motivate the teachers
to take this time,
a little older.
We also have to
attract teachers
first,
because we think
they will see
what kind of skills
there are in this area.
First, we have to
introduce these technologies to the teachers,
to avoid
technophobia,
because some teachers think
that with new technologies
it will no longer be necessary for them to be present.
Apart from that,
we will need
the best teachers
for new technologies.
And it is also necessary
for faculties where teachers are being educated
to be included in the curriculum,
to know how to work
with these new technologies.
And this will not happen today,
in the morning. And now, on the one hand,
we are also working on the Ministry,
we are performing informal
education and training,
but again, this will not be enough.
It will be necessary to do everything together
even more formally.
Can I ask a purely practical question?
For example,
what happened to you?
You are in a larger organization,
a decision comes from above,
now you will use some XY software.
From tomorrow on,
maybe education, maybe not,
maybe all-relevant education,
and from that time on,
you will use this software,
because we have decided so.
Do you have any advice?
Because experience
and research
says that people
learn from changes.
And people need to
change,
give, pack,
and tell them
why we do it.
And I'm also interested
how you actually
try to sell these changes
to people at the end of the day.
Because if Andra doesn't know
what the advantage of this software is,
he probably won't want to use it.
And you just said
your question.
We can never say
we will do it because I said so,
but we have to say
what the advantage is.
And also with teachers,
we will not use
new software in Python
because he is a minister
or president of the government
or director of the Institute for Education,
but because
students will get such skills
and your work will be more successful,
your work will be easier.
You have to tell people
what's in it for me.
After all, we all come out of it
that we want to get something,
some benefit.
I myself worked on projects for smart education.
And when we
offered new technologies,
the Internet of Things
to farmers,
we didn't say because we want green education
and digital education
for children.
I don't know if there will be costs
because you will know
easier whether it has come to some disease.
We told them
what benefits they will have
from using
new technologies.
No, if it were Deops,
or if it were that tooling monster,
then I would know how much
I have to give money in time.
We will simply
distribute where we can
profit,
so we don't have to look
at the code anymore.
We have two consequences.
One, if we can automate it,
Linter will fix it.
We can ask one more question.
We were talking about
some tools.
What is it now
when we see this commercial breakthrough
of the next generation of artificial intelligence
with large language models,
chat prompts?
It seems that a lot of people
and let's leave those
who are driving,
but a lot of people
have a little
delay, or rather
a technophobia that
this technology can
automate a lot of my work.
If I am satisfied
that we are using it now, then I will be absolutely satisfied.
This means that we will be able
to quickly learn
what to do with this technology,
how to use it.
Or use it.
I would like to hear that.
What do you see in this space?
How will we use it?
We have to be so smart
and use this technology
to help us,
so that we can be even better.
If I, as a researcher,
now this technology helps me
to get here,
it means that I can go from here
forward,
save my time
so that I can work
even better.
Everyone who has used
chat with GPT is currently the best.
Not everything he does is true.
If you know this area,
it can save you
a lot of initial work.
But from here on,
you can see how good or bad you are.
I see this as an additional
tool.
We have to communicate
with each other.
In some way,
we will need some kind of
regulation.
I am aiming for fake videos.
In the EU,
everyone is thinking about it.
Artificial intelligence,
but
personally,
I don't care about technology.
I care about people.
Because I don't trust
people to remember
for what purpose
they will use this technology.
That's why we need regulation.
Through history, we have found
a lot of people who use technology
for other good things.
This is probably
the question of artificial intelligence.
Will it help us
to regulate
these things
so that we won't do...
Yes, on the one hand...
Can it be legalized?
It's very difficult.
Because laws are
very slow
processes.
And it's true.
When you work with laws, you have to think about everything.
On the other hand, we are talking about
technologies that develop extremely fast.
What do we want for regulation?
For regulation, we want
to maximize the benefits.
On the other hand,
to reduce the risks.
Artificial intelligence is a technology
that is developing.
We don't know yet what benefits
it will bring us.
We don't know all the risks.
If we work with laws,
then it's even worse.
Because the process is slow.
What do we need to start talking about?
We have a huge debate
about the United Nations
and about the world of Europe.
They are our news.
We need to start
about ethics by design
in artificial intelligence.
We need to agree
to have a consensus
about the rules we will use
when creating new technologies.
So that we don't come to the point
of regulation.
regulation as we would like it to be.
What I notice globally,
what is happening is that maybe
some countries will regulate less
just because they will come faster to some breakthroughs.
But here we have to ask ourselves what we want.
Because some countries will do that.
Some countries, at the end,
use these technologies, for example,
mostly for monitoring their existence.
Do we want that? I personally do not want that.
Some countries are going exclusively for commercialization
and are probably more successful.
The goal of Europe is still to establish
human rights, consumer rights,
the protection of personal data in advance.
And I personally think that is right.
That is, we all want
that it will be used less,
as we said, face recognition,
connection of some...
We are reducing the possibility of hacking of technology.
Okay.
Now it's going to be hard.
It was the most interesting.
In the last segment, we prepared a few questions
more about you.
We studied your questions first.
We started with the ministry.
And we were like, okay,
you are a minister, you have a great role.
So we said, okay,
we will have more of these fake topics at the end.
Now, in your career, you have done
a lot of research, academic work.
That is, health, smart cities,
socialization, support.
How and why did you jump from
some academic research world
to politics?
When I started working at the Faculty of Electrical Engineering,
I was using a tool,
a psychological tool,
which tells you what your profile is, what it means to you.
And all the psychological tests I took
showed that impact means the most to me.
And where you can make the biggest impact,
if you can look at it that way,
is in politics, in creating real politicians.
And maybe just from that word,
because I was doing everything in the economy,
I started my career in the economy,
a beautiful experience.
And I would also like all colleagues in universities and faculties
to work in a large international field,
because there were different sectors, special development,
special marketing, where I learned that
if you work in the same field, you speak a different language
and you can learn to talk to your colleagues.
Then I worked at a university,
which is again a different world, a research work,
a teaching work, you also make a huge impact,
if you can see it that way.
Then I started working on European projects,
this change, experience, knowledge.
And that's when I first touched on policymaking,
because we talked a lot about policymaking
through Interac Europe,
and I saw what effect you can actually achieve
with that work.
This policymaking,
you mentioned it many times in previous interviews,
what is the main difference between a policymaker
and a politician?
A policymaker doesn't have to be a member of a political party
to establish a policy.
A politician often doesn't deal
so much with establishing a policy,
but with making an agenda.
So you see yourself more as an engineer than a policymaker?
Yes.
Now,
when we were preparing this podcast,
we tried to put together a bunch of questions
that maybe some of you couldn't predict.
Let's say,
Interac or CGPT,
that means they're not copy-pastes
from Digital Slovenia 2030,
because it's a bit different,
because we're not professional journalists.
What are you talking about?
It's a good thing we have,
maybe we had more time as professional journalists
to think about these questions.
Tomorrow we don't have to write new columns.
Now, we were wondering,
OK, we don't have to ask you
questions that would activate
a bunch of Twitter bots,
let's put it that way.
How do you look at this communication
through social media?
For example...
I don't look at the questions I would ask.
It would be like this.
Because someone doesn't like how I write.
Someone would get stuck in what I'm wearing today.
These are people
who don't have anything smart.
I also get e-mails
asking where I came from.
But someone won't like it
and will ask me where I got my Slavic clothes from.
I just let it go.
I don't even choose those comments anymore.
I decided to ignore
the comments of certain journalists.
The worst thing for me
is that you have children.
I don't know how,
but somehow these comments come to my child.
And my child has to think
about what to write about his mother.
That's the worst and the hardest.
Yes.
It feels like a war zone.
That's the word.
Even when we were preparing for this,
we really tried to focus on ourselves.
And now we know
that we will definitely get some messages back.
But we tried to get that personality.
Because it seems important to us.
For everyone.
And we didn't like those parts.
I think we will be able to think strategically.
We will hold on if we want to make breakthroughs.
Yes.
You can also build a filter
so that what is written there
doesn't have a daily state in the real world.
And vice versa.
I would like to talk about
your online presence.
In Grodje we are working
through trial and error.
There are three important segments in Grodje.
First we start with pre-preparation.
Who will host?
Then we have recording.
Post-production and everything else.
And the third part
where we need to pack the personality
and give it a nice picture
and sell it to our audience.
So that they can consume it.
All those parts are extremely important.
And if we do all the production
and marketing
and if we don't pack the personality
and if we don't work on it
and if we will do it and if we did it
then it's too soon to say goodbye.
We have learned that it's very important
to tell people what you do
and communicate with them.
And my question is
how do you balance that focus?
Because if you don't tell people what you do
then they won't know.
I agree.
And it's often in this problem
because we already have a lot in Slovenia.
We already exist in Slovenia.
But people don't know that it exists.
Even in our ministry
where all digital content is free
and everyone can use it.
And we are looking for new ways
how to present it to people.
You have a similar problem
of seeking attention
because you need to tell people
what you do.
You need to get people's attention
so that they will know about it.
So that it doesn't look like propaganda.
That was one of the questions
or the guidelines for this episode.
I hope there won't be another PR.
I hope we managed to break it
and get to the last important questions.
These are short ones.
These are a bunch of short questions.
We said that this is not purely PR.
What would two engineers ask you
if you weren't a journalist?
Which operating system do you like
the most for daily use?
That's a typical question.
I can say that I use MacOS and Windows
every day.
Which is your favorite
programming language and tool?
That's a common question.
You can probably answer it yourself.
It's not necessary.
Why do I like Java the most?
It was the first solution
that I programmed
and that went into production
and then came to life.
I was working on GSMR
and it was programmed in Java.
Maybe it was the beginning of my career
and the first product that came to life.
Which framework would you use in Grodno?
No!
Those were the electrical ones.
That's just the protocol.
It has to be on GUMP.
That's a question that you love.
That's a daily tool.
I mean a tool.
No, that's a daily tool.
I wrote that down.
Are you interested in playing video games?
Have you ever played?
What's your opinion on that?
I'll start again.
Right now I play FIFA
and we have it at home
until 2015 and every year later.
I can't play it at home yet
but I think it's the best.
Two or three controllers
and let's go.
We had a question about NK Maribor
and then we moved on.
Which is the best football club?
Itak.
Itak is a champion.
It's a celebration from the last season.
We moved on to the end.
I would like to thank you
for your speech.
If you want to name the audience
for the last thought before we move on.
Maybe I would say
that the day before I became a minister
I didn't think about what they do
at the ministry.
Now, when you look at it from the inside
you see that you have done something.
When do they have a problem with marketing?
When do they have a problem with various trusts
that they are trying to solve?
Maybe a little more patience
and a little more constructiveness would not hurt.
Thank you.
I would like to thank all the listeners
and viewers.
I would also like to thank all the supporters
on Patreon.
Thank you for being with us and listening to us.
Thank you to all the team for your effort.
Thank you both for your time.
Good luck.
Thank you.