Ok, at the beginning it's a bit awkward, because at the beginning there has to be silence so that Dejan can pick up the sounds of the ambience,
and at the end there has to be silence so that it can properly give sound.
But today, unlike last year when we were at the Interprofessional Board in Celje,
today we are in our co-working slash hackerspace.
So it's a bit more soft.
I totally miss most of those intros, so I'm talking about completely irrelevant things.
But yeah, now that the jingle has run out, it's time to introduce the guest.
My name is Maja Voje, hello.
Long time no see, thank you for inviting me. I've been waiting for this for two years.
Now, I've been waiting, I said two years, now it's time for you to come to Belgrade.
But yeah, a lot of our ideas have to mature somehow, they have to come to a point where we are all somehow for that action,
and now I'm ready for you to write your book, and now you just need to publish it.
In thirty days.
And I know it's quite a big project for you, and now I think it's time for us to welcome you.
Now, that's that part, why, okay.
Now, when I wrote that Maja Voje would come to Belgrade, I also got a question from our audience,
why, what does it have to do with Belgrade?
You have programming here, and you have some hardcore programmers.
What does Maja Voje have to do with what you do?
Now, I'll just step back a bit, and I'll tell you what we're trying to achieve in Belgrade,
so that this question is answered a bit.
So, in Belgrade, we have two separate groups, one of them is deep tech,
deep topics in programming, technology, and development.
And then, on the other side, we're trying to create two separate groups,
which are topics that are connected to the fact that you can do deep tech.
And that's what we have inside, from entrepreneurship, marketing, sales, to housing in Slovenia,
to UX design, and so on.
And these things have to work together, they have to work together,
and that's why I think we absolutely can't do it without talking about the topics that are close to you,
that you represent.
Okay, that's my intro.
No, no, thank you very much.
You know, I've also been working with programmers for 10 years, I have impostor syndrome.
But I've been working in the technology industry for a long time,
and if you don't know how to program, they give you a degree in OECM,
a little bit of HR, a little bit of accounting,
in fact, you also bake pancakes on Fridays.
So, you know, I've never really felt that I really belong inside.
And also, you know, we're in the group Growth Hacking Slovenia,
which also has programmers inside.
But I have a crazy fear at times, because I know that you are the most critical thinkers,
and that you see bullshit all over you.
And so, most of the tech economists are like a horde of golden carriers.
It's like, we see something, we get excited, we go, and there's no panic.
And so, to be honest, I see a very good barrier if we participate.
Because I've also done a lot of research for the book Go-to-Market Strategies,
and, for example, marketing people didn't understand those books at all.
Most of them.
And e-commerce people even less.
I mean, there was a technical founder, product managers,
and those who were already established.
And sometimes, you know, when we work, for example, on a freelance job,
when we already have 130 people who have helped us open businesses,
I would almost say that programmers are the easiest,
not the easiest because, I don't know, it would underestimate how hard it is to do it,
but here the challenge is very big.
And if you learn a little bit about business, but it's so little,
I mean, if I could learn programming,
it would be almost ten times longer process,
because you will learn a little bit about business.
And yes, I think in all these years, I hope we will be able to tell you
in such a transparent and understandable way,
if not, then you will correct me.
I am...
Well, we might come back to this later,
but I also did a test,
and I asked five colleagues, good programmers,
who Maja Vojana is.
No, I'm kidding, because nothing would happen to me.
Nothing would happen to me.
No, but they are very interesting speakers.
For example, out of five, four knew that you exist.
That's good.
That's very good.
That's great.
Without a YouTube voice, great.
It seems to me that marketing and sales
are also full of people who understand what you do,
and a lot of people have the same...
Eh, this is some kind of marketing, and then they decide.
Full version, yes.
Yes, and there is a lot of that.
Now, we can go back to where we started.
In the beginning, programmers and people who work with this technology
solve problems on some basis.
There is a very different range of problems.
Most of the examples, after we come to today's lecture,
we go to the fact that people solve themselves.
But when it comes to marketing and sales,
I think you can work with a lot of people,
and you can have a lot of human touch.
And these are not always the same people who have the same traits,
who are interested in the same things.
What do you think about that?
No, fair.
I would say, as a common denominator,
I met everyone who said, we solve problems.
When it comes to marketing and sales,
we also think that we solve problems,
but the difference is that maybe we come from a different prism.
And here I am, working with the Swiss e-commerce company,
with technical founders, and in all Balkan countries,
because the state of Switzerland sponsors it, thanks to Switzerland,
the difference is that we have an exceptional technical talent here.
And then you ask yourself, purely pragmatically,
will the next time I come from Slovenia,
I don't know, some dropshipper,
some kind of wannabe Chinese bitch,
no, no, it won't be.
Yes, it will, it's such a nice exit for the founder,
but the added value of it is limited to the optimization
of the lifestyle of some people,
except if they go to SAS later.
And here I saw such a bias,
when it comes to the environment,
exactly what you said, it touches people, right?
What is most natural for me?
For example, let's solve such a problem,
let's do a mental experiment.
How would you get 100 users,
and how would I get 100 users for my product?
How would you get them?
Now that we have a podcast.
Yes, for example, it's easy,
but let's say we have a new solution,
which you have here in the laboratory,
how would you get your first 100 users?
I'm probably not the most...
Well, you know, how would you do it?
I'm probably not the most intelligent,
I'm usually a little biased,
because I'm not the best example of that.
You're really biased.
Yes, but I'm currently on LinkedIn,
for example, the biggest profile,
there I have the most friends, followers,
shit, I won't cut it with me,
but they are my close friends.
You already have 6,000, right? 6,000.
Yes, and there I have a big following,
so I would probably post the easiest on LinkedIn.
The second part is probably...
I would probably develop this podcast
in an interesting way,
or, I don't know, on some online community.
That would probably be a no-brainer,
and the most valuable.
You can also refer to this podcast,
in fact, that's exactly our marketing,
especially market strategy, if you want.
Yes.
And in fact,
we built our podcast to that point
without throwing money into advertising.
Not really,
but without buying ads.
Everything we built,
we built organically
and without any ads.
Now, how do we finance this?
Again, another question,
but today we convinced people
to listen from the beginning.
In the first episode,
maybe it wasn't smart to listen at all,
but today, this personal network
was the easiest to activate.
Now, at some point,
if I remember correctly,
we also decided that
we don't care if this podcast
would be listened by millions of people,
but we want to know
what is the maximum size
that we can reach in this space.
We said that this is our strategy,
that we will be present in this technological space
and that we will try to do the most inside.
We are aware of this,
that's why we are targeting and moving inside.
We also have stickers in the garden,
and we also sent them by mail to the fans.
This helps us a lot.
Of course, people who work on your product
also work on other people's products,
so this part also works.
Now I don't know if this fits more into marketing
or sales, but it will.
I'm giving you a second year of economics
to get things in order,
because you're already doing some things
very, very, very, very well.
But if I look at the technical partners
I work with,
they want to get in touch with people
at all costs.
They won't do interviews,
they will start sales,
so they won't go to their...
Is this a myth or is it true?
What?
No, it's true.
Oh my God, oh my God.
What if it's offloaded?
No, sorry.
Look, people have been paying me
for my mentoring job
so that we can write emails together.
Because it's weird for them to write emails.
And look, this week,
tomorrow is my day,
which is for Y Combinator,
and we're holding on to them.
But the question we have to solve
is how to get 500 applications for Beto.
And they ran some LinkedIn
and did some outreach campaigns
and such things.
And I think,
my assumption is that
a typical technical founder
is afraid of contact with people,
while contact with people is the easiest.
Because what would I do?
For the first 100 users,
I would send an email,
hello, I did something new,
you know, on the split page,
and see if you're interested.
Before that,
I would test my stuff
for 200 people for feedback.
You also participate in my research,
I don't know if you know that,
but you're my favorite tester,
because you know how to think critically.
And so, you know,
I'm always good at looking at things
through the prism of what is mission critical.
So what do I want to do now?
What does mission critical mean?
Mission critical means
you have a goal,
and what will drive you to your goal,
because then you can think like a horse.
And what is the best horse harness?
These are Russian horses.
They have to be at 80%,
but they have to see the nature itself.
So in any case,
you know,
the amount of ballast
that you remove from your life
to go against the natural lines,
with a goal,
that's crazy
when you have such a very aggressive goal.
And for example,
those 500 founders,
and also the two of us with Tim,
as we said at the beginning of the year,
we both want to reach 100 followers this year.
Let's go, let's go, let's go.
And I'm not interested in anything else,
but how can we get 100 followers
to live a better life.
And that's for me,
I think it's a little bit of ADHD,
but that's how I live.
I function the best when you give me a goal,
and when we go to that goal,
because it helps me decide.
How do you choose a goal?
I make it up.
I don't know,
but sometimes you have to calculate something,
but you give it.
Because,
thank you so much for asking me this,
for the goal.
Here we have another problem,
everyone in Slovenia and in the region,
we underestimate our work.
And that's because they sell consulting,
and stories,
and also in the product part.
Here, Simon Belak always told me,
raise, raise, double,
maybe add another zero.
But the fact is,
you know,
because of the sociocultural heritage,
we come out of a kind of prism,
is it okay that I deserve more
than my mother?
Is it okay,
I mean,
speaking in cash,
is it okay that I know
that if I used to work for 5 euros,
now I have about 10 euros a month.
And in terms of pricing,
and in terms of consulting,
we are really the most weird in the world.
No,
we still have it,
it's a real problem,
but.
It's a little wrong for us to sell,
if we go back to those 100 and 100 users,
it's wrong for us to sell
to those 100 users,
some part.
Yes,
and you feel fully responsible
when you sell it.
Because,
especially in such products,
you know,
they affect human life.
For example,
even if you work,
I don't know,
what kind of health technology,
and so on.
I,
now,
really,
when I get a support mail,
and I ask it,
I'm going to look at LinkedIn,
I'm going to talk,
and I'm going to put it in touch
with some other source,
which is close to a similar profile,
because I feel,
in fact,
such a huge responsibility,
right?
And then,
in fact,
your ethical or moral responsibility
of which products
you will then push forward,
right?
Also,
probably for your podcast,
you know exactly,
look,
you took the conditions
with which you do well,
and now,
I'm not going to name
one company,
I'm going to name my
growth lab,
to sponsor your podcast,
so that you would have
such a mission critical,
GTM strategies,
so that you would have
that thing,
mission critical.
I mean,
that appears to me,
interesting problems
appear to us,
right?
Yes.
Because,
there are companies
with which you want
to somehow connect,
and you ask them,
and then,
then you have
such a company,
when you think,
oh,
how can I write
a book,
how can I
have such a friendly
kiss?
And you heard stories,
right?
I mean,
there are people
you trust.
Yes,
and it's not
that bad,
simply.
I mean,
look,
now that you've
published a book,
it will be forever
on the internet.
Yes,
OK,
now we're warmed up.
Now we're really
full of topics here.
Yes.
So,
before we listen to
that GTM strategy,
let's go back
to the topic.
For you,
it's now
3.5 years,
I looked,
3 years and 5 months.
Thank you.
Since you started
releasing in your
first episode
of the podcast
Renaissance,
with that
great
French
Chanson.
Chanson,
yes.
And,
you really had,
That French
Chanson.
You really had
an exceptional
palette
of guests.
Today,
this morning,
I listened to one
with Rok Hrastnik.
But,
you're the one
who went to the show.
You're the one
who went to the show,
not the guest.
Well,
look,
I want to say
that I listened
to a few of them,
that you really
contributed a lot
to the marketing,
sales,
space,
and also
wider.
And then,
you have
a huge frequency,
a really
big frequency,
that we have,
for example,
when we,
when you have
a lot of
guests.
I'll talk about
the meeting,
when we have it
in Grodno.
Really,
congratulations
for this achievement.
Hey,
I thank you so much,
because,
you know,
here again,
Impostor Syndrome
strikes me out,
because you are
one of the smartest
people I know.
Yes,
good,
Simon Bilak.
Okay,
okay,
okay.
No,
but,
you know,
as far as I'm concerned,
we did
not spend
four years
on economic
development,
not like
marketing,
business,
let's go,
but that we
were able to
slowly,
move forward.
And we're trying
to do that,
I think,
in a group
called
Growth Hacking,
because I really
really believe
in cooperation,
I believe in
critical thinking,
and if I
told you
what episode
I didn't
watch,
you would
say,
oh,
represent
the market
share,
make the
competitor bubbles
different in
size according
to their market
share.
And that
wasn't
fun.
I stopped
recording
and then
like,
let's change
one more
episode,
let's prepare
something,
so that
this episode
will work
organically.
I'm sorry
that someone
has to write
ten pages,
it's too much
for me.
Could you
send the
questions forward?
I always
send the
questions forward,
because I
mostly worked
with people
who are not
so well-trained
in the media,
and then you
get someone
who is
the first
person
with a microphone,
and I
told
young women
that the
best thing
about being
a woman
is that
I'm not
afraid
of being
filmed.
I'm not
afraid of
being filmed.
It's
not a
big deal,
but I
don't
mind if
I'm filmed
or not.
I
don't
mind
if I'm
filmed.
I
don't
mind
if I'm
filmed.
I
don't
mind
if I'm
filmed.
I
don't
mind
if
I'm
filmed
or not.
When
it comes
to
the
topic,
I
don't
mind
if I'm
filmed.
I
can't
decide
what
the
topic
is.
I
don't
mind
if
I'm
filmed.
I
don't
mind
if
I'm
filmed.
I
can't
decide
what
the
topic
is.
I
don't
mind
if I'm
filmed.
I
don't
mind
if I'm
filmed.
I
don't
mind
if I'm
filmed.
I
don't
mind
if I'm
filmed.
riverside
podcast
that
I
made
more than
20 episodes.
I
don't
mind
if I'm
filmed.
I
don't
mind
if I'm
filmed.
I
don't
mind
if I'm
filmed.
OK.
Yeah,
I
don't
mind
if I'm
filmed.
I
don't
mind
if I'm
filmed.
Yeah,
I
don't
mind
if I'm
filmed.
don't
mind
if I'm
filmed.
Yeah,
I
don't
mind
if I'm
filmed.
I
don't
mind
if I'm
filmed.
I
don't
mind
if I'm
filmed.
I
don't
mind
if
I'm
filmed.
I
don't
mind
if I'm
filmed.
Yeah,
I
don't
mind
if I'm
filmed.
Because
this
fixed
setting
doesn't
take
into
consideration
how
our
WordPress
site
is.
Super
technological
challenge.
Super
technological
challenge.
I
don't
mind
if I'm
filmed.
But
the team
we
talked
to
might
not
have
as
serious
technical
problems.
And
then you
have
to
take
it
into
consideration
and
then
you
get
to
the
next
stage.
So
I
don't
mind
if
I'm
filmed.
But
I
don't
mind
if I'm
filmed.
I
don't
mind
if I'm
filmed.
I
don't
mind
if I'm
filmed.
I
don't
mind
if I'm
filmed.
I
don't
mind
if I'm
filmed.
And
so
you
are
supposed
to
be
that
in
the
same
place.
And
I
don't
mind
if
I'm
filmed.
I
don't
mind
if I'm
filmed.
And
so
you
are
supposed
to
be
that
in
the
same
place.
And
I
don't
mind
if
I'm
filmed.
And
so
you
are
supposed
to
be
that
in
the
same
place.
And
so
you
are
supposed
to
be
that
in
the
same
place.
And
so
you
are
supposed
to
be
that
in
the
same
place.
And
so
you
are
supposed
to
be
that
in
the
same
place.
And
so
you
are
supposed
to
be
that
in
the
same
place.
And
so
you
are
supposed
to
be
that
in
the
same
place.
And
so
you
are
supposed
to
be
that
in
the
same
place.
And
so
you
are
supposed
to
be
that
in
the
same
place.
And
so
you
are
supposed
to
be
that
in
to produce more content, not so much attention in the zone, so that people can eat it all.
Does that make sense?
In a total sense, and it can also be related to who you serve, right?
For example, most of these people, sorry, I said on Instagram, and that's not easy,
I mean, Darwin, a critical thinker, that's not easy.
You put it up there and then it's like, wow, you look good today.
It's a different audience.
And I understand that your audience has higher criteria.
I also, for example, when I work with Ben Williams from SNIK,
and here with Boss, with Wes Bush, I also put more effort into it.
And I'm also 30 years old when I talk about intros.
But I think it's a bit of a problem for the local environment.
I took it totally easy because it could have been fun for me.
That was the primary agenda.
And here, I fully respect what you did.
I wouldn't have been able to do that.
What did we do?
Sorry, what did you do with the team?
I'm talking to myself now, it's a bit messy, I'm adjusting.
But I don't know if she would be prepared to put so much will and so much discipline into such a project.
I didn't see it that way.
Because R.O.I. said it openly in the Slovenian podcast I had.
I had maybe 20 sponsors, I don't know if, I would say 15.
So that was one such thing.
I did more for people who were my guests.
I know what kind of business they started out of it.
I always saw it as a platform.
Because you give a person who ultimately is not well-known, but is good.
Of course, like Hrastnik, who is well-known and good.
But I always saw it as a jumping board for someone's career.
And if I could help someone, I don't know, for a business, for 10-20K,
if I could get some new pages out of it.
That was top for me. That was amazing for me.
To talk to a new generation of people.
I think the most I got from the podcast is talent.
New members of the community.
Because I think both of you have communities on Facebook.
And the younger generation doesn't want to be on Facebook.
And many of them use Facebook just because of our groups.
We've probably heard that too, haven't we?
Yes.
But, yes, added value.
Look, I don't know.
Why did I let them do it?
Because I wanted to make an impact,
spread it through the English language.
And somehow, after three and a half years,
it wasn't a challenge anymore.
I didn't want to go pro, like Otto and the team.
It should have been more.
But, no, I mean,
for the book, I wrote in English.
Why? Because, look,
I have two million people here in Slovenia,
I love my language,
I love my people,
I will always help them, I will always mentor them,
I will always work in the community.
It's a little selfish for me,
but if you do so much research,
and if you produce such a level of knowledge,
like I did last year,
and then I said a thousand things no,
and then I wrote,
and did five interviews,
and did science,
so that I could then position
this healthy biography, I don't know,
of Franz Josef,
I don't name anyone else.
They washed a lot of news for us,
but OK, we'll start with that.
That's how they are.
As long as we're normal.
When we were at the beginning of our podcast,
I think we talked
in Ljubljana,
and I think
at that time
there was
some kind of
duet about it.
I'm always a duet,
everything else is overthinking.
Duet, and you gave me
a lot of your
direct experience,
and readings,
and at the end
when you concluded
the story,
you also published readings.
I think that was the best episode,
it had about 4,100 listeners
on the podcast system,
plus probably even more,
because they are only from one platform.
But that's a very nice
reading in this market
for such a podcast.
Congratulations on that.
Thank you, anyway.
You were on the list of the best podcasts.
Did you ever
fall into
releasing and then
watching those readings?
Because the rest of the work,
we'll talk about it later,
those metrics, analytics,
statistics,
it seems to me that in the first few hours
you can already see if something is wrong,
if it's flying, if it's not going to fly.
I just said I won't watch it,
it doesn't matter.
Input-output metrics.
That's a very important thing for me,
also on LinkedIn, when we talk,
and I get a lot of comments
on private messages,
why is this post so good,
why does it only have 200 hits,
and what other problems.
I always remember their business model.
And I have an ironic story
about how you earn 10 euros a month.
Are you interested?
You have two pages when they pay you,
and 5 euros, you have 100 pages
when they pay you, 100 euros.
So now the question is,
where do you want to play the game?
Do you want to have a low price,
and then full volume,
and you will go to the same figure,
or will you worry that your message
will come from two of those people
who need to be heard?
When we do demand generation,
that's what I call generating questions,
we all move forward
in the general phase,
before someone contacts us
and needs something.
We somehow imagine it,
or form it,
I won't say program it,
so that our message is delivered.
And here,
the key question
is one of the first principles,
where do you want to play the game?
Because if you want
to get two new pages,
you don't have to do LinkedIn posts every day
and post on Twitter,
you don't have to.
You have to go to an event,
to meet a shopper,
or a company manager,
tell them that you are a programmer,
and then tell them that
you would like to have a meeting with them.
I analyze it a bit more,
but that's how business works.
Or you are a friend with a friend,
or with me,
or with Jure uhalov,
and you show that you know how to work.
People ask us,
do you know who this Slovenian player
is in love with?
I think that if you are in the vicinity of the epicenter,
you will get a lot of business out of it.
What I want to tell you with that,
yes, you come late,
you update if there are comments,
but then you snap your fingers
and say, no, Maja it,
these are one of those metrics.
These are metrics that in your business
have no final result.
Yes, everything sounds great on paper,
but in a real episode,
an influencer with 30k followers
would cry.
Do I want to do that?
Do I really want to do that?
Is that the intelligence of the people
and intellectual talent
that I can reach?
Sorry, but if we go to a reality show?
Yes.
Would you go?
Reality show.
Where would you go?
To watch a reality show.
I can't watch a reality show.
How about you? You are more data-driven,
you work a lot for analytics.
How do you feel about it?
Actually,
I realized that
it is easier
to communicate with the team
if you say
this episode has
such a volume
versus that one.
That's much better and in a way
I can see the connection.
If you get to the point
when you say we need
new microphones,
we need a new supporter,
it is easier if you have some
devices to operate with
as much as you can.
Also to see
if the product is growing or not,
if it is stagnating,
that is also important.
So, yes,
as I said before,
you start watching those devices
and you can also
have some
more
different topics.
How can a programmer earn
10k a month?
You go to a Slovenian developer
and you have 5k views.
Well, no.
Because it is not your value.
We made
an episode
in Grodno, which I called
Tagon.
They are for juniors,
for beginners,
not only for young people,
but for anyone who wants to learn
to program, because we saw
that there is a lot of potential
for growth in this segment,
that there are a lot of questions
about themselves,
because for young people
local topics are not so much,
and there is a lot of opportunity.
It is true, as my colleague
said, the title we gave
is Money Printing Title, and maybe
that's why people think
that becoming a programmer is
a money printing career.
Not far from it, but people
have it many times.
So, our episodes,
for example,
we made them for beginners,
they are much better than others,
and I think it is also true
that we made them not only for
everyone, but also for
our community.
What do you mean?
You know, as you said,
when I started thinking about
how you motivate your team,
I mean, here at GTM Strategist
I have eight people who work
from three different countries,
and my first thing I do on Saturday
is to see how many emails
we have on the waitlist,
to see how much has been reached on LinkedIn,
and where new supporters
have supported us internationally.
And that's great,
because when you need to motivate your team,
you have to be a role model.
Again,
I'm a leadership douchebag.
I'm like, let's go,
mission critical, ninja, let's go.
I hear you're a general.
Yes,
that's what they called me.
But what is very important to me,
psychological safety is very important
for this new generation,
and I can work from 4 a.m. to 8 p.m.,
but I'm afraid
I won't be able to do it
if it's not my company.
So you can still
put a lot of pressure on yourself.
But what you said,
that you have a feedback loop,
that you can improve,
I think the only difference
in the way you talk,
is that in my podcast
I never really talk.
That was my side project,
I've been doing it for two hours.
You put a lot of pressure
on your mindset,
and then you don't have it.
You don't have it?
Yes.
The goal was to get to know
a lot of people,
share knowledge,
and ask questions,
which was very challenging for me.
And it somehow happened.
When I saw your strategy,
I was like,
Maja, you from business school,
but it was very, very, very
strategically planned.
It was also interesting
when Matej showed me your Discord.
I've never been to your Discord,
but then I saw
the comments,
it's a very powerful community.
It's a great way
to engage with people.
And I don't think people in Facebook groups
will ever achieve that.
So if you want to make people younger,
you have to shift the platform.
We're at 40 minutes now.
No, no, you're drinking red wine.
I'm drinking red wine.
Antioxidants.
Maybe later
we'll...
Again, promise to come to the book.
We have to come to the book.
We have to come to the book,
because it's up to date for your listeners.
I think everyone gets value
because
we have supporters
who,
in your podcast,
you haven't done before,
but we made a Patreon.
That's something
we have.
Patreon is,
I have to say what it is,
because I wanted someone to say it.
I understand, because arjala has been
doing it for a long time.
I chose it
because
maybe it's too much
and I don't know why.
We're not that big to make it significant.
But Patreon
is a platform where
you can
choose a monthly
donation
with the creator
and in exchange
for that donation
you get premium access,
merch, colors,
pictures, whatever.
Mentoring with Otto.
That's not what we're doing.
BB, BB, BB.
No, but we divided,
we made four
packages.
The smallest, I think, is
3 euros per month.
The most expensive, I think, is 40.
And we have some supporters
who help
to finance an episode.
For example,
the episode we're doing now
will get pictures,
a week later they'll see the episode,
listen to it, write it down.
We tried to make a clip
of ourselves with them,
so we knew what our strategy
would be,
and how to lie to them.
I was very happy and
it wasn't intuitive
to do it,
but it turned out
to be very welcome.
They helped us a lot.
Thank you to all Patreons for that.
You probably financed it all by yourself.
What is it?
Look, Otto, again, it's like a dream for me.
No, no,
you think I have a strategy
and a plan,
but I'm doing something
that I'm interested in doing.
In my opinion,
the funniest thing
when I go to a club,
in 90% of cases,
they write back,
what a great energy!
And I'm like, what the fuck is energy?
What does that mean?
I put some crystals on it.
Do not cringe me,
I'm not a joker, okay?
Then I realized that energy
means a passion for business.
Maybe because I feel
certain things,
but I'm also excited
to do business.
And you know,
it's all a game to me.
I'm like, can I sell today
for three hours of tea?
Can I get 500 supporters?
Can I do that?
That's why I'm so funny.
Because I'm such a positive person
that I go and get involved
in this goal and find a way
to do it.
And I did it.
There were a few more sports,
but those people who are
interested in the military
or some other disciplines,
it really, really, really attracts.
Why? Because I think
that we are like a society,
we have already fallen into such a melancholy
that nothing is possible.
In my opinion, everything is possible.
I would like to work with your friend.
Come, I'm sitting here on the podcast.
Would you be nice
if I fucked first?
I'm the newest person in the world
and I wrote to you 14 times
before you wrote to me.
No, I would just say that
you didn't just write to me,
you also sent me a nice message.
I sent a voice message.
I must admit that my fans
were contemplating
why I would get such a nice message.
And then, you know,
I'm just saying,
it's marketing today.
No, I just wanted your respect.
No, I respect you,
from the posts you have,
you do it well,
and I just wanted one-on-one
over you.
So this game is not
an endgame.
I am very honored to sit here,
to talk, but I am again
very, very, very, very, very
honored in life.
I think it is important for us
to build a relationship.
Let's get out of this
Oh yeah.
Communities.
I will now...
Fuck, I'm doing this intro now.
In Grodje, we somehow
came up with
two components.
One is the community,
the other is the media
that gives content.
And also the Discord,
which you mentioned before,
is part of it.
I somehow invite people
to come to Grodje,
to join the Discord,
to get some hints
on what the next topics will be,
to give us feedback,
to be in contact
with us,
so that you don't lie
to yourself,
you know, for whom you lie,
or how you lie to the person,
or how you lie to the audience.
Let me tell you a public secret.
What kind of business do you do together?
Are you talking about rap?
What kind of business do you have?
Oh, how can I answer that now?
Has it already happened, or not?
I mean,
I don't have to now,
because they're not here,
but yeah, I mean,
almost everyone got it because of that job,
absolutely.
It has nothing to do with the relationship, right?
Yeah, and also because
directly in the team,
or later, absolutely, yeah.
Well, at the end of the day,
people are doing business,
people are doing business with people,
and since a powerful community
exists,
I mean, the relationships are
more powerful,
more connected, it's easier to work, right?
So I think that
maybe only the listeners
don't engage with that community,
don't pay attention to it, but absolutely
there is a very powerful community.
Also last summer,
for example, we also went
to help out
at
meetups, for example,
and at some conferences,
because
either we were already selling there,
or people are now paying attention
to having a really good meetup,
and they don't have that
marketing machinery, I guess.
And then we invited people,
and now we tried a few times
to say, okay, this is that conference,
we'll be there,
we'll be a community sponsor,
we'll invite some people,
and you'll give us, I don't know, a guest speech,
and then we're all happy, right?
So that also works, for example.
But if I go back to the community,
now, we have our own community,
it's still small, it's growing,
but... How many channels do you have?
On Discord it's around 300 people.
But that's not a small community,
I'm not a small community,
I'm my own Facebook chat.
No, but the other community
that we both hold,
Growth Hacking Slovenia,
has around 9000 people.
Or 13, right?
Slovenian is around 15.
Oh, you're fast.
But, I have to admit,
that
what you mentioned before,
among the groups,
I notice that the platforms
for those communities
are also quite unique.
No shit.
If you go to Facebook at night,
they have more Facebook, right?
And now, if we say 10,000,
or 15,000,
or whatever those numbers are on Facebook,
now people think, oh, shit,
there are 15,000 people,
I'll post for a job, or for an event,
10,000 people will see,
that's great.
If I write a copy and a picture,
God forbid I post a video,
it'll be even worse.
And culture, too.
Thank you for mentioning it,
because I also have a
freelance group,
Growth Hacking Slovenia,
because there's more intimacy.
You have to be careful,
what you post,
but we have to stick to the rules,
because otherwise, the energy is lost,
and it turns into a mess.
And thank you, too,
when you post something,
and spoil our admin job,
I hope we thank you enough for that.
No, because once and for all,
it's like in passive training.
Okay, I have a dog, you have children,
so you can comment from a different perspective.
I was in a passive group.
Once and for all,
they're looking for me,
and if you let one down,
then you don't have any more precedent
that you're used to it.
And sorry, I'm sorry,
I didn't have much interest
to read something,
but I was in a group of people
who are profitable,
and would sell it for 4 euros.
I think that's not something
I would like to do in my free time.
Speaking of those intimate communities,
I would like to ask you
what do you think is the key
to a successful group?
I think you need,
in an organization,
maybe someone
who is a little more
experienced,
a little more visible,
and a little more clear,
I don't know,
to push some new content,
to generate content,
to make content,
but is more visible.
Then I think
you also need someone
who will want content
that is not in line
with those rules.
And you need both.
You also need people
who...
Now,
people in the flesh,
and I think you need
to be fully consistent
with those rules.
Once you see it,
without missing a beat.
If I go to Slovenian developers,
there was a big push,
let's change this rule,
let's add that rule,
let's add the third rule,
and it seems to me that
I don't know how we will enforce
that rule, but you,
Miha Medven...
Miha, we like you.
He took
some more time
to clean it up.
But now,
I think that
this community exists for some time,
people have children,
I didn't have a couple of admins
with Slovenian developers
who let me use Facebook,
so the generation is changing.
I don't know,
you need a mix.
Now,
I personally,
the only reason I still have Facebook
is this group.
What do you think?
A couple of years ago,
I was faced with this question.
Do I delete Facebook,
and that's it?
Or should I try
to push the Slovenian development
forward a little bit,
and maybe do something more?
And then we had
this, now it's a different time,
this show that you know,
and we let people
show it.
what they are doing, and some interesting things happened there.
Miha is also full of those post-matches where you call people to ask stupid questions.
Watch me.
Yeah, right.
So...
Those are some kind of experiments, but...
I don't know, it seems to me that...
Artful engagement, yeah.
I think everyone engages, and they are there.
It's still the biggest tech community on the web in Slovenia,
and it pays off to be a good citizen.
I also think that if you are a fool in there,
your boss, your partner, your professor, your teacher, whatever, your colleague,
and people are often not aware of that, but still,
it's such a big community that not everyone can see it.
So it pays off to take it all in.
I know it's toxic sometimes, and I have my problems.
I once had an anxiety attack when I logged in, yeah.
I know it can be very unpleasant,
but I still think you have to admit that...
I think a lot of people today are consumers of those media
without total engagement.
They just watch it, and they won't press like, comment, nothing.
And that's it.
I think that's also happening.
So people will see it, but they don't have to know.
No, I'm so glad you're talking about it,
because I have a hypothesis that every community
goes through three different phases, development phases.
The first phase is you, and then your uphill battle.
Like you're climbing a mountain,
and then you ask your friends if they want to engage with you,
and then you get to the top, and that's it.
And when you get to that critical mass,
people get together and start to develop that feeling of intimacy.
For example, if you're going to talk, you talk in a different way
than if you're going to talk in big groups.
Because you have to play different social games,
play different characters.
And here it's really interesting to me,
what is the scale at which you break?
When you look at it evolutionarily,
how long have you known each other?
If you look back, you met, I don't know, you and a neighbor of yours,
and maybe you met 100 or 200 people.
That's how our brains developed.
And now, suddenly, it's a message,
when you broadcast it to 10,000 people,
that you can, I don't know,
under the profile picture of a dog,
write back that you're a fool,
and that you're lying anyway,
and that, I don't know, this political party is the law.
So there's a lot of pressure,
for which our brains,
which have evolved evolutionarily,
adapt to the tribe,
they're not used to such large tribes.
And you can't engage those 10,000 people,
but at some point, you just want to run,
and you can be a secret with the rule.
And then the question is,
can we do it, or why are we doing it?
Why are we doing it?
I think my answer is,
because we still have a platform,
like you said, for job posts,
for young people to make careers,
and fuck good media,
and for trusting good media.
And now, do we think we're some kind of brokers of trust?
Fuck no.
But everyone knows that this information
that they receive,
that everyone is semi-relevant,
they're attacked in the comments.
So the communities are self-sanctioned.
And here, I think, there's a big difference
between large and small communities,
because everyone has their own
different forms,
from masterminds,
to mentors,
to mega-groups,
which I feel like they're being watched.
Yeah, it's not nice.
It's not nice?
No, it's very...
Even if you go back,
if I go back to
Facebook,
I think that as a platform
they've also come to a phase
where they're confused.
Late majority, late majority,
babi!
I see that they're also a bit confused
that groups are actually
one of those...
I don't know, maybe I'm biased,
but I have a feeling that
Facebook is still
the last remaining useful feature
for me.
I'm probably biased
about that channel.
Now, when we
publish our content,
we put it on YouTube,
and then we link it
to Slovenian developers,
and we also have a page
in Grodno on Facebook,
where we also publish it normally.
But...
I think I fully realized
that our page
is a
slot machine.
Now, I'll put in
a certain amount of cash,
then I'll put in that...
Once I know that we've put
a crazy amount of money in,
10-20 euros,
it's quite something.
5000 in total, bravo!
Marinka Wittler, great!
But there was a problem.
Who am I talking to?
It's quite something.
And then...
Now we have some people
on Facebook, we give them
personal information, if people are
really passionate about Facebook,
they get everything there, but...
I don't know, I don't see it as a channel
of the future.
You said slot machine,
I call it a pay-to-play algorithm.
I've seen that a lot on LinkedIn,
and I've measured it.
For example, if you publish something
on LinkedIn as a page,
you get everything, if you go from a few
personal profiles. And that's why through
companies, we're working on
employee-generated content,
and I recently had a friend
from ActiveCampaign,
and we had a conversation, how can smart
people, like engineers and developers,
be inspired to participate
in employee-generated content
programs? Marketing will
participate, not panic. Sales will
participate.
These are less-remaining,
I don't know.
No, no, no. You know what I want to say?
I mean, what is the logic,
purely algorithmic logic,
if a company wants to sell you
their advertising solutions,
recruiting solutions, whatnot,
if you're a slogan on the platform,
and they sell your eyes,
and they have a subtle interest to keep you up.
And how we work with companies
like that, purely for their
commercial activity,
to hire 5-10 employees,
to post, to share,
from the perspective of reach,
from the perspective of engagement,
just be it.
And those changes that happen,
by force, do certain things
that maybe,
I don't know if they were evolutionarily
OK, because, sorry,
that you attack your engineer, your developer,
your CTO,
that he writes cringe posts,
how he was a god in the 14th century,
and how he didn't believe that God
could program, and now he leads a team
of 20 people, because
the company will have a business like,
sorry, this is not the best use of your time.
And now I don't know,
purely from the perspective of channels,
it all looks like they're strong channels,
but every channel you work on
has opportunity costs.
Every thing, and you know how you do it,
for example, if you're doing a service,
and the agency, we, for example,
together with a colleague on a project,
in August, we made 12 million
for a Slovenian company.
And we did it through outreach,
because it's totally cringe
to send personalized messages to people,
saying, hey, maybe you're interested in this and that,
but in an unintelligent way.
It wasn't very researched.
And here, you know,
I would say to people,
come and get involved for 6 months,
and post on LinkedIn every day,
and Instagram stories.
I've already seen your reaction.
One of those classic,
one of those classic...
You're a very dynamic speaker.
Sorry, sorry,
this is like...
No, no, it's a bit old-fashioned,
it's a bit of a Jeremy approach,
you have to hold yourself up.
I'm going to sleep now,
God forbid.
No, come on, what did you want to ask before?
That you're fully triggered
when people say you have to post
every day on LinkedIn.
And your pictures of your kids,
and your cats, and...
Privacy invasion.
OK, and what about our coffee machine,
our coffee machine,
our, I don't know, engine?
OK, look,
my filter for content is
does the world become more intelligent with it?
And if the answer is no...
That's it.
Look, I'm also a humorist,
I have a bit of added value,
I'm a fan of memes
and all that stuff.
I just said that again,
how much a politician...
Actually, today...
Is it an added value?
Did I tell you something you don't know yet?
Did I pray to you so nicely?
Only, Maja, if I sell, I don't know,
tires, and I don't know,
I can generate some money
every week.
Yes.
Yes?
OK.
Yes.
How do you find a genuine brand?
You feel it.
I think we are people by now.
Is it something that the boss sets,
or is it something that you go to the factory to ask,
or is it something that people tell you?
Pay-to-Marketer.
I always had the feeling that
there is so much content,
so much noise,
that we will eventually come to a point
where you really have to be authentic,
and people will also find out,
okay, this is fake,
this is not fake.
Ben Williams said that,
I know, even when we talked,
and a critical thinker, right?
Because if you say to your corporate chair,
you know, say hello to your team,
welcome new employees
from the programming field,
so, come on.
You write, these are technological challenges
that we are solving,
this is how we function,
we are trying not to do more than
30 hours a week for it,
and that's it, take it or leave it.
And I think transparency here,
you know, to take this layer of fluff,
you can't always do it.
You have worked with corporate,
I have worked with corporate,
you know what compliance is,
you know what it is,
you have to hire 6 employees
to be super transparent,
because sometimes you mess up a bit.
But in smaller teams,
and if you work as a personal brand,
sorry, the way we talk,
I sometimes check it,
is it the language I would say to you?
Would it be like,
respected, today I am honored
that I talked to the gentleman
on the podcast in Grodno.
And it seems to me that
the bullshit filter is definitely here,
but I really believe,
that content must always be done
with a certain degree of attention
to quality, because I don't know,
if you paint your half-painted cow
and your dog watching you every day,
you are still like,
my life is a little better
because I saw that picture or not.
Well, I don't know,
we all have different interests
why we make content,
I don't, because it takes me a long time
to learn something.
An interesting case I saw recently,
also from the page
that you mentioned
about your products,
an interesting case happened to me,
some company,
we talked that maybe
I would shoot something with them,
and
they didn't see
that they are exceptional,
but
from our perspective
they were, I don't know,
data center,
full amazing,
some servers, clusters, whatever,
and we as a page
pay attention
to that uniqueness,
that passion,
that's an interesting thing.
You probably have to include
your page in that.
That's the law. And the agency,
and the foreign expert,
because it's normal for you,
and when you are in your discipline,
in your science,
you don't see more important things,
that some fresh eyes see.
How do you do that?
I don't know, if you are doing
custom research,
you say, today we have open doors
in the company, and then you see
what people like.
Let me tell you,
I did custom research for my book.
Amazing, amazing.
I will add that too.
That's great.
That's Diablo, right?
Diablo, yes.
Although I had lessons from Primorska,
but I said no,
we will drink Cabernet Sauvignon.
Cabernet Sauvignon is the only
good wine in our guest.
Everything is like that.
If you order Cabernet Sauvignon in a restaurant,
you can't get a bad one.
Don't make fun of me.
No, no, no.
If we go to another round,
we will come back to that.
As I told you,
at the beginning of this conversation,
I was half life and half fear.
What would the programmers think of me?
You are so exposed to the programmers.
I mean, I try.
I would like to be even more,
but they don't accept me.
Why?
Because I come and talk.
A few days ago, I started recording
in Hotline Hany Music,
where we talked on a cell phone.
I said, guys, what are you doing?
I am Maja Voje.
I am also interested in computers.
How did you react to that?
Freeze.
I don't know what to do.
I am a little overwhelmed.
I try to be nice.
Some people treat me
better than others.
I am really interested in these things.
I go crazy about these things.
But later in the research,
I was afraid if this book
is good for a product manager,
for a developer, for a technical founder.
Because, sorry,
someone from marketing
or from a group of people
I will say,
it was easy for me
after I did a session with
70,000 people on Udemy
and I have been in this conversation
for so many years.
But I know this.
In a simple way,
to present it to people
who will use it a lot,
and at the beginning
the most difficult thing
was product pricing.
Because I didn't know much about it.
Product was really strange to me.
And then I had a product manager
from Google who helped me
to structure it.
But what I told you here
is that I asked a lot for help.
I don't have anything to say.
If I don't know something,
I don't understand something,
I ask for feedback.
And you also participated
in the first round of feedback.
I recorded a weird video
and I wrote a book about it.
This is my head.
But I sent it very intentionally
on 50 pages
on different profiles
and I saw exactly
where the positive feedback
and where the negative feedback came from.
And then I mapped those feedbacks.
The green ones,
the ones that were OK.
The ones that were like
I don't give up.
It's cool, it's over.
And the ones that were
really good, but not clear.
And then there were feedbacks
that didn't go through at all.
I don't want to say it's anti-persona,
but there were people who said
I don't have to climb
because I'm not fucking Nutella
and I don't have to satisfy myself.
Damn, you took that from the text.
One of my favorite.
What came out of the first round
of this research is that
I work very well with product managers,
I work very well with technical founders,
and with people who
understand sales
and marketing more than just
which channel we will choose
to get customers.
Because they understand the pricing.
For example, if you sell to different segments
of customers, you will also achieve
a higher price.
If you sell to May VM,
if you sell to marketers,
you will be able to sell to Juri.
That's what I think.
But we have a slightly different
readiness to pay.
But what I really wanted to tell you
is that through this research
I got a very clear idea
of who I was talking to.
And that opened my eyes
because then I knew
which examples I had to include in the book.
I was very interviewed in the process.
I put Amplitude in the book,
I put Figma in the book,
I put MongoDB in the book,
you don't have to translate it.
You explained it to me.
I put Snyk in the book.
No.
Shit, I don't know.
I'm making a lot of mistakes.
You showed me that video,
I watched it because I was interested
in what it was about.
I can relate to a lot of products,
the stories
with which I worked,
but why
does this part
seem so important to me?
Why did I sit here
for half a day?
For example,
you have to ask a person
to come,
you have to ask
a person to come,
then you have to ask
Jano to come,
someone to help technically.
You have to do everything,
then you have to talk to her.
No problems at all.
That's the funniest part.
Then you wait for the product
to be made, for Jano to do it,
and then it's done.
MP4, whatever, it's done,
Jano delivers it to you.
A lot of work, energy,
time, everything,
and then it's like,
now we have to go to the market,
now we have to release it,
how will we get to the audience
that we thought we had?
If I don't do this part right,
if I don't do this part right,
we will release it,
let's say, on Sunday night,
and no one will see it,
or we will release it
on other channels,
and no one will see it,
and I see that there is
a very big possibility
for a fail,
whether we will sell it,
whether the episode will be successful or not.
The product can still be excellent.
Yes, we can have
I don't know who,
and we will totally fail,
because this part is not right,
and the topics you touched on
in the book you sent me,
I haven't finished the book yet,
but I want to say
that it is extremely important
to understand
who you will sell it to,
who you will sell it to, what do you mean?
I am asked only three questions
in the book. Who can I sell it to?
Who is my target audience?
The second question is, who do I sell it to?
What price do I put on it?
And the third, how do I choose channels?
And I think that the general name
is always the target audience.
As I said before, when I started making videos,
if you sell it, I don't know, Moto2, or Maja,
or Jana, it's a different price
than if you sell it, I don't know,
but it's a very different product
and a different price
depending on your decision
on who you will sell it to.
And as far as channels are concerned,
I also have a brilliant example,
we were making refrigeration systems
for the self-driving vehicle,
for one company,
and you know that the number of pages
in this world is measured
in hundreds, not in thousands,
and if you happen to work
with a fifth of those pages,
it's much smarter
that you just write an email,
hello, John,
we work so good together,
tell me a little bit,
where do you go to meetings,
where do you choose magazines,
what influencers do you follow,
what kind of community,
and on the basis of that
you find the other five John's
that you can sell to,
so that you don't have to do
your stupid research
So, look, there are examples
where marketing is very simple,
there are examples where marketing
and differentiation are very complex
in some more competitive platforms.
But I always say,
when you don't know, ask,
and ask those people
who are actually your target audience,
you can decide for yourself.
Don't you think
that one step
with these target audiences
is to get
to know them better?
No, I don't think so.
First of all,
with UX, with product research,
one of the interesting problems
is that if you talk to people
in private, they will try to
talk to you and say,
oh, great, you did it,
because they don't want to disappoint you.
And here is the problem
with recruiting,
how do you recruit?
You know, the best UX test
is when I go to the market
and I find an application
and I didn't say anything
that I would get a gift,
but I was like, come, come.
I would like to test this
on your phone.
What did I get?
An ideal environment,
from the point of view of the network,
so that it wasn't a laboratory environment,
because everyone was working
continuously, but people were
looking at different screens
and I was always thinking,
if you don't know, go outside,
go and test it.
If you ask someone to write
some nonsense,
what will you write in your book?
Go, show your face,
you will get money now,
because when you invest
in the next 50 years,
you can still improve.
A brilliant example,
you probably didn't know.
Are you ready?
This is a business model
of my book,
because I wanted to sell it
for 27, but no,
because you won't sell it anyway.
Kindle book can't be more expensive than 10?
No, fixed price.
Oh, wow.
I made a calculation
and a projection.
No, no, no, I mean, I probably won't be selling books through my front page as often as I do there.
But now I can still adapt from the point of view of bundles, now I can trust that information.
I just imagined that I would do it, that I would prepare it for the launch date.
I would be surprised. I think I would be surprised, it would be terrible.
So, look, whatever you can do here is very, very, very, very important.
And as far as the research side is concerned, I almost see it as an excuse, right?
Because you can always remember three thousand things why you can't do some things,
and why a certain thing is bad.
But in reality, if you talk to other people, it's probably better than speculating
why you may not be good at talking to people.
Because if nothing else, it has already been proven in society that it is not good to talk to people,
which is also a purely scientific method.
And I think this is a kind of private procrastination, or maybe sometimes a bit of a mental rabbit hole.
You know, looking for things that are not convenient for you to do.
I always say, look, fuck it, do it.
Every time I do something else, I do it because I think it's the most mission critical,
or I'm hurting my business.
So, what better solution to make?
One of the... I don't know, I hope you have it in the book.
What, what, what do you have?
Wikipedia says that...
Wikipedia says what?
You know that.
Troubleshooter professional.
Correctly, Wikipedia says.
Someone writes, la la la, the other is like a rabbit.
La la la, unique value proposition of USP.
Now, I'm really sorry I don't remember now,
but one of your colleagues, I think he was also in your podcast,
talked a lot about branding, brand perception.
In fact, what you are, what you represent, and where that USP is,
and how you see yourself, how others see you, and how...
That was probably a transition to positioning.
Transition, yes.
He doesn't have to go into that.
I'll see you.
I'll see who you're talking to.
Very good question.
USP in the Go-To-Market strategy,
how important is it, how is it connected?
Do people need to know what your USP is,
do you communicate that?
Let's go back a few steps.
What do you do?
What is Product Market Fit?
Does your audience know what Product Market Fit is?
Or will you quickly explain it to the camera?
What is Product Market Fit?
You go first.
Those terms, you go first.
Okay.
That's what he said.
Okay, that's what he said.
And that's the decision.
Yes, again.
That's what he said, that we are in the business
to solve certain challenges.
And after we decide which challenges we want to solve,
we have to find people who have that challenge,
and then make a decision that actually offers
a solution that will solve that challenge.
For example, if my dad wanted to sell me,
I don't know, an empty sheet of paper,
and my dad would be like,
here's an empty sheet of paper,
would you buy it?
And I would say, no, why?
It doesn't change any added value.
Dad, go to Jan and try it again,
because it's okay to sell.
But it's very, very interesting to me,
because here's one more thing we're missing.
They might like the product a lot,
but they'll be ready to pay for it.
And I had a team last week
who told me they had 24 buyers,
and I got, I don't know, 4-5 emails from them.
We actually have 4 buyers who pay us,
and 8 who said they would start paying by the end of the year,
and the rest, who we encourage a lot
to get onboarded on the platform and do it.
And I was like, Mayday, Mayday, we have a problem.
So, yeah, now I could change those challenges a bit.
And most of us, when we're struggling,
it's not just, can we get 500 users?
Can we shop those 1,000 fake emails
on Discord and such challenges?
But at the same time,
like in the question, did we develop something
that the market actually wants and solves a problem for them?
Are they ready to pay us for it?
And is it because they pay us,
or can our business survive?
I think that's the return on investment
that's happening a lot in Europe.
And I'm sorry, we don't have millions here,
most of us don't,
but it has to run in three months,
because otherwise we'll have to invest
our personal cash in the long run.
You have three months, break it or make it.
Fair enough.
Have you ever been in that situation?
Yeah, we forgot, Mayday, what happened.
I mean, it wasn't easy for us.
For example, last year,
we were fixing to make a new Boho,
because Boho is different,
and you need a new Boho, I guess.
At that time, it had even worse...
At that time, it had worse...
At that time, it had even worse interface
than the one you have today.
And we said, OK, we'll use the latest technology,
we'll make a new, nice interface,
and everyone will want to use Boho,
because we'll make it.
We even thought of a logo,
a dog that loves Boho,
and that was great.
Very cute, very nice,
and we released it,
and we said, OK, Boho doesn't have
that, how do you say it,
market-in-market,
so it can...
Anyway, we developed some features,
it went really well,
but again, we came across
the problem
that there wasn't
a strategy, you know.
How are we going to tell people
that we have this Boho killer app,
which will replace Boho?
We came across this problem,
how are we going to get
the first pages to trust
that we have a big enough platform
to sell things,
and to create
a marketplace,
all by ourselves.
Yes, because you have two problems,
the cold start problem,
where you have to get a salary,
and those who will buy it.
Yes, the chicken egg problem.
There are some theories
on how to solve it,
and it's very interesting,
so if anyone is interested,
google it.
Now,
what are we going to announce?
We can print all the t-shirts,
so we can write ads.
It's just
a nice example,
when you get involved
in being a developer,
and you solve
technical problems,
to think about what the market needs.
It's one of many.
Amazing, thank you so much for sharing this.
For me,
it's the most beautiful thing
when I see an overdeveloped product.
When I see how everything is done,
and you are not only a technical founder,
you are also a ninja,
and you know how to solve things on your own.
But when I see a 45-year-old
from Luxembourg,
who works in a corporation,
and then invests in his startup,
which is run by a horde of Romanian
developers,
and now he has his own application,
which shouldn't exist,
and I'm like, oh my god,
this shouldn't exist.
Here I see that the market wants it,
the market needs it,
and here I think it's so fundamental,
that you know how to test everything.
For example,
as a freelancer,
we sold our team in two days,
for 20 euros,
the first cohort through Word Document.
Before that,
we were constantly developing,
and if you buy this job
from PwDF, or from Pitch,
or from the fact that
they give you an appointment,
it's different,
because I'm not a developer myself,
and I don't know how to develop a product,
I pay for the product,
and this project is not for me.
So, if you know,
you can still develop
a minimal version,
and here comes the first concept,
this product,
before you buy it,
maybe in our region we have this tendency
to give too many things for free,
and then the user doesn't have
the opportunity to convert,
because we already solved the problem for him for free.
This also happens,
but
it seems to me
that here,
a modern consumer
is developing in this direction,
that he wants to see things before he gives,
I don't know, shut up and take my money,
and here it seems to me that
when you go back to transparency,
you won't buy a cat in a jacket,
you won't buy,
I don't know, that someone will solve
the problem for you,
before you see it,
you won't, because we are sceptical,
and we have already seen things,
and you don't believe such promises.
Crazy, isn't it?
No, it's crazy.
You know what the problem is?
When I took your notes,
that's a book,
those are not notes, that's a book.
Sorry, you sent me the first chapter,
you didn't send me the whole book.
That's the third chapter,
but it's a good section.
I printed it,
there were so many sheets,
I put two pages on one A4,
and then I could put more paper in the printer.
As we thought, a breakthrough.
No,
what else can I look at,
what else do I have in my notebook?
If you are interested,
you can add more to it.
Yes, I will,
but we will do it later.
We have one and a half,
what are your plans for us?
Chips.
Startups.
No, we will fix it.
What did I write?
Interesting.
Feedback loop.
Maybe you can add more,
I saw that in your notes.
How important is the feedback loop
for product development?
Tell me,
what is the easiest way to do it?
Does it mean
that you click your page,
and send an email,
or measure
UPS,
or what is it?
NPS.
NPS is easy.
For someone who worked
in a market research company,
I don't know that expression.
No, it's simple.
You are working on things,
and when they are brought to you,
you can learn additional things.
But,
feedback loop.
The more you can learn,
the faster you can grow.
My hypothesis is
that when you launch products
or go to the market,
it's two-way.
It's an infinite loop.
First, you can do research,
then inception.
I sent a tab,
and when I liked the book chapter,
based on your feedback,
I created a landing page,
and that landing page
after 1,400 searches
converts to 51%.
I haven't seen it yet,
and I don't know 1,400 people,
so they are not my family and friends.
With the fact that I learned
from you with quality research,
with the fact that I went
to test a prototype in writing,
I was able to create a product
that gave me a higher level
of confidence,
with the fact that I was able
to measure the conversion rate
with a validator.
And here, I think
that you are doing this
because of a level of confidence.
How do you say confidence
confidence
that you generate?
For example, if you talk to two colleagues
and they tell you to buy something from you,
it's not the same as if
100 people swipe a card
and say cash on the account.
That's a different level
of confidence.
But for you to get an inception,
how you will empirically
check in the next loop,
it's good to really touch
your pages and talk to them,
to see what's going on
and if nothing is going on,
call them, pick up the phone,
ask them what's going on
at the moment,
it will take you a few minutes,
but from all this talk,
a few days will come.
For this kind of research,
people pay 20 euros a month
so that others do it
for them, so that they don't need it.
So these things really have
a lot of added value.
Still, you don't want to be
in touch with people,
so give them an exit poll on the split page
and ask them what's stopping you
from becoming a premium subscriber
today and you will learn a lot
from it and then find
really good studies that you can improve.
So for me,
the research part and then
experimenting and having
these assumptions and
testing them,
what could be my critical assumption,
that I have to sell Kindle
for more than 10 euros.
If I pushed it,
launch over, it wouldn't be good.
The economy of the project would collapse.
And these things are good
between mapping forward and
having a methodology of how it can be done.
Now, through a change like a math scientist,
probably... No.
No? Makes sense? No.
I mean, I've only gone through
one chapter, so I don't know what's left,
but...
You already got added value here.
I got added value.
One question, I'm still
interested in this topic.
It seems to me that when you're a start-up,
when you're a
pizza-size team,
when you're behind the scenes,
it may seem
that it's a lie to do those things
and maybe you don't realize that it's your advantage.
That's totally your advantage.
Yes, that you're just wrong.
You're just wrong.
You have nothing to lose, but...
These questions are important
for start-ups,
for SMEs,
and for corporations.
And probably the bigger you are,
the more dependent you are on
the go-to-market strategy.
Totally. Can I ask you
one more question? Because I know what's
coming next, but...
No, I'm done with my next question.
I don't know, but okay.
Okay, then I'll let you finish.
When you said that,
I was asked if I knew
how much work it would take to
write a book again.
Why did you ask that?
Sara Stojanovski.
She's a very good friend of mine.
Great, because I'm a customer discovery ninja.
You have such a reasonable part
around you.
My team in Grodno is very...
We don't have such a deep...
We're much more...
Let's just do it.
That's great, isn't it?
I think we'd need someone
with a voice of reason.
It pays off.
I don't know.
For me, it would be more
retrospective than anything else.
She asked me if I would do it again.
I said no.
I really wouldn't.
It would be awful.
You're done with writing a book.
With a note.
I wrote 1,500 pages.
It was awful.
Now there will be 250 users.
What would they teach me?
Because of that...
First of all, I know how to work with data.
I talk all day.
If you ask most of my team what they do all day,
they answer the phone and talk.
They think that.
I work in a restaurant, I do strategy and partnerships.
But it's very, very, very
important to me.
What kind of person do you
work with on that path?
For example, when you have a product
to work on,
I always tell my team
that you will observe more
the things you didn't do than the things you did.
And you can see
what the conclusion is.
I understand that you're afraid.
I understand that it's weird for you to do it.
I understand that you're running your last mile here.
But do it.
Do it, because you'll never see anything else.
True.
Older people are better.
You realize that you always have
some...
time.
Some time for that.
Would it be possible
for you to think about
getting some younger employees?
No, no, no.
No.
Assistants.
We still have a lot of time,
but we'll be able to talk about it later.
Are we recording?
I don't know exactly when, but I don't know.
I think it's half an hour.
Okay.
In...
Growth Hacking.
I'll go back to Growth Hacking,
because that's also a topic
you're interested in.
I want to be more associated with it
because I have bad rap.
Why?
I really don't like it.
I have a course
made by 70,000 people.
And on a daily basis
I get 20 messages
from gentlemen and ladies
from India and Pakistan.
And then this
outsourcing started.
Lady Majority,
SCOS, Growth Hacking,
and so on.
Here I am.
I have a lot of good friends.
I know a lot of influencers
from this field.
I told them
that we believe in the method of experimentation.
We believe that
instead of thinking about
what you do in marketing
and that you count on your genius,
creativity and whatnots,
you measure and get data
and get feedback
if you could do more or less.
If we call it experimentation,
Growth Hacking,
Agile Marketing,
I can't do it.
I'm sorry that
5 Growth Hackers
will tell me how to hack
their SEO, split pages.
It's not because I went to science.
I went to science because I believed
that there is a scientific approach
in something that I was taught
on a fax machine.
I think we need
rebranding.
That was about Growth Hacking.
Everyone said to me,
yes, you can grow products
that have a good product market fit.
My point is, nobody told you how to get there.
You can choose
and with those blanks and tasks,
I said,
I wanted to write
not a cookie cutter recipe,
but I wanted to write step by step
what you can do and what you can be aware of
so that it will be more likely for you
that you can confidently
prepare.
Back to my question.
What was it?
Growth Hacking.
Then I went to rent.
I wrote down
some points. Criticism.
We've already talked about that.
Maybe Zete would like to
say something.
In your book,
also in
Market Strategist,
you have written MongoDB.
I think you have it.
And
a bunch of other brands.
Now,
when we first talked at the beginning
about developers and
some skepticism
adversity
in marketing.
I'm nervous.
A big
challenge
or problem is that
tech companies
can have
excellent marketing
and can
oversell.
Yes, build products.
It's not necessary to build a product,
but they can only position it
in an unintended space
or sell some features
that are not stable.
Before that
it was a big step.
Then it happened that
the whole world
used MongoDB in the same way
for the same things.
Because the marketing
from MongoDB is very good.
They hack at college.
I have written here
that RitinkDB is an example
of a company that
went bankrupt, but their
opinion was that they are very good,
they know how to do it,
excellent documentation,
excellent sales,
webinars, videos, conferences,
all this machinery works,
but at the end of the day
the features that went wrong
were not delivered.
This is
some kind of criticism
where I see that
on my side they come to the point
that I'm angry
about technology.
Probably my colleagues
have such experiences.
It is said that
you learn, but is it really good
marketing or is it just
technology? Very good.
These things
are very
challenging.
That's why people are so
attached to it.
It makes sense, because when you learn something,
it probably lasts months and months,
and when I learn to click something,
it lasts a few minutes.
The investment we have
to adopt a new
technological tool and framework
is very different.
Sorry if I wasted 15 minutes
talking about whether I liked
Canon or Google Meetings,
it really has no
radical consequences,
but you saw that it has consequences.
You have to perceive it differently.
I think
that here
the product has grown
and the buzzword
for me is show, don't tell.
Give cash back if you can't deliver.
No questions asked.
That sounds much simpler.
If I have a system
and a website that depends on
my income, for example,
and does not deliver
the whole product because
the technology is not accurate
and was chosen
on the basis of hype,
not on the basis of
research accuracy,
that's a problem.
That was my criticism.
Here, like Shopify,
they are ridiculously expensive
when scaling.
At first, it sounds good,
but then it jumps a bit.
For example, if you choose
at the beginning and think
in the course of one year
what is your best decision,
if you are a good entrepreneur
in the 5th or 10th year,
what is your scaleable business,
who is your scaleable team,
if you have to make decisions,
is it always possible?
No, because we are not fully informed.
So it's great that you pay attention to these things.
Okay.
You could have guessed
that you answered me so nicely.
No, I'm not.
I hang out with Simon Pilak a lot.
He's in good shape now.
Now, what else?
That other thing was too cool.
I thought you were going to say
that you are old-fashioned.
I saw your LinkedIn profile.
Oh my God.
I'm sorry.
You have a lot of...
I wanted to say that you have
in companies where you work
too little written what you paid.
Great.
I had LinkedIn growth.
Are you going to give anything
for LinkedIn growth?
No, but I would use this opportunity
to see
that...
People don't know how powerful LinkedIn is, how important it is for them,
and the growth you've made, how did you make it, I don't know.
Without permission.
Yeah, anyway, you mentioned it.
It's very visible and very important, especially for young juniors who don't know what to write online.
But LinkedIn has become your online image, your identity, whatever.
Give more attention to this topic.
That idea came to me, that somehow I have to look at people as part of this podcast or something.
Hey, can I say something about that?
I have to get your brain out of your ass.
No, you said it so nicely here on LinkedIn.
Now I'll tell you one more thing, come on, let me do this.
So how can we, when we work in marketing and sales,
what can we do here so that we don't become a developer's cringe?
How can we be normal to developers and engineers?
I think it's a very good strategy.
For example, what we see with Developer Advocates.
For example, I don't know, an Markani was one of our guests before,
who is actually a person who is a former developer,
who worked with developers, who was a developer.
So was my John Cutler.
And at some point he decided to choose someone else.
Influencer.
But he goes to tech conferences, is with developers, understands their problems,
brings the problems back to the headquarters and discusses them.
He's there, he's a bit like preparing all these channels,
and he's not an outsider, but he's actually an insider.
He's an embed.
He's an advocate from the inside.
I think it's really worth it for the business and for the community.
Because he knows what the trends are, he knows what the plants are that are coming,
he knows what they are.
He speaks the language.
Yes, he speaks the language.
And he's not a fake, he's that.
That's very important.
I saw the same thing with John Cutler at Amplitude,
and with Ben Williams at Snyk.
These guys, I mean, again, I'm afraid of them, like I'm afraid of you,
because I know that you won't do all this bullshit,
because sometimes we serve them in the world.
I think it's great to choose a partner when you're ready to listen to them.
Because we all think well,
we think that we bring some technologies and solutions to the world,
that they will be OK.
But we also need you to deal with us.
You know, I come from Biskul, so I'm not the smartest person in the world.
I'm just saying that I'm not.
If I don't have a developer or someone who explains these things to me,
what we sell, what we do and what Roadmap is,
I will probably have a very bad time in my job and I won't be able to do it.
It's all the same for developers.
As a developer, as an engineer, you can't be good and efficient
if you don't understand where that money is flowing to.
So I'm trying my best.
Shocking.
Shocking, but I'm trying my best.
It's not a big problem.
Nothing, let's wrap it up.
Thank you very much.
I know you have a little more to say.
Do you have anything to add?
Or do you want a burek on the web?
Let's try something better than a burek.
No, thank you very much.
This conversation meant so much to me
because I learned to fit in here
as if I were a victim of being discriminated against by developers.
But really, I haven't said a word in 10 years.
But I had an interest.
At that time, I only needed a mentor.
And he was the one who supported me,
who supported me,
and who brought me all this.
Here, we still need more developers,
and more people who will stand up for themselves.
And we, as a business,
can give you a point or two
as a substitute
so that you can create a website.
So that's it. Let's go.
Let's go. Oh my God.
Kepica.com.
Wait a minute.
Thank you to everyone who stayed until the end.
Long live Matej.
No, wait.
At 45 minutes, we would like to thank
our supporters and sponsors.
So we thank HumanFrog and 3FSA for their support.
We also thank Patreon
for their support.
And everyone who is with us.
Maja, thank you very much for this conversation.
Maybe some other time.
No, thank you.
Okay, super. The best.