Here it is, this boat is meant for us to hitchhike, so I can hitchhike up, you know, so it will come in handy.
Now, you know, the jingles have run out.
First of all, I would like to say hello to both of you in the new episode of Ogrodio.
Andraž really wanted Ogrodio to be able to talk about something intimate, to be able to talk in peace.
No, in fact, a few months ago, we heard that she would come and record this for us.
And we had the idea that she really is an ideal guest for our show, this intimate scene.
Such a little dark light, a little bit of smoke.
And then we thought, let's have it on the bridge.
When it will be more intimate.
When it will be more intimate, with this live audience, with all the noise.
We are waiting for the engine to start.
Here, between the two political parties, you have a stand.
Yes, today we are filming in Dejansko, we are also live streaming this episode of Ogrodio.
Now we are filming on the stand of the company Human Frog.
This is a company that also supports us on our path.
So that's why we took this opportunity.
I hope that Jan will be able to record the sound in 5 days.
So that it will be proper and that everything will be fine.
So that all the listeners won't say that this is inaudible and so on.
We will use all the AI to fix it.
Now, when we were preparing for the episode with Urško, we all wanted to animate.
We said that maybe it would be best to give you a powerful question first.
And then I will ask you who you are.
A powerful question.
Let me tell you why you see hackathons as a good way to innovate.
Are hackathons your tools, your mission, your lifestyle?
All of the above.
First of all, thank you in advance.
I really wanted to be here from the start.
But I was preparing for the show on the bridge.
I didn't know that the show would be on the bridge.
I was waiting for the idea to come.
It was not so easy.
Thank you for waiting for me.
Hackathons, Ogrodio, business, mission.
Absolutely.
Because what I have learned over the years,
is that the energy that happens there,
even the most skeptical customers,
come to the end and say,
hey, we want a little more of this,
also for us in the space, in Pundelk.
You, Otoš, were really crazy about it.
But it's hard to explain to people what kind of vibe happens
when people start creating,
when they forget all the obstacles.
All that was not possible in the morning,
starts to disappear.
And then that energy, that hype, that adrenaline,
that they will create something in just two days.
That's what I always say.
After eight years,
this is the best way to spend the weekend.
We go to parties,
and I'm like, I'm a hackathon.
You said it like that,
Urška works only during the weekends.
During the week, she's happy.
I won't say that I really like to work,
but after the hackathon,
in Pundelk in the morning,
I sit down with the same energy,
I treat the team and everything else,
what to do next.
But I wanted to say that
some people go to parties,
some people go to Zrče,
some to EXIT,
but I have a saying,
we have a hackathon,
we can do it,
and this weekend,
we can do it.
Is this the end?
Forever 42.
I don't know.
Did you leave a mark on 42?
You say 42 and more.
I said that everything that will be asked,
because we know that 42 will be the answer forever.
But a lot, because there are so many of them,
we do it internally,
just for business,
and in those fields,
we don't talk publicly,
because everything is done,
something is being done for them internally,
so this weekend,
we had two.
Now maybe those segues,
we stopped this question,
and jumped directly into the water,
to the hackathon,
but let's take a step back.
Who is Urška?
Who are you?
42.
Can I continue now?
No, I mean,
I'll say it differently.
I met you
when you came to our office,
to look for your father,
who was on a hackathon.
The office was so energetic,
even though you came
with Hristo Ljubljanaški,
who is here today,
but so energetic,
so full of energy,
so passionate,
so much,
transformation,
innovations,
on a higher level,
so I don't know,
you were there in the morning,
and I was like,
where is this female energy coming from?
Thank you, Andraž,
I didn't see it that way,
but really, thank you.
I don't know, it's hard to say,
because I've been asked many times,
does life support me somehow?
I don't know if I'm asking
who I am,
the eternal optimist,
but I've decided
that you always have a chance,
you sit down and cry,
and everyone is guilty,
or you sit down
and say, oh, why me,
and you say, hey, look,
it was supposed to be like this,
and then it turned into something
nicer and nicer,
and I always believed
that it was much better,
and I think we have a little too little
of this sun, heat, energy,
that I've ever seen in the world.
I know it sounds like a cliché,
but that's how I live.
Great,
for me it's too little of this,
too little of this,
and then when you meet such a person,
who lives this business,
or really,
somewhere I'm passionate about it,
it's not like, let's sell something,
and earn some money,
but when you've seen
how happy you are,
I don't know,
now I have a question about you,
when people say to me,
oh, you do these things,
IT geeks and such,
they get tired,
they get tired of hanging out,
how do you convey this energy,
that I can tell you what I see,
this, this, this,
and you see Rototunarap,
screaming and everything,
but you see that smile,
and you say,
that's good,
those hackathons,
that you organize,
I was probably,
maybe a few percent less than you,
but,
those are
marathon events,
marathon and sprint,
in one weekend,
to do something,
to create an idea,
to develop,
to get to know the subject,
to get to know the problem,
to do a solution,
to present a solution,
to communicate with other stakeholders,
that's just how you should experience it.
Now, you know,
if you don't have enough energy
in that locomotive,
people will say,
oh, look,
the organizers,
that's stupid,
let's go to Zrča,
or whatever,
so I think that,
considering that I've been
to good and bad hackathons,
it's very important,
what kind of energy is generated,
besides, you know,
it's important for everything,
it's not a goal,
but hackathons,
maybe,
work with people,
but you have to be fast.
First of all,
people don't know how to imagine it,
participants know
what they are going to solve,
because they are prepared.
But most of the time,
let's say, on Saturday morning,
members of the team
get to know each other on Saturday morning,
and at night,
at 6.30 p.m.,
they have to connect,
build, create an interesting solution,
talk to each other,
and prepare the right speech,
not just one-hour speech,
or five-minute speech,
and all that,
besides being technical,
you always have to add
a little bit of professionalism,
so practically,
you have them completely
focused on the adrenaline,
and then it's good
if we come up with
a little bit of ingenuity,
What is hackathon?
We are all here,
all three of us are talking,
because we all know.
Maybe we should talk about
Andraž in the hackathon.
Do we have to invite him?
No, it's a challenge for everyone.
It's also a challenge,
this term is very
exploited, used,
people also
make some wrong assumptions,
you can also
use a lot of people,
a lot of companies,
for example,
they organize things by themselves,
they don't know exactly
what to prepare,
what will happen,
what people expect,
and a lot of people
are on both sides.
Maybe it's in the sense
of how to organize a hackathon.
Let's go to the break.
This is easy marathon innovation.
What does it mean?
If you have a one-hour job,
two-hour job, three, four,
this sprint can't be a hackathon,
because it's a marathon.
This is exactly what Otto said,
because of the trend,
everyone got a hackathon label.
A hackathon is a marathon
of innovation,
where you come up with
an idea or a problem
that needs to be solved,
people get together,
it doesn't matter,
the question is always
who can participate in a hackathon.
Whoever has the desire and energy,
even if it's for a very technical
or very business-oriented job,
as little as a person
from the outside,
we will get a more diversified solution.
That is, thinking out of the box.
Exactly.
And the passion to solve something,
to be something.
We had a daily attendance
of 13,
an old girl,
and the oldest, I think you were 63,
at A-Bank.
At A-Bank I wasn't.
Yes, we found one where he wasn't.
He was 63,
very excited,
and then we asked him why,
and he said, straight to the point,
I've been a committee member for so many decades
that I don't think
there's ever been a sign
that my bank has gone.
True that.
And it doesn't matter.
He came, competed,
he was with the young people in the team,
he had a good team,
the team had a good time,
so really, the desire must be there.
Now, why do the participants appear?
There are different motivations.
Which change.
Motivations change.
The father will then ask him
what all the deals were.
Now, at first, he's like,
I can't sleep,
I can't sleep.
I have written here
a few steps through the hackathon,
and then at the beginning,
the goal.
I can also return to the question,
how do you prepare
for the hackathon
and how do you prepare
and probably
many of the hackathons
we've been to, both of them,
are very different
because how well do you set the goal?
What are we going to hack?
What are we going to develop?
Why are we doing this goal?
What is it for?
My first question is,
first of all, I want to understand why we do it.
Because
some people don't even know what it is
and they think it's fine,
but when you ask them why they do it,
we also start to think,
what are we going to do
with this hackathon?
If you know that you would like to have it
because it's good to do it,
fine, but we already have a problem
that you would like to solve.
And when it happens,
we will call you back.
I would imagine,
if I interrupt you,
that, I don't know,
how it is in Slovenia,
if you have experience,
I see that Slovenian companies
do it because it's good PR,
because it's a good way
to quickly do some recruitment
or get some potential staff,
that it's a site.
The question is,
how many of these companies
really want to solve
some innovative problem
that they want to solve?
That it's more about
brand awareness,
how we,
as a bank,
that we are still
relevant,
we are looking for a staff
because we will
renovate the IT department
or something like that.
Is it more in this direction
or are there companies
that actually see this
as we are looking for
something to solve
or we want to make our product
on a different level
and we need some
untrained people
from inside the company
and maybe someone in the business
that sees it differently
or how to make it
a business model or something like that.
Very good question
and also very complex
to tell you from the right.
Most of our customers,
and I'm saying this out loud,
because I have to have
a satisfied customer
and all the participants.
My task is to make the participants
happy and to get something out of it.
What I mean is that I want to have
a clear picture of what will happen.
Now most people come in
with the idea that they will develop
and look for a new product.
A lot of times when they see
what comes from Hackathon
they start to hesitate
and wait for Unicorn.
On Sunday night Unicorn will be born
and on Monday they will sell it
on the market.
You said that all companies
have a lot of skills.
Vrhunjski was on the development
and I know that Triglav was also there.
They are the first example of a personal
Hackathon where they were looking
for something new,
for the future,
2017, 2018,
and then they decided
to put Unicorn in development
and we worked with them
on the development of the product
with a team from Hackathon
plus an internal team from Triglav.
It was a mixed team.
The team that developed the idea,
they did interviews,
a bit of a strange competition
and so on,
we led them through everything
because that is our role in the end.
That is what we do after Hackathon.
But what happened here?
What was so unique
was that this team
did the software solutions
and this team organized
the software solutions.
We also did a developer Hackathon
where they knew exactly
that this team from the first Hackathon
came in three months to this
and now we need a solution for that.
So all companies,
I would say,
not even 50% of them
manage to make a long-term implementation.
We need to be aware of this
and we are back to
Unicorn is not born on a Sunday night.
Can I say it again?
And then when you go
in the development of the product
from zero to one
according to startup methodologies,
you realize many times
that the market does not need
what Hackathon and hackers think.
But because you can write
and talk about Hackathon
and it is open for the public
and for the students,
this next step is not known.
Because the next day
when we come to the handbook
and then one day
you can say
that we are still developing
and we will not say anything
until the product is ready
for launch.
And I can say at this moment
that we have two products
ready for launch.
And because of this,
it is not so complicated
because you just make a handbook
for your customers.
I have a couple of questions.
One is
42.
It is what you said.
The product is developing
and you have
MVP.
That's what I meant.
So,
from the MVP
to the handbook
or the developer of the
Hackathon handbook,
you implement it
so that the product
is ready for launch?
Yes.
Do you have
a good story
that there is a product
that has developed?
Can I say it?
I would like to know
because then the participants
also sign it.
My question is
because
as I understand
or I had the opportunity to see,
the participants
give their forgiveness.
They are paid
with some kind
of your positive energy,
customer wishes,
pizzas,
drinks and so on.
We have a great catering.
They eat well
because I am a gourmet.
Now my wife
will listen to this
and she will say why do you go to the Hackathon
and everything you get is pizza.
No, no, no.
Pizza comes at the end.
My question is
what did he get?
He showed something there.
It was a prototype.
Maybe he was not chosen for the best.
Something like that.
And here
a Nendy is signed.
The company can pick it up.
A famous shot.
Maybe I am exaggerating.
All right, all right.
Directly in the straight of the heart.
It is practical.
Let's be practical.
I went through the whole process
because the candidates
were paid for it.
But of course,
we have to understand
the mentality of the corporation.
We paid a lot for it.
We will give awards.
They give their people
for the weekend.
In their budget
they thought
we will have an IP
when the weekend happens at the Hackathon.
Now we are back to what happens
at the Hackathon.
Practically
it is like this.
At the Open Data Hackathon
where there is a lot of open data
for everything and everything
there is a person
who wants to know
what is going to happen.
However, the next day
when we come to the meeting
we will see what are the real possibilities
and not.
And if this team
would like to develop it
it will be signed
Go for it!
Run, be happy!
In a specific example
I would give a euro
if I think
that this team will do it.
So, if someone would like
to know how many
42 people came
to ask for it
one team.
This famous IP
is just a storm of spirits.
When you tell them
that they can come
everyone is happy
and only one came to ask
to sign an IP
and we will do it.
And this team
is developing it
in Austria.
We are not interested
in your ideas
from one hackathon
to another.
Your job is to make sure
that the clients are protected.
It is hard to say
who is important to me.
It is just
something that can be known
through a hackathon.
When I start a hackathon
I always change with an appointment
and I don't have an appointment
for a hackathon.
I am there for the participants
to feel good.
If there is a moment
when someone has a problem
I will moderate
the relations
and the meeting
ends on Sunday evening.
If we talk about the participants
and the development of the product
we have a program
similar to startup incubation
and participants
are usually paid
a fee for it.
They get a reward
for the weekend
and a fee for the program.
As I mentioned
a few minutes ago
the MVP team
has shown
that there is a case
and they have signed
a partnership agreement
and they are developing
it including
the maintenance of the system.
In the beginning
we make sure
that everything is fair play
because you can't
start a hackathon
if you don't like it.
I always try to explain
to the participants
that they need to understand
what a hackathon is.
The only thing that holds them back
is the IP member inside.
He writes that it is his
and he feels good about it.
Whatever happens, it is all his.
We also have to make sure
that he is moderate
because if he starts a hackathon
you can't do anything
because it is not ours.
I would like to add a few words.
From my perspective
as a developer
we all talk about
TechDevPodcast
but these events are not
only developers' hackathons
but also businesses
so let's not be afraid of it.
I would say
that you should
look for a partnership
and at the beginning
there is a nice link
where you can sign up
and there is a search engine
Now, if people are sincere in their intentions, if they are honest, pick up that document.
If you see that it is written inside that there are some bizarre requirements, do not apply.
That would be a general rule. If it is possible, ask.
Now, if you have an idea that you have already developed, that you have already done,
and you are concerned about that task, ask, but do not go into that task, because it will be more difficult for you to use it.
Those tasks are especially sensitive from the inside.
I do not know, Slovenian developers, if I go to that Facebook group ...
The group that I am afraid of!
It is a large and sometimes toxic group, but I would say so.
There was a moment when people do not know why they organize hackathons,
they copy those copyright legal documents because they already have them,
and then, or it is really annoying to look for employees,
and you come to those ethical questions the day before it starts happening, and you have to be careful.
We can probably explain what the bad results look like.
What is the biggest red flag, I do not know, you probably heard it,
there was a hackathon that you did not have, and they told you that it was going there, and that's it.
In general, I hear more reports, less of those with papyrology, and then further reports,
they do not come to say hello in the morning, even the organizers,
they break the rules, and then they just walk around the city a little, and that's it.
I do not go to bed, I really do not go to bed,
and then at night I look for someone who wants to work with me,
if I can help him with something, and give him some advice.
For me, when you let the competitors do what they want to do,
it hurts my soul, it is something that I do not have to do.
I also hear such stories, that they are packed in suitcases,
and then you have to, I do not know, from various employed members,
they pick you up, you have such and such a rule,
including now I drink, so they do not give it back to you,
at night you can hear it.
The fact is, let's move forward, I would say,
maybe in this direction it is not accepted, I am more of an optimist,
the one who organizes it, let's push him a little,
now you will see through his answers,
does the person really think, is he sincere, honest,
or is he like, you know, oh yeah, no,
but you know how it would be for us now.
No, look, I always tell them to correct,
because I also have it with me,
and I tell them, if you do not go, we will change,
if the candidate develops.
As far as employment is concerned,
they also have to have a practical conversation,
so in the next few days, if not,
it leads the candidate to some kind of conversation.
Because not in the last hackathons,
why is it such a good talent pool?
Because everything from Saturday afternoon,
when we have a kick-off,
because I always think,
oh, drama, drama, we do not know what we are solving yet,
oh, shit, there will be no unicorn yet,
what now?
From Saturday afternoon, everyone is still politically correct,
teams, mentors, everyone is a little nice,
a little, la, la, la.
And then there was, you know, if they come in,
they come in, they come in more,
these are real characters.
And I will not say that only the candidate
has the potential to be corrected.
But this mandate suits him perfectly,
because there is management,
there is management, usually the mentors and the commission
always come to correct, greet,
and finally listen.
So they have a lot of people to correct,
and in the end, even the candidate can say,
wait a minute, I have this energy,
and I don't like their approach the most.
So it goes in both directions,
and I practically always promote in both directions,
for both.
I wasn't on the side of the mandate
and for my understanding,
everyone had to be happy on Sunday night,
which is really a pity.
Let us, now,
now there is a hackathon,
Friday is now 4 o'clock,
so I think it's your start time
for this hackathon.
No, no, we are working on Saturday morning,
developers are after work, you know,
at 9 o'clock, and then they call,
oh, at 9 o'clock, we're going to open in China.
Let us, let us,
let us,
through a hackathon,
which you organize,
a classic,
for a bank,
for a corporation,
which is slowly moving,
to become a tanker.
Now, wait, not that,
Slovenian Railways.
I haven't succeeded with them yet.
I've been there many times,
and I think some of my friends told me,
and I remember, Malala,
or maybe me, right?
When the other one is there,
then it will be different.
I think if we can do it with a hackathon,
if we do engineering,
because we also do engineering.
Probably in China, but faster.
Absolutely.
Unfortunately, we start at 9 o'clock in the morning.
Now the question is,
why do you call?
In person, in person.
Yes, in person or also online,
around the heart.
Which is practical.
Now, if it's about,
let's say, more locally,
then I'll write it down,
because I don't know if there will be a possibility
of a hybrid,
also a day before,
because people are already a little confused.
We are with Maribor,
we have to move to Kranj.
But you probably have better results
if it's live.
I mean, like that.
It's a very interesting game.
Much more effective,
much more done online.
Really?
And much more fun live.
I can tell you this.
All my maltreatment,
we're not going to play it now,
we have a quiz now,
you can't listen.
That's how we were at the beginning,
when we talked about energy,
which is a real
day-to-day job,
and you're also...
My team is watching our interview.
No, but with a day-to-day job
as a developer,
you do a lot of things in a deep focus.
You plan,
you draw, you organize,
and then there's some execution.
And execution is important.
Now, if you have a routine,
to put yourself up,
on the other hand,
you have someone who is trying
to make you feel good.
You're in the beginning,
and in the end you're in the middle.
In the middle we were like
this, this, this, this.
No, we're going to...
Sorry to interrupt you,
but let's go to the next hour.
At nine o'clock.
Yes, at nine o'clock.
At nine o'clock I start shouting,
and then they tell me,
first coffee,
and then we start,
we lift everything
that is still a bit stuck.
Then we listen,
why is it a hackathon,
the manager then explains
the details of the challenge,
and what is very important,
what are all the connections with the challenge,
they have already tried,
and why it didn't work.
I told him that,
after one or two hackathons,
when it happened to us that the manager
at the end of the week said
OK, that's fine,
you're on a hackathon,
that young people are interested,
and it's OK again,
but in any case,
so that no one would say
why we didn't do it,
explain what you did and what didn't work,
why it didn't work,
so that the competitors get it.
Then we go a little,
and now I've already changed a little,
because I've already sent a video
for pre-preparation,
so that the competitors get it,
the team gets it,
then they need to give a fan name,
because the worst thing is
if the team is 1, 2, 3, 4,
and then you're Rata Špavla.
Name drop.
When you see such creativity,
what a name,
because today we had hundreds
in the future,
and all together there were some like that.
You see that people can do it,
and out of the box they will go,
because what is the purpose of an introductory work?
To prepare them as much as possible,
and tell them,
even if every day,
because a lot of the participants
at Hackathon are also representatives
of the company,
and then they are mixed in a group,
so that they understand
that this is really something different,
that not today, the day you say
it can be done, it can be done,
but that today, the day you say
it can be done, it can be done.
And then they sing about 12 songs,
this is a station,
always very good catering,
and then when he stands there,
because he is fired,
because people have different bio-rhythms,
and up to two are left alone,
because they need a little
brainstorming,
then my team,
what do you need,
how do we brainstorm,
how do we get to it,
and then listen to the first
notes of what would be solved
and give their views.
Mentors should also be prepared.
In this step, when
you need push from mentors,
from your team,
so that someone comes
with so much
ignorance, not the right word,
but to shock him so much
that he does not know.
In the first mentoring,
three, four teams,
what would you do?
Because for two or three hours
brainstorming is done,
the problem is that you know everything,
you still have to google a little,
what is, what is not,
but you know,
in the end, there is no idea
even in the evening,
most of the time it happens
that in two or three in the morning
come aha moments,
the night has this magical power,
and then when you try everything live,
then the teams are already a bit like this,
again a fun challenge,
again I hit a little on the shoulder,
but I had to shame something,
but we fight so much.
I evaluate what energy
and what would go to the audience.
Now we had, for example,
Jeopardy quiz, we died of laughter,
and so, mathematically,
I could give it to you to see what you know.
I did not know the question,
but I was very proud,
because I was waving in the back.
We know that it is not hackathon related,
directly,
because it is a little, you know,
the brains work a little,
we go up and down,
and so on,
but you know,
too much of this stress,
we have nothing yet,
and in this way it is also difficult to get to the solution,
they need a little,
then drink for an hour,
power nap, sleep under the table,
they go home to sleep,
and we really have to be all night.
It is important to change the whole team.
I do not know, in the morning in Bosnia,
now we need four more hours of time,
when we are, oops, overslept,
and we miss it.
No, when it's too busy,
you have nothing there.
So, a lot of independent work,
and constant rotation of mentors.
Teams.
A few times I mentioned teams.
How do you create teams?
How do you not create teams?
I do not create them
to give the same results.
Can it be with Lonely Wolf?
I always ask Lonely Wolf,
to get to know him.
Do you want a team this time?
Or do you have such limited time capacities
that you want to be Lonely Wolf?
This is the team with Paula.
Yes, this is Paula.
At the beginning,
as a participant,
I would like to explain
what your goals are.
Are they goals
that you will achieve on your own?
Are you able to
maybe now
look for a more business role?
Have you decided
that you will now develop
front-end or design?
It's a different role
for different goals.
People come to me
because they have
a business idea
and they would like to validate it.
Some people also want to present themselves
on the handbook.
I would like to work with them
and I am interested in what they are.
Some people come just for fun.
But creating a team
is a very important step.
Because if you choose a team
poorly, you can have problems.
I dedicate a lot of time to this.
This means
that you develop psychological profiles.
I don't develop psychological profiles.
I work in a different style
just to show them
how to work together optimally.
But I study a lot
what I wrote.
It is very important to me
that there are
as many different teams
with as many different views.
And if it is possible,
depending on the generation,
I try to bring
different generations together.
Because if you bring
different generations together,
it will take too long
for everyone to say
their opinion about everything.
If it doesn't work,
I go to a very wide
generational ladder.
The only similarities I look for
are in the generation.
Everything else is
a developer, a UX,
an artist,
so that the team has
as many different views.
As we had last weekend,
it was only for producers and engineers
who were 50-50 in the team.
That's it.
If we have only for developers,
then I look again
what I wrote.
There is a field
that I really like.
This field tells me a lot
about why I applied.
So that I can bring
similar motivation together.
So that I don't have to
go job hunting
because I know he will hang with mentors.
And I try
to bring them together
so that the team
will function
as fast as possible.
One great task
at a few of these events
was to prepare
each team
for an employee in the company.
If it's a big job,
if it's possible.
And today you have someone
who introduced the website
and you can ask him
and he goes to look at the data.
We have already tried this in the company.
Here you are.
No, no, no.
I will only follow what you said
with the question why.
What are the best guest answers?
There are 4 groups.
Treasure Hunters
because you also have
Serial Winners.
Pauli is also doing well.
These are the ones who will
go looking for awards.
Some are a bit shy.
No, no, no.
I will go for pizza and thank you for the award.
If you come here a lot
you get to know the system.
What are the things
you need to pay attention to
in order to win.
We have a lot of people
who have already won a lot of awards.
These are the ones
who know how to hack the system.
They know how to hack the system.
They know how it works.
But it's also true
that a few of these
have already failed
because the real projects
are being worked on.
They can't hack anymore
because it's the end of the project.
If I'm not wrong,
Treasure Hunters
come here to test
a new challenge
to see how far they can go.
Some of them like to test their own money.
Are they usually
students?
They are 63 years old.
You have a lot of time.
Students
and pensioners.
Everyone who has
a little time at their disposal.
No, everyone who has a will.
But most of the time
they are representatives
of startups
or students.
They are all students.
Indians.
Believe it or not,
they are all
competing
with older students.
At this point...
No, no, no, wait, wait.
Wait, wait.
Job hunters?
Now you two can ask
if they like it.
I will make an EPP at this point.
Do we have an EPP?
I forgot the jingle.
Everyone who listens to us
these people
support us on Patreon.
So if you subscribe to Patreon
you help us develop this project.
We also thank
the Human Frog company.
Today we were able to do this project.
And the Trifas company
that supports us.
And also you who listen to us
and follow us.
Subscribe so we can do this project.
That's the EPP.
I like it.
We also have a group on LinkedIn.
You can subscribe there.
I mean a group.
A page.
We are on all social channels.
On X.
On X we are not.
No, because someone took the handle.
Look, Sorči.
Ogrodje.ca
and the page where all the links are selected.
Anyway, that was the EPP.
I fully support.
Guys, do it all.
If a team does good things,
do it all.
Not because they surprised me today,
but because I've known them for a long time
and I'm a big fan.
Thank you.
We appreciate it.
One more thing,
because Jobhunter,
I didn't mention it.
They really want
to develop.
Maybe they will win
so that they will develop
this product with the company.
A winner is not necessarily
equally inspired by development.
That's the same.
That's why I also have in the public image
if you want further development for them.
Because I prepare candidates
over the weekend
if further development comes.
I always ask the winners
if they are still for it.
They say no.
This weekend we got it.
We care about it.
Another hackathon, another prize.
It can also be like that.
They say no, I'm not interested.
And then I ask the next ones
who are the most determined
and who want it.
They say yes.
And then we go forward
with the handbook.
Winners are not always
equally inspired by development.
You have competitors
who are inspired by development.
Paula managed to do something.
I would...
I think that
if you optimize everything
just to win
this prize
then you are involved
in a bunch of other things.
I would also
ask you
what are those things
that are
the most popular
in Delegions
and technical hackathons?
They don't wake up in the morning.
They come and sleep.
You see them
wearing hoodies
to the chin.
They have hands like this.
You know who came.
He came in the morning
because he had to.
Let's let him sleep.
The biggest obstacle
is that they don't listen to the handbook.
We had a team
in Benajstik
who came in the evening
and said
that the handbook doesn't make sense.
Respect.
The handbook knows
what it is made for.
It was healthy
but they still messed it up.
If you come to a hackathon
for an idea
it is out of the box.
You have to listen to it
to see what it really needs.
What it is really interested in.
And here,
in the introductory part
of the first mentoring,
because Delegions are so used
to being able to talk
to the handbook,
we have to know
that the corporation that gave the call
on Saturday
didn't think about it anymore
because they thought about it for a long time.
The call on Saturday morning
lasts for half a year, one year.
Which means that they really
need a solution for this problem.
They need a team that decides
that they really don't have
this problem.
I have a solution for you,
don't worry about anything else.
Until now, thank God,
we only had one team
in Benajstik
who came in the evening
and said that the handbook doesn't make sense.
This is practically
one of those
where I see that it takes a lot of time
for the team to decide
that they will be able
to transfer the handbook to someone else.
You won't.
If he decides in the morning
that this is a big problem,
try to solve this big problem.
I know that you came here
to have fun,
but it's okay.
Creators and so on.
Let me ask you this.
What comes next?
At the end,
slides, pitch,
prototype, MVP,
package?
Package, package, package.
I mean, at the end,
how do you package it
and present it?
Very real, very direct.
At the first five,
pitch.
Because, you know,
you can say this, you can say that,
and they can see that the mistakes were made.
What they wanted was told in the pitch.
That's why it's so important
that it's in the fifth minute.
Then, when we move away,
sometimes it happens
that it comes suddenly.
For me, this is not
in the first five
the best point.
For me, this four is so much better
because it has documentation in front of it.
That's why they give away the documentation.
They don't just give the pitch,
but also everything they worked on for the weekend.
Because, at the end,
wow, how many times it happens
that the first three places
are taken for granted.
You know, we don't have to, we don't know.
And then again, I'll be like,
wow, I swear I won't be paid for this MVP.
Can I say one more thing?
Okay, I think I was also there.
We had a problem
and there was a whole committee
for the trustee Triglav.
We couldn't decide between the first three.
And the committee accepted
that we would have twice the first place,
twice the second, and twice the third
because there were two challenges.
Hello? Yes!
You know, that's when I try to decide.
It's not easy to live in Larež, when the commission comes and says something about the closed door.
It's one thing, and then it starts, what is it for, what is it for, what do we need, what will it be like, what will it be like.
And with this commission circle, we are practically already talking about the implementation of the event.
What can we do in Pondelj?
How, for example, if you are looking for a technical solution, how is this technical action solution playing a role?
Because you can have a person who did not implement it technically, but how he imagined it, how he talked about it,
in which he chose the architecture, he is top.
He can win.
It is not necessary, it is absolutely desired, it absolutely conveys points,
but if something like you just said, that the whole structure and that he shows,
if I had one, if I could program this a little more today in the team, it would look like this,
and that the commission ignores, because it really is that the commission ignores what is happening.
Because what is the purpose of the fact that the competitors show,
my tool does this, so that the commission ignores what has already been said.
Because a lot of times it happens that when we try to train them,
the pitch must be really storytelling, really simple to say,
because the commission will not understand in the end.
So I like to say in a plastic way, I do not care which phone is ringing or not,
but when I accept it, he must do what I need.
And in such a way, the commission looks at the solutions of the participants.
It is the same with startups.
I am also talking about startups.
If you can explain in an easy-peasy way what you did, it does not matter.
You can sell without it.
Absolutely.
And that helps.
This display, that you have programmed something, it is very important.
Now, for example, when we have the New Age AI revolution,
I have had the opportunity to be in the role of a mentor,
I do not know, Hackathon, on the DragonHack in Ljubljana.
Top.
And the DragonHack team, why?
Well, they also do competitions here.
And they also listen to it.
Then shout out.
Do we have them?
Yes.
Also as competitors on our Hackathon.
They are top.
Excellent execution, really top prepared.
Half a year of preparation.
And they also win, I'll tell you.
They really know.
Yes, yes, yes.
Half a year of preparation, I think it was, if not more,
that they organized everything together.
And you thanked them nicely.
When you are in the log, on the other side, on Sunday,
when they come and tell you, I do not remember,
I think there will be, I do not know, 60 teams,
five people, or how many there were,
and they tell you, these are our criteria, these are the pitches,
you have an hour to look at it.
With a little too.
And then they will choose someone.
And then when you find out who is working on the other side,
because you also went through a few of those events,
you know, it's not easy.
But when you find out who is working on the other side,
because you also went through a few of those events,
it's stressful and extremely responsible.
So it's not an easy task.
But then you ask yourself again, in that interview,
what are the criteria by which we will choose.
And now we choose the most innovative,
how innovative we can definitely talk,
whether we will choose the most professional,
whether we will choose the most technical,
whether we will choose five awards for different things.
You know what, this is also, in fact,
now Dragonhack has a lot of different challenges
for different entrants, right?
So in that business you can have a little more flexibility
what is the same, what will prevail.
Because here, if there is one entrant,
this is what the commission must have clear.
Either we will finally award the most futuristic,
or we will finally award the most realistic for tomorrow's show.
But it must be in line with the title of Hackathon.
If the title of Hackathon is, we had,
for example, the market of the future,
then it cannot win something that can be in the market in the future.
Because it means that we are thinking about something that will happen,
and the competitors understood that.
That's what the commission needs.
You said the future,
and the competitors have developed futurism,
which means we evaluate futurism.
So the commission must,
and the mentors must understand what is the title,
what is the topic of Hackathon,
and what will be the criteria, what is that.
Everything is OK,
if tomorrow's implementation is the most necessary.
We just have to communicate this with the competitors on Saturday.
So that they understand that their out-of-the-box
is not the kind of out-of-the-box
that has to go a step forward tomorrow.
Here is another question,
maybe we could go a little further,
but how do you limit the set of technologies?
Do you limit this too?
Because, for example,
as I mentioned before,
in the age of AI,
whatever you come up with,
that pitch deck,
you can hire it,
or do whatever you want with it.
If you have a pitch deck,
you can probably determine how long it will take,
and then it will stop.
Then you can see quite quickly,
is this a real price,
will you pay for it or not.
That's exactly it.
It's true, isn't it?
Believe it or not,
when we get involved,
we see that you are in this world,
and I am in innovation,
and so on, and startups,
we all live in a bubble,
that everyone is using it.
You will be surprised
how little they are using yet.
We have already had a group,
which included 40 people,
two of whom raised their hand
to use ChatGPT once a week.
We have a bubble,
you guys are developing technologies,
and you are adopting trends
through startups,
and then you think,
I am the brightest person
in the world,
and sometimes I think,
look, this Saturday I had,
we gave a quiz,
and there was no rule
that you can't google us,
and I thought,
who the hell is asking,
there was no rule
that you can't know us.
Then there was that,
no one had installed it,
and then you are like,
what, you don't have it yet?
From Monday on,
it will help you a little.
I think the fact is,
that these technologies
are not yet so widely known,
widely used,
that people would adopt them,
that they would have to deal with it,
and we would say,
no, we are not working on it yet.
I think we are a year away
from that.
But you had,
for example,
Hackatonic,
which was a technical partner,
and Microsoft,
which I know was a partner.
Open Data Hackathon,
that's the big initiative of our country,
doesn't it have a nice connection
with our country?
It's a traditional idea.
It started in 2018,
I can tell you who,
Aleš Vešič.
I hope he will come,
we have already talked.
Aleš is so passionate about Open Data,
that he is for all the other issues.
And in 2018,
at the Ministry of the Interior,
for public administration,
sorry, pardon,
proposed an action
that more promotion should be done
in Open Data.
And every year,
another ministry is engaged
to give a call,
to open data,
and for young people to make
technological solutions.
And this is the only hackathon,
where all the competitors
in everyday life
are technological partners.
Can we name them?
I don't know,
you will know.
Microsoft said
go wild,
this is Azure,
what should be used.
If you have a technology,
and you can say,
I used 10% of the technology,
it doesn't matter.
If you have this,
this is ours,
give it full steam,
and go.
This is such a nice motivation,
that you will come to this,
Open Data.
Last year we had LAN,
it was wonderful.
There is a hackathon
on Open Data.
The ministry provides
the call and the data.
The Ministry for Public Administration,
now I think it's Digitalization,
I won't say it,
because the Ministry for Public Administration
and Digitalization,
they give awards.
Matejka,
the sponsor,
the one who pays for the production,
is another corporation.
All the technological partners,
Microsoft said,
GDI, Xlab, Comtrade,
I don't know,
it's wonderful to see
this cooperation and partnership.
Last year we had a nice event,
we celebrated Demence
with Roša.
These are the moments
when you deal with Open Data,
the data,
you see how many people
are supported by Demence,
because they all have one member in the family.
The most emotional hackathon
I've ever done in my life.
All the organizers,
all the technological partners,
everyone came up with the idea
and said we have it at home.
As you say,
good things happen.
The municipality of Kran
participated.
The question is
who will implement it next?
Of course,
they give awards,
the minister who has IPCC
and the famous agreement,
but they give the letter
that it's OK.
But the municipality of Kran
was the one
that started talking to the competitors
and started implementing
certain solutions,
because one of the challenges
is that on Open Data
all the solutions come to the table.
Who of you was there?
Did you work with Paolo?
Yes, I worked with him once.
He was on Open Data
when he came.
I got a letter from Japan.
Bravo to Italy.
Zoran Janković sent me a letter.
Nice.
And a train ride.
Are you going on a train ride?
I'm waiting for the right time
for you to tell me
where the train is.
Open Data is really nice.
Open Data is interesting.
Challenges are great,
but it's also interesting
that Aleš
is the base of open data
and he's like
I would like to have
this and that.
He also says
that all data
must be publicly available
according to a directive.
It doesn't always mean
that you have to have Excel,
but that you have to have
consistent data.
He also shows you
how to use open data.
Today you can develop
a lot of interesting products
if you know where the data is.
It's our duty
to emphasize that
if you need them,
you should tell them.
A little bit of criticism.
How does the state
know
how to make
these accesses?
It's not like they tell you
that this is FTP
where you will get
those CSVs,
but there are some
open API's
or
the other option is
that the state knows
how to classify the data
so that you can ask
what you can do with it.
Here we have the
Dump directive.
That's why you have Aleš.
Aleš Veršič,
who is a big fan of Dump.
A great example of this
is Pesek Pesluša.
Greetings to him.
His product
AutoLog
is from
the OpenData archive.
They started collecting data
in different formats
and they created
the AutoLog product
where you type in the address of a big car
and you get kilometers of technical
overview. If someone
reviewed the data on the car
you can see exactly who
reviewed it.
OpenData is used
to develop products
over OpenData and I think
this product is now integrated
in AMSS as well.
Such products are possible
and there are
at least 2-3 similar products
for similar development.
I think that's it.
You know all the bases.
You can tell everything.
For example,
you can see that someone
forgot the V8,
or they could fix it manually.
Something needs to be started.
Yes, something needs to be started.
This is important.
This is the real world.
If you work with a company,
they will give you everything.
You have an initiative,
you have a channel,
you can ask questions,
people will help you.
This is an additional value.
You can see the company from the inside.
For example, Petrol.
You wrote a blog.
Yes, that's right.
Can you say
that you forgot?
No, I forgot.
In the beginning,
you were not allowed to say
what you were doing.
I know him.
I explained everything to him.
You told me that one day
he made an ad for me.
He also wrote a blog.
No, that's not right.
You did a good job.
You have to learn PR.
You are the best.
You did a great job.
We don't have a budget for anything else.
I wanted to say something about Petrol.
It was interesting.
I don't remember
if I said it correctly,
but we always have
a page that comes to Petrol
in the office.
I say 3 minutes.
Or a minute and a half.
We would like to increase that time
to 3 minutes because it would mean
blah, blah, blah.
Then you start thinking
what could
develop in you.
Are there any other products
that would develop in you?
Is there anyone else who thinks
like you do about Petrol?
Corporate decision-making,
corporate design,
corporate recruiting,
corporate selection of technologies.
You can get insights
very quickly.
I think that
all corporations
or the customer
adapts to these steps
in time.
It's faster.
It's possible.
It's interesting.
If we do it in two days,
in the weekend,
then...
You come to the situation many times.
Especially if it's a company
that is doing it for the first time.
You already know
these things.
It's different.
If you say we will do it
in the summer,
do you have data about it?
Yes, we can fix it in the second week.
It's the fastest way.
But again, it's information.
Data exists.
You think about it later.
It's what we say.
You can think about it later
and you will see.
Plus or minus is OK.
You can say in the pitch
who has the data and
what is the functionality.
And they understand it.
In the beginning.
No, they don't understand it.
He can say one sentence
in which he doesn't know yet.
I see it as an event.
But if you are quick,
it doesn't end in a week.
Even if you didn't win.
Absolutely.
First, you meet
mentors.
You meet people
who are operative
or decision-makers.
With whom you can
build a network.
If you leave the team,
you establish a connection
with other teams.
You establish contacts.
After,
if you say you will develop
a new product,
why not call the one
you established a connection with?
It's important to cooperate.
So you can
benefit from it.
I've heard about it
with Pristop.
With that team we go there,
we go together,
we go to the city,
and that's it.
You've chosen everything.
I tried.
That's exactly what he said.
That's exactly it.
On Sunday evening,
whatever happens,
he has contacts,
he knows, he will develop something.
But not on a last-minute note
with brief young developers
to work.
You know?
Probably there are such
notes.
They are fully underrated.
That's it.
The eternal topic.
Everything is also not on those
Sundays.
But now,
the paper,
the PowerPoint, you have to bring it somewhere.
On Sunday evening,
Hurshka does his debriefing.
If you are lucky, you will talk
with the handbook.
You have to say what are the expectations today.
Will you be able to bring it today?
Will it be possible to use this technology today?
Before that,
engineering, business.
Will it be possible or not?
There is also a drawback.
If you are a student team,
you get such a gag.
For fun.
A reference
that you are 20 and
such a corporation trusted you.
I think it's pretty cool.
Definitely.
I've noticed
that, for example,
the number of Slovenian students
is much higher
than that of students.
The population is more like that.
In England, for example,
the population is much older.
Younger professionals.
Maybe they were also
more targeted.
Yes.
But it was,
I don't want to say more serious,
because you can't hear it right.
Yes, yes.
Business developers
and professional designers
from those companies.
Maybe they are targeted differently.
Maybe we are not so mature yet.
Or what?
Can we say
that you are a tattoo artist?
Yes, yes.
It depends on how much knowledge
and mileage the customer has.
If there is nothing,
you can't trust them.
I think it's important
to motivate and engage
with all due respect.
There are young people
who still want to prove themselves
in business,
and there are those
who already have a business
and come to compete
for a contract
with someone specific.
Contractors who work
in 2IN and Hackathon
and look for jobs
in junior and senior hackathons.
It has nothing to do with age,
but it has more to do
with the rank of the hackathon.
A contract requires a mileage.
And you have to know
that when you do it,
you have to implement it.
Here, when you go to a junior hackathon,
you can make sure
that you are up to the task.
When you say contract,
it goes beyond our capabilities.
We didn't quite understand
how to implement it.
When you work in a senior hackathon,
it's not really a question of age.
It's just about who will start
and with what age.
So you have these approaches.
I count and I hope
that Slovenian contractors
of this rank
are in the UK.
In the UK,
we have companies that have been
doing this for a long time.
In Slovenia and our region,
they are even more junior
when it comes to hackathons.
They have been doing it for a long time
and they have learned
what it means for them.
The UK is one of the first
in Europe to do it.
Hackathons came from the US
from 2000 years ago.
When the first typewriter
and the Internet became popular,
they started doing it.
It lasted.
Before that,
hardcore developers
brought it to business
product development.
It was a trend for us
about 5 years ago.
In 2017,
it was the biggest.
there were a lot of hackathons.
I've never heard
of such a craze.
It was a must.
I'm sure you've heard of it.
A lot has changed.
I'm sure you've seen it.
There are still people
who say
they want to do a hackathon.
What do we know about IZIL?
We have an app.
We've seen the chat GPT.
We'd like to use it.
We have a health database.
If anyone knows.
We'd like to do something.
Is IZIL good?
IZIL is good.
It's a great IZIL.
You have new tools.
You have new technology.
Domain knowledge is great.
Do you know
what marketing means
for a business?
Organizing for a business?
Motivating for a business?
Preparing for a league?
In the end,
it's all real.
I'm just saying.
Be professional about it.
It's important
to protect people.
Exactly.
Not all competitors
are as important
as a handkerchief.
A handkerchief has to understand that.
Let me tell you.
We have to make sure
that everyone is happy.
Not just one side.
If you do a hackathon
a little too easily.
We'll be at the event.
All of them are just students.
Opa, opa, opa, opa.
Don't be like that.
They are your future participants,
your future mentors,
your future performers.
Be respectful.
Even if they are young,
it seems to you that they will
transfer everything.
I would like to apologize.
Some wisdom.
When I was
in the mentor's vlog,
when I was in the mentor's vlog,
I saw what people
were preparing.
If someone tells me
that these young people are apathetic,
that they don't care about anything,
that they only like games,
that they only...
I didn't start with the ones
that showed up.
Simply, you don't know what you're talking about.
Exactly.
Don't look at them.
I agree.
And when people say
that we are not people,
that we don't get people.
Look, there was
a lot of young engineers
who were full of energy
for two or three days.
They were developing software,
hardware, AI,
electronics,
everything.
I think that
there is potential.
Maybe, as you said,
there are steps between
generations, between views,
between companies, between thoughts.
Between thoughts.
If we talk about young people,
that's one of the reasons
why I'm so loud.
Because we have a lot of young entrepreneurs.
We have some young people here.
We old people forget
that we were the same
with this attitude.
For our elders, we were all a bit like
Oh, you young people,
how many times have I heard that.
Because it's a generational leap.
It can't be different.
And I think that today,
young people, elders,
everyone,
the world is developing so fast.
I think that, sorry,
we are in a bubble.
I wouldn't be so young to say
that I would be a dinosaur
or a dinosaur, really.
And give me a chance.
I'm different.
I can contribute a lot.
They teach us things we don't know.
We are their mentors in other areas.
Not all gamers are apathetic.
We, young people,
weren't the biggest star
of everything our elders imagined.
Quite the opposite, I would say.
The only difference is
that today,
I always say,
because our elders
always do this.
We were able to do that.
And we said a lot of things
that we didn't even notice.
Let's thank each other for that.
Let's remember
what we did.
Now, social media,
schools, education,
that's why kids don't come home
and can't think of a conversation.
Not that I don't talk to them,
but we were called
to find out
what's going on in our lives.
Because our mom didn't know everything.
And what can you do on the next day?
I didn't look at the Internet
for that intelligence.
Now, it's all like that.
Eyeballing.
That's how it all goes.
They are a bit different.
Let's go back to the challenge.
They had to find each other.
They found each other,
but they didn't know
what to do.
Young people today
have so much knowledge.
They are marred with digitalization.
You know,
when we were born,
I remember
when we had one phone
in our apartment
and we ran to the door
and it was locked.
It's a different world.
They can teach us
what to do,
what not to do.
They are different.
We were different.
Our parents were different.
We have to realize
that it's all good.
Together we can do
amazing things,
even though we have
13-65 people in our team.
It's important to have a will
and a desire,
so we can communicate
with each other.
If you go into a room
and see that there are
20 people,
what are we going to do with them?
They probably have so many
smart things to say
that you just sit down
and your mouth falls down.
Young people are the law.
This is the question
I wanted to ask you before.
What kind of feedback
do you get
when people are sceptical
and go into a hackathon?
What is the message
in this message?
Maybe it's a product,
but how does it affect
the whole process
in the company?
Is it a transformation?
Is it a message
that even if we start
internal hackathons,
if we start people
in a way
that stimulates
thinking outside the box,
changing teams,
giving projects to other teams,
let's look at this.
Are there any positive effects
that a hackathon
can have?
Absolutely.
That was my aha moment.
As soon as I started,
I was confused.
Why do people only know me
through hackathons?
But then you embrace it.
When you see that
without a hackathon,
it's hard to get
to an aha moment
in such a short time.
When they see this energy,
their employees
are in teams and they come
and say how crazy it was,
young people are crazy,
we want this.
And then you think
how to implement it
and
many times it happens
that we put a new approach
to solving new projects
because we use it
for innovation.
We let people do
what they want
without thinking,
but if you have an idea,
we do internal hackathons.
We start with different departments
so that one gets
a different view,
and then they start
to understand why
I struggle with this image.
You have been struggling
with this image for 20 years,
and a 20-year-old man
didn't ask him why he is struggling.
He just works and knows
that he is doing well
because every hackathon
sends him an image.
Then they get together
and talk about
what they need.
We help them
because they can do something
and then we start to work.
That is why this phase
of long-term development
with hackathons is very important.
What do we do next?
We put young people in
and then,
in addition to the development
of the product,
we add skills of coaching.
From solving conflicts
to working in a team
in the ideal world
there is an end result,
an MVP who is hired
for long-term development
and someone
who shows
from the company's interest
that he would like to be an intern
if he wants to develop
the skills to become a system.
This goes on.
These are all the consequences
of hackathons,
of which nothing is known.
During the weekend
a lot of people write
how happy they were
and then they become an intern.
This is the magic
that happens
when the employee
wants a little more.
A smart employee
is driven by this.
This PR is just
a good side effect.
We always
explain in advance
the benefits.
When they see and hear this,
they are a little skeptical
because they don't know
that it is possible with one hackathon.
One hackathon?
Wouldn't it be enough
for a couple of months?
No, one hackathon is enough.
Two days.
You will all think
that you have been
an intern for two months.
You are so tense
and you help so many people
and you are responsible.
They are also skeptical.
How is it usually
when an employee
steps out of the booth
and you tell him
that there is
some kind of engagement
that he can enjoy
with some resources and people.
We don't have these people.
We have employees.
We don't have to spend so much time
waiting for you to come
and say that it is all for you.
Can I
to be time cautious
upgrade Andraž's question?
Go ahead.
I don't know why
we have to orientate
over time.
It is Jan's fourth
shoot today and
he has to go to bed.
He could have put a microphone.
No, I am kidding.
I would upgrade him.
Considering that today
we are at the interagency
board meeting.
It is a meeting about entrepreneurship
and everything.
Tell us
in this context
what do you want
Slovenian entrepreneurs
to be able to do more
so that they don't fall asleep.
Why do they fall asleep?
Give us that.
Why do you
want to innovate?
I was hoping
that you would bring your gadget
and show it.
I don't know if you have it.
Nokia?
I don't know if I have it in my backpack.
I always bring Nokia with me.
Give us
that.
What do we want?
Dignity and freedom.
I don't know if all companies
want something else,
but 10% of their time
is wasted.
If you say
that we will do coaching
and time management,
we will find food for thought.
We have so much time
on our hands
that if we can
come to a couple of hours
a week,
you don't know
what will happen next.
Why did we start with Nokia?
I know it's a bad case.
It's bad for us.
Nokia died,
but Nokia had
a reputation in the world.
I didn't think
anything could happen to it.
I'm sorry,
95% of the market still works like this.
Who can't change anything?
They didn't understand
the speed, development,
desire and need of the user.
We are changing.
The world is changing.
Young people are becoming buyers.
Those young people
will dictate our products
for five years from now.
If we get old,
everything on paper
and Excel,
it's not up to you.
Why would anyone still work
with these machines and Excel?
We need to be patient
for a certain percentage of the time
and try to learn
from people
where we have problems.
We should always
work with people with ideas.
Something happened
in a person's history
within a corporation.
He came once with a proposal,
another time,
and I told him to do
what he was supposed to do.
We need to support
such people.
I always say
that there are
no stupid ideas,
no stupid questions,
no stupid days.
It's all about
what will happen next.
That's how
everyone started with innovation.
If everyone reduced
what exists today
and what can't be done,
we need to be patient
that it's okay
to try and fail.
We need to know
that we shouldn't
always innovate
something disruptive
that doesn't exist yet.
Every company
has so many areas
that can be uplifted
and made a bit more competitive.
We need to save time
and it's often
so fast and dynamic
that we need to do it.
In the past,
companies were made
for 50, 60, 70 years.
Today, a company's life cycle
can be only 5-7 years.
Technology and manpower
have changed us so much.
Even the older generation
doesn't understand
how to fight
for things
that need to be done.
You can't watch TV
10 years old
without pictures
for your TV show.
You can't.
If you think
that you don't need it,
you're wrong.
We need to be
very demanding
to our users.
When we work in our companies,
we think that no one
is demanding
to themselves and their companies.
The world is changing.
Why do banks
and hackers
work so much?
They know that the world
is changing so much
that they don't know
what will happen.
Look at the young people
and the revolution.
The young people will
start a company
in two years.
We, as a demanding user,
and the young people
who are at their peak.
The 30-year-old
is already a manager,
a millionaire,
but he is demanding.
He wants things
to be like this.
We need to be a little bit more
diligent.
We can't be dumb and stupid
because it's fun.
Innovation is created
at 4 p.m. on Friday
with the same enthusiasm.
If someone comes
with an idea,
first of all,
we need to
think about
how to succeed.
We don't have time for that.
It has nothing to do with it.
We need to change the rhetoric.
What should we do?
When we adopt this rhetoric
on a daily basis,
you ask,
what else do you have?
What if you succeed?
What else do you have?
Let's start this conversation
that doesn't hurt.
In this way,
we prepare our company
to have a long future.
The world is small today.
You work in Austria.
A little in Austria,
a little in Japan,
a little in America.
We are lucky
that we got
somewhere in the world.
In the whole world.
Between Japan and America.
Andras,
the last question.
Jan,
your best shot.
You always give me
the last question
because I don't have a question.
42.
Your last answer
was a good one.
A good conclusion.
Unless you would like
to add something.
If we talk about
corporate transformation,
is it true?
We just touched on hackathons.
It was there at the beginning.
Then he said,
if we only talk about hackathons,
do we have enough?
I said, yes.
If you catch me with time,
I will say now.
Do you have enough
participants in hackathons?
Do you have enough companies
to organize them?
If you are a member of one
or another group,
where can you find
contact to you?
On all social networks
I hit.
I don't write posts.
I am often asked
to write nice posts.
Last night
I replied to her e-mail.
Should I say it?
Urska Afna.
The complicated part.
Transformation-lighthouse.com
Transformati on
minus lighthouse
H O U S E
There will be a link.
Under the episode description.
At this point,
Urska, thank you very much
for taking the time to be here.
Andraž, thank you.
Jan, the team, thank you very much
for your help.
Subscribe, give us feedback.
See you next time.
Bye!