Let's start with the episode in Grodno again, with the 24th attempt to make a good analysis of technology,
development, technical culture, everything that is connected here, everything that is balanced.
And today we will try...
At first I thought we would talk about some side projects, about how people start their small projects,
and those projects grow and grow and grow.
And I thought this would be a good start, and then Luka would get in, and then I started looking for who Luka Renko is,
and what he did, and when I started looking for him, I realized that maybe...
Especially after you sent me an email, I realized that maybe this is not the best.
My side project is not a side project.
Well, I went to look at your github, but...
Anyway, we have prepared together this...
How do I say this...
NIT, and we will try here today to talk a little about how...
Well, maybe a little more about bigger projects,
that we will talk a little about investing in those bigger projects,
we will talk a little about the technological ecosystem that is needed for this,
what else did he add...
We have some sweet sources.
Of course, we will also talk in the follow-up, but very briefly, because I think...
In the follow-up, we will talk, we will listen, yes.
Now, I didn't want to dedicate the whole episode to the follow-up, because I don't have much to say about it.
I've already said it five times.
But the rest of what you say is also very impressive,
and that's why we invited you today, so you can say something.
And yes, we know that today you are selling a ship.
At the beginning, you told us about the podcast, or about the YouTube video,
there is a link to support, where you can support us,
and you will also help us in the future.
You will start with the first question, right?
Yes, I will.
Wait, let me take it out.
Suspense.
Now I will be like an old gentleman, who will have a...
You will be a good businessman.
Yes.
Wait, I have to correct myself a little, but...
Wait, yes.
Here, as a first...
It's simple, right?
Luka, how do you see yourself?
Because when we were preparing for the episode,
or when we accepted you,
you are a man of many images,
or when you are at Jadarnica,
when you receive various awards on behalf of the community,
which is building wonderful projects.
But how do you see yourself? Who are you?
I see myself as someone who has successfully built teams,
developed teams.
I did that a few times in my career,
and I really enjoyed it.
Building teams, building successors,
successful managers, new leaders, and so on.
After Outfit7, I decided that I would not go
into that rollercoaster,
a scale-up company, once again.
I would not go if there was not a really good idea,
which would motivate me to work.
I decided what I would start with.
One of the tasks was that I wanted to return to the environment
in which I grew up.
That is the part where I started investing,
where Silicon Garden is being built,
where we try to help local startups,
especially in the phase where it is the most difficult
to get capital at the moment.
That is the early stage,
where the developers are not interested yet.
They do not have the basic validation yet.
We, the locals, know these people better,
we know what they are capable of,
and what results can be achieved.
The other thing I wanted to protect
was working with people.
That is why I decided to do coaching.
In a similar way I was working with my manager.
I do it without any methodology.
When I work with a few people,
I have four managers at the moment,
out of two companies there are a lot of people
who are changing.
I work with them weekly,
and that is my stick,
where I help these people build themselves
to the next level.
I deal with their challenges,
their individuality, and so on.
One thing I found out is that I was lucky in my career.
I had a few managers who were pen and desk,
but they were very persistent,
and they gave me a lot.
I came across some challenges
that I did not even think about.
I was an engineer,
I worked in development,
and through the process I realized
that I am more interested in other things.
That is how I work.
Can you say that as a single contributor
you cannot go back as much?
I worked as a team,
so my projects were always team projects,
my whole professional life.
They were not one-man jobs
from the first project.
I realized that.
On the other hand,
you have to take more responsibility,
and you have to take responsibility for others.
That was one of the things
that my first manager, Andrej Kuščar,
made me struggle for a year or two.
He said to me,
you can work for three,
but you cannot scale anymore.
You have to start helping.
I had no time,
but I had to do it.
Those were hard lessons
that I experienced and changed.
Over time, I realized that other things
were also important for me.
I wanted to ask you
about investment.
You started talking about management.
Is good management in Slovenia
something that you can learn
in college or school,
or do you have to have some predispositions?
Are we good managers in Slovenia?
Do we have good material to become good managers?
I think we have good material,
as long as we have people who want to learn
and work on themselves.
Once you become a better manager,
you can start changing other people.
You can lead and be a good leader.
I think we have to realize
that good management can happen
in companies with good culture.
You have to have an environment
where the culture is good,
healthy, open, trustworthy.
That's where good management can come in.
You can have managers, MBAs,
who come in and do hard shots
in a certain environment,
but I believe they are proper leaders
in a product company
that you want to succeed in.
You said that you have to work on yourself.
What do you mean by that?
You have to realize your own limitations,
your own fears,
your own subconscious problems
that limit you in thinking.
You have to realize
that you can't work with people
who are more compatible with you.
As a manager, you work with different people.
People have different value systems.
You can't work with them,
so you have to adjust your communication
so that you can replace them.
I think all these tasks are important.
If you don't start working on yourself
to adapt to certain limitations,
it will be easier for me to work this way.
When I managed other managers,
I managed a lot of things.
I noticed this when I wanted to hire someone.
A psychologist who was part of the hiring process
for someone I worked with for four years
said that he wouldn't fit in our culture.
I said, how can I not know him?
He said he was looking for a competitor.
There is a very rough culture in Outfit.
People expect to fight for their decisions,
and so on.
He said he was looking for a competitor.
I thought back and said,
yes!
When I hired him,
I worked with other managers a lot.
I was a micro-manager,
so I was interested.
I wanted to know what it was like.
I wasn't delegating responsibilities
but I was looking around.
People thought I was looking for a competitor.
Suddenly you realize
that everything is going through your hands.
I had a similar experience later on.
I adjusted to these people.
He had a good approach.
He is a leader today.
I think he has about 60 people in the company.
I think we can do better than that.
I wouldn't fit into the culture we had.
We have a more technical audience here.
Most of them are developers and engineers.
To some extent,
a lot of people work as juniors or seniors.
At some point,
most organizations expect you to become a team leader.
Or a squad leader.
At some point,
you become a manager.
Then you have to decide
if you want to focus on engineering
or manage people.
At some point, it was the same for you.
Yes, it was the same for me.
At Herman Soft Lab,
we struggled a lot.
In the beginning,
it was easier to have a managerial career.
It was a digital agency company
where there were project managers.
It was easier to show responsibility
that you have 10 people.
Then we managed to reach an agreement
in the recording system
that you can become a senior manager
or even more.
At Herman Soft Lab,
I made my first career to the top engineering level.
I was chief technology for the entire area,
but I didn't have a sub-manager.
I wasn't a team manager.
Then I decided
that I wanted to do something else
and I started working as a manager
for the entire business unit.
I am responsible for the fact
that engineering has to be
balanced with management.
In real companies,
they have a level of chief,
when they are at the level of senior VP.
In Slovenia,
there are not many companies
that have such a need.
Someone at this level
is at the top in the world.
I don't have the same expectations
that everyone has to be at the top.
I see management in many nuances.
We have a lot of
imagined thinking
about what a manager should be like.
We imagine that we need a manager
of this team and what it should be like.
People are very different.
They need more things
and maybe they will not be satisfied
only with team management.
I think that the organization
should adapt to the people it has.
Create a structure that is ideal
with the people you have at the moment
and fulfill these roles.
A role is a team manager.
A team manager is a person
who cares about his career path,
his next steps and so on.
On the other hand,
you have other managerial roles.
A technology leader,
a development leader in a field,
on a component, on a back-end, etc.
This person is also a team manager.
I see it as a role.
Phew, that was a good warm-up.
Will you continue?
We are shocked.
I mean, are we?
Talk like a classic manager.
I would like to.
The structure of the company
is a bit stupid.
It seems to me that we often copy
from a larger environment
and then try to copy it
to a smaller environment or to Slovenia.
In the end, we come to the conclusion
that technologically we all need Kubernetes
or the management of some teams.
They are not relevant.
My experience is primarily
in the scale of the company.
The company grows fast.
I don't have myself for a startup.
If I had a startup,
I don't know how I would do it.
I would say that I was the first person
who prepared for the next level.
I worked on a product,
a backup product.
I grew from a team of 12 people
to 150 people who developed
and supported the product.
I didn't have the experience,
but I see myself as a scale-up manager.
In this scale-up mode,
a lot of companies forgot
where they are and why they are successful.
Do you mean culturally?
Culturally, yes.
When a company grows,
founders have to delegate.
They don't ask themselves
what made them successful.
What are the strong values
they lived by in the first year.
What do they have to protect from this?
Can I ask you this?
Our guests before you
talked a lot about values.
Can you give us a few values
that seem very important to you?
Give us a few plastic examples.
What do you mean by values?
Values mean something
for the mentality of the company.
Let's talk about Outfit7.
We thought about it a lot.
We brainwashed people.
My experience with HMSoftLab is that
on the one hand,
we are not in the middle.
On the other hand,
we have a very strict culture in certain areas.
In my career,
we have a very strong culture.
We have a very good teamwork.
It was very important for us
to work well together.
The team is more than just an individual.
I didn't realize it until I went out.
Because it's a different environment.
People who went out
have a different attitude.
In Outfit7, we had specific tasks
that we gave.
One of the most important ones was No Limits.
It was a thing that said
that we shouldn't limit ourselves.
We shouldn't limit ourselves in our thinking.
Because the possibilities are limitless.
What can we do?
If you limit yourself in the beginning,
your goal becomes low,
and then you are satisfied with it.
From what I learned,
you can always go higher.
I can tell you an anecdote.
My previous manager always said
that he didn't like me because I was too ambitious.
I always said, no, you are too ambitious.
When you see that someone
gives you the opportunity
to go one step further...
That's not a bad word.
You can be unrealistically ambitious
and give people unreal goals.
You can also disappoint them.
Sure, but those goals must be something
that you want to achieve.
And even if you don't achieve them,
you have to ask yourself why.
They had to be on the reach.
There were failures.
But if you don't limit yourself in the beginning,
if you don't limit yourself in the beginning,
then...
For example, we worked on No Limits
and two teams appeared on the project.
We worked on No Game.
It was a team of 20-40 people.
Then VFX Artist started to doubt something
and started talking to QA Lead.
They started to say,
if this mechanic still works,
and so on.
These are doubts, fears.
Art comes to you quickly.
You have to know if it's worth it to work so hard.
And in that moment,
we quickly decided to go together
and discuss what worries us.
Why are these doubts?
Why do we think it won't happen?
Let's get rid of these fears.
Let's see and discuss.
This is very natural.
We don't limit our ambitions.
Can I ask you one more question?
I recently talked to some members
and they said that we want to...
Especially big and older organizations
have a hard time with innovations.
One of the reasons they called him
is because they lost the feeling
that you can fail.
It has to be in the culture
that we will try,
and if it doesn't work,
we will do something else.
Can you tell us how you do it?
Failure is acceptable and we will all learn.
I had big failures on Outfit.
Million-dollar failures.
We invested in a new game mechanic,
a multiplayer mechanic,
a new brand, a big launch,
and it just didn't work.
For a game that was tested on the internet
by 200 people, it showed the best engagement.
We haven't had such engagement on any other game.
You get a lot of pressure,
you get disappointed,
because of your own feelings.
It's hard if it's a failure.
We tried a few more things
until we finally trusted the product.
It's a big investment,
and you can't believe that someone
who puts so much energy into it,
just doesn't accept it.
On the other hand,
you put it on the side,
because you need to catch up in 2-3 years.
That's your survival.
If you don't succeed in 2-3 years,
how much freedom do you have
to maintain your competitiveness?
It's like content creation.
If every episode was like nothing,
I don't know where we would be.
Before we talked about some values,
I always wondered,
I think that my circle of people
and acquaintances,
we're all technical perfectionists.
We're real, we work on the market,
we're not academics,
we still have to work,
but technical expertise is important to us.
You meet people in your career,
and they say,
it's good that you have all that knowledge,
but try to be as scrappy as possible.
It's not 100% good,
because perfectionists can't be better.
80% is something I would do,
and you say, let's do this.
Then there are some values,
which are more scrappy,
but if it doesn't work,
how do you look at it?
I think that most start-ups
are in a scrappy mode.
The faster you can get to a prototype,
MVP or whatever,
and get some confirmation,
some feedback,
so I was in the same situation.
In the beginning, I was thinking about another abstraction layer, just in case, if I were to change the base or something like that.
Then I learned a lot that this would only complicate refactoring in the future.
It would be much easier to change the base and everything around it.
I was very pragmatic about it.
Outfit culture itself was completely scrappy from that point of view.
He is responsible, quick and dirty, make it work.
We will fix it when we succeed, we will fix it on a certain level.
Is it the same when you mentioned scale-up?
Does that mean that when you get to the phase where you realize that you are interested,
is it then the time to go in that direction?
Yes, I think that's how he called me.
When he was alone, we knew each other from high school, because he was still in elementary school.
But when he was 15 years old, I didn't have any contact with him.
Then he pinged me on e-mail, I would like to scale-up a company, etc.
Would you like to come and take over as a VP of Engineering Technologies?
I said to him, I'm not interested.
I said, I'm really into software.
I did backup recovery systems, archiving and so on.
What are you, a cat?
First of all, I never played games.
Me neither.
I've never been in that space.
I'm just a meme.
But I said, let's listen to each other.
I'm just interested in the whole story and so on.
But he just presented the story to me again.
The problem is that he has it.
The company will now have to grow.
We have to do it at the next level.
He needs someone who has international experience.
He has experience in building teams.
When I came, there were 10 people.
Founders, two animation students, an office manager and so on.
A very small team.
We knew how to sell.
We knew how to sell the story.
For example, Google App Engine sales.
We had it on the back-end.
It was so well released.
He made a stream for the game again.
It was interesting for me.
To see such a project.
To go a little further.
Actually, I fell on the back-end.
In the final phase.
In that story.
And to go back to international.
I was on some projects that did not develop so quickly.
And I regret it a little.
Will you ask any more questions?
Or try to get more investment in the world?
Yes.
I would like to move on.
Because
These things are all very interesting.
Because of our sponsors.
Because they are our contemporaries.
I would like to be younger.
This is definitely very interesting to me.
Time is limited.
We will try to connect everything somehow.
Try to tell us a little more.
What does the other part of your description do?
Coaching investor.
Can you tell us
For laymen.
For beginners.
So that we all understand.
What is this discipline?
What is this investment?
What are we investing in?
When you make an exit.
Slovenia is already
Some IT firm.
Made exits.
Sizable exits.
One thing.
That was probably it.
That I actually had some money.
That I got with the exit.
With which I did not deal.
I was lying on the account and I did not know what.
What.
Now a little gambling.
Then bitcoin.
I did not deal with it.
I did not want to trust it.
I needed an exit from the company.
Also because I started to understand.
What do I want to do with it.
So part of the investment.
For me is also that.
The funds I made there.
I incorporate them.
I invest them in some projects that I think are important.
I support some projects that are important.
And in the final phase.
I also protect them to some extent.
I do not lose them.
I assume that looking at your background.
You also understand them well.
All right.
I do not.
My investment is not something that is very close to me.
I have to say.
I was also in the investment committee.
Maybe a devil's advocate.
Someone who challenges for devs.
I could not get the most hype.
I could not know.
What is the next trend.
Maybe.
I have seen some feelings.
I know very well about the team.
I know well.
Will the team work together?
Is it complementary?
Do we have the right energy?
I know that.
I think it is a good assessment.
I often look at it.
The Silicon Garden is a company.
We are founders.
We made exits.
People we worked with.
When we got some capital.
We collected together.
Approximately 6 million funds.
From 25 individuals.
We started to invest ourselves.
Not everyone works alone.
We distributed the funds.
We set up a structure.
We started to invest in the Slovenian community.
From our networks.
Slovenians are also auto-innovators.
We have networks with them.
And so on.
To be healthy.
On the one hand,
it gave me a sense of what is happening.
I am not in technology anymore.
It gives me a lot.
On the other hand,
I think that
we should try to help.
And in the end,
we hope to make some good exits.
Some good stories.
Some next outfits.
And in the end,
we deserve it.
The idea is to have a good return.
My question is
about
the investment
in Silicon Gardens.
At what stage
does Silicon Gardens help companies?
Can you briefly tell us
what are the rounds of investment?
I think a lot of people don't understand
how it works.
It's an exit.
It doesn't mean you run away from the company.
You can explain the terminology.
I'm not the best at explaining it.
Basically,
it's like this.
You can create a startup,
and you invest
on your own.
You come to your funds on your own.
So, I would eat some money,
and then...
Outfit7 was created
without any capital.
It's a company
that came to its first hit
with its own funds.
It's a company
that came to its first hit
with its own funds.
From that point of view,
it's an ideal outcome.
You create a business
that has a side.
It's on the market.
It has a healthy growth
in the background.
You don't need
daily capital.
Not everyone is in that position.
Not everyone has 300 euros
to finance half a year,
or a couple of friends
to do it.
In that case,
you need
family, friends, and fools.
They are probably the first ones.
Friends, family,
or something
like that.
Something from NASA
for such a gamble.
You need to invest them.
They believe in your idea,
and they give you money
to do something for them.
That's the angel round.
They come in healthy.
If it's 10 euros,
if it's 50,
I don't know.
Then there are
Silicon Gardens
that are early stage.
Early stage means
that they are startups
that don't have a product yet.
They may have a prototype,
an idea.
We invest in people
that we believe have potential.
Whether the idea is good,
whether the team is good,
whether the founders have a drive
and are strong enough
to believe in that story.
Whether we know them well,
because they are former employees
of our networks,
and we know exactly what
these people are capable of.
You want to support them.
It's like a lottery ticket
and you simply give them money.
We at Silicon Gardens
invest in startups
from 100,000 euros
to half a million.
We let them invest in one startup
for half a million.
We have distributed 6 million funds
over 5 years.
We are going into the last year
and we are preparing a new stock.
We are planning a 30 million stock
and we will focus
on the wider region.
Founders and investors
from Croatia and Serbia
would invest in us.
We want to expand our network.
But in the same style.
Founders for founders.
We believe
that we as founders,
managers and successful startups
can help the world
and feed ourselves.
I have to ask you
specifically
about the audience.
About the audience.
Easy, you got it wrong.
You are our fan
so you probably listened to everything.
My question is
what kind of money
do you transfer
to the company
you invest in?
The most
is that we can
help them.
We have different
profiles of people
who can help.
We have people who are
really good at
marketing, e-commerce
and so on.
App development
and on the other hand
distribution,
and so on.
We can help founders.
Can I
ask you
one more thing.
Do you get
paid?
Yes.
Does that mean you add
someone for the job?
No, founders are
like a supervisory board.
It's more like an advisory board.
It's someone who prepares
the company.
There is always someone
in charge
for every startup.
He prepares the startup.
And then that person
calls other investors.
Not only those who work
in the investment committee.
Can you,
when you have experience
in aerospace and so on,
can you connect with him
and so on.
Also the network
is extremely powerful.
Also the experience.
Jugoslav Petković
who went through the investment rounds
with TUI Miskladi or
Manta or Outbrain.
They have experience
with TUI Miskladi
and how to prepare for the next round.
So you need
a million-dollar investment
instead of 100,000 euros.
If we take
I am
an ambitious, full eager
person or I have a small
team.
Maybe we already have a product.
Maybe we put it on the market,
we didn't put it on the market.
For example, let's say we are chosen.
From 100,000 to
500,000 euros,
we often get 5,000,
if I understand correctly.
It covers the fact that
you can
hire the right person,
because we are running out of time.
We put it aside and
try to move it to a new phase.
For example,
in the next phase
we won't be able to
exit yet,
but we can get
the next round of investment.
Yes, that's right.
When you
put the stocks in,
the stocks need to be
installed with a timer.
That needs to be done.
That's a good question.
Why are there versions 1, 2, 3?
Investors who
have entered the stock market
have entered into some conditions.
These conditions are
that the stock will receive
the capital from investors,
which will be paid
in 5 years, in some tranches.
This is when the stock
needs money,
or a year in advance.
Let's say
the stock
in Silicon Gardens 2
is installed with a timer
for 5 years of investment,
5 years of exit
or monetization,
plus 2 years
of extension
for start-ups with additional potential,
or are just about to exit,
and it would be worth waiting.
What does this mean in practice?
If you have
investors inside,
if you have
friends, family and fools,
they probably won't expect
to get their money back in 10 years.
Mom will probably be happy
to have a job.
And she will be worried
about those 10 euros.
If you have
investors inside,
they are there
to have a financial outcome.
This is why
they will encourage you
to stay in the market
as long as possible.
Ideally,
with the first investment,
you are successful.
How successful can you be
if you are just struggling?
Maybe one round is enough
to make you successful in the market.
You start to have some income.
Maybe you can finance it
with a small loan.
Maybe it's easier
to look for investors
for the next round.
What does it mean to be a successful investor?
Do you sell the company
or do you work for a company
or do you just have
a constant influx?
As I said, it depends
on the time.
They actually leave the company.
You can leave it in many ways.
One way is to go to the stock market
and get an IPO,
the initial public offering,
and leave the stock market.
You have already sold the company.
Another option is
to get a new investor
who has brought
your startup to a certain level.
They invest in the company.
When they invest,
they give 3 million.
Of these 3 million,
2 million goes to the company
for a long-term growth.
1 million is collected
by the previous investors.
That's how it works.
The previous investors pay.
Yes, they pay.
If you are under pressure
from certain circumstances,
it's a mistake.
Generally speaking,
what are the expectations?
In most startups,
you expect
1 out of 10 investments
to be successful.
They will do x10
and you will cover
everything else.
Then there will be a few startups
that will succeed,
x2, x3, x4,
and some will probably
go bankrupt.
You will not be able to return
the investments.
You need to calculate
the numbers.
You can't invest in stocks with that.
When you are in a stock market,
you have to invest in everything.
You have to have a certain
return.
You want a certain return,
but there is also a risk
in investing.
You don't invest in state bonds
or coins.
You need to get a new partner
for every investment.
If you are a founder,
you need a new partner.
They have new knowledge,
new thinking,
new appetites,
and you will have to deal
with them in the future.
That means that
on the roadmap
or on a plan
if you want to invest
in a company,
you will have an impact.
Definitely.
If a company takes
capital from you,
does that mean
that they have to propose
a plan of what to do?
Do you put it on a roadmap
or on a projection?
No, they don't recommend
any goals.
Some investors
or even more investors
in a company
take the lead role.
They are more active
with management
and founders,
and others support them.
Otherwise,
30 years later,
everyone has their own vision
of what founders should do.
You have someone
who is a lead investor
and a new round is coming.
Investors in previous rounds
are very much on the side.
You are more or less following
and you expect that those who are new
will be the ones to take the lead.
They will be the founders.
For example,
we help a lot with product management,
but when it comes to
organizing markets,
scaling,
and so on,
a different company can
achieve much more.
It has a lot of potential.
Speaking of investing,
we skipped
all the questions we had.
I would like to ask
what happens
when a company grows
and invests in a market
and we don't have an answer.
Everyone pays.
Was that a good answer?
I think it was good.
What interests me more
is what Silicon Gardens
is looking for.
We have a lot of stocks
and all of them
differ a lot.
One thing is definitely
regionality and the network.
You get to know people
you invest in regionally.
You don't have a local
scout
that you put on the
website or comment.
What are the other things
that you invest in?
You invest in things
that you will get to know.
We know software for service,
we know app businesses,
we know ad tech businesses,
we know e-commerce
and so on.
We know brand building
in the final phase.
You will always have
more potential for knowledge
and you will see your bias.
You have to be careful
not to let that bias overwhelm you.
You think you represent it
and because you do,
it seems more real to you.
That is a part of the problem.
DNA of the people
who do the scouts
and us on the investment committee
is definitely known
in decision making.
You can learn from that.
You can learn from those skills
and you can't rely on them.
You mentioned industry,
but on your website
it says
that you are looking for
proven market traction.
Can you tell us
what that means?
I can tell you
about BirdBuddy.
BirdBuddy.
I know one of the co-founders,
he is a product manager
at Outfit.
You know what kind of person he is
and what you can expect from him.
When you came up with that idea,
people in France
came to us
to ask if we would do
a Kickstarter campaign.
Kickstarter, Kickstarter,
it doesn't sound good.
But after you showed us
what you have done,
in the sense that
you made a whole web presence,
this product already exists,
that you got credit cards
from people
and people already bought it,
and you made a campaign
where you evaluated
how much the campaign would cost,
and that there were paying users
who gave you a credit card
for which you said
sorry, we don't have that yet,
and you made a cancellation,
but you validated
that the market exists for that.
You know,
you haven't done anything like that before.
You know, it was just an idea
and it wasn't
a photoshopped picture.
But it's very unimportant.
Unimportant with the methodology
of advertising campaigns
on Facebook,
how much we will pay for them,
what will be the price,
and so on.
And when someone brings it to you,
and you say, hey,
let's give them 50-100 euros
to make a Kickstarter campaign,
a good promotion,
if they worked so hard for this,
it's worth supporting.
And so maybe we invested
more because of the traction
and because it's a lifestyle business.
It's a good business for some people,
but it's hard to sell it.
It's hard to scale it to a certain level
because we brought it with us
or with a software,
or with hardware.
But they showed
that they have the idea,
and we believed in it.
We didn't prepare it
because of how much they believed
in the market,
in the enthusiasts,
and so on.
And then they proved
that it's worth it.
Maybe we believed in it at the beginning.
BirdBuddy is an amazing story.
I saw
a real-time feed
where you can
turn on the cameras
and they send back the footage,
and in real-time you see the birds from all over the world.
You can also see
other cameras and birds.
It's really interesting
how they managed
to create such a global brand.
It's really fascinating.
It's the best thing ever.
That's an example
of an atypical startup.
It is not a typical startup for investing in VC, which has proven its worth over time, but Traction showed you how to do it on paper.
And they validated it with credit cards.
No, we made a flyer, and there are some enthusiasts on Facebook, they talk a lot about it.
How many of those cards did you pull? That's the question.
Now I turned it to the side, so we don't make a mess.
Homemade water from a pipe, that's not good.
That's the stuff we have.
The stuff we have.
Here I have two questions, let's go to the last one in this pile.
Can you tell us what is the biggest difference between the Silicon Gardens and the Slovenian business complex?
Can you tell us that?
I am also the type of person who wants to invest in a lot, so I got involved in the business angels.
I once went as a trainer to this business complex to get to know it a bit.
The difference I see is what you actually want as a return.
And now, like in the Slovenian business complex, they invest money in the market.
They don't look at the exit as an outcome, they invest money in a certain environment.
I noticed that in this assessment, a lifestyle business is supported very quickly.
The idea is great, but then you ask yourself, what is a lifestyle business?
That means that you see that this can be done by a founder and two more people will survive.
Great.
And now, if it is supported, two people make a local business out of it,
they survive, they have a solidly paid service and so on, and a sustainable business, nothing bad.
For a company, this is not enough.
And I think that is one of the biggest differences.
Now, for example, a business company has the idea that if you find a foreign investor,
they will add a combination.
I don't agree with that.
But everything is a bit oriented in that direction.
The difference is also in the fact that you invest your own money,
or you manage someone else's money.
We put our own money in it.
When we manage this company, it is an amateur-led company.
The first Silicon Garden company, which invested in Flavia, Arpovia and so on,
was entirely amateur-oriented.
D.O.O. invested in 10 companies, put them on those tickets,
and completely unprofessionally...
Do you mean because you were still in school?
I was not healthy at the time, but that was the way they were...
A start-up?
Yes, a start-up.
The two of us went to do a real investment, an alternative investment.
The minimum investment according to the Slovenian legislation was 150,000 euros.
You cannot invest in such a company,
because you have to be an informed investor.
This is a guarantee that you do not put people under your wing.
When someone invests 150,000 euros in something,
they know that there can be risks,
and they can probably survive without those 150,000 euros.
When you manage that...
For example, as an investment committee,
I am aware that I manage my own money,
but also from some of my friends,
and I also have a responsibility for them.
For example, there are some evaluators.
You come to KS, evaluate some points,
then some are counted,
and in the end they get 1 dinar.
For some points.
There are 5 evaluators,
and half of them are...
In the last month there were 20.
Yes.
In the end, maybe this is not the most potential,
but it is a child's system,
from which people invest.
It's a little different.
Public money is not our money,
it is our money.
I just wanted to...
I think it's good that we have it,
but it's something else.
It is something else,
and it is also needed on the market,
but it is not completely irreplaceable.
I just added an asterisk.
I also participated a few times
as a part of the Slovenian business team,
as a mentor.
OK, there are different tasks.
Find out both,
if you are in the phase of searching.
I will just say that at this point.
Will we have any more questions
at this point, Andras?
No.
We skipped some questions.
Supporters will know in the future
what these three questions are.
Yes.
I can say it again,
if you like these personalities,
and if you want to support
our task,
we will put some links below,
so please support us,
it will help everyone.
We support Slovenians too little
from the things we create,
so I can only support.
Yes, so we all support Tomas.
Now,
the next task,
I have here
two more tasks,
and then we will move on.
Maybe we will talk about the potential
of technological companies.
We are trying to
make this podcast work.
We asked
our audience
for questions,
and Matej sent us a question.
Will you read it?
I will.
Matej wrote,
lately we are looking at
whether more money is invested
in companies whose product
is based on information technology.
In most cases,
we are talking about
10 million investments.
Many times, companies
do not realize
the love they have
for collecting capital.
Do you think
in recent years
we are spending
too much money
on information technology?
Yes, of course.
The situation has changed a lot
in recent months,
maybe in the last half a year.
Valuations are different.
In startups
valuations are well known.
Before,
it was easy to estimate
1 million,
but now
we will have to show something.
It is not that easy
to get 1 million.
It has changed a lot.
And yes,
certain companies
have a lot of capital
that they try to place
in the market.
EF, which is in different areas
in Slovenia, Croatia,
EF is the first company
in the world,
they have funds
that they have to reinvest.
The goal is
to invest in the market
and to buy
a lot of luck.
Some of them
will be satisfied.
How lucky you are,
how well you have decided,
how well you have estimated
some potentials,
it will be seen
in a few years,
maybe in 5-10 years.
It is not known
how many start-ups
will be pivoted
in the end.
If the founders
are ready
and have the grit
to do it.
Yes,
some investments surprised me,
but again,
I support
money to be invested.
You can't estimate
the price.
We were interested
in RoboDločar.
Why did we choose RoboDločar?
Maybe it will work out,
but I always asked
why it turned out so badly,
what was wrong with it,
what did we learn from it?
It is a school,
every failure is a school.
You learn here.
I think that
we can exaggerate
the failure
and put a label on it
and it is like that and so on.
I think that
you have to be persistent,
at least you learn from those failures.
I would like
to try
to focus on
the potential of technological companies.
We are more interested
in
Slovenia's
technological companies
or
companies that
work in this area,
competitive or
European.
Can
you tell us
more about it?
On a technological level?
I don't know where
it could be
a little better,
do we need
more support,
do we need a different infrastructure,
where are
the opportunities
to make it better?
We need a better educational system.
Do we need a better educational system?
If we
compare us
to Silicon Valley,
I lived there
for a few months in 1992
and my family and I
were there for a year.
If I look at
the situation there
or here,
we are not there yet.
You can imagine
that Silicon Valley
started with Hewlett-Packard,
Intel,
microprocessors,
and that drove
the next start-ups.
Those people then
invested and created
the next companies.
It is the 20th generation
of those companies
and I think we are
on the 1st or 2nd generation.
We are not there yet.
There are no stories yet.
I can tell you that
if I look at
the software industry,
which was the biggest IT company
for many years,
a successful story came out of it.
I can say that
a story came out of it.
Click, Sportradar,
a story came out.
Investing in Slovenia
was 150 million in the last period.
It came out of it.
So,
the next generations
are already here.
We need to encourage the environment.
I think it is better
if those people who created Exit
invest in the environment
because it is hard on the one hand.
It is hard to go back.
There is also
an investment mode
where you have to grow.
It is not something you have done before
and you can get used to it.
It is not simple.
We are not all for that.
Not everyone who has capital
will naturally
want to do that.
You want more than that.
Everything goes into some
impermanence and so on.
I also invest in
the decision of impermanence.
It is part of
preserving some values
for a long time.
You don't have to think about it.
I am
from the audience
again.
Draž says
you are a passionate supporter
of the inhabitants.
One of the new topics
is the Technological Forum of Slovenia.
I forgot about that.
Can you tell us
where will
that forum be?
Is it a topic
where we will get
a more connected
community?
Why is that?
It is still
planned
to launch
somewhere in May.
Publicity and so on.
We established
an economic interest association.
It is a formal form.
The Slovenian Technological Forum.
We are waiting for the government
to confirm the use of the word
Slovenian.
We haven't got it yet.
We are a technological forum.
The idea is
that we have been listening
for many years.
Many of the entrepreneurs
who tried to do something
changed the environment
and adapted to the environment
of the technological sector.
They worked hard
and got a lot of information
about the company.
I am a representative
and so on.
Marcik also tried
different associations
and an economic forum
and so on.
They were unsuccessful.
In the last year and a half
there were
17 companies
who joined us.
We said
that we will give
20,000 euros
for this project.
We believe
that we will put our money
into it.
We will create
an association
that will try
to place
an agenda
in the public.
We will lobby politicians
and try to persuade
the public and politicians
to start
working.
I think
we will have to
create a vision
of what Slovenia should be.
A strategic plan.
No, not a strategic plan.
A vision.
What do we want to be in 10 years?
A less defined,
but a starting point.
Something that
the society would accept.
This is not
just something
for the environment,
it is everything.
The technological sector
must be successful
if we do not improve education.
If the environment
is not open
to the migration
of immigrants
and their families.
We need a lot of
initiatives.
Silicon Gardens
is one of the members.
We see that
if we invest in the Slovenian sector,
in the next round,
this sector will move
to Delaware, London,
or somewhere else,
because a venture capitalist
from Silicon Valley
will not come to a notary
in Slovenia with a power of attorney
where he will be able
to invest.
No way.
This is
a problem
that he will not solve.
There are some problems
that can be solved
with low-hanging fruit.
There are also problems
that need to be imagined
as a vision,
to start believing
that something can be done.
I believe in politics
as a vision.
If we look back
while I was preparing
politics
before independence
and so on,
we had a vision
of an independent state,
of the European Union,
we had a vision of the euro,
and the whole society
was working to achieve it.
A lot of things
had to be adapted
to achieve it.
Now we are moving
without any vision.
We are talking about
a bit of tourism,
a bit of dark metal,
a bit of aquaponics.
My question is
related to that.
What kind of infrastructure
is really important,
purely plastic,
what kind of infrastructure
is needed for this kind of
tasks?
Sometimes they say
you need a railway,
you need a highway.
Where do you see
this basic
base layer
that is really needed?
I am a big advocate
that education is
one of the big tasks.
I am not talking about
the vehement digitization
and so on.
This aspect seems important to me,
but it seems more important
that the next generation
that comes out
of the school system
would experience
more things,
more cooperation and so on.
Today, the school is very competitive
in terms of individualized
assessments and some fight
for that.
You have to create
a foundation for cooperation
and so on.
Education seems to me
to be one of the key tasks.
When I say
digitization,
I mean that
if you look at Nobel Prizes
most of the awards
were awarded
in different fields
for achievements
that were effective
due to the use
of data
and information technologies
that enabled
breakthroughs.
Today,
chemists, physicists,
everyone needs
to be literate
in digital sciences
a long time ago.
If we don't use
these talents of young children,
we probably won't
be able to go to Bangalore.
I was lucky
when I was in school.
I had a math teacher
who opened my eyes.
He was really good
at computer science
at the Kran High School.
He was led by a teacher.
I think we need more of that.
That's one thing.
The other is bureaucratic trust.
Bureaucratic trust is nonsense.
When you say
this is trust,
can we send it?
We don't have it in the company.
If there is a trust,
where can you send it?
Someone set it up.
What is the solution?
How can we remove this trust?
This is where
the journalist's
inexperience comes in.
Maybe the journalists would
do better.
There is a quote.
If you want to make enemies,
try to change something.
It sounds like an uphill battle.
Yes.
I agree.
We also think
a lot
about how
we will be able to communicate
this information.
If you try to change something,
it's a disaster.
I think we need a new vision.
We need to imagine
a better future.
Why?
And then we hope to
talk about it.
A good example
is Digital Serbia.
They are an IT company.
Serbia is in a different situation.
The success rate is too good.
We tolerate everything.
It's not bad enough yet.
It's good.
When you are in a worse situation,
it's easier to grow.
They launched
a voice
where they said,
I'm learning Python at school.
That was the vision.
Then they came to this.
They started
programming based on
Word and writing.
It's a creative work.
It's a creative creation.
They do it
with students,
students and so on.
You continue.
When we were preparing,
we thought a lot.
I'm an investor.
We have certain problems
with law
or with
not so modern
legislation.
We thought,
what does it look like in Slovenia
if you want to make a business
for employees?
When I listen to it,
I feel like
we are at a point
where
the legislation
states that certain institutions
wrote their own laws
and proposed them.
Maybe it helped
to change the law.
I'm talking about
the evolution
of diseases.
How do you see
this topic
of employee capital?
We are working on it.
There will be steps in lobbying.
Lobbying has mixed feelings.
In Slovenia,
it's a taboo.
I don't think
it should be.
It depends on the person
who does it and the way you do it.
I don't think it's the best
if laws
come out of the blue
and are proposed.
I think the parliament
has to do its job.
They are paid
to do their job.
I don't want this.
On the other hand,
if you want to change something,
you have to show the way.
There are different ways.
How do you solve
the problem of
giving a startup
and making it profitable?
The biggest problem
is that people
don't buy it.
If they buy it for nominal value,
they will pay
in cash.
More than you plan to invest.
That's exactly what's happening.
People are looking for a way
to do it.
They establish a company
and that company invests.
It's hidden behind a holding company.
Slovenia or anywhere else.
It's transparent
but it's not treated
as a source of income.
Or, I don't know,
in the end,
the Industrial Democracy Institute
adopts the ESOP model
which is a company
as a part of the system.
I would like to see it as something that cannot be picked up by a large number of people.
On the other hand, there is a great potential that people who are involved in some great stories
will gain some added value and then pay a capital gain.
And in the end, the money, the people who are here, in Slovenia, who are working here,
creating a family and so on, will probably be used by the majority here in the final phase,
and not invested.
Are we, as a society, aware that we live in such a global world,
so that capital can jump quickly, but we are too little?
Too little, too little.
Do things happen quickly, or do we get confused because we are not aware of it?
I don't know if we are not aware of it, but I think it's a priority.
We are a typical example of status quo.
Why would I change anything? It's just a part of it.
It's not that bad.
I think that's the main problem.
Are we going to eat now, or are we going to ask some followers?
Because he's been struggling with it.
We can't eat here if we don't ask some followers.
We'll sort it out. I think we have one more message from the audience.
Yes, we can sort it out.
You have it in front of you. Please, do it.
You can make a drink of water if we need it.
Or a top dog.
Did you find it?
Yes, I did.
Majalko asked a question about technology.
I believe you have it very respected.
Luka leads a huge team of volunteers,
where he has created a trailer during the pandemic.
He has a question about soft skills,
and how he came up with the organization of the work at the same time.
I believe that technology is not the most demanding thing in all these projects,
but how do you organize a group of volunteers?
It's like herding the cats.
Yes, it's very different.
I was lucky enough to experience it myself.
I was in Ubuntu and KDE community for 4 years,
and I was very active.
I saw it there.
I saw the Ubuntu canonical, Ubuntu community,
and the aspect of mixing it.
Problems that arise there,
and that's where I tried to solve them.
In Ubuntu community, which we had at KDE,
and I learned a lot there.
I saw that things are different there.
It's not like in a company,
where you make a top-level decision,
and then it's done.
Community and meritocracy are the best types.
What you do, you do.
If you do something good,
you'll be on the right track,
and you'll keep doing it.
The advantage of being an investigator during COVID
was that, on the one hand,
you could stay at home,
work from home,
and on the other hand,
there were some smart people.
They were worried about what would happen,
and they said,
this seems more important to me
than what I do in the office.
We had a few people
who were on the other side,
because we were so engaged,
and interested,
that we changed the priorities.
In the beginning, it was very simple,
because people were very engaged.
I didn't change the plan,
I just put together my Excel table,
and that was it.
Then it all came together.
I said, let's not do it again,
and it happened overnight.
I was a comfortable person,
and when I fell asleep,
in the 10th grade,
it was dark again,
and I said, wow,
yesterday I said let's not do it,
and now this.
You don't need a lot,
because the environment is such
that people are people.
There were people from the academic sphere,
who first tasted
what it is like in an entrepreneurial environment.
We had a more entrepreneurial culture,
a more mentality,
because there were a lot of developers,
IT people, product managers,
who were from such agile companies.
And there were people from the academic world,
professors from different faculties,
scientists,
and they first tasted
what fast-paced moving was like,
and they enjoyed it.
Because they were used to doing
big tasks,
and it was impossible for them.
Now they are all over the country,
and there is no funding,
and there was a can-do mentality.
It was very simple.
Then later,
the motivation,
the question is again
the individual who sees it as a responsibility,
and moves forward.
Last year and a half,
it was Maja Založnik,
COVID-19,
last year and a half,
Maja Založnik,
and some other people
who jumped in at the moment.
If there were 300 people active,
100 people active weekly,
and so on,
now we have a scientific community
behind it,
which is the bearer of the project,
so that we can collect donations
through it,
and so on.
That was the main reason
for establishing it,
and also because we got
a commercial version of SLEK
as a non-profit.
And these tasks,
to offer some infrastructure,
but the society is not the one
that contributes,
it is the ones
that contribute,
and so on.
Some individuals
came up with the idea,
they were ready to do it,
and then there was
Jakar Danev,
who coded it,
and in the end,
we had a new service.
What is now easier,
what is not,
it is hard to find
motivation,
it is hard to find the team spirit,
because they are just volunteers,
and they all have the same time
to invest,
and then they wait for this,
and that, and so on.
Is this a model,
do you need
a state entity
in these projects,
or does it transcend?
No,
you don't need it.
Are you making an offer
for public good?
Yes,
it came up as a response
to a need,
I think we gave a need to the market.
If I tell you what
the MWP was,
when I was asked what it was,
I said that all I need
is one page,
I go to one link every day,
and I can get
quick information about what is going on,
or I go deeper and find everything there.
I don't need to have five pages,
three levels down somewhere,
to find waste water,
data, or whatever.
That was the idea,
when the idea came up.
That's why it's on the long side now,
because we haven't refactored it yet,
redesigned it,
and it still serves as the main idea.
And then there was a need.
We were millions of users,
and there are millions of users
who access it every month.
One thing that I think
is particularly important
is that
open source models
enable transparency.
They enable openness and transparency,
and it's all visible.
Is this also a part
where it was the basis
for trust that was needed
at the same time, I think?
Yes, to some extent.
Data that we created
was all in CSV,
in GitHub, in Diffie.
Everything was visible.
People could verify it,
correct it, and send it back.
And while we were working
on the data,
we had the validation automatically built in.
Tanja Ambrozic,
who used to work in RIC,
the old accounting center,
as an analytician,
still sends Excel daily
and recommends
if something is missing in a model.
You learn something
from the people
who sing about it.
Transparency certainly helps.
It also helps that
a few junior engineers
who were at Sladilnik
found future jobs
at the reference base of Sladilnik.
This also happened.
I don't know.
At the end of the day,
Maybe it's a great example
for discussion,
but someone like Šarkaš
is now looking for a new career
in IT.
He worked here on COVID,
on healthcare,
and contributed a lot.
It enables a certain environment,
and in the end,
the community is the greatest value.
The connections we established
are the greatest value
for Sladilnik.
Now,
we have a whiteboard here,
and it says that we are running out of time
for an extremely interesting
part.
I would just quickly...
The repository is on GitHub,
the organization is on GitHub,
on Slack. If Sladilnik interests you
and you are developers,
I think you will find a link to it,
if you haven't yet.
So, on behalf of our
team, thank you for Sladilnik,
and to you and everyone who worked hard
for Sladilnik.
To conclude,
we have two more questions,
and then we will wrap up.
Right at the end.
There.
Now,
when I look at
some of the people
who are connected to Silicon Garden,
and I think
it's a step
in the right direction,
as a student,
a few people
stayed in Slovenia.
You could have gone to Tuin,
and you were in Tuin,
but why did you
stay in Slovenia?
Why didn't you run away to Tuin?
I would say,
because of Radansk.
When I worked
at Silicon Valley,
I really enjoyed
the environment.
In 1999-2000,
I was appointed
to San Jose Mercury News,
which is a local newspaper,
and I was reading it
every day,
on paper, if you can imagine.
Inside, there were only good stories
about what was happening,
about new startups,
in a daily newspaper.
There were also other local stories,
about the process of downtown San Jose,
and the fact that this positivism
can do anything,
was incredible.
The project I was working on
didn't go well,
and I was looking for
an alternative,
so that I could stay there.
I identified three companies
that I talked to,
but in the end,
as the right engineer
wrote,
I was ready to
leave,
and I didn't like it.
I didn't like
the fact that
if I didn't prepare
the food myself,
I wouldn't eat well.
There were companies
that were on a different level.
In the end,
I was a fan of Radansk,
and I had the feeling that
Radansk found me there.
So, I decided
that the quality of life
in Slovenia is relatively good.
We don't know
what we have
at what distance.
As long as you're not a fan,
you don't know.
Maybe I'm hard-delivered,
that this is so good,
maybe I'm a baker,
I don't know.
I'm a fan of Radansk,
but I don't know
I had a lot of colleagues
with whom I could
go to Inno,
I did careers at EMC,
Microsoft, Oracle.
We had a lot of coaching
at the same time.
Part of that
was that there were no opportunities,
but I decided that
it's a matter of personal decisions.
Maybe I had a challenge
because of that,
maybe a small one on the other hand,
you can make great stories from here.
One last question.
Give us another
world for young people
in the industry.
I also wrote that young people
can listen to older people.
We all don't know something,
so we need a good world.
Young people who are moving
to the sector
at the moment,
or maybe us,
who are young at heart.
I would like to ask
if you are doing something
that motivates you personally?
That's a question
you should ask once a month.
Do you do it
because it motivates you personally?
Do you do it with a personal motivation?
Do you believe in the story you are doing?
And if not,
do you think about what would
motivate you?
Maybe it's an independent path,
maybe it's a quick course.
I haven't done a lot
in the history of my career.
I've been at Hermes Softlab for 18 years,
since I was 18.
When I found out I would be
in the market at 36,
I found out I would have half my life
there, in a company.
And the last year and a half
I was more worried
about how I, as a manager
of another company,
would take on another team.
I grew up in a team,
they bought me,
I was under their care,
and because of that,
I was able to survive
the last year and a half,
which were not ideal for my career.
Ask yourself,
does it motivate you?
If you are doing something
with your personal joy,
I believe there are a lot of opportunities
in the world of IT,
where you can do it.
I am responsible for loyalty,
I am not the kind of person
to change things,
but think about
what you do,
is it a product, a story,
do you really believe in it?
And if not, do you believe in it?
That's the first step.
Why don't you believe in it?
Why are you not fully in it?
Because when you start doing it,
it will be easy.
Then you start functioning differently.
It's not a service anymore,
it's something that enriches you,
you start enjoying it,
and it's not hard at all.
And the environment around you
will change.
When you change,
the environment around you will change.
Thank you, Luka,
that was our exit.
Thank you again, Luka Renko,
for your interview, we appreciate it.
Thank you, Tepan Draž,
thank you to the team,
thank you to Dollar Media for the production,
thank you to the viewers.
Thank you, because you're doing
such a dedicated podcast in this area,
I think it's really enjoyable.
If you listen to it regularly.
Yes.
The problem is that
there are no more daily commutes,
and then there are opportunities for that,
even when I wash dishes,
I still listen to the podcast,
and it's just fleeting time,
the listener does too much,
and so on.
I listen to it regularly.
You can listen to us too,
we have a diadrama.
No, we have other sounds,
you don't like them.
Thank you for being with us,
see you next time,
there are links below for support,
and see you next time.
Did we forget something? That's it.
Thank you.
Good luck.