Let's start. Welcome to the new episode of Eugrodija.
This is the 20th episode.
21th.
21th episode.
The second episode with video support.
If you read the first one, it was an experiment.
The first one was an experiment, but it was so good that it wasn't exactly a pure experiment.
So today we will try to succeed with video support,
and we will be more reliable to our co-producers on sound, so we respect that too.
Today we have a new guest with us, Dr. C. R. Goll.
We will talk about Artificial Intelligence, Artificial Intelligence from the perspective of engineering.
We will try to go deeper into how Artificial Intelligence changes our world,
how it changes the planet, how we will lose services.
We talked a little about those topics that are related to it.
I won't talk anymore, because then Andraža won't like it, because I have too many secrets.
No problem, you will tell a lot of things, and listeners and viewers will be disappointed,
because we won't touch those things, because we will run out of time.
Yes.
We don't know how long this episode will be.
If it's too long, we will split it into two parts.
Now, Boris, can I introduce you?
You can try.
I can try.
Boris is a master that I have been training for years,
and he positions himself very well in Artificial Intelligence, in the use of Artificial Intelligence,
and is a part of the product of the use of Artificial Intelligence and machine learning.
You also have a very interesting career path, so I will ask you a few questions about that.
So, today you are in charge of Artificial Intelligence, data, and data science, if I understand correctly.
Yes, I lead the data discipline, and everything that is related to data falls into it.
Data engineering, machine learning, data analytics.
Now, when we last talked in person, I think we talked in Porto Rojo,
and you said you were going to the Slovenian Entry Festival, and you will be the headliner there.
How did you present yourself there?
Actually, I remember well, because I focused so much on what I was going to say, or show,
that I had the idea that half of it was just talking about slides, and the other half was demo examples,
and that's a lot of art, so you can really prepare me well if I want to sing in a short time.
Now, let's first find out how you tried to create such a serious business that deals with Artificial Intelligence.
Or we will first find out what Artificial Intelligence is.
Or we will first find out what Buzzword is, and what it really is.
Well, okay, let's start with that.
I mean, I don't know if we're going to go back now.
Now, tell me, why do you believe so much in Artificial Intelligence, that you and your friends decided to establish Ektimo,
and why do you think it's time to do some sub-ethnic business in this area?
Well, first of all, I want to say that it was all part of a big strategic plan.
It wasn't like that in the beginning.
At the very beginning, I thought I was doing things related to finance,
quantitative finance, fascinating algorithms, the idea that you can make better decisions
if you look at the data at the top, and so on.
We established this business at a very interesting time,
when in the Slovenian area, the financial industry was at its peak in the 1920s,
ready to invest.
So, I started to think a lot about how we could expand what we were doing with algorithms,
and so I quickly realized that what I was starting to gain in terms of data knowledge,
there was no reason to limit it to just one industry.
I was even younger at the time, and a bit more naive.
Then, when I looked at what was happening in the United States in this area in the late 1990s,
I had a feeling that everything was already done, that I could start a business here.
Later on, I learned that we were probably Slovenia, five years ago, maybe even more.
But you positioned yourself as a company that would work in Slovenia,
did you say Slovenian market, or whoever comes?
Yes, you're right, maybe it wasn't so strategically thought out.
In practice, we were a company that worked mostly in the Slovenian area,
more because of intelligence than because of strategy.
What I later saw was that it was crucial to find a way to talk to people in the markets,
where there was enough capital for investment in this area,
maybe there was also a greater market development, and later on,
the transition to these markets.
If I were to go back in time, I would try to make it so that in six months of my life,
somewhere in the suburbs of London, I would show up at some meetups,
and I would get in touch with people.
Now, let's explain what this business is about, what problems do you have,
what do you solve, to make it clearer.
We're still talking about ECT.
Yes, yes.
It's a bit of a blast from the past, as you would say.
That's how you put it.
It's good that we started with that.
What kind of artificial intelligence was there in the 18th century?
Or a little earlier.
The idea was to help companies build systems where data science was a key element.
But as some kind of advanced BI?
No, no, no.
I mean, to set up models of machine learning that would make predictions,
which would then be used by companies.
But in a very generic way, do you mean a different type of data,
or is it a specific type?
It was more generic.
Generic in the sense that we didn't move to an industrial vertical,
but more niche in the sense that we targeted data science.
We didn't offer data engineering students,
software development by hand, and so on.
Now, one topic that we will somehow discuss a little later.
People have come, and even today,
companies that implement artificial intelligence,
that solve problems with artificial intelligence,
because they are looking for a solution that will be based on artificial intelligence.
Is this knowledge available on the market?
Or do people come and say,
we have such a big problem that we can't solve it any other way,
can you help us?
Is this knowledge available on the market?
I think it can be divided into two categories.
I think that many of the problems that companies have,
they don't realize that with the right model of artificial intelligence,
they could solve it today.
I think that people on the market will be looking for people
to help them implement this thing,
because they simply don't realize that it can be solved in this way.
But I think there is a lot of it.
In the last 10 years, we have invested a little too little in this,
we don't have an internal team.
Can someone on the market help us put this together quickly?
Because we are a little behind, for example.
You are old-fashioned.
I went a little further.
You went from Ektima to Comtrade, Digital Services,
and now you are developing these things in Endavit.
With a larger reach, in a larger company, with a larger budget,
everything together has become more serious.
I haven't thought about it yet.
Actually, it was quite a leap from Ektima
to one of the larger IT companies in Slovenia, in Riga at the time.
It was an interesting experience.
I think that someone who is used to living in a small company
and constantly working on innovation
can bring a lot to a larger company.
It is difficult, because it is very rare in 10 years
that someone makes a leap from a small management company
to a larger company.
My experience was very positive.
Then, a little later, I moved to a foreign company,
which has an even larger system.
We will talk about this a little later,
about Artificial Intelligence.
Do you think that the size of the company
that deals with these technologies has a role?
Can we say that these are tools that Andraž Zdelek
from SP can take and start working with?
Do you need a larger engineering team?
Do you think that this is an experience?
This is something that has changed a lot
in the last few months or years.
Actually, for applications of Artificial Intelligence,
when it was five years ago,
there was a tendency for larger teams to implement it easier.
Now, with the arrival of new models,
pre-learned, with huge amounts of data,
with better tooling that helps these things in production,
it seems to me that it is more even ground.
Perhaps a larger company can cope
with greater difficulties in implementation,
because there is no need for limitations
when it comes to technological solutions.
But there can be limitations in how to change business processes
so that this technology can reach its goal.
Change management in large companies is really difficult.
OK.
Watch this segway, Andraž.
Now that I've prepared for this episode,
I've read some books about Artificial Intelligence,
Artificial Intelligence for Engineers,
and I've read some different books.
One book that I will refer to later in the notes
is this one, How Machines Think.
In this book, there are very illustrative
algorithms that are used,
from what should be done to drive a smart car,
to how smart video recognition is,
various concepts.
The introduction is like this,
let's talk about how machines think,
how machines are prepared to be smarter,
and what algorithms are behind it.
In the introduction of this book,
a very good example is that in 1737,
a French artist made a robot,
an automaton, that could play the piano.
It could play 12 different melodies,
12 different songs.
It had a mechanism like those old clocks,
and it was very popular.
It was seen by the majority of people
as a crazy thing for gamers and entertainment.
He made it, and then a group of skeptics
started asking themselves how this thing works.
King Ludwig, who was the boss at the time,
said that it was a fake, that it couldn't be.
There was a little girl inside,
who knew how to play it, 5 years old,
and she knew the melodies.
They totally rejected him.
The church also said that it was a blasphemy,
that the machine couldn't be smarter.
Then he wrote that he presented his idea,
how his machine works in front of an academy of science,
and he explained the mechanisms,
how the hands move, and how the machine works.
He got a recognition from the Science Board,
that it was a legit machine.
But society saw all the problems
through what was done,
and they didn't understand what to do,
how the machine works,
and why it was made.
I'd like to dig deeper into these things,
and see how these algorithms work today,
what is needed for things to work,
and how we develop them in the future.
Here we're probably...
Okay, go ahead.
Great.
Here we're probably talking about something
that was learned in advance.
The algorithm only works once,
for those 15 minutes, and so on.
When we talk about AI,
the parameters can change.
The decision-making tree is much bigger.
I can put it this way.
The algorithm is a whole procedure
to solve a specific problem.
And that's true when we talk about this system.
I agree that this is a definition of the algorithm.
But I think that...
I guess it depends on how broadly
and extensively you define the problem.
In the beginning,
the path this technology chose
was always more against the system,
because the same system can solve
a lot of different problems.
And I think that in the end,
it will go in that direction,
with a system that is always more complex.
We can then debate where this complexity ends.
This is a topic that is often separated
when people say, for example,
complex artificial intelligence.
What does that mean?
It means that people are not entirely AI,
because there are a lot of problems
that we don't have and don't know.
We are not biologically well-constructed
to be able to solve them entirely.
I agree.
The operating system knows everything.
And then you have programs
that are specifically designed
to solve a specific problem.
Can you imagine that?
Yes.
You have a whole core...
You are going to skip the whole story,
but I think that the systems
that are still at the beginning,
but are still accessible enough
for us to start working with them today.
We can work on such a system.
We have an orchestrator that gets tasks
and then decides for an individual task
that came up.
Which other sub-system is best suited
to solve that task.
It sends that task to the sub-system,
it is already present,
and it needs to solve that task even more,
or it can solve it by itself
and send it back to the orchestrator as a solution.
That is one such system.
Most artificial intelligence systems
are not like that today.
Most systems are not like that.
Maybe it would be good to take a step back
because of these differences,
because now we have more to change.
Most artificial intelligence systems
functioned in such a way
that they solved one exact,
very precisely defined problem.
To solve such a problem,
it was necessary to learn the model again.
Most of the time it meant
to get the data,
to get the information,
to get the data that was taken very precisely
with that specific problem.
To mark that data, for example.
If we wanted to classify things,
we could first mark it,
learn the model,
then put that model into production,
see how well it works,
and as soon as there were
more noticeable changes in the distribution of those examples,
we went out of the distribution
where it was learned,
the problem was no longer working well,
then the whole art was to find out when it happens,
to give new data,
to give a new designation.
Problems are very, very difficult,
and subsequently also difficult
in an unusual way.
Even if the system, as it was learned,
knew how to solve that problem relatively well,
if we then think through the whole life cycle,
what expenses will there be,
how many people will be able to keep some distance,
it's not a pile of water.
What started to change
with those pre-learned models,
a few years ago,
was the concept that if we take a model
and really learn it
in a huge amount of data,
which includes a lot of different problems,
we can imagine
how a pile of different distributions
would mix together
and thus learn,
then we come to a model
that is able to solve
different problems
in the same model
and is also somewhat more robust
because it was not in such a singular distribution at all.
But what you're talking about now,
is that something you've already used?
Yes, yes.
Let's put it this way,
the architecture of transformers
was the driving force
for the development of this trend.
I think it was in 2017,
somewhere around that time.
An important thing here was
the need for a change
in the classical system.
The data had to be rewritten.
One interesting solution was the so-called
self-supervised learning,
where we can take unmarked data
and imagine,
or rather say it in pictures,
that we have a picture,
and give it an analog model
on the basis of the remains of the picture
to tell us which cube we took out.
And we can do the same for the text.
But if you only chose one
out of the whole set,
would that be enough?
No, no. Imagine you take
100 million pictures,
each of which you take out a cube,
and then you say...
Oh, you mean a subset of 100,000.
No, no. You take 100 million pictures,
each of which you take out a cube,
you use the rest of the cubes,
and you give it an analog model
to tell you what's missing.
Because at one point you don't need
to know what's missing.
You try to learn from the context,
from the remains of the picture.
It's the same with speech.
I'll give you some examples.
For example, let's talk about language.
Language was the driver
of the development of new methods.
For example,
basic sentences.
An apple fell out.
But then there was a tree,
but that word is missing now.
When a model sees enough sentences,
if it wants to become better
when it tells you
what word is missing,
it probably forms a representation
instead of an apple growing on a tree.
If it falls from a tree,
it's more likely to fall from a tree
than from a shelf.
It can also fall from a shelf.
We'll get to that later.
You need a huge amount of data
to be able to...
To work with solutions.
It must cost a lot.
It's a huge cost.
To some extent, it's true.
But it's not the same concept.
Trash in, trash out.
You can help your neighbors.
For example, if you have some data trust.
For example, Wikipedia, or books, for example.
And then you can look at some of the basic properties of the text in those high-quality sources.
Then you go through everything you've scraped down from the Internet,
and then you protect those things that are a little more similar to those high-quality sources,
and the rest goes to the side.
So, in fact, if you've calculated it all, it took you some money and time,
but in the sense of programming, you don't have to deal with it much,
because those things fall out on their own.
And we have a lot of that data.
So those models...
We have a lot, who has a lot?
Well, you can have a lot of them.
At the beginning there is this Common Crawl,
which is actually a collection of what scrapers pick up from the Internet.
It's available, although it's huge.
So maybe you need a little more money to be able to do something with it,
but at the beginning those data are there, you can use them.
Now, I'm going to tell you about a project we started,
and I'm going to tell you about the problems you've already solved in some way,
and you're going to tell me what the next generation of such a system would be like,
so that it can be done better.
Are you ready for that?
What?
Are you going to tell me your pet project?
No, no, no.
I'm going to be stupid in consulting.
I'll pay you later.
Okay, so the problem was this.
We developed a technology for massively inquiring people.
More languages around the world.
People come in and you ask them questions,
you put a chat bot,
you ask them questions,
people give you answers,
they get a reward.
Which in theory is a very good way to get very interesting data,
you can do it massively, great.
The problem is that this concept of giving people a reward for participating on the Internet
attracts a lot of off-roaders, logically.
And the challenge we had was how to develop a system
that would ensure that those who answer the question
would answer honestly,
not just click,
and as soon as they come to the reward, they pay.
We needed a system that would give a score,
or an indicator,
if the answer really belongs to the person or not.
And what did we do?
We created a system that recorded all the small micro-interactions
that a person did on the control room,
and then we combined them with the answers.
For example, how you moved the mouse,
how you moved the hoverboard to an element,
how you changed your mind.
For example, you asked him,
is the moon the sun?
And then you asked him the other question,
is the moon still the sun?
And if these two answers were correct, it was a logical task.
Anyway, we collected a huge amount of data and parameters,
we formed some 12 features,
and then we said,
okay, a combination of micrometrics and answers,
we can label and make a label,
this is legit, this is not legit.
And we labeled the dataset,
and we had a relatively good system to prepare it,
whether it was in a file or not.
The task was great,
but there was a problem,
when the user changed,
the interactions started to change,
then there were problems,
for example, the number of questions changed,
and it affected...
Whatever we changed,
it was actually not robust enough,
we had to train it again,
learn it again.
This will prepare the life cycle,
how the scoring works,
whether it is still relevant or not,
because it started to affect us.
This is an example of what we were doing,
and we solved the problem.
I wonder how we could do it more robustly,
in the context where you put it first.
Is it possible?
It is possible,
but on the other side,
on the front side,
capabilities are improving.
Absolutely.
I would like to ask,
why did you need to collect data?
Do you mean data for fraud prevention,
or just data?
No, just data.
Data was used for market research,
on a global scale,
we were interested in
whether people use YouTube,
TikTok,
how long they are on TikTok,
mobile banking,
we were interested in everything
people do in the digital space.
These data were very important
for global corporations,
they have to allocate a global budget
for product development,
marketing,
and so on.
These are very important data
on what people do.
The problem is that
when you give a bounty
for someone to solve it,
then you have a question,
people click on the question,
if you click on the question,
then it is something
that is quite easy to automate.
Oh yes.
Or if it is for some simple
text input and so on,
it is not difficult to do.
With these new approaches,
I would probably say
that the fraud detection part
has changed the way
data is collected.
Why not have a proactive bot,
which would find people
in a carefully selected
natural habitat,
and talk to them
in a free-flow chat,
which is then
a little harder
to swallow.
I can say that
I was very hijacked
in the whole debate,
but the next thing
I described was text.
People write text
or click buttons.
The next generation of this system
was sound.
These questions were written,
those questions were processed
through sound,
and then it went into
listen mode,
and when you answered,
part of the real-time
speech-to-text transition
took place.
And what you are doing
quickly showed
what was happening
in the space.
Then it turned out
that people solve it
in an underground railway
or on a bus.
On the other hand,
you collected emotions,
people answered very gently,
or when they realized
that the microphones
were about to turn off.
It turned out that
through a lot of scripting,
a lot of people today
make fun of writing
buttons for the microphone,
and that the script
started to fail
because they didn't have a microphone.
So, yes,
this aspect can be improved,
but then comes
the scale.
Textually,
interacting with people
is really expensive,
because sound and infrastructure
are different things.
Privacy is also important.
Yes, I agree.
It's a waste of time and money.
Yes.
Okay, I'm done.
As far as
Frodo is concerned,
there is a constant
war, a competition
between...
What is a cat-and-mouse game?
The only thing that is clear
is that you can't
use artificial intelligence
in this game,
and let others
have the advantage.
I think it quickly
fell apart.
When we looked at the data
in this system,
when we activated our system,
it fell apart
very quickly.
But then
a few people
got to know
the tools you use
against the ones you use,
and then they started simulating
how the mouse moves to make it work better.
And it really is a cat-and-mouse game.
Frodo completely.
Yes,
when you have money in your pocket,
on the other hand,
there is a lot of interest in it.
I'll give you
an example,
I wouldn't call it a fraud,
but a dark pattern.
For example,
a company
offers you an order,
it's very easy to make an order,
but if you want
to cancel it,
it's very difficult.
You have to go through all the steps,
and for them,
it may not be
the most moral
or so on,
but it's understandable.
They have even less
of their own systems,
because you are
allowed to do it
in an unoptimal way.
What happens
is that
as you
imagine
and imagine,
one thing that will
slowly raise the cost
for this dark pattern
is that
the logic
on their side looks completely different.
For example,
if you have a bot
that can automatically
go through all those
strange steps and cancel the order,
they may now have
on their side
some expense
that goes
for the interaction
with your bot.
It can be very expensive for you,
but they have to be in an interaction
with millions of bots,
and
these things can
turn upside down.
I think we'll see some of that
in this area.
These quite obvious
dark patterns may not work anymore,
because there will be some level of
intelligence on both sides,
not just on one.
But that's good.
One more
similar example.
For example,
in law,
not all people have
laws for everything,
but people have
very different access
to people who can help them
navigate these laws.
And of course,
this is very much needed.
A company that has a lot of money for its employees
may have a lot of money
and manage to do something.
Now, if you
introduce
an extra-priced service,
legal aid,
that
reduces the gap
between what the weak
and the powerful have,
I think this can change
the whole dynamic.
Which is good again.
I mean, I believe
that...
Why are you avoiding me?
Let's move on
to the topics that are weak.
No, no, I'm trying, but...
What has become,
I see it as evolutionarily good,
and at the same time,
this gap is decreasing.
So,
a company that doesn't have these opportunities
is now coming to some opportunities,
while a company that needs it a lot
is now,
its position is now a bit different.
Let's be specific,
for those who may be more interested.
A company that deals with such things
is Do Not Pay.
They have become
quite well-known in this area,
and it's worth looking at
what is the last thing they have.
This Do Not Pay,
I understood,
they are fighting
against you paying
those subscriptions,
that you don't pay anything.
No, I think they are positioning themselves
as some kind of
small consumer
average person advocate.
In various interactions
with the system.
It can be about cancelling orders,
it can be about some kind of
basic legal aid, and so on.
But I think that
just a few weeks ago,
they challenged
to give some kind of award
to an artificial intelligence
that will be able to win
in court in some cases.
Yes, in Germany,
I think it will be in Germany,
there will be a trial,
although I think it will still be
for some parking lot,
some high stakes.
And the party
will represent itself,
because it has the opportunity,
and it will have a hearing,
where the model will decide
But they also offered
for one million dollars
an award to someone who would be prepared
to go to a similar trial,
but in front of the US Constitutional Court.
Which would be hard to do,
because people commented
that you can't do that
at all.
But
I believe they are quite confident
in what they currently have,
what is currently possible.
For example, I saw a video
where they were talking
with a representative
of a charity
about lowering the age limit,
and it was broadcasted.
I think
it was for Comcast,
to lower the age limit.
And that's just
the tip of the iceberg
where it will go.
I think you can see
even more of this
in the meat industry.
Will it always be
affordable?
I look at it
as a usable perspective
when it comes to
new products.
For example,
what are the products
that people would like
to have and use?
One option is to look at
what rich people use
and try to
imagine what it would look like
if you did it a thousand times cheaper.
Would things change or not?
Of course it would be cheaper.
I think that things
like an assistant
who instead of you
handles
offering telecommunications,
or I don't know, you make
various reservations,
something together with which you want to engage,
I think there is a lot of potential here.
I think that
this year will be the same
when these types of agents
will move forward.
Now I would like to
try to talk
a little more about these concepts.
What we could do at the beginning.
Can you explain to us
the concept
of artificial intelligence,
machine learning and deep learning?
What are the
connections and where
does it lead us?
What is the buzzword?
What is the marketing buzzword?
What is Hollywood?
What is sci-fi?
What is the business
we are talking about in this term?
Let's start with artificial intelligence.
The most
adored word here.
This is a very
complex thing.
A lot of things
can fall into it.
I personally
see it like this.
A system that
produces outputs
based on some inputs
that are consistent
with some
optimization function.
This is the subsequent point
that we can almost
talk about. For example,
a system that looks
at the value
of a temperature sensor
and then
gives you an output
based on the value
is a kind of intelligence.
It sounds like
an if
or case clause.
It can be.
I do not exclude them
automatically
.
This is purely
official.
In practice, people use it like this.
Artificial intelligence is all
that we don't know how to do yet.
Subsequently, it also directs
the whole
discussion.
For example, one company says it uses
artificial intelligence.
It uses some three inputs.
Then you get a lot of money.
Maybe.
But people will say
that this is not artificial intelligence.
Artificial intelligence is just that.
Then we go forward.
Do you want to say that
artificial intelligence is what is massively
needed in marketing purposes?
In any case,
it is needed.
I see that
you added a bunch of products
with new names, which are actually old products.
Now we have some kind of artificial intelligence
inside.
Probably similar to what you said before.
A couple of ifs that are now smartly decided.
I think this is an example.
As far as ifs are concerned,
this moment,
maybe the last two years, is quite harmful.
Because, for example,
people use it as an excuse.
Oh, this is not
really smart.
These are just if-inputs.
We are now very deep
in a period when
we have gone relatively far away
from any kind of if-inputs.
But then,
no one is offended
because we all
saw those memes
where it says up and down,
and then there are if-inputs.
But we are no longer the same.
Yes, but I mean,
if we go back,
what kind of machine do you think
at the end of the day
there is a machine
that works on some
zeros?
Yes, I don't know.
It is true that we have built more abstractions,
especially in mathematics.
I mean, the counter-argument
for this kind of argument
is always that
you are not some kind of machine.
If they would look deep enough at you,
what would they see? Some molecules?
Where is the magic?
He says he has a soul,
and he has free will.
Yes, but all machines now also say they have.
Only the right to work can be at the beginning.
Sooner or later, you won't even need that anymore.
But if we go back
a little bit,
if the concept of artificial intelligence is so complex,
then what is machine learning?
A lot of people use it just like that,
as a nickname.
Machine learning is
the process of
teaching something to the model,
or the machine
is teaching something.
So,
we are a bit more complicated here.
We are not
decision-makers,
we don't have any
functions, but this is
just a learning process.
But machine learning is
key to artificial intelligence?
Yes.
In the beginning...
I mean, you can
accept...
You will have examples when you can
accept some decisions,
or produce some output,
without having to have a very powerful component of some learning.
Most of the things that interest you
are necessary learning.
And if we go
to deep learning,
deep learning is a special
branch of machine
learning,
which is based on many
neural networks,
as some basic
architecture.
Probably,
some other architectures could
implement this concept, but
this is a paradigm
that has been
implemented
for the last 10 years,
and still exists.
Of course,
the question is, what now?
Is this it?
I don't think so yet.
I think there is still a long way
to go for
improvement.
I like
this definition.
I can say that it was
a period of deep learning.
Then we switched to
big learning.
I like it, because
it's a great buzzword,
deep learning and big data combined.
If you can't sell anything with it,
then you really can't do anything.
But the point is,
models that require
so much computational power,
and are trained on such huge amounts of data,
that you can't
transfer them to a smaller laboratory,
but only big tech
or very well-funded startups
can do it.
That's what we've seen in the last few years.
The models that are
talked about the most today
are typical examples of that.
With those cutting-edge
products,
and then we'll talk more about those products,
is there
a way of deep learning
or
an evolution of deep learning,
or is it a hybrid approach?
Is it a secret?
The reason why
we're here,
why we're talking about it today,
is deep learning.
If that didn't happen,
and if we didn't have those things,
then I wouldn't be talking about it.
Maybe I'd be talking about it in CryptoCon.
No, I wouldn't.
I still have a few lists.
Those two things are definitely connected.
Crypto and AI
are definitely connected.
No, let's move on.
We'll cut that part.
What was really important
within deep learning
was the point, I think I already mentioned it,
the architecture of transformers.
I think it's better to
do it with a few slides.
But the mechanism
that's behind it
is attention.
That was very, very
important.
Roughly speaking, it's because
you get a context,
and then you take
the whole context,
and you weigh the parts
in the context
that deserve more attention.
But that process is
human interaction,
when it decides,
or is it built
based on what?
As much as it can
pay attention to. That's the beauty of it.
So this paradigm, when it started, is now being applied to all possible examples of use.
At the beginning, they were words, then they were pictures, then they are now multimodal models that can take colors out, connect those colors, and so on.
Can I ask about deep learning? Is it about neural networks that are connected to each other?
What do you mean by deep? What is meant by deep? Layers that you can put together, neurons that you can put together?
Imagine that you have layers made up of many neurons, and the signal travels through those layers, and those layers are typically large.
What is it, 100,000, 10,000,000?
No, no, I don't mean 100,000,000.
Just a feeling?
Well, let me put it this way, basic things. We talk a lot about parameters in these models.
Here, a parameter is, let's say, the weight of each connection between two neurons.
How many connections are there?
At the moment, let's say, I don't know, the model used by PTTRI has 175 billion connections.
Now, in fact, there are also more complex models that go against billions, or maybe we are already somewhere above that.
But is that a parameter that you add when you learn the network?
No, no, that's the same thing that the network learns. The network learns how it should be.
But the number that you mentioned, billions, is that a limit that you want to train?
Not more, but is that the consequence?
Yes, you define that.
At the beginning, when you set up the architecture of the network, you know how many layers to choose, how many connections to choose, and so on.
But what are the values ​​of each of these, the network then learns by itself.
I don't know.
Did you learn anything?
That's the whole point. Well, not just me, I hope there will be people who will learn and listen to us here.
Now, we have a question, can you tell us a little more about the projects you are doing in NDAVI with these technologies?
Then I can ask you more about AI products, and maybe we can talk a little about how they work for you.
I would really like to hear what kind of day-to-day project you are working on, so that people can get a sense of what the industry is doing.
I know you work with 4GTP, so you can say.
Maybe it would be like this, what is this moment?
If we make a time lapse, what are the problems that are being solved?
Are they really real?
We can detect some things in the pictures for the purposes of production or medicine.
We can tell some prices, we can tell the amount of inventory that is needed.
These are things that are already known to people.
But at the same time, we are still actively developing internally.
Now we can go for things that use the latest technologies as much as possible.
For example, coding assistants, systems for optimally managing knowledge in companies, various bots for answering questions, and so on.
When you go to a job interview, they always ask you what your pet projects are.
Do you want to say what your pet project is?
I'm working a little more on how you play.
I can also sum it up.
Sometimes there are some things that I do and they are so interesting that I can say about my pet project.
One thing that I do in my free time is a semantic scanner for tweets.
This is such a functionality that a person would like to be productive on their own.
What do I mean by that?
For example, I like a bunch of tweets.
Then there comes a moment when someone grabs me and I would like to touch on some topics that have come to my radar.
But how do you find this now?
Now I'm doing this, for example, I'm going to take this tweet, then I'm going to take some tweets that are contextually related to it.
Then you take a picture that someone has pasted, and then you look at what the personality of that picture is.
Then you look at what people wrote in that tweet when they quoted it or tweeted it.
Then you take it all together, put it in GPT-3 to summarize it carefully.
Then you put all these things in a vector database, and in the end, it's not over yet.
The idea is to write a topic that interests you and automatically attracts those tweets that are the most relevant.
In other words, you have to understand the nature of tweets, you have to know how to connect with the broader context of what people are saying.
But also on the other hand, when you ask a question, you can ...
Yes, but the biggest thing is, for example, this was a project that would be like ...
Five years ago, the research department and I don't know how many different engineers, now I often do it myself as a hobby.
Because simply with the models of GPT-3, the context is automatically pre-learned.
To actually make a user, more like a researcher.
I mean, yes, plus it helps me write code.
If I need something ...
So you described it as something that someone can come in quite quickly and start using quite quickly.
Yes, if I wanted people to take something away from this conversation, it is that time has really changed.
And technology has really become more accessible.
Instead of talking about some academic articles that you can study, let's talk about the fact that they are simply tools that you just start using and are completely no-code.
You know what, a big challenge is that sometimes it happens in front of juniors.
Andraš will probably confirm this.
That people pick up an article, watch a YouTube tutorial, put themselves in the subject.
Then they come to the service.
Then you realize that more than that tutorial, people don't have context, background, depth.
And when these challenges begin, when they start, you have to know how to put them together somehow.
Here is the part where you say that these people need a little self-interest in the problem and self-research.
Yes, just self-research and go, for example, look at how the JavaScript library works.
It's probably a magnitude more simple than understanding all these exercises.
It's probably.
It's pretty much the same here.
It's pretty much the same.
I mean, no, we just came into an era where these are products.
Where products are used.
You use a product to help you optimize a part of your work or beginning, whatever.
I don't think there are any such examples here.
Maybe I would say this here.
When it comes to the use of artificial intelligence, I think that in the past we have focused a lot on the use of examples that are really not exemplary for this.
And to some extent, if we look at the amount of investment that went into the car itself.
This is a kind of newscast, where the car is driven in almost the entire world at high speed.
At any moment, human lives are at risk.
And one mistake and life is over.
High stakes, totally.
Yes, it's full of high stakes.
It could be even worse, but okay.
And of course, then you do something and it's 99.99%, but that's way too little.
And every next decimal becomes a billion, or a tenth of a billion, or whatever.
For once, I would say that the best examples for use are those that can help you do something many times a day.
And if you do it wrong, you can catch it pretty quickly.
And then pressing Generate again is not a problem.
And then you get used to the fact that the system must always be correct.
And these systems, for the most part, are available today and you can start using them.
So for people who are thinking about what would be a good starting product for artificial intelligence,
or for machine learning, choose some products that are not so high stakes,
and that do not endanger your life.
Imagine a company.
For example, a company that has never done a lot of data science,
and then it goes into the water.
And they decide where they're going to apply it.
That's going to cost us a lot.
And then we're going to go into the most high-stakes part,
because we want to improve those investments.
That's going to cost us the most, that's going to hurt the most.
And then they try to solve this very difficult, very high-stakes problem.
Every step is painful.
And at the end of the day, artificial intelligence didn't really get us to the fourth decimal point.
We were completely disappointed.
At the same time, they have someone in the back office,
who actually has a lot of time and his own life,
to start a completely unoptimized process,
so he could totally, simply optimize it,
but he doesn't think it's high stakes, and then he doesn't go into it.
Now that's it.
When people talk about digital transformation in the industry,
I don't know, our industry is out of date, it needs to be transformed,
let's first divide what processes you have,
and maybe start automating those low-hanging fruits,
such projects,
not first take your favorite artificial intelligence,
and then go to the most hardcore problem you have.
Maybe that's how you start.
I would like them to have a positive attitude towards it,
to ask them what they want from life.
And that's where it starts.
Can we make this system so that there will be less life with artificial intelligence?
Now I have this...
Jesus, how am I going to connect this, Andras?
I don't know, you imagined it.
Maybe we should talk a little about the products
that use artificial intelligence,
and then we'll go there and look for a source and connect it.
Now I've written down a few of those more well-known,
more current products, and some of them may be less well-known.
I think you know everything, if you don't know anything, we'll be sorry.
But I think you know everything.
The first product that changed this whole part of the space,
and that really made such a pump,
I mean, lift for security.
Lift for security, yes.
It's GitHub Copilot.
This is a plugin that you get for your IDE,
and this plugin prepares a code that you write, I think in the comments,
and when you write a comment, it offers you a snippet of the solution,
you click Tab or Enter, and it fills it out for you.
This part is taught on GitHub's repository,
that is, all the code that GitHub has.
Do we know publicly or privately?
I mean, I know this product pretty well,
so it's taught on Mars,
it's used in its core,
these are GPT-3 codec models.
These were actually models that were taught both on the top of the code,
and in plain language.
Then, when it was already taught,
it was only slightly adapted to work better with code.
But yes, basically, this is a GPT-3 model.
It started as a GPT-3 model,
and then it was fine-tuned.
You described it as quite simple,
quite trivial,
more of a marketing tool,
nothing special, you could have done it at home.
I mean, practically...
100 dollars a year, or 10 dollars a month.
You can do it yourself for that kind of money.
No, Oto, do you use it now?
No, I don't.
Do you write code with this system?
No, I have a lot of...
You know, it's a bit like this.
I have almost 200 open-source repositories on my GitHub,
and in there you can find everything,
examples, prototypes, whatever.
And when I was given those snippets, those cores,
it meant that I had my own archive,
or that I was giving it to the community,
so that people could use it.
I don't know if I,
when I had those 200 repositories,
and the pull requests,
when I gave them all out,
I don't know if I knew at the time
that someone would use it,
and that someone would use the GitHub Copilot
and take my snippets out.
Do you know what I mean?
It's a part of it.
It's a part of you.
If I write a brutal scale there,
my example will be very unique,
and someone will write,
I need this brutal example.
Ultimately, they will take my code.
Or they will pay and then...
Not in that way, maybe.
No, what...
Should we go to the picture?
No, I'm here with the same problem.
Maybe it's easier to explain it like this.
Also, those models for generated pictures
were taught on a whole set of
such and different pictures.
People gave them very different names,
and they didn't think,
almost none of them,
that an AI would learn it.
If the AI looks at all those sets of pictures,
it learns some representation.
Those pictures are not stored inside it.
Only those in the weight
are stabilized,
or then learned in such a way.
Then, when you write a text inside,
that text is translated into a picture,
but it's actually on the basis of those representations
of visual concepts that were learned.
They are not code now.
No, no, that's not the basis.
No, that's not the basis.
I think, for example,
for a generated picture,
the size went down to 4 gigabytes.
You know, with those models,
stable diffusion...
I mean, where in those 4 gigabytes
are the preserved works of art from all over the world?
Now, if you happen to find
that a snippet came out,
which is really very similar to something
that you worked on...
It's beautiful, exactly.
You can find examples.
That's enough for you.
If you imagine a distribution of codes,
if you happen to know each other in one box,
you have a very large company
that works on the same problem,
most of your representations
in that model of distribution
were taken out of what you contributed.
And the rest will be the same.
Maybe the next generation
that you will generate
will be a little different
than the one you wrote.
It's a real problem.
There are also models
that were strictly learned
on codes that have a permissive license.
If you published something
under an MIT license,
I think it's hard to convince
someone to find a way
to use what you don't like.
But do you think that...
Maybe at the beginning,
when you open a GitHub project,
when you upload it,
there could be a checkbox
that would say
how to use the code for Copilot
and you could have the possibility
to do that.
In some phases, it will appear.
But not now, when we've already done it.
Let me give you an example
from art.
I think it could be like that.
I don't know much about art
and I believe it will go in that direction.
For example, in art,
some...
not so many organizations,
but a team
that works on one of those
big datasets of pictures
gave the artist the opportunity
to say,
I don't want to be involved in this.
What will be the result?
A lot of artists
will say,
can you please include me?
Because a hundred people
is a hundred miracles.
And that model will learn that.
And then,
someone will realize
that if he writes
the prompt that leads
the model to do something,
he can say,
give me a combination
of this, this, this, and this artist.
From those who
gave permission,
the result will be so
that it will look indistinguishable
from what he would produce
if he said he doesn't want to be included.
And...
That's the problem.
In the end, a lot of people
moved one step forward,
because they didn't
directly contribute to the learning.
But when the model,
the visual or coding learning,
will be able to
reproduce the same code
in the end,
it will be very similar to what they did.
Well,
if that's a problem
that will happen,
I imagine that this thing
can end up in a court.
It already ended up in a court.
How did it end up?
A project
like GitHub
or Copilot,
Antitrust,
something like that.
I don't hope to speculate,
because it's more of a question
than it really is.
Look,
what would happen to this industry
if,
let's say,
Europe, full privacy
heavy,
if you want
to make those data sets
that we will train on,
and if, let's say,
Copilot or any AI,
you have to explicitly
get permission from people
to be in that data set.
Because now it's the other way around.
Now we download everything,
the whole internet, Wikipedia,
if you say otherwise,
everyone has to give permission,
you have a lot of problems in this industry.
Because you don't have a data set.
Now I see
how are you going to prove
that he's in the data set?
Yeah, I don't know.
Like you said,
in the end it's all about the weight.
He said,
it's not the database,
it's the TV channel.
How are you going to prove
that I'm here?
It's the same picture you post on Facebook,
it's not yours anymore.
Let's put it this way,
in practice,
how many examples
where you write a code
but don't get a license?
Then at the other end of the world
there's a programmer
who looks at your code
and writes his own.
Maybe he's a little biased,
a little changed,
but in reality,
your code was his main belief.
You won't even know it.
It's not easy to prove these things.
Sometimes it's so obvious
that it hurts your head.
But it's the same art.
People looking at pictures
and making their own versions
or covers in music,
it's like a war in progress.
It can happen.
If we go with strict regulations,
it can also
lead to
this kind of abuse.
Then people would say,
wait a minute,
I can't draw almost
the same thing,
because each of them
will be similar to the existing author.
Can this also be used
as a counter?
In the sense of proof,
that you can use
artificial intelligence to prove
that this is a copy.
Yes, I think
to some extent it can.
It's hard to do it
with any kind of readiness.
How do you look for similarities?
Semantic or...
Ok, next product.
Now we'll go to products
from OpenAI.
It's a startup company.
Is it still a startup?
What did you do it for?
When I was doing research,
Microsoft said
they would invest 10 billion dollars
in the company that made
ChatGTP.
These are chats.
Very expensive chats.
I think they invested
before that.
Some incorrect data shows
that they already invested 3 billion.
Microsoft puts a lot
on OpenAI.
Clips will always be used.
Then you'll open Office
and say, hey, I need
to import my books.
The thing will happen.
The main thing is
that they have
some data
on how to work with Microsoft
and how to connect,
how to share profits,
and so on.
One thing that a lot of people
probably didn't hear.
Again,
it's an agreement
that you can't
break.
You can't
If they deserve more than 250 billion, it's all theirs.
Yes, yes.
I chose that 75% is paid.
If you are interested in the research of the company,
google it, it's interesting to know how it works.
Now, Andras has researched the 4GTP a lot,
because he was on some other day,
and he thought about it.
But when I saw the 4GTP and what OpenAI does,
and when you look at it from a different perspective,
I have a feeling that in the first 15-20 years,
google is starting to take care of their core business,
which is search and advertising.
There are a lot of things that we can talk about in more detail,
but I have a feeling that maybe there will be a revolution in this space.
And also when you started that semantic search,
to open up those topics.
Do you have a feeling that the guys have stopped a trend
that we simply don't have to ignore anymore?
I mean, looking at the fact that it's only in the media,
that it's the hottest topic in the last two months.
I mean, they're sour cucumbers anyway.
It's interesting to me.
Maybe it's interesting to OpenAI too.
It's the beginning of GPT.
It's a very slow modification of the GPT-3 model.
I started using GPT-3 in the summer of 2020,
and that's when I experienced it,
I think, because now there are a lot of people.
Then after the best efforts for the last two years,
I was not impressed,
and a large part of that time was already available.
I won't say that I didn't manage to impress anyone,
but a lot of people didn't even look at it.
It wasn't a big undertaking to try to implement something with it.
So I would say...
More.
That chat, GPT, is a great example of what can be done with user experience.
It's a better example of user experience,
and not an achievement, as for Artificial Intelligence.
What was Artificial Intelligence on this topic,
it was done two years ago.
But when you use it,
chatbots like this,
and those online assistants,
we have now experienced two big leaps.
When the scientific world came,
around 2000, when all the videos first started,
and then when Facebook gave support for chatbots in its messenger platform,
and now we have this chat interface again.
I don't see that it would be that different.
Chatbots were a total flop, I think.
They were.
The problem was simply the methodology they used.
It wasn't mature enough for what UX designers wanted it to be.
So Zadeva tried to understand what IT was,
and then she wanted to dive into some of those pre-prepared conversation tracks.
And we don't talk to people like that.
You wrote a track about how it wouldn't work,
so I think you're a bit ahead now.
Yes, but for a call center, that's exactly it.
Of course, it's not.
But on the other side of the phone,
there's a diagram that says,
OK, he's asking about this, we have to answer that,
we have to ask him that.
If we link it to the product we mentioned earlier,
that we massively agitate people,
and we're looking for these Zadeva.
You know, today people are already used to it.
They have an icon on their phones, on their computers,
and they know that if they press that button,
an action will take place.
You don't know what's going to happen,
you don't know what he knows,
you don't know where he's going to chase you,
you don't know what he's up to,
you don't know anything,
and you just can't get them to do something.
For me, that's what triggers them,
that they don't know,
and then they start talking,
and then we believe that...
Yes, they're fully self-confident,
and they need two hours to talk to the same button.
Wait, wait, wait.
I don't know what that button is capable of.
Yes, that's right.
And you're going to be one of them.
Do you know what that woman, or man,
is capable of?
I don't know.
Is that possible?
You ask yourself,
what if they start talking about something
that I'm not prepared to talk about?
That's a good point.
I believe that for some people it's a problem.
For some people, conversations are stressful,
and they're worried.
You know what else?
If I don't know what he knows,
there's a person there,
and if he doesn't know,
maybe he'll ask,
maybe he'll give you the best possible answer.
People will be able to interpolate
from incomplete data.
You see?
Exactly, those systems are capable of that now.
That's why we're going to talk again
in a new era of chatbots.
I actually think that
a different term will probably be used
to make a little breakthrough
in what happened.
I don't know if it's an assistant or an agent.
So a bot has a negative...
I mean, like a chatbot.
That's bullshit.
Space.
Yes.
They'll use the argument,
we've already created chatbots as a company,
and they were a total fail.
And then when one thing fails,
and something better comes up,
it's hard to reintroduce it,
because there's already a bone there.
I think marketing will dig it up
In the end, it doesn't matter.
Maybe if we just go back to OpenAI,
as we introduced it.
OpenAI is really
the main player,
this moment in this area.
And now, why?
What was the thing that differentiated them
from the others?
They were very comfortable
putting all their chips
on the hypothesis of scaling.
And now they're experiencing a payoff
for putting it on.
Because, for example, in 2019,
people were laughing at everything.
For example, the GPT-2 model came out,
I was already very fascinated by it.
And people simply didn't believe,
I mean, when I say people,
I mean experts in the field,
that if we scale it up a bit more,
we'll achieve much more impressive results.
And that's exactly what happened.
Because it can go further.
I mean, with this push forward,
does what they're starting to do
still escalate even more,
or is there some limit
to which we'll reach?
I mean, as far as I can see,
we don't know.
But if I wanted to bet on something,
I would say that we still have
plenty of room for scaling.
I don't see us running anywhere.
Because, for example,
in the previous methodology,
let's say this deep learning
without big learning,
it started to show up.
For example, in computer vision,
there wasn't much drastic improvement.
I mean, you get up to 98% accuracy,
but then every tenth percent
is very difficult.
But here, it's going pretty well.
I wrote to myself,
this chat GTP,
I wrote a couple of problems,
or challenges that I see
with this thing.
And if you're going to investigate
these problems yourself,
you'll see them.
One of the problems is that
when they were training
these models,
it took some time
to build all those models.
Actually, one.
And then
you have a snapshot
of the current world
of those models.
And he doesn't know, for example,
who is the current president
of the United States,
he doesn't know these current things.
Do you think that if they
increase the size,
they still won't have
the up-to-date world,
do you think it will be incorporated somehow,
that it will be more alive?
When will this be visible?
I miss that, I have to learn that.
I think that's
a key question.
So if anyone fell asleep,
thank you.
Yes, really.
The current model, I think
they all say that it's
from 2021,
in the fall,
autumn,
so the data they saw
are static.
And you can't
solve it just by scaling.
I mean,
if something happened
that hasn't happened yet,
you have to know.
If you solve it by scaling,
it would be interesting.
But there are other solutions,
which are quite simple.
So he doesn't need
to have all the knowledge of the world
written in his notes.
That's why it's good
to put it in a context,
what is the knowledge in the notes,
and how can we draw
some kind of analogy
for how people work.
I will put this analogy,
and then it will be easier to talk about it.
For example, let's take a person.
You have a short-term memory.
For example, if you solve a task,
you have to know
what you are doing.
If you write a code for a function,
you probably know
what function it is.
That's a short-term memory.
Then you have a long-term memory.
You can think
that you remember them,
but you can attach them.
You can simply
use that knowledge.
But it's not easy.
You can either not remember something,
or you remember something,
or you mix it up with another memory.
A human memory
is not necessarily the easiest.
Then
you have the knowledge
of yourself.
You can go to Google,
search for a book,
and so on.
How does this look
in language models?
Language models have
a prompt.
I think a lot of people
have experimented with it.
It's a guide
that you give to the model,
and then it continues
the text from the guide.
The guide has a short-term memory
logo.
That's what the model
has in front of it,
so it can work the easiest.
The role of a long-term memory
in models is played
by
neurons or weights.
The entire neural network of the model
is actually
some kind of long-term memory.
But that doesn't mean
that models don't have to use
other forms of memory.
Models can
connect to the prompt,
they can look at the database,
they can look at some repository
of texts, and then
from there, in a short-term memory,
they attach
information that is relevant
for solving the problem they are working on.
This is now a mechanism
that will support a lot of
solutions, but at the moment
there is not enough focus on it.
People expect that this neural network,
if all the information is stored,
is not a base.
I see these models
as some kind of glue,
because they are complex enough
to quickly capture the context
and you can put them together.
For example, between the problem
you have and the data you need,
this problem is solved.
I wrote
integration
as a problem.
Today,
if you put a table inside
and make some connections
from that table,
probably in such a concept
you will connect
with other models,
with other systems, and
extrapolate knowledge from that.
This is the kind of integration
we see.
In a way.
I'll give you an example,
it's quite simple.
For example, these models are not
good at arithmetic.
It's a bit strange, but it is.
If you multiply
two six-digit numbers,
it will probably work.
But you can tell this model
in a short-term memory.
You can tell it,
you are not good at arithmetic.
If the user
asks a question
when you think he is
exceeding his ability,
then you write a Python code
that will
look for a solution to that question
and
calculate the result and return it.
You can tell this model.
If you ask him
what 2 plus 3 is,
then he answers
from his long-term memory.
He will answer correctly.
If you give him to multiply
two six-digit numbers,
he will write a
mini Python function
and he will give you the answer.
I could very vehemently say
that you are now
a machine for neurosymbolic
computing.
Then there are
use cases
where you can monetize
GTP and PNA products
so that
companies will use
GTP
and
GTP3 as
a core.
Then they will
access
their specific data,
their
use case, or
train for their domain
that is specific
finance or
accounting. I think that the most
simple use cases in companies
will come
from this title,
in a similar setting.
You will use it as a member
because you will make one process
simpler.
You will be able to
pull out full value
from the automation of certain processes.
For example,
a company has a lot of
internal rules and documents.
Everyone has to follow
all of this.
This is complicated.
If something happens and you as an employee
have to react to it,
you are not sure what to do.
In companies it looks like
you start asking around
if you know how to do it,
and then they ask you.
Such things can be
solved in such a way that
when you ask for a point,
it will not weigh you down.
No, it will do
semantic search of all internal rules,
search for relevant
problems, and on the basis of this
it will give you an answer
to what is the right thing to do.
But you just said
that you will ask for a point.
Yes, I know.
Again, the use case
will be a point
and you will ask
and the database
will not be static,
it will go through and on the basis of this
they will find the best answer.
And maybe this is what ...
Yes, but from the point of view
of user experience,
I think the difference is
that a private car and a tank
are both vehicles.
I agree that
user experience is better,
but
it's just that maybe
you should ask for a point.
Yes, yes, yes.
It's hard for people
to understand
how important
this improvement is
that they have their own
hands-on experience interaction with these systems.
You have to
try to see.
Ok, I think
I will connect two things here.
In machine learning,
when we evolve the quality
of models, we break
the basic inputs
on a test dataset,
then on a real dataset,
and then we look at how much we have
done today. And then you have
metrics, accuracy,
recall, precision,
which actually describe how good
and high quality these models are.
And when we
talk about machine learning systems,
this is very important,
because you know,
if you have a well-trained model
or not so well-trained,
it will work differently than you think.
And now,
when I used
this 4GTP,
when you put
some problems in it,
which are maybe a little more
fringe or a little more on the edge,
because there is not much knowledge about it,
it still responds very
self-assuredly.
It responds very
well,
it takes action.
For example, I don't know, you give it a code,
you say, make me a code review,
then it writes you 7 points of code review
and what you need to improve.
And then 3 points are real,
but the other 4 are total nonsense.
But
it doesn't say that anywhere.
There is no warning anywhere,
no confidence,
but now I see that people take, for example,
the output of these tools,
generate, I don't know,
a marketing newsletter,
or I don't know, a podcast script,
I don't know,
and sell it as a solution.
And then
they push so far
for you to take it,
that it's amazing,
that it's not far from it.
Definitely not.
That's why it's right.
There are some warnings.
Yes, there are, but I agree.
This is really needed in some way
of this model.
It is not in the spirit of use.
Yes, people find very creative ways
to exploit these technologies.
The key,
successful way of using it
is in integration.
If you need
symbolic capability,
for example, now you have an interaction with Wolfram Alpha.
You can
use a natural language
task that comes in your model,
and then
it gets the output
and communicates it.
The same goes for these tools.
When you give it a guide
at the beginning, it is very helpful for you.
The answer is
based on the things
that came from
those memories.
It can't answer your problem
with those snippets
and tell you that it doesn't have
concrete information.
This can be solved
to some extent with prompt engineering.
You can't use it
as a chatbot for launching
fucking rockets.
You said that
you can also write a prompt
on your own.
Then it becomes
some kind of art.
That's right.
ChatGPT
has some art
where it doesn't go
and what it won't answer.
But
there are people who
went to research how to write
a prompt so that everyone gets
a prompt injection.
Maybe because
it's about prompt engineering.
When these models first came out in 2020,
everything was in prompt engineering.
You could ask
in the right way
to get what you wanted.
But now
reinforcement learning
with human feedback is being done
in these models.
We have a model that was learned
unsupervised.
If we give it
a task, it gives a result.
Then we have people
who grade
whether the answer is good or not.
On the basis of this grading
the second model is learned
to tell us
how a person would
evaluate the answer given by the first model.
Once
we have both models,
the first one gives
the results, the second one tells
if it was good or not.
Reinforcement learning happens.
This leads to a model
that follows the driver
who gave it to you.
A large part of
prompt engineering does this
because
the way the model is
constructed is
to simplify it as much as possible.
OK.
Phew.
Vlade, do you have anything else?
Do you want to go to the bathroom?
No, no, no.
I have a few more questions
and then we'll wrap up.
Now I will
step out of
these products
and ask
the field of artificial intelligence,
machine learning, deep learning,
the product we have
now changed,
does this field grow exponentially?
The things we saw
at the beginning of the year 2021
and 2020,
and now
it's boom.
Does it really grow?
Or is it just media talk?
I went specifically
to look for an answer to this question,
but the number of
research papers published,
the number of articles published,
the number of codes published,
the number of projects published,
the activity within this space,
everything grows exponentially.
And also the tools,
their quality
is improving almost exponentially.
Things like today,
when we film this,
are interesting,
but by the end of the year
they will be much, much, much better
than they are now, because again
we have this exponential growth.
I have some charts here
and all the charts go up quickly.
And now my question will be
ok, let's say
this hypothesis holds,
that growth is really fast and
exponential.
But now, how does it grow?
Is it because
it's such an interesting
opportunity to make
a big leap, to really put
a lot of money in it?
Or is it software
that enables us to do this?
Or is it hardware that enables us to do this?
Or is it hardware prices that enable us to do this?
What is the reason
for this exponential growth?
In the end, Richard Sutton wrote a short essay entitled The Bitter Lesson,
where he said some time ago that if we look through the art of intelligence,
what has been achieved, what has not been, then we draw a line,
why did all this happen? It is because all these achievements, in a way,
were supported by hardware and so much more computational power.
And I think this is still true.
When we talk about scaling, of course, we will always need more computational power for scaling.
And in order to overcome this, if we count on hardware becoming more capable,
it is not just hardware.
I will also talk about ways to optimize things with better software and so on.
But that is the basis.
And here, to say that we have a powerful cut-off on the horizon,
to see it now, no, no.
Because no, not only in the individual processor core.
I am currently very confident that in the next three years,
in terms of hardware, we will still grow.
Unless there is an exogenous event, like a war or something like that.
But other than that, in the next three years we will still grow.
Three years of computing is…
Ten years.
Fifteen years in some other words.
And do you hope to tell us where we will grow?
I mean, let's say, what will happen at the end of this year for AI?
What do you hope to say, where will we be?
One thing that is already highly anticipated is the arrival of GPT-4.
I think that when it happens, it will be much bigger than what it was at the beginning of GPT.
It's hard to say what the functionality will be like.
My expectation is that the model will be more connected to the Internet.
It will enable delegating tasks, which I could manage independently.
Then I expect, when it comes to generating videos,
I expect a drastic improvement by the end of this year.
I think we will reach the point where you can generate an entire evening with one shot.
It won't be the most valuable thing until the end of this year, but look, the next year…
But here, the video is again about deepfake.
Yes, you know, when it comes to deepfakes,
we have to find a solution that won't be connected to detecting it,
because it's a losing battle.
I suggest that the solution be more in the sense of cryptography.
So, if you have a cryptographically verified channel
through which someone gives information,
then you can assume that if the information came from that channel,
and I hope so, if not, then not.
No matter how you try to detect something,
some time goes by, then a better meme comes and it doesn't work anymore.
When we were talking earlier, Miska and Mucka…
Yes, that's true.
What people have shown is that it is possible to manipulate deepfakes quite well.
So, what is the added value of being able to include deepfakes in a healthy way,
is an important question.
But I think that more like those media deepfakes,
which would worry me, is when an agent calls you
and has a pleasant conversation with you on the phone,
or you have a video call with him.
To some extent, voice already exists.
To some extent.
It's a kind of a scheme, right?
Or should I say, they're already here.
Yes, but what's the point if you won't be able to hear anymore?
I'm more interested in whether something is being done against it,
that is, whether you will know or detect that it is an output
that was generated through an AI system,
that on the other hand, it is really a bot,
and then record the voice.
The Chinese have a great solution now.
Everything that is generated with artificial intelligence,
all images and all photos must have water,
it must be generated.
They solved the problem.
Yes, they solved it.
You know, it's a new technology, radical,
some kind of crop picture, you know.
Okay.
Now I have two or three more questions here,
and then we'll wrap up.
You asked this question, but what is the role of a data scientist
or a machine learning engineer in this whole aspect?
I think that we will now fight against artificial intelligence.
I don't know, probably a lost battle.
We probably have to learn how to work with it.
I mean, what is the role of a modern engineer in this area?
You see, this question is a bit about the role,
what people are doing, and a bit about AI safety.
But it's done, it's been mixed.
What will you do when you start programming on some scale?
We'll write a podcast host.
You'll say that today.
If you have an idea for today's show,
you can generate it.
The guy who does OpenAI has a contract for,
what did you say?
For that, how do you say, universal income,
and through that he will give back to people
who will no longer have a job because of it.
But let's go back to that.
Let's go back to those vlogs.
Yes, to the vlogs.
Well, a data scientist,
who was so attracted to the title,
I mean, still is,
but when people join Data Science,
they expect to be able to build models,
and to be able to get to know a lot of different architectures,
which they will use creatively, and so on.
But that part is a bit boring.
Because, for example, in the usual Data Science,
the problems in the field are well understood,
and the models that solve it are well known and documented,
but they don't really need that creativity.
Because a lot of those people are the happiest when they say
that they won't actually do that.
Plus, there are various AutoML methods,
which, even if you have to do it,
it's fully automated.
And consequently, the role of Data Science
is now at two ends.
The first is understanding which data we need,
and are those data okay,
and it's very clean.
Marsik doesn't really care if you promise
that you will learn some sophisticated models,
but that's an essential part of it.
On the other hand, there is communication.
Constantly, aha, now we got something out of those models,
and now we need to show it to the stakeholders,
why, and what would be good to do with it.
And again, there is also a field where
Marsik is not really looking for that.
He would rather develop models.
Well, now, in Machine Learning Engineering,
I think that this engineer part came from
building something,
because a builder of a system that works continuously
and has to work really smoothly,
and verified, and so on.
Here it is more about setting,
I would say, a pipeline,
which will go from, let's say,
a business problem or a query,
to the final implementation,
in accordance with the entire verification that must take place,
so that everything flows smoothly.
In short, building and maintaining such systems.
So, in a way, these are roles that are always more divergent.
Again, it's like that.
Even a Machine Learning Engineer
will not need to spend a lot of time
on learning models.
For example, what is happening now,
where new architectures are being used,
whether you are in the universities,
where the budget for calculating is very financially limited,
and in those development departments,
companies that have decided to invest a lot of money in it.
And then they have a role,
which is now decided again,
not only by a Machine Learning Engineer,
but by a Research Scientist.
But also for,
let's say, for ordinary engineers,
because it sounds very stupid,
but let's say you are a web developer,
that you are, I don't know, a front-end developer,
that is, you are not a Data Science or Machine Learning Engineer.
It seems to me that it is smart to be in touch with this technology,
because now you have to use it,
or it turns into a non-functional thing.
I can give you an example.
For example, someone had an example,
that is, he had a plugin that was written in jQuery,
and he had some other template,
and he put it inside gtp,
and he said, write me a React component out of it.
And the React component was executed,
you fix it a little, boom, and it worked.
These are some examples,
where you have to build a little knowledge,
that now this tool will help you improve it.
You don't have to be a ML Engineer,
but these tools can help you, or what, I don't know.
Yes, maybe a little personal perspective,
which can be a little boring.
One thing I definitely noticed,
when it comes to implementing some such tools,
which is GPT,
I noticed that people who work in marketing,
people development, managers, sales,
in short, such people are much faster
in using these technologies.
For example, I don't know, I show it to them once,
and then we sit down in two months
and casually change it so that they use it every day.
It seems to me that for people
who are more focused on development,
it's not always like that,
but often you can feel some kind of resistance,
and a very strong skepticism
about what we can do with these tools.
I mean, my recommendation is
to pay attention to this,
not necessarily only for tools that are for development,
but also for other things.
For example, one side is,
which is very useful,
Future Tools,
which is really worth looking at,
because it is such a carefully selected set of products
that can be used today
for solving various things.
I don't know, I would say banal,
how to increase the resolution of the image,
and of course, there is also such a tool
when the GPTs are up and down.
I think it will go in that direction,
and there will also be senior developers
who will use these tools
to make them even better.
Also, if I look at Twitter,
I will say that people
who I know are pretty good developers,
then after a few months of using these tools,
they recommend that they make them
not only very effective,
but also that more than a hundred of their codes
are created by using these tools.
Okay, last question.
Are you ready?
I was a little shy about that.
I would also like to know
what management is doing,
how to connect
this part of artificial intelligence and management,
or is management now making more different decisions
on these tools,
or is there a better distance
and still deciding the way we have decided so far?
That's a bit of a shopping question.
But what would you say today,
for example, to technological companies
and their management?
The first thing that I think is most useful,
if everything is clear,
is to get a hands-on experience
with these tools for all people in management.
You don't have to generate codes,
but start using them,
take an hour, ask questions,
see what you get back.
I think that this one-hour experience
will be worth more than a group of consultants
with one-hour posts,
to see what can be done.
As far as management is concerned,
and how it will be applied to companies,
I think they will be at a point
that is not too far away from that.
Companies will start to appear
that will entrust a part of their responsibilities
to a dedicated agent.
For example, the company Antropic,
which is one of the most important players
in large models,
recently published an article,
I think it was titled Constitutional AI,
where they investigated
how you can give a model some rules,
or directions, or values,
so that it doesn't neglect them.
Then it transplants other models
that are consistent with it,
and trains them through it
and automatically becomes more synchronous
with those directions.
I think that the company will start,
when it investigates new business models,
to form an infrastructure as code.
We will have a company as code.
You can have an orchestrator,
in the sense of a COO,
who will then assign tasks under the manager,
and then he will process them,
and in some of those tasks,
he will hire people,
in others, maybe not at all.
In short, I think it will all work
more closely together.
And now, I mean,
you can see where...
I mean, if we go into the engineering world,
or some companies,
are there some...
Can there already be
a certain part of the workplace threatened?
Let's say that AI, for example,
will replace or halve
a person's job.
At the moment, my assessment is that
this is an extremely unused technology.
In the sense that,
through most of the history of artificial intelligence,
we had these illusions,
what would be given,
then you tried it, and it didn't work.
Or it wasn't there yet.
Then, relatively quickly,
we jumped into a period
when a lot of things can be done,
but nobody knows about it.
Or even if they know, they are sceptical,
oh, that's not possible yet.
And we have...
Inefficiency.
Yes.
Incorrect.
And even if we're talking about
general artificial intelligence,
it always seems to me
that at some point we will have these systems at will,
but they won't be used,
which will be tragicomic,
but it will happen.
So,
when we're talking about opportunities for people,
you have to realize
that what will be struggling
is this communication and awareness
of how to spread among people.
Let's say that GPT has done a lot here,
but still,
in a way, very, very little.
So, people who are worried
about what the foundations are doing now,
that it will be automated,
they can think about it,
and they can, when they start,
focus more on the communication direction.
To be that connection element
that helps people
to fill in those gaps.
Scary.
Oh yeah?
Did you think about it?
I also wrote here
the risk of questions.
Risk, opportunity,
it's connected.
Yeah.
Maybe that's also
the timeline situation.
We've already implemented chat twice in our company,
and it was a fail twice.
People still call the call center,
and we hired 60 people in the call center.
Why, for God's sake, would we have a third or fourth GTP?
But technology is probably like that.
Now you will have a bot, now you will have an agent.
But technology is developing,
it's getting better and better.
Yeah, that's what I wanted to say.
For example, when we work on those announcements,
where we are, and how long
it will take us to get there.
I'm currently working on Metacolus,
which is a kind of prediction market.
It's a specific question.
When will it be publicly known,
or I think it will be announced
that it is not yet available.
For example, artificial intelligence,
and then in this question,
they say it's a mistake.
Artificial intelligence,
which is only defined that it will
reach a certain level of performance
on one of the four benchmarks.
For example, this year,
in January,
there was this announcement,
which is usually done by people
who know something about it.
It was in 2042.
A few days ago I looked at it,
and now it's 2027.
We're getting there.
No, this prediction may only give
an illustration of how much
expectations have changed
over the course of a year,
and I find it interesting
to look at companies that make
plans, for example,
plans for 10 years in the future.
I don't hope to make plans
for 10 years in the future.
We're getting there.
Let's tell people that
they should learn more
in machine learning.
They should find out
what these models are.
They should be more open
to these technologies.
We can tell them that
there is a lot of documentation,
a lot of examples,
and that they should not use
these tasks too often,
that they should become
more ergonomic,
that there are fewer tasks
and that they should be more
alert and aware of these technologies,
that they are most prepared for tasks,
and that it's probably a good time
to get rid of these things.
Yes, I think the time is now
the best,
it would be even better
a day ago.
Maybe one such
general thing.
Neural networks have
a kind of easiness,
catastrophic forgetting,
or something like that.
When you train a network,
it adds healthy data,
and then you start to train it
on a slightly different problem,
and it forgets quickly.
I have the feeling that
a lot of people have this
catastrophic remembering problem.
People start to build
some expertise in a field,
they draw some value,
self-value from it,
and it's very difficult for them
to accidentally come across a technology
that makes that skill less useful.
Yes, because I didn't learn it,
I didn't know it.
Part of it is that people
don't program into our habits,
and we build
a whole mindset around it,
and then it's hard
to come up with something new
if we don't deprogram
or start using
these new tasks.
Yes, but
there's something special
about our industry,
that things happen really fast,
and if
you don't invest
your time and
money in development
and acquiring your knowledge,
you get stuck.
I don't know, I won't have much to say
if we don't talk about these things.
These are the experiences
that teach you
that you shouldn't fall asleep.
Yes, OK.
Well, I think
we should go and eat
or something.
Why are you laughing?
What about the viewers and listeners?
If you're hungry, eat.
If you're in a hurry, wait a little longer.
Boris, thank you very much
for your time and views.
Last words?
Thank you for everything.
I also told you
to watch Endavo,
and Karirse,
who also has some interesting roles.
Brendan from Steklanička.
Yes, Steklanička.
So watch Endavo.
Andraž, thank you
for your time.
Jan, thank you too.
So,
listen to us more,
share this with your colleagues,
give us some feedback,
and see you next time.
Bye.