Welcome to the new episode of Yugrodija, our new podcast with video support.
Today we are in Zbranje, in Kristalni PalaÄi, on the 7th floor,
hosted by Microsoft Slovenia.
Today we are joined by Bojan Vrhovnik, Senior Cloud Solution Architect,
who has been working with development at Microsoft for 15-16 years.
We invited him to Yugrodija today because we had an episode about cloud and IAC,
and we wanted to hear what's inside Microsoft's cloud,
how Azure is developing, what life at Microsoft looks like,
because we are now interested in what you are starting in this story.
Let's have a debate with you today, maybe we'll chat a bit.
Did I forget anything?
Great, thank you for coming.
Thank you for coming. Did I forget anything?
No, great news.
When we were recording, we realized that there is relatively little cloud in Azure.
We both worked a lot with AWS, I worked a lot with GCP,
I worked with Azure, maybe Azure was a bit different,
so that's why we are here.
Great.
Now, let's start with the introductory part,
which is the easiest and most difficult to do,
but I have to ask you to tell us what you are starting at Microsoft.
As you said, I am a Cloud Solution Architect.
What is important to know is that Microsoft has many different types of Cloud Solution Architects.
So, you have Cloud Solution Architects that focus on pages,
and you have Cloud Solution Architects that focus on partners.
My job is related to partners.
What does this mean exactly?
Cloud Solution Architects.
They say something, but my job is to enable and collaborate with partners
to enable them for Azure.
Enable it for Azure, as they say.
In other words, to know how to use Azure to the best of their ability.
What does this mean exactly?
What does it look like in practice?
Enable for Azure.
It's a broad topic, but in practice it looks like this.
Now, you could say, okay, send me an email with all the roadmaps,
but in practice it's not like that.
What we are starting with is to say, okay,
you want to use Azure, let's have a look,
first, as you know, let's have a look where you are,
let's have a look at what you want to do with it,
and then we help you with various trainings, hackathons,
proof of concept projects, demos, and similar things.
I mean, we go from start to finish.
I mean, we actually teach them how to use Azure in practice
with the best practices we have.
The biggest problem is that people go to azure.com,
register, get a credit card, take the first decision they see,
and say, okay, I'm going to use it.
They get a 100% credit so they can try it.
Yes, that's always the case.
It's the same with every cloud platform.
You have the same 100% option,
where you have specific devices that are 100% in a specific field,
and then you also have specific services that can be used.
So, partners usually have, if they work with Microsoft,
we have a so-called partner program,
and in the partner program they get, depending on what tier they are in,
they also get specific credits that they can use monthly for Azure.
What does that mean?
For example, they have a so-called MSDN,
or Microsoft Software Developer Network,
an account where they have $100, $150 a month
so they can use Azure for free in their development.
And, of course, a lot of other programs that we have.
We're going to go into more detail,
but just to say, partners,
are they parties, or are they people who have overwritten it,
or are they above it?
I mean, what does a partner mean?
It depends, if we look at it.
Are they all using Azure?
No, no.
So, partners can also be parties.
A party is someone who uses your solution.
Partners then use the solution,
and then sell it forward.
They also have their own parties that help them,
they also have their own solutions that they want to sell forward.
And our task, when we look at partners,
is that partners are of many types.
Some are services partners who offer their services.
Some are ISVs, Independent Software Vendors,
who develop solutions and then sell them.
Azure has one of its options,
Marketplace, through which solutions are then sold.
One way or another.
And then there are the various world variants that exist.
And then we have a third type of partner,
and there are many more.
For example, cloud is the most relevant,
which is called CSP, Cloud Solution Provider.
It says, I am a partner,
and I will sell Microsoft Azure Cloud.
The other side says,
I would like to have Azure Cloud,
and I would like to buy this and that,
but I don't know how to work with it.
And then CSP creates the contract,
the subscription,
sets the environment, helps, and so on.
So there are many different types.
Okay.
We will go back first.
In one of my interviews,
you said you were a policeman.
Yes, yes, yes.
To establish my character.
I still have that vibe.
Maybe, maybe.
We will go back to Microsoft.
So,
when you hear,
although not so much,
but I am from Tajikistan,
so I have two children,
a wife and a neighbor's cat,
because she is more with us than with the neighbor.
When I finished elementary school,
I decided that I would go to be a policeman,
and I went to secondary school in Tacen.
It was the old one, not the new one.
It was a four-year school.
I was there for four years,
and then I went to a police school,
and I went to work in the field.
Of course, when you wake up in the morning.
In two months,
I had some pretty interesting events.
Which you can't miss.
Which I can't miss in November,
because you have to respect the work of those
who are really in the field.
Anyway,
after those two months,
I decided that maybe this is not for me,
and then I applied to the Faculty of Computer Science
and started studying there.
Maybe as an interesting thing,
until high school,
or middle school,
I didn't even have a computer yet.
So I was still in high school with a computer.
Imagine,
when you come to a first-year faculty,
you come to a programming subject,
there you see a lot of students
who are from VEGO,
where they had computers,
and programming for five years.
You don't even know what Linux is,
what Windows is,
what it is.
So it was a very,
very interesting beginning.
Okay.
Now,
before we continue this conversation,
we have to be honest,
we are not Microsoft guys,
we don't work with Microsoft technologies,
so probably...
No, no, no,
that's not true.
Okay,
but probably we can draw some parallels here.
We are also in an unknown territory,
so we can talk a little more.
No, no, no.
We use VESA code.
We use GitHub.
That's already pretty good.
I thought you said VESA Codium.
And C Sharp,
and TypeScript.
Great.
Now,
a little further from what you did at Frio,
Fax,
to Microsoft,
did you work in any other local companies?
Yes,
actually in MIS,
I started as a student,
I started at Datalab.
I mostly worked there as a web developer,
so I wasn't just developing a help desk.
At the time,
there weren't those fancy black and white desks,
if I'm not mistaken,
at the time,
there wasn't any.
So,
my job was,
maybe this is interesting,
how did my interview for that service look like?
Maybe I'll just put it down.
I came to the interview for the service,
the director accepted me.
He showed me,
look,
this is the code we have,
and we would like to make this help desk system,
so that users can see how this whole thing works.
I looked at it and said,
yes,
I can do this in two weeks,
even more,
to use Totnet,
the technology they wanted to give me,
at the time it was a classic ASP.
Oh,
okay.
Which was,
PHP minus minus,
as it was called,
and I said,
no,
I can do this better,
and I said,
look,
if I do it better,
you know,
we agreed on the price,
I want a raise,
so,
I have certain rights,
if not,
you can't let me go.
And I said,
okay,
deal.
So,
you have two weeks,
to do it for me.
So,
the raise was really good.
Great.
So,
you have two weeks,
to do it for me.
So,
you have two weeks,
to do it for me.
Great.
Now,
a lot of people are probably asking,
okay,
I know Totnet very well,
and I work with Azure,
and there is a lot more Azure,
as I said,
than the two of us.
People are probably asking,
how can you then come to
some Microsoft job,
and then you started
applying,
or,
did you work independently,
to be noticed,
or,
how do you get to that,
to,
but.
Yeah.
So.
The second thing that would be interesting is what we can do with the costs.
If you send someone to Azure and give them a virtual one, will it be overkill?
The second thing is the question we always ask.
What about the availability?
Do they have different requirements in terms of availability?
I don't understand the question.
I can give them a virtual one, I can give them an Azure one.
Most of them are for service.
That's one part, but that's a very expensive part.
For me, WordPress is like a platform for service,
which means that everything has to do with the operating system.
You don't have to pay for a license, you don't have to pay for management,
but everything that interests them is the application.
In a simple way, you can put it on...
Demo?
No, WordPress.
If I go back, it's a platform for service,
but there are more different solutions that you can use.
One of them is Azure App Service.
Azure App Service is a web application,
it's serverless, it has Azure functions,
it has storage and similar things.
For WordPress, we have a very special solution,
which is WordPress in Azure Web App,
which means that there is a partnership with WordPress,
there is a proposal,
which has the ability to run it on the platform for service part.
Platform for service means that the management part,
the operating system, updates and similar things are run by Microsoft,
so also when it comes to the network and all that.
But you get stuck with the application.
It means that he comes up and says,
OK, I would like to have WordPress, click, click, click, click,
he gets WordPress.
He says where he would like to host the base,
he would like to host the base on the same server,
and he gets too many requests,
which means that you need to be alive all the time, 24-7.
I need to have, I don't know, maybe I can sleep at night,
I don't need scaling, I don't need more.
So you can install more options.
Now with the platform for service, you don't have the option
to turn it off.
What you can do is say,
OK, I will host the application,
it will be on one server,
for example, I know that tomorrow there will be a preview day,
and everyone will go to meet,
and I want, for example, if there is a lot of requests,
to add a healthy virtual environment,
and I can, for example, continue that.
In this example, I have to choose the way
I will store the data,
so you said MySQL,
one option is that it is on the same server,
but that's a problem if you scale horizontally,
you need to store the data somewhere,
where it won't be,
if one server flies away,
the base flies away,
no one will be happy.
And here is a backup of the system?
Yes, so you have more options.
Now VWAP has an automatically integrated backup,
which is stored in the storage,
or directly to the system,
which offers the best solution,
because then you have to connect
to that server and get the data down,
which is not optimal.
You also have the option to say,
I would like to expect that it will be,
I don't know where the hairdressers in Slovenia are,
but I like the hairdresser Ena,
I think it was someone else,
I don't know, it doesn't matter.
Anyway, my wife cuts my hair then.
My wife is my hairdresser.
And I have a webpage for her,
which scales.
But what I want to say is that,
if we take the application and say,
hey, this has to scale,
then we also have solutions
that are connected to the server.
We can say, oh, MySQL,
we have Azure MySQL,
Azure MySQL,
so the server,
this part has an integrated backup.
It has one thing that is phenomenal,
which is called point-in-time restore,
which means that,
if this part flies,
you can say,
I'm interested in what happened
to the food five minutes before 12,
and you can go back to the same state,
which means that you do differential backups,
and so on.
Which means you can decide
what machine you will have in the back,
and so on,
but you don't deal with the machine,
but only with data.
Now, if we look at this hairdresser,
what would it look like?
A person would say,
oh, I would like to switch to Azure now.
He goes and says,
give me WordPress,
he shows him the options,
click, click, click,
he shows him the guide,
which, of course,
we have excellent documentation.
In the guide,
he tells you,
go to the admin center,
click this, click that,
and it will export you
WordPress zip file,
whatever it is,
so you have the whole structure,
imported in,
and he tells you,
do you want to have the domain listed above?
You say, yes, great,
choose a domain.
Now, if you have,
for example,
a domain on GoDaddy,
it's automatically integrated.
Oh, wow, OK.
You just click on Azure,
and with GoDaddy,
we have a partnership,
and it automatically gives you this.
If you don't have this,
you enter a CNAME or A-record,
or whatever you enter,
so you get a link.
Or you can say,
hey, I would like Azure to give me a domain.
And you get it through Azure.
And I get it through Azure.
That's right, of course.
And all certificates,
SSL and similar for you.
And when you finish this,
you're basically up and running.
So, now,
for the database,
you say,
will you have it on the server?
You say, yes.
It does everything for you.
If you say no.
That sounds like a good job,
and you're good to go.
Not at all.
Because,
now we come to the story of migration.
Now, we have tools
that know
what you can do automatically.
What do you mean?
You have tools,
let's say Azure Migrate,
which is installed on your system.
Now, let's say it works for Windows.
Let's say a web application.
You do this,
and you do an analysis,
but let's say it's for cloud.
You enter,
let's say it is.
You enter cloud.
It tells you,
where would you like to deploy it?
You say,
great,
I'll choose,
I don't know,
what's closest to me.
Let's say it's low-earth.
Amsterdam.
Okay, let's go to West Europe.
You choose,
it takes you through the whole process.
Finish.
And what you get back is
URL.
You click on the URL,
and your site is installed.
Let's say,
okay,
we don't have these applications locally,
because we chose
a Slovenian vendor,
a WordPress site,
and scaling is not important to us,
because we are quite small.
Or maybe there are some solutions,
which are scaled to zero.
That is,
in some paths.
if the thing is not accessible,
that the replicas are simply
scaled to zero.
If the thing is only up to one.
Yes, we have a lot of these solutions.
For the most part,
when containers are used,
for example,
there is a variant,
where they are used a lot.
We have a part,
which is called Static Web Apps,
where you can use storage,
where you pay for the outbound process,
and you pay for the storage of data.
That is one part of the optimization.
The other part of the optimization,
if you have containers,
you have a lot of options.
For example,
Azure Container Apps,
which is a solution,
which is used in the background,
if you don't have it,
but if you put it in a container,
WordPress,
you can put it there,
and if there is no traffic,
you can continue,
no matter what happens.
That means,
if there are no requests
for a period of ten minutes,
you can turn it off.
However,
you can also have it
as a start-up.
Yes, of course.
You can have it as a start-up,
and things will be set up,
or I don't know.
Container Instance
is a start-up,
which is used a lot.
The trick is,
that you have a container,
which is set up,
and when you need it,
it is turned off.
And those Azure App Services,
are they a set of languages,
technologies,
that you support?
Where?
Azure App Services?
Yes, Azure App Services.
That's what you mentioned,
about the WordPress.
Yes,
the story behind it is very simple.
It means,
which team...
I will just add one more thing.
We are not talking about containers.
We are talking about,
bring your PHP file,
and upload it.
Yes,
we all understand that.
Platform for service.
Yes,
we all understand that.
We are talking about options.
Yes.
For example,
App Service,
as such,
imagine,
it is a server,
which lives somewhere,
and you get access to it.
I won't say the entire server,
but you can.
But you have access to,
for example,
to,
now you have seen,
I mean,
not Windows,
but Linux,
but you have access to,
for example,
WWW root folder,
access,
where you can have more things.
By default,
tools are already installed,
for example,
you have Node,
you have PHP,
you have certain versions,
you have,
for example,
.NET,
you have,
HTML.
Logically.
And now,
do you upgrade it yourself?
That's right.
We have...
Is this WordPress instance
upgraded by itself?
No,
no,
no.
So,
we have,
now,
you have a server.
Yes.
On this server,
tools are installed,
and,
of course,
security is the most important thing.
So,
we are responsible for this part.
You,
as a user,
have the option
to choose
which SDK
you want to use.
You can say,
latest,
which means
that when a new version comes,
it will be updated,
or you can say,
I need 4.7,
PHP for that,
because that WordPress moniker,
whatever,
for the part that I need,
I don't know,
a big plugin or whatever.
But,
the good thing is
that you have all the tools
that you already use,
you can also use them
later.
We also have integrated,
for example,
I see you said
that you are inspired.
TypeScript,
we also have an editor
that is directly,
the option
that you can
get a browser,
you can see,
we call it Monaco editor,
but,
I don't know,
you can see,
you can set the files,
you can edit them.
You can edit directly.
Yes,
yes.
So,
you can use
whichever tool you are interested in.
Because,
for example,
if we install,
if there are already pre-installed tools,
you can also
add your own,
if you want.
Aha,
ok.
This is,
in the end,
a server that you,
I will say,
don't require rent,
just so that it doesn't
mess up
with the management
of updates
and so on.
Ok,
enough
about Freezer.
Yes,
yes.
I am satisfied.
What do you say?
What else are you hiding?
I don't know,
but I think about it a lot.
For example,
normally,
this Freezer
doesn't come to Microsoft
from Slovenia.
On the other hand,
I don't know this world
that well.
I mean,
that something comes
through those partners
who have a relationship
with Microsoft.
That is,
some revenue
from PayPal
gets some help.
As for some people
who are not partners,
I know that this is
more difficult to assess.
But,
I don't know,
as we say,
this means
that something
is being hacked.
We are in some
Slovenian community
and we are not partners.
Maybe,
how do you feel
about this?
Well,
I mean,
it is very difficult
to say.
Although,
in Slovenia,
these are the business
data that I got.
So,
Cloud is used
as such.
38% of people.
Which is,
in fact,
very,
very interesting.
On the other hand,
those of you,
for example,
who are,
I don't know,
hobby developers,
but also professional
developers,
are,
for example,
in Slovenia,
we,
all of us
are in Slovenia,
and we have
various events
that are free.
So,
some are community,
some are,
for example,
third party.
I don't know,
we are going
through this
through the road.
We are in BTC,
through the road
are those
technological hubs.
And we go there
and we want to sell
things.
And then people
come and listen
and ask
from start-ups
to companies.
So,
that's
the connection
with the cloud.
But,
on the other hand,
it's like this,
we have a very,
very powerful
documentation part
that I mentioned,
which is also
very strongly
connected
with LinkedIn
learning,
as it's called.
That was
before,
I don't know
how it's called,
but anyway.
So,
for each event,
it's one
that you have
a video,
and another
that you have
in the scan
and how to deploy
and web app
on Azure.
And you have
one option
and when you click,
you can come to
the documentation
and you can say,
try this,
and you have
a button there
and it makes
a playground
and you can try
this playground
whenever you are
interested.
Or,
for example,
you sit down
on the table
and you can
see
those interactive
tutorials
in the sense
that you have
to go up
and it really
leads you
through
this simple
procedure.
Or,
if you say,
I don't know
who can help
me,
and we already
got
Microsoft
calls,
and I would
like to
deploy
Windows
in the cloud,
who can
help me,
we then
redirected
them to
partners.
We have
partners
in Slovenia
who can
help us
through
the process
of either
development
or,
for example,
various
frisbees
that you mentioned.
I also had
an example
where I helped
a butcher
to make
meat.
So,
it's not
just for
developers.
People who
are not
experts
actually
know how
to make
meat.
Great.
So,
the next
topic
we wanted
to ask
a little
more about
is
Microsoft
as an
organization
has,
I think,
over
120,000
employees.
That's
right.
How
can you
communicate
in such
a large
organization?
I mean,
that's,
I don't
know.
For example,
that's
how
you
communicate
with
people.
Maybe
you can
get a
feel for
what it
looks like.
So,
now
you know
that we
use
Microsoft
Teams
for
communication.
Microsoft
Teams
doesn't
just
have the
option
that you
can
use
to
communicate
with
people.
You
can
use
Microsoft
Teams
for
communication
with
people.
You
can
use
Microsoft
Teams
for
communication
with
people.
You
can
use
Microsoft
Teams
for
communication
with
and
I'm interested in who the
program manager is
who deals with
the specifications of
Azure Search
because I'm interested in
how it works.
And now I have an option
to go to the internal
list,
which means
200,000 to
this cut.
It works,
but
I can probably
lose my life
when I search
because it's not
logical.
I mean, it's hard
to get.
You can use it
and then at the end
you go to the art
tool and say
responsible for
Azure Search.
You get it back.
Can you show me
I don't know
hierarchy of
people?
Who developed
this specific
feature?
And you actually
get it back.
It's easy.
You get one
from a thousand
people who
are interested in you,
right?
Then you just
find out when it's
available,
right?
Because the other
thing is that
these icons
are available,
busy,
and so on.
But it's green.
No,
you're working.
When you're working,
it automatically
changes.
I also have experience
with this.
On a very
large website,
of course,
there was
Microsoft Teams,
right?
And I was there
in some development
team.
It's a huge
organization,
a thousand
engineers plus.
And the
partner actually
wrote me
on Teams
that,
hey,
you know,
how we're
going to fix
this,
or you know,
get to know
these specific
tasks,
and then
Microsoft Teams
actually offers
you answers
at some point.
Ah,
looking at the
conversation.
Yes,
looking at the
context of the
conversation,
and it was
just,
nobody knows,
I don't know.
It was really
funny.
So,
I was very
surprised.
Yes,
I was also
surprised
that,
well,
at the
time,
I was
not
really
aware of
the
fact that
there are
internal
communications
and all
activities
have to be
digitized
in order to
give you
a relevant
answer.
So,
we actually
have a
task
called
dogfooding.
So,
before
you go
to work,
you can
try to
see if
you can
actually
drink water,
invest a
lot of
money,
and,
for example,
in the third
or fourth
phase,
I don't
know exactly
which
phase,
you actually
get access
to try
it out.
And,
for example,
then you
can
actually
get
a job
in the
third phase.
So,
you
can
actually
get a job
in the
third phase.
So,
I think
that
is
a very
important
thing.
And,
I think
that
is
a very
important
thing.
So,
I
am
actually
a
student
here
in
BiH.
I
was
born
in
Bih.
I
actually
have
a job
in
BiH.
So,
that
will
be
a
very
good
job
for me.
And,
well,
I
have
a job
here
in
BiH.
I
am
actually
a
student
here
in
BiH.
I
will
be
working
here
for
a
short
while.
I
will
be
working
here
for
a
short
while.
I
have
a job
here
in
BiH.
I
am
actually
a student
here
in
BiH.
I
will
be
working
here
for
a
short
while.
I
am
actually
a student
here
in
BiH.
I
will
be
working
here
for
a
short
while.
I
am
actually
a student
here
in
BiH.
I
will
be
working
here
for
a
short
while.
I
am
actually
a
student
here
in
BiH.
I
will
be
working
here
for
a
short
while.
I
am
actually
a
student
here
in
BiH.
I
will
be
working
here
for
a
short
while.
I
am
actually
a
student
here
in
BiH.
I
will
be
working
here
for
a
short
while.
I
am
actually
a
student
here
in
BiH.
I
will
be
working
here
for
a
short
while.
I
will
be
working
here
for
a
short
while.
I
will
be
working
here
for
a
short
time.
We
were
not
enemies,
but also
culture
changed,
so the
beginning was
competitiveness,
elevator pitches,
where you
could
deploy
technology
in
a child
or
in a
helicopter,
in an
elevator
pitch.
Then
it changed
because
there was
Windows Phone
and
we
took
evangelism,
but
the cloud
came and
the story
changed a lot.
Then
culture
changed,
there was
less
competitiveness,
but less
growth.
That's what
Microsoft
did wrong.
You don't
look at
things as
problems,
but you
look at
things as
opportunities.
You don't
look at
things as
personal gains,
but you
grow together.
Microsoft is
a partnership
organization,
realistically.
We are
partners
and we
work a lot,
we have
partners
and they
are also
partners.
You
help them,
you guide them
and you
take them
where they are.
If you came to
the bank and
said,
this, this is
for nothing,
I don't know, let's take a look at Linux for example, and let's take a look at Microsoft's server.
We'll tell you, it's a pity, because in the end it's an investment.
So what we did, we said, let's embrace it, let's move forward with the progress,
let's help people to be the most operative.
These are two important things that Microsoft did.
The first one was a mission statement, which is a power every investment and every person on the planet achieves more.
And here you can see everything we have, what we're doing, the innovation, the acquisitions.
You can see that it's all about productivity.
If you're productive, you've seen it a lot in Corona.
In the end, you can change from one hour, I mean, from one day, you can become digital.
You can work from home, in a limited way and so on.
And here, for example, the culture has also changed a lot in Microsoft.
And I see that as the biggest leap.
So instead of being an adversary, you're actually a help with, a companion, as you would call it, I don't know.
Now, last year, we had a conversation with Dr. Cergol from ENDAVE, who deals with Artificial Intelligence.
We heard about ChatGTP, then a week or two ago, the debate with Bing, Panica, Marketingers are really excited about all of this.
You even wrote AI Wars.
Do you think there will be a fork on the road again?
I mean, Microsoft is always innovating, in all of its variants.
What you mentioned, AI Wars, Bing, Edge, etc.
These are things we've already changed.
In fact, AI is not a new thing.
Maybe it's just as relevant now.
It's become more visible.
That's right, it's become more visible.
For example, before we invested in OpenAI, we started with AI as a platform.
You have a business called Cognitive Services.
Cognitive Services is your translator.
You can use Bing, which means Search, Images, you can use all of these things.
Before that, people were like, you have Bing, you have Chat, you can work with that.
A few years ago, we had a bot framework, where you could take a reward and create your own bot.
But it didn't work before.
Of course it did.
I think the main thing that happened here is that we are not the only three here,
because we are behind it.
We understand how it works, but there is a very wide audience,
and they are very surprised.
In the end, I think we all know that the answers from various AI systems are very confident,
but they also know a lot of stuff.
After all, technology is still technology.
It's impressive where we are heading.
For example, it was very impressive to me,
because now everyone is talking about language models and all the variants,
and everyone is interested in what is happening behind it.
I am not an expert in data and AI,
but as a developer, I have already used the Language Understanding Intelligent System,
known as LUIS.
At that time, as a developer, because I didn't know these things,
I said, look, go to this website.
This might be an interesting anecdote, if I can say it quickly.
Imagine, I had a lecture, I mean a meeting,
where we went through how a bot is built.
One of the options that LUIS has is that you can tell it,
ok, these are all the things you are learning on the basis of,
or you had an option where you told it, look, this is a website,
and from this website you make a crawler, which is something normal,
and it finds all the information that is interesting,
and it does it from a knowledge base.
And then we had this lecture, and the co-worker did it,
and we had questions, and one of them said,
yes, but this is not true, and he said,
and he told himself,
and he said, I didn't understand it,
and I said, yes, but this is from your side,
how do you think about it, from this and this and this part.
So, communication showed him,
in what way we were able to get this information back in one hour,
already at that time, using all these technologies,
so it was very impressive.
The other thing is, for example,
most of the sites I work on now,
I automatically integrate Azure Search as a cognitive service,
which means that it does, because you have this free option,
it does, it goes through all these options,
it creates an index, and then it has all these functionalities at will,
but I, as a developer of this,
I don't know, for example,
this algorithm, the second algorithm, the third algorithm,
but what do you do, you take the service,
click, click, click, click,
you log in, and it starts working as it should.
And this is, for example, this productivity,
which is so much for the EFAM,
you can see it, for example,
Bing, if you look at it, and chat,
and everything starts working.
The only enhancement of this is to use it.
What people have seen now,
is the practical use of what used to be one-time,
but if you now combine it with someone else,
you used to have it as a decision.
I think a lot of money has been spent
to make these things work,
because this computing power
that we are using to drive it,
is expensive.
Could developers be a little more ambitious,
and use,
if now Azure has 200-300 services,
could they be a little more ambitious,
and look at the most uncommon things,
and look at the various AI,
various audio things,
because I think, I don't know,
now I have a feeling that Mars,
which thing is already very well done,
but I think there is a lot of potential
for these things to merge together
and make some product,
maybe even more in the Slovenian space,
which is perhaps a little smaller.
Let's talk about Slovenia.
We had,
and we still have,
these various hackathons,
where we experimented
to use different things.
We had, for example,
sales where fans said,
this is all you have,
these are vouchers
that you can use for $100,
and then you see.
Now, this is an answer to the question,
that there could be more ambitious developers.
Now the question is,
what does a developer need?
What does it mean,
do you want to be a developer,
solve a problem,
and then you don't look at it,
will you use a service,
or will you use virtual?
Then you have developers,
for example, who are very,
they are very afraid,
on the basis of what I do with them,
on the basis of a service,
because then they will be trapped
on that specific service.
They always look for some variants,
what will I look for,
if I want to stop very quickly,
now if I use a computer,
then I have no end.
Here we come to these architectures,
where we talk in a hybrid cloud,
which is also one such variant,
which is also a hot potato lately,
which everyone likes,
hybrid models and so on.
In other words,
it's not a mistake to try,
you go up, try,
see if it suits you,
because in the end it is always like this,
most of those students who went up
solved 90% of the problem,
10% of the problem,
which is there,
is in the details,
because it is exactly the same details
that ultimately lead to problems.
Now, for example,
when I do demos,
workshops and similar things,
I have always shown two variants.
One is to use a service
to see how easy it is
to do it,
then from scratch,
I mean from scratch,
use it in a different way,
so that they see,
okay, it's okay,
I can achieve the same,
but I will be able to do
so much, so much, so much investment.
Then they have to calculate
what their total cost of ownership is,
how it actually works,
but the point is that
the more you try differently,
the more it doesn't make sense.
I agree.
We often have this debate
that in the end you hire three people
who pay a lot of money,
get a lot of supervisors
who amortize themselves,
and a lot of guards
who we often don't understand,
if they would take
the whole infrastructure
for the service,
I think they could
achieve more.
There are examples where it doesn't work,
but I think that in our community
there is a lot of people
who don't trust
or don't do the cost-benefit analysis.
Now I will introduce
two other examples.
Let's go to this example.
Okay.
We have two examples.
One is quite difficult.
Let's go to Slovenian pride.
Slovenian pride?
We won't talk about pharmaceutical companies
or energy companies,
but we will talk about the
manufacturing industry.
Something domestic.
Example two.
Kranjska kolbasa goes to...
Oops.
Okay.
She is getting serious.
This is a company,
fictitious again,
which deals with
domestic products
in Slovenia,
but most of the time
it is bought by a pharmaceutical company.
They wanted to modernize
and upgrade their production.
Most of them were employed.
Maybe they wanted to add an employee.
They got
some investments.
100 employees.
Three servers.
Seven years old.
Amortized for a long time.
We have already paid for extended warranty.
Yes, but
we would leave everything for later.
Then we have three servers
on which we have
specific orders.
Then we have
an open source system
20 years old.
Whatever.
Then we have
some hardware.
20 workstations,
20 office phones.
A close-up picture.
The investor
invested 10 million.
Of course,
it goes in the transition line,
but he decided
to invest 1 million
in the next
three to five years
in digitalization
or reducing the risk of
a budget of 1 million
in three to five years.
We'll see what happens
after that.
It's all thought out.
Would you give it to your partners
to work on?
Yes.
It's not a partner.
It's a party.
Everything is different.
Even if a partner works,
we help
our partners.
The first thing
to do is
to have
a Cloud Adoption Framework.
A Cloud Adoption Framework
is
a tool
that
we use
to improve
the practice of
migration.
With these migrations,
the question is
not only
to migrate,
but to decide
what goes
and what doesn't.
How do we do that?
The Cloud Adoption Framework
has four phases.
The first one is a strategy discussion.
We ask
for example,
what exactly
do they want to achieve?
I'll give you an example.
We had
a partnership.
It was a real partnership.
We had a partner
who was
an analyst.
He knew
his partner very well.
He said,
for the first time,
he will show us
how the Cloud Adoption Framework works.
He will call
his partner
and she will answer your questions.
We learned how it works.
He said,
they just want to migrate a couple of virtual machines.
They want to have a base
and connect to the cloud.
The partner comes
and we start with the questions.
The questions we ask
are, what are your motivations?
Everything is documented.
We have tools
in the framework
that you use to answer
the questions.
Why do you want to migrate to the cloud?
What are your current needs?
Where do you see challenges?
What do you want to achieve?
What are your final goals?
Here, you need
a lot of people
to see
where you are going.
The example I mentioned
was that the partner
at the end of the question
is always green.
In the end, he realized
that he wanted to migrate
a virtual machine.
He wanted to go to the services
because he wanted
to be able to pay
a certain number of employees.
He had no idea
because he only talked
to the IT department.
He didn't talk to the finance minister.
He didn't talk to other people.
This is the first part
where you talk.
What exactly is the goal?
The goal is to modernize
and to go to the cloud.
The first thing
we need to do
is to know
what the cloud means.
If you don't know
what you are going to use,
that's the point.
On the other hand,
if you say
that you don't care
and you know what to do,
but in practice everyone
who has a business will want to know
what is going on with it.
That's why the key people
who decided at the beginning
are represented.
We call it the organization.
In practice,
I will use a fax from RAS.
It's a RACI matrix.
Responsible, accountable,
consulted, informed.
Good knowledge, good decisions,
good knowledge.
Who deals with governance?
Who will make sure
that everything fits
the company's policies?
For example,
we have changed everything.
I was very happy
that two days ago
Sestanek came.
We are moving to Sestanek.
Sestanek came from
finance.
He is a chief financial officer.
He said,
no, these tasks will stay here
because they are bad financial data
that we don't want
and we don't want them to go anywhere.
Everything that we talked about
for two weeks went down the drain.
Thank God, it was only two weeks.
After this decision,
people are represented
so that they know what is going on.
The third thing that is done is assessment.
Assessment is done in the following way.
First, the decision is made
to see what we have.
An inventory environment is made.
You look at it
and we have a lot of tools for that.
For example,
what is very interesting,
we use DevOps for all these tasks.
We have our own solutions.
As you know, we have GitHub,
but we also have Azure DevOps.
In Azure DevOps,
we have a generator that generates
proposals,
structures, everything you need
so that you can go to DevOps
and use this additional framework.
For example, questions,
links, sentences, scripts,
everything you need
so that you have it all in one place
and then you run the whole project
as if it were a programming thing.
Assessment is done.
When you prepare it,
you can do it in many ways.
For example,
it usually looks like this
Excel gives it to you.
This is Excel.
This is, for example,
fast storage 1 server,
fast storage 2 server,
and similar things.
You look at the server and see
8 cores,
16GB of RAM,
32GB of RAM,
a lot of disks,
but in reality,
do they really use it?
No, you don't know if they really use it.
All 8 cores can be used,
only 2.
They can use it for 6 hours.
How to do it?
This is something that we use
as a second tool.
When you prepare
the whole organization,
what happens if you know
how many people are involved,
not only do you ask people
in their inventory,
but you can also scan them
so that you can prepare
the real situation
between those who work.
In practice,
most people
do overprovisioning,
others do one-on-one mapping,
which is very consumer-friendly.
Why?
Because if you take a website
and it's full-time for one week,
and the next week
it's all over,
it doesn't make sense
to have a server
with 8 cores and 32 GB RAM
because you'll pay a lot for it
and you won't need it in the end.
That's where the advantage
of the cloud comes in.
You can change it.
For example,
we'll have 5 servers
and we'll need
servers that are
available.
We call them spot machines
or B-series machines,
which will work
as fast
and effective
and then
idle.
For example,
in practice,
you have financial management.
I won't say they're in the cloud
because I don't know
but for them it would be
a perfect example.
Twice a year,
they have a deadline.
That's how the whole of Slovenia
works.
If you cover it up,
you need a huge server.
You have an assessment
based on the tools you can use.
We call them Azure Magritte
and Azure Magritte is based on
tools that are Microsoft specific.
For example,
you gave me an example
of a virtual machine
and a couple of servers
on a website.
What's really nice
is that if we use a Microsoft version,
it's installed
on the datacenter
they have,
and it's ready for a month
and you get
an Excel report
so you can see
exactly how many requests
and IOPs there were.
Then they give you a proposal
and say this would be the best
version in Azure.
As a cloud solution architect,
we never believe that,
because it's obvious.
Most of them give you
specific examples
and that's great,
but they always respect
the highest level.
For example, this was Medium.
So they always respect
Medium.
Then you can use Lodmin
and that's why it's important to have
a list of people
and ask them
what exactly
is being done on this server.
Then you can say
if that's important.
If you talk
during an assessment
about NSDB
that we call 5 hours,
5 hours means
re-host,
re-place, re-tire,
re-main,
re-retain,
re-tire.
Retire means
I have a datacenter
and the datacenter
has a jumpbox
so you can connect to the server.
You don't need that in Azure.
Do you really need to transfer
that server to the cloud?
Obviously not.
Do you need a server that
scans the data?
Do you need it?
Azure has solutions for that.
Then you can say
if it's re-tire, re-host,
or re-imagine.
Whatever you want to call it.
Okay.
That's a great answer.
It's great that it's normal.
For example,
why I don't work with Slovenian
parties is because
I have too little identity
to be able to listen to
those conversations.
It's weird that in Tuino
it's easier to have some
mature conversations.
After all, technology is
very experienced.
If you've been in the industry
for 15 years,
it's easy to decide
which party wants to be
aligned, champion,
and have them in an organization.
That's the hardest part.
We've decided that
we want to be able to
expose our business decisions
in the cloud.
That's our recipe.
We've decided
that there are definitely
two things we'd like to
add to the cloud.
First, we currently have
an active director
who takes care of
the workstations we have.
He manages the employees
so they can apply
and provide some policies
to the systems.
We're also thinking
that the production workers
who have access control
can use the same employee
with access control.
We don't want to have
two employees,
people who are in management
and people who are in production
and don't have computers.
That's the first use case
and the second use case is
something new.
The new Austrian investor is a bit worried and is interested in how much we have in production.
We have products that are in Austria, which are of good quality.
Those that are not good, we can say that it is optically solved.
A detector detects that the sausage is not good and turns it away.
We do not trust the people in the production to be able to describe these percentages.
That is why we say that we want to have it live.
This is an IoT problem.
We are interested in how they would put it together.
First of all, I think it is normal that we do not have a use case.
We want to avoid the AD detector.
Secondly, it is a bit more modern.
This is again a question.
I will answer the question so that you understand.
I will give you a context.
Cloud Adaption Framework is one of the areas that we are working on.
If we go from the ready phase, where we know what we have and what you have changed,
the next phase is called the landing zone.
This is also in the ready phase, which is already in the migrate phase.
The landing zone covers exactly what you have changed.
The landing zone works in a way that you decide what the environment in the cloud would look like.
The first thing you do is the identity democratization.
This means that you look at what you have.
For example, Active Directory.
You can connect it to Azure and then you have federated access.
Multi-factor authentication is always included.
One of the things that we call Privilege Identity Management is included.
Zero-Glass-Black-Break-Account and similar things are included.
These are the ways in which we make sure that you know exactly when something is happening.
What this means in practice is that you have a front worker,
you have an IT admin and he or she signs up normally.
Now, everything goes through Azure Active Directory.
You create a federation on AD.
You can also move AD up in the clouds.
You create new accounts.
The idea of Privilege Identity Management has a lot of features in the orders.
In the orders, what if a front-end worker needs access to something?
We call it Intermediate Access.
It has a different name, but the point is that you can access it at the same time
and then it is automatically replaced.
We have a methodology called Zero Trust Model.
You get access, but you also lose it.
It is all automated in a way that you install it, install it,
and it connects with each other.
It is great.
This would solve the first problem.
You mentioned that you have two sensors,
which measure all products that are and are not in order.
Because of auditing and the auditing trail,
we do not trust newly acquired companies to send the right data.
This is not a common example.
For example, in the automotive industry,
you see plastic parts for BMW.
This is a problem.
In some phases, you have optical detection of all parts,
and then you lose such a manual.
If the percentage is too high,
it means that there is a systematic failure in the production
and that someone has gone too far.
This can now be used by more different operators.
For example, we have fraud detection,
which allows you to recognize what is happening on the basis of data.
This is one way in which you can combine these different operators.
You can also inform people.
We have a very powerful alerting system
where you can set up what is exactly happening,
who will be notified, and where to sign up.
This is also an option in the landing zones.
What is the biggest problem?
I just gave a few examples of these operators.
These operators can be easily replaced.
Someone can say, I would not have this operator.
But this monitoring, scanning of these areas,
you want to be able to give a note at any time.
You are interested in what happened at the service,
who was available, who was available,
what were the elements,
and you want to measure it in such a way
that it can be easily done.
This is where the landing zone is very important.
If I go back to the centuries,
we have fraud detection, IoT Hub,
which is a very important part.
IoT Hub is a domain.
I send some data via MQTT protocol.
It is a different protocol.
MQTT is one of them.
It has bidirectional communication.
You can say, for example,
I send data via REST,
or via RAW.
I want to do a real-time analysis
of the data that comes in.
I want to have a specific time frame.
I want to see what is happening.
I can get, for example,
I worked with a partner,
who sent a stream,
a video,
in a cloud.
He wanted to detect,
for example, in that video,
a problem with a machine.
For example, they were working
in rural areas.
What happened?
They had a machine there
that cut wood.
And now we know
what kind of host you are.
There is no connection there.
I mean, there is data that has to fly,
has to be there.
They were streaming on a device,
via Bluetooth.
I mean, Bluetooth streaming.
On a device that worked as a proxy.
It took the data,
put it in a cloud,
and when the data
arrived in the stream itself,
then Azure,
using Venhub,
took it,
using Cognitive Services,
or Media Services,
which took the frames out,
using Fraud Detection,
to see, for example,
what were the changes.
Everything was recorded,
in a database.
He sent a notification,
and that notification came
to all the people who were
relevant,
that they did not need
to convert the entire infrastructure.
Everything they were doing so far,
with sensors,
was relevant.
Bidirectional communication.
I mean, back.
I mean, who knew
that there was a problem?
When someone was cutting a motor,
they didn't wait for half an hour,
for it to cut.
When the tractor was cut in half.
And what happened?
He sent the information
to the proxy,
then via Bluetooth,
he sent it to the machine,
and the machine shut down.
They tested it.
Although they didn't have a motor,
they only had a drill.
But we saw that there was
a new climate,
when he started drilling.
How long would a round trip
take? A few seconds?
For example,
we send something,
it's sent by e-mail.
It depends on the service.
We have five services,
and they have a certain service license agreement.
And for a specific month,
it has to be delivered
in 10 milliseconds.
If you choose a service,
a global service,
it has to come from there.
How does it come?
For example, if you're going to
make a round trip to the sea,
you'll need a few seconds
to get the information.
If you take
a solution,
for example,
if you're hosting something,
it has to come.
We have ways to connect
the whole part,
so that the latency
with the network is reduced.
For example,
ExpressRoute is one of the solutions.
This means that
you have a direct connection
with the providers,
HANA, Telekom, etc.
You have a direct connection
to Azure,
to the ad servers
all over the world.
The ad servers
are the most interesting.
Cloudflare has everything.
If you fly there
and want to access it,
you'll get the data
because it's spread close to you.
The closest ad server
is in the South.
When you fly to the South,
you go directly to the Azure backbone.
If we look at how much
data centers are connected
all over the world,
data centers are
in a lot of countries.
I don't have an exact figure,
but data centers are a bit like the sea.
When you decide,
you can get to it very quickly.
I would recommend
this part.
The most important thing
is that you can
change students,
automatically measure them,
so you know what the problem is.
For example, the service must be secure.
Who can access it?
These are relevant data.
For example, you said that Klobasa is protected.
Who can access it?
I don't know.
It must be protected,
so that all these things
are protected.
A lot of services are worried about it,
but CAF, Cloud Adoption Framework,
is worried about all the practices
being used in the best way.
One more question
about access controls.
For example,
I decided to establish a company
called Plosko in the EU.
We implement
access controls,
we have digital maps,
people can go there,
open the door,
and return.
Now, we have a small
security guard.
We know that we have
access controls in the cloud or locally.
For me,
Plosko in the EU
is easiest to integrate
so that I can open the door.
It's an open LDAP,
open ID connect,
a typical integration.
For example,
if I want to access
employees' names
and their
personal information.
We are connected via ADI.
We have Azure Active Directory
and Federation Services
that connect directly.
You can use open ID or LDAP
if you want.
We also have other services
that connect people
who don't have it.
For example,
if someone comes
and receives a card,
how will you identify him
and how will you know
what this person can do,
where he can access, and so on.
We had an insight
when we were working on a company.
We were playing with IoT
and we were working on the lights.
If someone comes,
the light turns on.
We were working with the employee
and he always had a ping.
We have solutions
such as
Azure B2C,
Azure B2B,
and similar services
that can be used by Azure Active Directory.
But it is also designed
to be used
by external logins.
I can make an account
in Azure Active Directory
and I can sign up
for anything.
For example,
outlook.com, twitter.com,
gmail.com,
and so on.
I can sign up
normally
and I can connect
to the entity in the cloud.
If you have an entity in the cloud,
you have all the enterprise services
that are on the cloud,
such as monitoring,
privilege identity,
and similar services
that you can perform.
Also,
what is nice
is that you get an option
for those who want to sign up
for a developer.
You get back
a way
to connect
to your code
that you have
in the application.
Now,
we talked about motorcycles.
We also talked about helmets.
We also talked about Zaire.
Two
questions
I still have.
One is about the community.
I will give you the last example.
I see that we are
close to the end.
The third example
that we wanted to give you
is a little more edgy,
a little closer to Kubernetes.
I assume that
you are more interested in it.
I will describe it to you.
The example is
Rocke,
a player who travels to Slovenia.
Do you know him?
No.
I mean, I know him.
I didn't play with him.
He ruled it.
A lot of girls
didn't go there.
When our podcast
will be listened by a lot of people,
Rocke will become even more popular.
We will now
do a startup.
Nothing has been done yet.
We can easily do anything.
There is a desire
for a multiplayer Rocke game
with an AI player,
player-to-player,
and also
with a player.
We have some AI models
that need to be trained
on a large amount of data,
make some
GPU-intensive computations.
Then we want
to have a mobile and web app.
We want to have
notifications.
That's nothing special.
Now we want to have
bi-directional communications,
WebSockets and HTTP2.
We expect a lot of users,
as we said.
What else?
We have a cousin who is a VC investor.
He will be our capital today.
No problem.
What is more important
is this
market.
We have to do it quickly.
How would you do it?
The question is
if we take all
the things
that we have already changed.
You have changed Kubernetes.
Kubernetes is a stupid thing
that everyone takes and says
that it is the solution for the whole problem.
But for this thing
it is not necessary
because it is the best solution.
It is nice, you can use it,
but it would require
different services.
Before you chose Kubernetes,
you should have believed in something else.
Of course.
I gave you a good example.
Kubernetes is a law.
You can do miracles,
you can destroy a lot of things.
I liked this.
I have a Raspberry Pi cluster
that is now black
because you can burn a Raspberry Pi
if you play too much.
And similar things.
What I want to say is that
Kubernetes is really great,
but sometimes you have to look
at what you need.
Kubernetes solves the problem
that you have a lot of servers
that you want to self-manage,
that you can communicate with each other,
that you can quickly scale,
that you can add servers.
Let me give you an example.
We used Service Fabric.
The learning curve of Service Fabric
is a bit more complex.
But let me give you
an example of a game
where planes were shooting each other.
What we use from behind
is an actor model
where
it shows
in detail
the framework that is used
by Orleans.
It is a Microsoft framework
that is open source,
but has been used since then.
Based on this,
they made tests
and used Service Fabric.
There is also a great video
on YouTube
where they demonstrate
how all these actors work.
It's phenomenal how quickly they do it.
Wait,
in the Orleans framework
there are names
such as
Silos,
etc.
From behind,
the whole story is
that you have a framework
that solves the problem
of how you store data,
how you work
with objects,
where you store them,
where they live.
Silos can be imagined
as one of the
very fast serializers
that store the state
of an object.
For example, a player
on a disc
through memory
is equal to
Orleans.
It is also open source.
Orleans is not just about
taking everything.
You can say,
I would like just one part.
You have a reference.
Ok, let's go.
You need to know what you are doing.
But if you want a fast serializer,
you take it down,
save it and move on.
My point is that
it depends on whether you have
already done the programming.
Sorry, additional question.
I have already developed
in Gojo.
Yes, in Gojo.
We already have a prototype.
That's not a problem.
What are you going to talk about?
In Gojo,
there is a different story.
Service Fabric
works on .NET.
It is a .NET framework.
.NET Core,
which runs on other platforms,
Orleans works on it.
And most of the work.
In Gojo,
for example,
if you want to use
front-end storage,
we have libraries
that you can use.
You also have
Go SDK
for managed libraries
with Azure.
For example,
you need to create a new service.
You can do it through Go.
You can easily
add things from scratch.
You also have web apps
that run on Go.
You also have background services,
where you can use scripts
from within Go.
The only thing you need is .exe.
You can't even hear it for women.
We have a way to use Go.
It is a game
where you have real-time communication.
You can use Go
in
a network,
and you can use it
for all communication.
You also have a learning machine.
Communication between them is PubSub,
which we have as a server.
We also have SignalR as a server.
SignalR is a Microsoft real-time framework.
PubSub is a web PubSub.
It is also
one of the solutions
that we have in this area.
It allows real communication
through websockets.
It also automatically knows
if a websocket is available.
You can optimize
everything in one place.
For example,
if I want to do machine learning
in one place,
if I want to do applications in one place,
if I want to do logging in one place,
in short, everything.
You can do it in one place,
scale it,
and you can put a task here.
The next question is
that we are very popular in Asia.
Multi-regional is on the table.
The second task
that I would like to do
depends on
whether you have a relationship or not.
NoSQL.
I can't go there,
but I can go there.
It doesn't matter.
If you are young,
you can change everything.
Is PubSub a global service?
Yes.
PubSub is easy.
Global services mean
that you can use it in more regions.
We have a global service
that we have in the world.
For example,
Traffic Manager,
which is a DNS-based
load balancer.
It is a global service.
You create it in a specific resource,
but it is global.
You create PubSub in a specific region,
but you have more options
to choose more regions.
You have a load balancer.
You have more ways
to use them.
I would like to add one more thing.
You can ask me later.
If I were to choose
something like this,
I would probably choose mix and match.
I would choose services
because I don't like machine learning.
Also, if you want to run
a machine learning that will work well,
you need a GPU.
That means you need
different virtual machines.
Kubernetes supports this.
Kubernetes chooses
this.
Again, this is expensive.
I would rather choose a pet service
in cooperation with machine learning
or in cooperation with
Cognitive Services,
which would combine PubSub
for communication between them.
I wouldn't choose PubSub
as a single service.
I would choose Event Grid.
Event Grid is
a global PubSub.
Event Grid?
Event Grid, yes.
Event Grid.
In Azure,
you have three main
messaging services.
One is Event Grid, which is a global
PubSub.
Then you have Enterprise
Service Bus.
Then you have
PubSub.
Event Grid
means you can
get inside...
You have Event Hub and similar
services for real-time streaming
and IoT, which we talked about.
Event Grid allows you to
collect a huge amount of information
and then decide how
this information will go forward.
You can filter on-wire.
You can filter
and decide.
You have
different formats
for the service.
The good thing is that you have
a standardized format
which is called Cloud Events.
It is also supported by Google and AWS.
You can cross-code.
That's right.
If you look at my GitHub,
on my github.com,
don't cry yet.
It's huge.
We did a webinar and we did a simulation in real-time for the use of serverless.
It looked like this. We had a hardware that was running and we simulated it.
This hardware was a Lambda function on AWS. It sent information to Event Grid.
Event Grid then produced all this information and sent it to the website.
On the website, the person then got the information and did a real-time data transfer.
Then we simulated it in such a way that this hardware, Lambda, sent data to the key.
Then we sent 100,000 data forward and Event Grid took it.
They did a real-time simulation when the whole thing moved up.
Then we showed how it was processed and worked on it.
Then we also had a Power BI as a reporting tool where you could pass this information to the person.
We also do some scoring.
Probably through Event Hub and Service Bus, you can easily pump it into a warehouse.
Yes, you can.
Event Grid is a PubSub.
You have a publisher and a subscriber.
We have a task called Stream Analytics, which collects data.
Then you write a query like language, what the data did, and you have an output.
The output is easy.
SQL is easy. Cosmos DB, for example.
I would recommend Cosmos DB because it has a task that has…
Can you tell us a bit more about Cosmos DB?
Cosmos DB is our solution for SQL.
It uses Sharding and similar tools.
The idea is that it uses NoSQL-like languages.
You can use it as a click API.
You can use SQLite syntax.
You can use MongoDB.
You can use MongoDB Connection.
It transforms when it's MongoDB.
Yes.
In the end, it writes performantly to more locations.
The advantage is that you have very low latency.
Plus, Geo Replication.
You can easily replicate it in Asia.
Everyone is good at it.
Everyone who uses TikTok.
And similar people who use it.
If this company, Torok.AI, started with budgets are tight,
and I tell you that mind developers, devops, cloud engineers,
mind developers don't like it,
I would be surprised if there is also this Azure for Gaming.
You have some products in this space that are specifically made for the gaming industry.
Yes, that's true, but it's a field that is really unknown.
Unfortunately, this field is really unknown.
This technology that we have now changed,
I think our audience will get to know it and use it.
You probably have it for some verticals.
We have clouds for very different variants.
You have a cloud for health.
You have a cloud for non-profit.
A cloud for the automotive industry and similar things.
So people are afraid to look at it from the inside,
their verticals that they are trying to develop.
That's right.
When someone decides to develop a game.
I told you about a game from my table,
because I cover Kubernetes, Dotnet, PowerShell and PAS.
So from my table, if I were to fly,
people who play games would probably remember
how the developers specialized for this field.
Then they could go into this story in more detail.
What is true is that...
I lost the thread.
PlayFab is much better.
No, no, I just want to say that if people go to our documentation,
in Azure we have one section called Azure Architecture Center.
Azure Architecture Center is not only about having a huge architecture,
but it also has one of the options for design patterns,
architecture styles, so that people understand what it is all about.
Then there is the next section that we call Technology Selection.
And then there is another section that we call Different Clouds.
In Different Clouds are all the information that people see
and can choose exactly which devices are connected,
what they can use, and so on.
It's like when you open a book, you help yourself.
Either your hand hurts or the cover.
Then there is a selection that brings you to the technologies that...
You help yourself.
It brings you to the technologies that you put some inputs into,
so that you can say, these are the three options out of the 300.
Yes, and here we go back to the story we mentioned at the beginning.
And then you have the helpers, as I mentioned at the beginning,
when we have internal bots that help you choose.
And one of them is the roadmaps that we have.
If you want to cut something, you can go to learn.microsoft.com
and you get a guide that takes you through the whole process.
And there you also have the option to choose and it includes
this part with connections, with interactive devices,
and also to us, contact to us.
So you have these options.
If, for example, you want to do a little more,
and you want specialized help, what happens?
You learn, you work, and then you say,
hey, there are five of us, we are self-developers,
what's the problem?
We need to set up a database.
Or I don't know, that it will really be set up correctly.
How can we do that?
And then you go to the marketplace,
and it gives you all the partners that are specialized for this area.
And then you say, okay, you are the closest,
let's take a look and make a story.
We solved the problem.
That's it.
Now I would really like to,
we have something in common,
so I would like to try to connect.
We are fully open-sourced.
We have a lot of partners.
This is very familiar to us.
And we've already talked a little bit about the community.
And maybe open-source is also successful because of the community.
So I wrote a couple of open-source projects
that I somehow discovered under Microsoft.
I wrote VS Code, TypeScript, .NET.
A few years ago, I chose Microsoft Searching Linux
and the whole story of how Microsoft joined the Linux Foundation,
that it is in the Linux kernel security list,
that kernel patches contribute.
And because of that, we also see
that you have Windows Services for Linux,
and you can use it on Windows.
There is some kind of collaboration,
and I went to look at other projects,
and I found that Windows calculator, for example,
is now open-sourced, released, written in C++ and C Sharp,
and is pre-installed on Windows.
I see that there is some kind of full transformation
happening in this area with Microsoft.
And now I'm trying to find a space
to ask Andras about PowerShell,
because you're also a full-time user,
and you know a lot about it.
This is your segue.
This is a bit of a joke, but it's not.
We are used to, if you go more from the Unix ecosystem,
and for us, I usually look at the black terminal,
because we need to use browsers,
but it's very close to us.
And then we had an environment,
and we were like, okay, this is our circle.
What kind of question would be the best?
And it was kind of an interesting pattern.
I think that my peers have a big problem
with learning PowerShell,
because it's hard to hear it.
For example, a few years ago,
we had some data flow, some files,
and now I know that if I right-click,
I can compress this file into a zip file,
and then I was like, okay,
I'm going to do this with PowerShell.
In Unix systems, I don't need to look at the documentation,
of course, I'm very experienced.
When you come to Microsoft as an employee,
or as a partner,
what is the way to learn PowerShell?
Because I think that the interface changes a lot.
What's the menu? What's the menu?
Because I really don't know how to click.
Okay, maybe...
Automation.
When we look at the open source,
we have a split page
with all the projects that Microsoft is working on.
If you look at the number of commits
that we've made in open source in the last few years,
it has increased a lot.
You just mentioned a few of them.
TypeScript, for example.
If you look at what's in common in all of this,
if you look at what TypeScript is based on,
you still have JavaScript, but you have these objects,
you have these languages.
Who is it based on?
If you look at it again,
Helzberg is based on C Sharp,
which is again an object language.
PowerShell, again, is an object language.
Everything works in such a way
that it becomes more and more productive.
We also have our own Linux, for example,
and similar tasks.
We're not just bosses.
AKS, for example,
Kubernetes Service,
has also invested a lot in the fact
that we've open sourced a virtual kubelet.
It's a small task that allows you...
It's an interface that you can use
to write your own kubelet,
which Kubernetes understands as its own.
It's an agent that lives on the machine
that makes sure that the information stays
and so on.
And what's great about it is that
because you have a virtual kubelet,
you can access the current services.
What's the problem?
I know I went a bit too far,
but that's how I get back.
That's how I get back.
But just as an illustration,
what's the problem?
Kubernetes still has so much behind it,
and what's the problem
if a virtual kubelet is missing?
You can make a new one,
but the new system will do it automatically.
But what's the problem?
You'll lose half a minute,
or 20 seconds, or more.
You need the task now.
If you sell some factories,
that's a lot of money flying around.
For example, in the future,
you can buy a kubelet with computers
that are already in the back,
and then the task is done.
Let's go back to PowerShell.
I jumped out of open source.
But it's open source, isn't it?
Yes, it is.
You have PowerShell on github.com,
forward slash Microsoft,
forward slash PowerShell,
and you get everything back.
The whole source code,
and you can see how things work.
And,
I think,
and,
and what's nice,
is that,
Microsoft doesn't always tell you
that you have to use PowerShell.
That's your own choice.
It doesn't always tell you
that you have to use Windows.
You can use Linux.
Although, you'll probably be a little limited,
because certain services on Linux
are definitely not.
For example, in Teams,
you can only use Skype.
You can't use Outlook,
and similar things.
And they didn't always tell you
that you can't use other services.
But,
you can also use Bash.
For PowerShell,
I started to learn it
at the beginning,
especially because
I saw a demo
where a person did
a search on the registry
to use
basic instructions
through PowerShell.
What did it look like?
For example, if it was in Bash,
you go to the terminal,
you type in cd Downloads,
and you type in ls,
and it takes you back.
In PowerShell,
because it's a dotnet,
you can use it
as a provider.
And it's the same.
You type in cd,
and in the registry,
you type in ls,
and you get the registry back.
You type in ls, star,
and so on.
In short, it gives you
a lot of power.
You don't need to type 30 times
to get the information back,
but you really get the power.
What's the biggest power?
I wrote it down,
and it's on my github,
for Kubernetes.
It's an engine,
where you type in kubectl,
which is a client tool
from Google.
You type in kubectl,
get pods.
I wrote an example of PowerShell,
where you type in cd,
pods.
You type in ls,
and it takes you back to pods.
The interaction
you want to have
with the system is completely different.
You don't work
only with text objects,
but you work with objects.
You use objects,
and you control them.
That's why I chose
the code.
If you look at the documentation,
all the examples are made
with Bash, with PowerShell,
and so on.
The easiest way, of course,
is to use
Microsoft Shop,
because on all servers
PowerShell is already
on top by default.
You don't need to install anything.
We have Windows subsystem for Linux,
but what's the problem?
On servers,
Windows 2022
is already an option to add it,
but you can install it as a package.
Then you have to use Bash,
and you can learn it.
We also have a tutorial on that.
Microsoft has an official tutorial
on www.microsoft.com,
where you can learn
how to use Bash,
and so on.
With PowerShell,
it's already built-in,
and you can use it normally.
Microsoft has also
introduced Open Source,
by the way,
Windows Terminal,
which is a tool on Windows
that can be used
not only for Linux,
but also for other ideas
that the community has,
regarding the use of Terminal,
and how it looks like for an application,
as it should look like,
in terms of usability,
design, usability,
portability, and so on.
It's the same as if,
for example,
on Linux,
I would take and use
Electricity,
or I would use Fish,
I would use it for those
who don't have it.
It's not a plus,
it's easier,
because we are Microsoft,
in the sense that all the documentation
is connected.
And you have your own security,
as we said.
It's nice to know
those things,
because when you come to a company
that does migration,
there is automation,
and you have to give something to them,
and everyone understands that,
even those who work
for Windows servers,
they understand PowerShell,
because it's integrated into the system.
I hope I answered your question.
I think you did.
Andraž, any last thoughts?
No,
I think it was great.
I think we didn't say
a lot of things,
so if someone listens to this,
we will put the links in the description.
Yes, yes.
I learned a lot of things.
Some things are just
symmetrical,
and others are new to me.
So it was great for me.
Bojan, any last thoughts?
My last thought
is that
you can see
that
the mission statement
that we have,
Empower Evernalization
on the planet,
I can see it in practice,
and I can say that
I am proud to be a part of it,
and to be a part of
Microsoft for the last time.
Very interesting things are happening,
it's fun to learn something new
every day.
That's one of the things
you have to do as a cloud solution architect,
you have to learn a lot.
That's a key thought.
Bojan,
Andraž, thank you for your time.
Thank you for listening,
thank you for your attention,
give us some feedback,
share with your friends, colleagues
and experts,
and see you next week.
Good luck, goodbye.
Thank you for having me, good luck.