And that's how our jingle came to be.
Today we are here in Porto Rojo,
in the conference room of Make It,
Jcon, Sjoug...
Wait, what else?
Yeah, Slovenia, cheers!
That's what's written there.
And that's where we're going to film
a new episode of Grodje.
An episode that we didn't really plan,
but because we met a great guest at the conference,
we decided to do it very spontaneously and quickly.
Especially because it was a great day at the conference
and I think we could hear more of what we heard today
and our guests as well.
The episodes may be a bit shorter than the others,
but everything will be very interesting.
So, that's a soft intro.
And I'd like to introduce the guest first.
Today with me is Amadea Derenda Mujezinovic.
Hello.
Amadea... Amadea...
I'll try to pronounce it correctly,
so you can correct me.
She's a senior UI, UX researcher.
I don't know if you're a consultant or contractor as well,
but you're currently working for Caldi.
Before that, I think you worked for Messi for 7 or 8 years.
That's right.
A company that makes medical devices, if I'm not mistaken.
You're also a very visible and very active member
of the UX community in Slovenia.
And... What else do I have to say?
You're also a co-founder of the Screen Savers project,
which is, if I understood correctly,
and you can correct me,
is an academy for UI, UX
and you teach courses for people
in service design, UX...
What else?
Actually, how to come...
How to prepare what to build,
and then somehow move it to development.
So we're actually going...
Now we're preparing to go into product management,
or this part, how to talk to stakeholders and so on.
But basically, we started from the fact
that this is a specific knowledge,
that we have visual designers,
and then when they come into tech,
it's a whole different world.
And there are other competencies that are also important.
And a few years ago we realized
that it's very difficult to do
and learn when you come from a company.
And also companies really don't know
how this role can help in reality.
We said, okay, let's do a few courses.
We did a few courses, now we have some mentors,
who cover various aspects from research
to product management, to UI.
We would also go more into leadership topics,
because we see that there is still a lot of space here.
And then there are things that we do on the side,
like consulting in companies, coaching,
also how to work with designers,
how to transform design as a role in the company.
So there are a lot of things.
Are you a corporation?
Are you a company?
A company.
A company, okay.
And otherwise you work in various fields.
That's right.
In this role.
Both are co-founders, and I'm still working.
So both take on the role of some people,
and I'm still working in Hlavijar,
and I'm still in Kaldi, because I've already changed.
So on the one hand, I set up these systems,
and then I'm trying to move more of this to Slovenia.
Okay.
Now, here I wrote down,
I don't know if you're still starting,
but for a while there was this GoJam,
where you actually helped to promote public administration,
or how to improve public services,
or can you tell me more about that?
Yes, actually, GoJams were part of an initiative called Service Jams,
and it's a global initiative,
where on a weekend,
the process that Service Designers and UXers use,
you do that on a weekend,
in 48 hours, you come up with an idea,
and then to a tested prototype.
These are hackathons.
It's not really a hackathon,
it's more about what to build,
than what to actually build.
Because there's a lot of code in hackathons,
and a lot is expected on the delivery,
but for us, it was always more,
when you go out to talk to people,
they have this problem,
to make the first prototype,
because this is a prototype.
But it's always around government services, right?
No, there were three.
We did three in a row.
There was the Service Jam,
which was very general,
about designing machines,
then there was the GoJam,
which was aimed at public administration,
and then there was the Sustainability Jam.
It was led by a team from Germany,
so we were very connected with them,
and we were very close to the community,
it was very fine, very powerful.
Also, how I got into UX,
my background is in graphic design,
because I've never really felt at home.
And then there was this jam,
I was a student, I needed a job,
I've been a cook for seven years,
I had no real experience,
and then there was this workshop,
I didn't even know what a workshop was.
And then there were a lot of people from D-Lab,
from the design studio,
and then I was like,
maybe I should go,
maybe I'll get a job out of it.
And then I came to Cain,
and they told me about this process,
and I was like, oh my God,
this is how it should be done,
this is how we have to do it.
If you say graphic design,
we're talking about...
What does graphic design mean today?
Did they teach you to draw, I don't know,
binoculars?
Did they teach you to make apps?
I mean, give us an explanation.
What did they teach you today?
That's actually a very good question.
Since I've been at FACS for a long time,
we'll never know.
For example, I worked at NTF,
Graphic Interactive Communication,
and the cool thing about NTF was
that we learned a little bit of everything.
From making some videos,
to creating some websites in Joomla,
to, I don't know,
having math and everything,
and we also had a little bit of graphic design.
What did we have back then?
There was graphic design for posters,
packaging, typography, and so on.
I think that most of all NTFs
still focus on graphic design,
around typography, around printing.
Everything goes in digital,
digital as a static, unnecessary thing in the media.
While when you work in TEC,
the apps are really alive.
And here, of course,
FACSs don't change very quickly,
they change the curriculum a lot,
but TEC develops very quickly.
In those computer schools,
they tell you that in the beginning
the colors will remain the same,
then you change the programming language,
and some concepts remain the same.
With graphic design,
I can ask you this question,
that the colors will still be the same.
The basic skill set will probably still be the same,
but the technology changes everything.
I think that the colors will remain the same,
the type will remain the same,
the look and feel, the brand, everything will remain the same.
But there is a big difference
in how these things are built.
In graphic design,
one of the things that I think
I suffered a bit with,
is that everyone has their own eyes.
And if you're not really that good,
it's hard to have a presence,
it's hard to have a status,
in the sense that you can say to a teacher,
this makes sense,
we won't give you any more.
But with UX and service design,
you go to research,
and someone else tells you these things,
and you bring back the proof,
and you're like, if so many people said that,
is it possible?
Sometimes it's not true, but...
Can I say something else?
I wrote down that you also have some drinks.
I'll say it like this,
if you're interested in UX, service design, UI design,
go to screensavers,
and go to GoJams,
but you also have some meetups,
or drinks,
we can invite people to that,
if you're interested.
Go ahead.
Service design,
times UX drinks,
so,
sometimes we do service design drinks,
one team,
Evo Iršinjaklević did a UX meetup,
and then we said,
this is a similar audience,
where we do similar things,
what if we combined it?
So, service design times UX drinks Ljubljana,
we do them monthly,
between October and May,
so we're online, we're live,
we have our guests,
we have our guests.
Do you have a presentation?
Usually,
we have some guests,
and then there are different formats,
from round tables,
to presentations,
some classic ones,
again, we have a lot of guests,
and we collaborate on the format.
We also work in an interactive way,
we include people,
it's very important for us
to include people during the event,
and to do it in some way.
To try to make it very interactive.
Great.
I'll put the link below,
so if you're interested,
go check it out.
Join us.
Now we're going to talk about
your talk at the conference.
As I said,
there were four tracks,
we heard from Kubernetes,
to Java,
and other technologies,
bass, etc.
But your talk stood out,
because it didn't fit
into just Java.
But when I listened to the talk,
in the end,
it was the biggest question.
I think there were ten questions,
people felt that what you said
is very important,
and that they have a lot more questions.
That's why I wanted you to say it again,
so that people can relate.
I would just like you to say
what the title was.
Or should I say it?
I already have the title.
The title was
Coexistence between Product Designers
and Developers.
The summary was
that developers,
product designers,
and product people
have to cooperate.
Why, how...
That was the talk.
And...
The starting point.
Then what?
First of all, thank you.
Thank you.
I have to say that
I was really...
I spent two weeks
asking myself
what I will do
and what I will need.
What will I have
to sell
to the European community.
I am very happy
that it was such a call.
And...
I talk a lot
about cooperation,
how we have to cooperate
and communicate
so that good products
and good apps
can only be created
if we work well together.
This is always reflected
in all the friction
that happens in teams.
But mostly because
we don't speak the same language.
And...
I don't know.
I often hear
how designers
don't know how to talk to developers
and we don't understand them.
On the other hand,
they don't understand us.
And nobody from us
speaks business.
And...
To be honest,
this cycle is a bit
strange.
It can already explode.
And...
There you gave
a good pitch
at the beginning
in the kitchen.
And you used
a very good analogy.
Say it again, please.
Yes.
We talked about
all the possible frameworks
that we often
take very seriously.
If they work on Spotify
they will also work for us.
And they are often taken as recipes.
We have some business
insights
for the beginning.
Then we add two back-end developers
to build
a strong base
for the team.
Then we add a front-end developer
and a designer
to make it better
and to improve it.
And a product manager
to mix it all together.
We put everything together.
We cook 6-8 sprints.
We mix all the other products.
And that's it.
Then we have an MVP.
It's strange why...
It's true.
The problem is
that the MVP
is not really an MVP.
I don't know if we should say
MVP 1.0.
Those things that we put out
are 0.5, 0.6.
Because in the end
to do something
in 0
it's really 0.
You do it well
when you put it out
but it's so stripped down.
This kitchen has a bombastic
logic.
Did it connect you
when you came to
the triangle
where you connected
the product manager,
designer
and developer?
Why does this triangle
have to work?
First we had to decide
what we're going to cook.
What's the MVP
that we're going to follow.
And now, as I said
in Real Life is Easy
you look at the time,
how many people are in the fridge.
In a digital product
it's not that simple.
Nothing is really simple
in a digital product.
When you have
some stakeholders,
more people influence
the menu.
Here we work
more with the main
cooks.
I think we often
forget that
in design, in development
you have a very, very
important role.
As I said,
we're not just cutting
vegetables.
But we have to cooperate
in this process
even before it starts cooking.
To define
the product well,
to define what we're doing,
why we're doing it,
for whom we're doing it.
The management brings
the business side here.
They make sure that things are
viable.
Development makes sure
that we can build things.
Design makes sure
that there's
always a user
for whom we're working.
It makes sure that
users are found
and that you want to use it.
Not that it's just
one person.
The role
of the developer
and designer
in functional teams
changes.
You can't
wait
for someone to magically
solve everything
and then you'll
be like,
let's build it.
You have to be very proactive
to get stakeholders
involved in the process.
They have to be
very early.
People are aware of that.
Of course.
Let me ask you
how do you
get developers involved
in the process?
What do you expect
from developers
in this way of cooking?
It's great
when developers start
from scratch.
When they come to research
or listen to an interview,
they understand better
what they can build.
Developers have
a specific point of view
and how they expand the world.
It's important
that we don't dream
about design or product.
Stories that are impossible.
It's great
when developers
and stakeholders
get involved.
It's important
that they are accountable
and that
they are the ones
who have to talk
and sell
and so on.
It's a mutual effort.
It's not the case
that developers
do a lot of work
and then come up with new
goals.
It's just
that
this question
took me a while
to answer.
I wanted to say that
if people...
It's easiest
to build things
without asking.
We have to
do it quickly
and we won't do research.
Research lasts.
Research is an effort.
Research means more people.
It means more meetings.
Tell me,
does it pay off?
Does it pay off to do research?
Tell us.
I think that research
pays off the most.
The best thing
that can happen is
that you do research and you know
that no one has this problem
and you are saved for years
and years.
I'm a bit afraid of that.
It's one thing
that
according to my experience
that research
has to be huge
and that you never need
money and resources.
On the other hand,
we don't necessarily want to know
what people have to say.
Also, a big part of it is
that
you need someone
who knows how to ask questions.
That was a question
today.
What if
we go
to an interview
and people have a wish list
and then we build a rocket?
Yes.
You can't take everything
that people say
as a feature that they
will build.
I think that I wrote
that what they say is not what you will build.
It's just the input
that you deconstruct
and then you know
what the community wants.
How do you choose
people to include
in your research
product?
Do you randomly sample people
or do you call the company's director?
Who do you include?
Do you include a website?
Give us an example of people
you include in your research.
It depends
from project to project.
For example, we at Caldeo
work on B2B and business applications.
It's often
a bit easier because
they are all business processes.
You know where to find these people
and you can ask them.
If you work as a consumer
for a business,
of course, you have a wider range.
On the other hand,
you have
a closer access.
You always
set goals
for which you build
in the beginning
or for which you plan to build.
Then you look at whether you really build
a company.
Is this my entire group?
It often turns out
that this is a subset
of these people.
We can target more clearly.
It's a great marketing coach
who knows exactly what to write.
It helps a lot
if you know your audience.
Audience, yes.
But do you always do this in a way for people who will pay in the end?
Is this a good indicator that you will pay for his development and you will give his priorities to the top, or...
I know it's a ungrateful question.
No, but I mean, yes, a real question.
Yes.
Sometimes it's hard to define, or rather, it's hard to determine who will pay, right?
And as far as I know, we also have different business models, right?
Because in B2B it is often the case that the user is someone else's buyer.
But...
Again...
It's important to know who you're developing a service for, right?
Yes.
It's very important to know who is the one who will benefit the most, or rather, who you will solve this problem the best.
Because if you solve this problem well for this person, for people, for a group of people, it is very likely that they will pay for it.
But these are all things that you can check within research.
We have different methods of how we do it, from checking concepts to validation, to interviewing, to testing prototypes.
In fact, this whole product development is nothing more than setting up some hypotheses,
building something, right? We want something that is as valuable as possible.
We check the hypothesis, and then we put new hypotheses on the basis of what we have learned.
In fact, you develop the product in a way that you make some small changes,
you put them out, you measure how they work, how people react,
and then you come back to the hypothesis, you check it, you implement it, and then you repeat the cycle.
This is the interactive approach to the development of digital stories in this way.
That's right.
When we first talked, I said that our podcast is MVP, and then you corrected me and said it was some other thing.
Tell me more about it.
It's MLP.
Minimal Lovable Product.
Yes, what is it?
There are two theses.
One is that we have to start at the beginning with MVP, which is the basic core functionality.
Then it comes a little more from the design, that the product has to be a little more lovable,
so that the user can use it, and that it is not just a basic core functionality,
but that you already think a little about what are the flows, what color is it,
how can we do some small things to make the use of it more pleasant.
Yes, ok.
So I think you definitely did this for Grodno.
We are somewhere, but I don't know.
Ok, tell me what is the next stage?
For MVP, MLP, what is the next stage?
When will you say, we are no longer MVP, we are now a product?
I mean,
is there a phase when you say, ok, now we have made a real product,
we will now only make small incremental changes?
Does this phase exist?
In my experience, when I worked on a lot of different products,
the big fear was that we were going to do MVP,
then we did all that research,
and then at some stage, someone who was maybe a decision maker before the story,
said, ok, now we want to put 100,000 users in this MVP.
Do you know how to get over this gap,
or how do you make this transition to a real product?
If you understand what I'm saying.
Yes, I understand.
I don't know if I have the best answer,
but in the ideal world,
it would look like you are building MVP,
then you find out approximately how many users there are,
in a certain time period.
MVP is built quickly and has its limitations.
Recently, we had a really good talk on this topic at Drinks,
where we talked about how MVP works with no-code tools.
Just because it's really about the validation of the concept,
and at some point, you really have to put the MVP aside,
and maybe not look at it from scratch,
but put something new on it.
We can go back to what you said,
that the inclusion of developers in the development phase
is what helps.
The developers say, look,
the constraints of what we are going to do are
that there can be a maximum of 5 users,
and that everyone is from the same folder.
That's right.
Before I ask you more about the common language and toolset,
tell me a little more about the decision-making.
I think you touched on that as well.
There was also an analogy on Steve Jobs.
Can you tell us about that, please?
Because it's very important to me.
A big part of our job is decision-making,
which is the acceptance of a bunch of decisions
based on some full insights
that you get from different directions.
How do you decide that one direction is right,
or that two directions are right?
And then there's the example of Steve Jobs,
who always wears a black turtleneck and blue jeans,
because it reduces the number of decisions
that he made on a daily basis.
And it's true that we have more decisions
on the day we have to make.
We have less headspace,
or rather, when we are influenced,
we make worse decisions.
And the first step for making good decisions
is headspace,
which means that you can,
that you are capable,
that you are able...
To somehow focus your mind
on what the decision today is,
that we have to make.
And the other part of that is
that we lack a repetitive understanding
of what those decisions mean.
And now, again, we don't have
that common language
that we used at the beginning
to really understand
what a decision really means.
And here comes the product trio again.
We have all three perspectives.
We have product, we have design,
we have development.
All three are important.
And here we have to understand each other very well
and understand the implications
that come with every decision.
And the problem is that
we don't have time in teams
and we don't have that common language.
Okay.
Let's go a little further
into the common language
that we speak.
I expected at the beginning
when I heard you,
what kind of God would you imagine?
What kind of God
could that common language be?
And very simply,
where do you decide
what is the easiest,
what is the most expensive
for all stakeholders?
Yes, visual beings.
Visualization.
All the basics,
why we prototype,
why show design in prototyping.
Not only design,
prototyping is not a new thing.
When we start building things together,
and when we start looking at them together,
it's much better
than just talking to each other.
Because with words,
one word for me
means something completely different
because we don't have the same experiences,
because in another experience,
another upbringing.
And it's hard to put exactly the same thing in your head.
Especially if it's about
business applications,
complex business systems.
That's right.
And then to transfer it
so that everyone understands the same thing,
it's quite impossible.
And now we can visualize these things,
but we always pay more attention
to the fact that
sometimes it's a thing,
I don't know, when you have a problem,
how to solve it,
you can't change it.
You can't just put an example
on the board and say,
okay, let's do it now.
Let's draw.
I'm not talking about
drawing interfaces,
screens,
but drawing flowcharts,
putting things on posts,
moving posts left and right,
looking for patterns.
No matter how hard
it is,
we have enough understanding
for something
to make a decision.
That means,
in your work,
you probably draw a lot of sketches,
probably flowcharts,
I understood that.
Between your slides,
you also showed paper prototypes,
which I found very interesting.
Yes.
If I understood correctly,
at MESSI,
you made prototypes
out of cardboard.
Digital cardboard.
Can you explain that?
We had an example
when we had a concept
of an app,
drawing flowcharts,
a process within
healthcare.
I was thinking,
for two days,
that I would do it,
because it was
powerful,
but in a different program.
At that moment,
I was thinking,
how can I make it
show
the interaction
I need to understand,
which has many possibilities,
in an interactive prototype.
I didn't like that.
We had a reservation
for a healthcare in Gorna Vasa.
I was like,
I have to have something.
What is the easiest way?
It was
to make out of cardboard
some kind of computer screen
to show
our healthcare.
Then I had prepared
rubber bands
out of cut post-its.
When it clicked,
I imagined
what would happen next.
From the beginning.
It was the best.
The rubber band was
made in Unigur,
and it confirmed our concept
that it would work that way.
That was it.
And today,
it's boring,
you document it, break the prototype
and you have a great result.
You probably ate
months and months of development.
In the same story.
I wrote here
that you use
a tool called Breaking Stuff Down.
You mentioned
that it's a tool
that you use.
I hope I pronounced it right.
You break the concepts
with the stakeholders
so that everyone gets the same understanding.
What do you think about it?
How do you do it?
Now,
how do you do it?
You have a tool,
for example,
Customer Journey
or Customer Journey Map
is a tool where
you get things from research
and then you map them
and then you look
at what we still lack,
what we still don't understand.
It's a powerful tool.
But
everything we start
is Breaking Stuff Down.
So,
you go to an interview,
you get, I don't know,
two pages of content
and then you have to
fit it in.
This part is still there,
this is relevant for that,
this is for marketing,
and then
you make
a sense-making.
And a lot of times
we use digital whiteboards
like Summiro,
Fake Jam, there are a million of them.
And you have everything
in one place
so that you can see the patterns.
And more often,
even at these meetings,
we still
talk at the end.
You don't just
write and look at them,
but
now we have a collective picture.
And that's the goal of everything.
Ok.
I have one more question
and then we'll move it to a radio station
in Porto.
I asked you
about writing
some stories
or documentation
like that.
Now,
we're talking about visual.
Ok, I get it.
Is it enough
to tell people that everyone can
start doing the same things?
Where do you start
writing documents that
are not yet taken?
I mean,
I think I've learned
that developers enjoy
writing programs,
coding, products,
but writing documentation
is the average,
or most developers enjoy it.
Then, on the other hand,
it's also a defense of the documentation.
Give us
a smart world.
What would you say
is the smartest thing to write?
That's the question.
What would be the smartest thing to write?
To be defended.
I know, I know.
There was a catch at the end.
I mean,
at the beginning, I can say
that I think it's bad.
There are really few people
who enjoy writing documentation.
Even foreign designers.
Ok, yeah.
Terrible.
It depends on the team.
Some teams,
or I would say, the bigger the team,
the more documentation
they have,
because it's harder for us.
You have to have more details.
Is it a combination
of having
a user flow chart,
and in Figma,
what each block means,
what the interactions are,
or is it some kind of a jury,
in epics and stories?
I believe
that every team
has to figure out
how to make it better.
Because every team
works differently.
Now,
there were great collaborations,
when you were a designer and a developer,
but you didn't need
a jury.
The designer didn't fully understand,
and things happened.
Probably it also depends on the size of the team.
That's great.
I mean, the bigger the team,
the longer
things take.
I think we all know that.
You answered well.
I would say
that maybe you write
some small paragraphs,
so that the stakeholders
who don't know how to program,
don't understand design,
understand a bit more.
Maybe you also
write user stories
together,
and maybe that's all
the concept of those user stories
tells.
I'm following your last question.
OK.
For example, the process
we're working on with Kyle,
we work a lot with him,
and it's like this,
who writes the user stories,
who in the team,
is it a designer,
is it a product manager,
what exactly do the stories have to be,
I'm very much like
the quality of a user story
from my point of view,
has a specific design.
While others say,
no, you just write a bit.
So we're combining those things
with the fact that
we include
development as soon as possible.
So the day before,
I don't know, I'm going to make some
design ideas,
I'm sitting with the developer
where I'm going to compete,
we go to the stakeholders,
we confirm it,
we finish it, whatever.
Once again, I sit with the developer,
I define things,
I solve it, then it goes to the story.
And then we sit again
to go through everything.
So you can start
working on it today.
OK, my last question
is this.
Let's say that most of us
are developers.
What can you
give to developers
around the world?
How can you make it easier
to work with them?
To make it easier to work with them
so they can contribute more
to the whole flow?
Can you maybe add that now?
Yes, I really want
both for developers
and for designers
to get involved in this process.
So that
we're not the only ones
at the end who are
putting together things that others
order for us.
Because I think we all have
these specific views and perspectives.
So for developers,
let's get involved
as soon as possible.
As many times
as you can,
ask us,
help us do things,
whatever it is,
help us intelligibly.
Because a lot of times
those return calls
are just
some kind of frustration.
When a developer
builds what someone ordered
and then it wasn't cool
or too complex
and designers on the other hand
suffer because
things don't look the way we designed them.
So as much as possible
in this communication
I can say for sure
that designers and
producers want
this perspective
and if you give us
better products.
Yes, and their lives
will be easier.
Okay.
Amadea, I thank you
for being a guest
of this ad hoc episode in Grodno.
Thank you for having us.
From Portorož, I would like to thank
all our Patreon supporters.
I would also like to thank
Trifas who supports us.
Kaldi.
Thank you for being with us
and thank you for inviting us
to share this episode with your colleagues.
See you next time.