Here it is. And now...
Every second is valuable in this journey.
Is this the intro?
Or will we start soon?
What intro? Is that it?
I mean...
At the beginning...
Dear viewers, this is it.
And with me are...
Andras and Andras2.
With me are...
Together, Andras2.
And we've been here for 3 hours.
Don't say anything.
It doesn't matter.
It's a matter of context.
We're filming a blog of two losers.
Two losers.
What did you give up?
I gave up my ether.
Because...
No, it's too obvious.
I'll explain to you what ether is.
Anyway.
Today we're going to film...
I don't know how many.
About 35-40 episodes.
In December.
Today is the shooting day.
So we've already filmed one episode.
It's a well-known topic.
But we decided to expand it today.
We're going to be freelancers.
That's how I understood it.
If you heard in the last episode
how to get a remote job.
All three of us in this office
all three of us in this office
manage remote jobs.
We live the life of
we live the life of
some professional workers.
Remote workers.
What else would be an example?
I'd have to say
I'm a consultant for myself.
I'm a remote worker at 4Hire.
First of all,
we're entrepreneurs.
We have our own
entity,
we have our own entity,
we have a website.
a website.
It's not the same thing.
A website or an assignment?
Assignments and websites.
A website comes and goes,
but a website is probably
delayed and delayed all the time.
Let's say there are two examples.
But above all,
it's one of the elements
of the ideal dimension.
It means that if you're
a singer for a long time,
then you have to get a job.
If you're a remote worker,
then it's a different game.
If you work for someone for three months,
because you have a project with them,
what is it then?
I think you work as a remote worker
and then you have other jobs.
If you have them,
they give you jobs.
Now,
the question is,
what are you interested in?
Work-life balance?
Looking for a partner?
Maintaining a partner?
You put a mastodon on the table.
We talked about
what to talk about.
We talked about what to talk about.
I don't know.
He said you are 10 years in this business.
What are you doing?
What challenges have you found?
He started...
Let's start with that.
My main task was
my main task was
space.
I joined a co-working.
Because
I didn't want to work at home.
You have a
you have a contract
but you lack
a social contact
coffee,
food and so on.
I needed
to find
a place.
We have been here for 9 years.
I needed
to find
a place.
I needed to find a place.
My first contact
was with a Slovenian company.
We got a contract
and I started working
as a Slovenian.
It was my first contact.
The contract is remote.
Communication is remote.
The contract came to Slovenia.
We planned and drew.
You went there?
I went there.
One of the
most memorable
moments of the scene
I worked for
The Labs.
It was a project.
At the beginning of my career
I was sent to England.
I lived in London.
I worked abroad.
I established a relationship.
I learned about the culture.
It was my first contact
with the world.
Later
I looked for
a job abroad.
I worked for them.
I had an arrangement.
I went to England
once a month for a week.
I worked for them
for a week.
I went back to Slovenia
and worked here.
You were already
on your own.
Yes.
For a while
I worked
from home.
I worked in
cafes, bookstores.
different setups.
Then I came
to Giga Tronce.
There were more of us
who worked as freelancers.
I started to work as a writer.
If I was
alone
with my wife
I had more
peace at home.
If I have a family
with three children
it is harder to get
a job.
If you have children
it is harder to concentrate.
If you don't have
a physical space
where you can work in peace
it is not a problem.
You will have
space and peace
and you will teach
your neighbors
that when you are at home
you are also at work.
You are not at home
but you are at work.
You can explain this to your partners
when they grow up.
If you have small children
they won't understand
that you need a meeting
or whatever.
This part can be
very challenging.
Children just don't understand
and you can
explain it to them.
Yes.
You?
When I was a student
I started working
with students.
We mostly worked
remotely.
There were
millions of projects.
I didn't have
that much cash.
I didn't have that much cash
and I worked
locally.
I don't like
working
at home.
I hate
having
a space
where I work.
It's weird when you talk to people
and you say you work remotely.
People say you work from home.
I say I work remotely for lunch
because I don't work from home.
I think that's interesting.
Yes, that's it.
You mentioned
that you
try to work
locally.
Also in Tuini.
Yes.
As a digital nomad.
Did that
handle you?
You were more of a developer
or a system developer.
I mean
if you have
debates,
if you write documents,
if you have an appointment
or a meeting
and you don't need
a deep focus on work
when you can focus
on a very
difficult thing.
I need peace
or less distraction.
If I have a work
that I can edit
and put it in a feature
or anywhere
and I practiced that.
Then there are
challenges.
For example, if you have to
look at the time in a feature
you have to look at the time.
If you go to the toilet
it's good to check
if you will be able to do it.
There are some practical challenges.
Internet.
Will mobile
or 5G be enough
or will Wi-Fi be enough?
Public
Wi-Fi
will be needed.
These are some challenges.
For deep work
I need challenges.
I never
worked in a local
and I never opened a laptop.
I didn't
have the intention
to work all day
in a cafe.
I studied that a lot.
When someone says
you work in a local
you are in the center
and you work there.
I worked in a hotel in Ljubljana.
There were no guests in the hotel
at that time.
It was a small motel.
I told
all the guys
that they were very happy
and their superiors were very happy.
I already had a visa
and I came to them.
I didn't work there.
I was a student
and I calculated
that it will pay off.
There was no culture of co-working.
I didn't want
to work at home.
Because I
procrastinated at home
and didn't do anything.
I had a friend.
I talked
to her
and I worked.
If you can work remotely
it wasn't my job
to work remotely.
Now it's not.
If you have interviews
or if you optimize some business processes
you can't work remotely.
I try
not to work remotely
because it stops you
because it's a travel time
and you can't work remotely.
I worked in the industry
and you can't
connect everything in series
to one job.
I mean, you can
but you can't
because you have other problems.
If it was a more
classic development
like web development and programming
I worked remotely.
They were German
employees
and students.
With time
I mean
now I look at it like this.
I have an SP
and it's not a business
but I work with
a company which has
very funny implications.
In the contract it says
if you break this NDA, it's this and that.
It's a bit different than
when you go to a company in the USA
because there are differences.
Now the cost I pay
for co-working
is the cost of a restaurant.
I look at it like this.
It's an interesting thing
when I don't understand people.
I have a computer
and I rent a space where I work.
People do a lot of optimizations
to work from home,
to have low expenses,
to have their own computer.
When people tell me
you have to pay this and that
per month for a computer
it's easy.
You don't have to worry
about the expenses.
You have to try
to see if it works
and if it doesn't
you can fix it.
I look at it differently.
It's the cost of a restaurant.
If I don't have amortization
it's a bit
like a restaurant.
How do you
look at the space
and fix it?
You are now
94 out of 97
and you can start a new job.
How do you find that balance
when you were
in a family with kids
or when you were single?
I can hijack it.
I will tell you about it later.
I heard
two good stories.
One is relevant
for WeWork.
A company
that went bankrupt
this week.
I can mention it.
We went to see a documentary.
Adam.
He is an interesting character.
I have the experience
that I was in America
with WeWork writers
and in London.
It was an interesting model.
They wanted to
unite the community
and the mobile
style of work.
You will travel
around the world
and you go from one writer to another.
It's interesting.
It was interesting
and
it was a mantra
or a vibe
for the company.
If you were in a start-up
or in WeWork
where were you?
You would expect
that if you are a new
and hip player
you have to be there.
There were
unicorns
and unicorns came from them.
I was in WeWork
which was interesting.
You had a card
and you could...
When did it come?
I can't remember.
You didn't start
or work there.
It was a premium service.
It was in Resnica.
You had
an idea
which you have today
in a modern office.
You had
phone booths for Skype
and smaller ones.
You had bigger offices.
If the company
needed more space
you could scale the office.
I understand everything.
It was good but it doesn't work.
Financially...
For example,
Polygon
was in a degraded area
and it had its price.
WeWork
was in a premium location.
They had a different
clientele.
They had so much
injection of capital
that they went bankrupt.
You can say it was a good idea
it's a franchise
you can travel a lot.
As a user...
As a user I can tell you
that at some point
it became too expensive
and we looked for alternatives.
As a user it was good
but at some point
there was a technical problem
and they told us to go
5 streets ahead
and that was it.
The worst thing
for me was
going to a cafe
or a pub
in a shared space
and you had people there
who were probably
doing similar things
and you could talk to them
and exchange ideas.
At the beginning it's interesting
and you see similar people
but you have space.
Sometimes it seems like
our or any other co-working
is the same.
You have a social contact
where you have
some people who
either do similar things
or solve similar problems.
Which is really bad.
Because if you're in a pub
and you can't hear each other
you won't get to know
only the monks
or the clergymen
who write in JavaScript
but you'll get to know other people.
I understand that
What I want to say
is that I've been watching you
for 7 years
and we're always the same.
I always want to meet
someone else.
But everything changes.
Shoutout to Virak.
Yeah, we get to meet each other
and it's great.
I remember
in Bali
I was in a co-working
which was
even though
it wasn't exactly a co-working
we had a few of them
it was a smaller part
but it was
in Bali
on a warm day
and you went to work in a pub
the pub was
some kind of a hut
made of bamboo
and you set up your laptop
and there was rice in the field
and you saw the sheep stealing the rice
but
that's not important to me anymore.
Yeah, of course.
But I work.
That would be
my statistic
to meet someone else in a pub.
I work.
It's true that you also have
different people doing different things.
I worked
when you have to watch Timezone
and I worked
when I was in the office
and I needed some deep work
so people went home
and I started to work
under the same Timezone.
I also heard about robberies
when they were stealing the rice.
So you had distractions.
Yes, I had distractions
but
maybe
like you said
you also meet different people
when they come to the pub.
In V-Work they were more professional
because they were
in the pub
they were more
let's say lifestyle entrepreneurs
or people who moved to the pub
so they could
cook or something.
German nomads.
Yes, German nomads who were exiting
or I don't know
what they were doing
and they were rich and they were looking for a successor.
That was also interesting.
Also the service
breakfasts, dinners
I don't know what they were doing.
There were so many cooks
who came to work.
Those are two stories
I wanted to share with you
to put it in context.
You can work anywhere
but only at home
if you work remotely.
What was it like
working with Covid?
Did you work with Covid?
You are asking
because you have children.
Yes, I was with my wife.
I had a child
so I don't know.
I have PTSD.
I don't know.
We were lucky
because
all the employees
for whom I worked
were
quite
perceptive
of the situation.
Then
in the household
one elder
can take over
the children
while the other
takes over the service
and then the roles change.
With a little effort
everything is possible.
In my case,
I didn't feel
it was tricky.
I don't have
any...
You don't remember?
You want to forget.
You gave me a lot of time
to think about it.
My children were
2,19?
2,20.
I had a very young child
and my wife was at home
with the child.
We combined it.
We were at home.
What did you experience?
We combined it.
We were in the same apartment.
I worked in the children's room.
The children slept in the other room.
You are reborn.
I think
that those of us
who are remote workers
or contractors
have to communicate
with the contractor.
It was a must.
I think that
everyone who is
a part-time worker
was only sent
to work from home.
The work could
still be done.
I feel
that there was
less obedience
and understanding.
I had a chance to see it.
I can hear a train.
It's December.
You are in a bad mood.
I'm in a very bad mood.
You probably had
a different experience.
I think
that all of you
who were without a child
had a different experience.
It was a awesome time
for people
who are very introverted.
We don't have to go anywhere.
We are at home.
We have a lot of time.
We don't have to go anywhere.
Maybe from the beginning.
I believe so.
It was the same for me when I was at home, even if there was no COVID.
I was alone, I just started to watch out.
There was a problem that there wasn't that many people at home,
and at that time we had a full house.
It's tricky when there are two people.
I just started to watch out.
Before that, I started doing shows.
At home, I was used to seeing things differently.
After I stopped doing shows,
I was used to seeing things differently.
It seems to have changed.
For me, it's different.
I work too much, but it's not sustainable.
It's not a quality to work 12 hours a day.
If you work 12 hours a day, you'll work 10 days, and then you'll die.
We can go into that debate.
I watched out.
When COVID came, I'd been working remotely for almost 10 years.
I watched out for one thing that seemed to me
to be the only thing I could do remotely.
People who were in the position
that they had to work remotely,
they prepared a lot of things.
They were like,
how are we going to solve this?
It was like a warm water.
I remember a middle manager
who said,
now I see how much you need information
that I didn't know was important.
I understand that.
When we expect you to be a team player,
you don't see much of yourself on the bench.
I understand that it's a problem
how I engage you remotely,
how I involve you in the team,
and that you're worried about being overlooked.
There are things like that.
For someone like him,
it was the first time in his life
that he saw how we work.
I had the same situation.
I worked remotely.
I and two other employees were remote.
The rest were in the office.
Before COVID happened,
I was mostly in the team.
If I didn't ask directly,
or attend meetings,
it was mostly on the sidewalks,
or in small coffee shops.
I was always worried
that they would stop me.
There were no such things there.
When COVID happened,
everyone realized that
they had to share information.
Not only did they realize
that they had to,
they realized the value of being there.
I also had the experience
when the company went from
non-remote to remote.
When you make a decision,
they prepare it in the office
and don't write it down.
Maybe a week later,
the decision was approved.
Maybe it was a strategic decision,
but they weren't logged in.
Let's go back to the work-life balance.
Let me ask you the same question.
In reality,
your day goes by
very similarly to the day
of every white-collar worker.
You wake up in the morning,
wash your hands,
and then go home.
Yes, but when we talk here,
most of us work
for one employee.
I usually start with a contract
for multiple employees at once.
It's a challenge
how to divide the work.
I try to communicate
with the employees.
I try to work with employees.
I don't have the context
of switching between employees.
It's like multitasking.
It takes a lot of time
to switch from one person to another.
You have to wait for information
from someone else.
The context switching
takes a lot of time.
I tried to train my employees
in a way
so that they are satisfied
with the work I do.
On Thursdays, I have someone else.
On Fridays, I have someone else.
Maybe we'll get to Friday.
I had a slightly different hack.
It was more like
you are now someone
on the side of the counter.
You look like someone
Everything was urgent
and everything was necessary.
It all depends on how you prepare
the contract, how you communicate.
You don't have to judge me.
What I noticed
is that I didn't group the contracts
by day
but by meetings.
All the meetings took place in one day.
I had dedicated days
that were only for meetings.
I didn't have other days
for deep work.
I could take 4 hours in a row
and I knew that those 4 hours
would be filled with messages
and I tried to communicate
and adjust the rhythm
so that I could be the most focused
and optimize how things went.
I have a lot of free time.
Yes, because you work
for one contract.
I always work for one contract.
What you said about one contract
is that I have a project
and I work for one contract.
Then I have less workload
and I don't have more contracts.
People say that I work for one contract
for years.
I work for the project
and I work for one contract.
People don't understand
that I work for one contract
but I don't work full time for it.
I work on my own projects.
Does that make sense?
Yes, but how do you prioritize
your projects?
I change for a project
that I have to do.
I learned that because
people change things
and if you don't say
that you work for a small project
to see if it fits you
it's not good.
You can be very experienced
and you have a professional attitude
but it just doesn't fit.
Then I do something small
and then I do a bigger project
and I want it to be completed.
I have a lot of risk.
I can change management
and I have a whole problem.
It has to be completed
so that it doesn't happen
that Lada turned 90 degrees
and we'll do something else.
From the context of a project
it can always be changed.
It's a project.
No, it's not like that.
It can be changed
but management of expectation
is something else.
I work for someone
and if we can assign tasks
for example, if we have a legacy system
that's deprecated
and we want to replace it
with Kubernetes for container orchestration
can you assign me tasks
outside of that scope?
It's part of the contract.
The difference is
if you say I'm open to work
because I don't know how people imagine it.
Let's be honest.
I'm just asking
about the high level
how you organize your day
and how you organize your week.
For me it's simple.
In the morning I'm open
and in the afternoon I'm not allowed to work.
I don't want to talk about systems
because you can hear that a lot.
We do everything.
For a front-end developer
or someone who works on those things
they're probably not on-call.
It's a well-known concept to be on-call.
It's a funny thing.
How do you deal with it
because we're a small company
and we all have to be on-call
so we can share the risk.
When you're a developer
you're always on-call.
If a company calls you
you have to say we're not working.
I've never been on-call in my life.
You know what a pager duty is?
If you have a pager duty
you have to think about it.
It's even worse if you're implicitly on-call.
That means you don't have any policies
to make a system work.
I learn from inventors
in four-change systems.
People understand you can't cover 24 hours
if you don't have four-change work.
It's a typical story
when you're on-call a lot.
That's why I wanted to talk about it.
That's why I'm a hoster.
I don't work.
There can be some special requirements
and I can work.
My good will allows me to work
but that's the baseline.
I've had that in my career
but it was also in the past.
Different positions.
Everyone was expecting it
and there were expectations.
I was responsible
and didn't hide anything.
You didn't go to the movies.
Does that mean you went to the movies
with a laptop?
No, that means I had the laptop
close to me.
On-call doesn't mean
you have to do everything
in the next four minutes.
If I had to solve something
in the next hour,
the laptop was close enough.
I was lucky
that I had a remote.
I was using my laptop
with an UMTS card
3G and so on.
I could open the laptop
and work anywhere.
There was a computer
that came with mobile data
because I was part of it.
I tried to compensate
and take care of it.
Work-life balance? No.
You can't be on tier 1
and be on-call.
That's it.
How did you get out of that segment?
You can tell us.
A few times it happened to me
that a client came to me
and said,
I don't know, holidays are coming.
Maybe a little before the holidays.
But people are still talking.
Who will be on-call at that time?
We have to worry about the holidays.
If you're in an e-commerce,
it's a problem.
Who will be monitoring?
I have to make sure
that everything is in order.
Otherwise, people come to me
and say, what are you doing?
We'll put you on-call.
Hello, what are you doing?
The first answer is,
sorry, we don't have a contract.
It's a premium.
The second answer is,
I'll be a team player.
I feel so responsible for the project
that I don't have to take responsibility
to fix the system.
Maybe I don't know it enough.
It's fully responsible.
I know that.
I have a certain number of members
who talk about such situations.
It's possible, even if I'm not
directly in the position.
It's possible for me to be called
for an on-call, for example.
It's possible, but I've noticed
that it's not convenient for me
to be called for a good money.
It's not convenient for my pleasure.
There's a limit.
Maybe I really can't do it.
If someone listens to this work
and doesn't allow you to force them...
No.
I mean, not force.
You have to agree politely.
What are your expectations?
I've never been on-call,
but I'm learning how to implement it.
It's a bit weird.
If you're a fire brigade,
you have these four changes.
If you want to cover weekends
and employees in 24-7,
for example.
I'm not talking about firemen.
I'm talking about firemen in 24-7.
You can have a business
in our sector,
which is similar.
You want to cover 24-7.
It's not unique to our industry.
No.
If you're a fireman,
you can't cover firemen in 24-7.
You can't cover firemen in 24-7.
It's because one person...
I have this problem with employees.
Their assistant is more operational.
One person can't do it
because he'll be fired.
It doesn't mean he's active every day.
He can't be prepared.
It's like we're doing baby steps.
People are in the service
until the next shift.
If you don't have four people
on rotation,
you can't prepare
for such shifts.
It's complicated.
If you're a startup with two engineers,
it's a global product.
You have to be on time.
How are you going to do it?
These are the problems.
I would be on call.
My problem is that I've never been compensated.
I've always felt guilty
because I was inexperienced.
I have a clear intention
It's nice to be on call,
but it has to be sustainable.
You have to be aware of it.
I've seen it many times.
They delegate this task to juniors.
I've seen it.
One thing we have to be aware of
is what exactly is expected
from you when you're on call.
If you're on call as a DevOps,
a cloud engineer,
or an app player,
whatever,
you don't have to know how to fix it.
You don't have to know how to debug it.
You have to be aware of
how the system will react.
How are we going to deal with these problems?
What can we do proactively?
Why are we on call?
You have two reasons why people are on call.
The first reason is that you have commercial damage.
Your business suffers and you lose money.
That's the number one reason.
You have it, but you don't.
Let's leave it as it is.
It's a service level agreement.
You have your business partners
who use your services.
In the meantime,
the engineers will look at it and try to fix it.
The funniest thing is
that in Slovenia we have a lot of...
We say,
let's leave these people on call.
Why do we have them?
Maybe the business doesn't lose a lot of money.
Not a lot of e-commerce,
multi-regional, longer hours.
SLA is also very important.
The problem is that when you prepare
on-call rotation, you don't know what to write in SLA.
It happened to me a lot.
I made a promise to myself
that I don't have to make plans
for reliability.
I don't know what to write for God.
A lot of times it says
that an engineer will look at it for half an hour
and make an assessment.
It's called response time.
It's defined as a response time
where you are aware
that you took over,
but it doesn't mean that you will fix it.
It's a time when you took over the business.
It's often confused.
People think it's a time
when you have to fix it.
If it says in SLA that it's half an hour
for someone to take over,
the engineer will look at it,
track the SLA response,
accept it, and start working on the basic triage.
It can be so trivial that he'll be alone.
Depending on the weather,
he might wake up in the middle of the night.
Let's stop for a moment.
If KPI put this here...
KPI means
Key Performance Indicators.
Customer Satisfaction Factor.
It turns out that the customer
is more satisfied
if someone starts to talk to him,
send him some emails,
and reply quickly,
even if they didn't reply for a day.
If they are aware that something is going on,
they hear me,
it's much more valuable than
fixing it quickly.
You can attack the customer
in this way.
It's a good trade-off.
My advice is
not to get too toxic.
Try to learn from it.
Don't burn out just because
things are working.
Not every cryptocurrency exchange
will lose cash if something doesn't work.
That's a good example.
In the past,
I had a situation
where the customer
doesn't know what he wants.
He knows that he wants a long Ferrari,
and then you start to explain
the high availability,
that the system must be resilient,
and if we go further,
through the cloud,
where a lot of equipment is added,
and everything is connected,
everything is feasible,
but are you ready to invest that money?
This is the situation.
If you lose so much,
and if you invest so much,
which is more than their loss,
it's a redundant task,
the management must decide
whether it's a problem
and how we are ready to invest.
Is this the problem we have with Andra?
Normal people look at the work-life balance
more than JavaScript handlers.
No.
I had a similar example today.
You go to Slack,
a developer,
a solid developer,
and the charts are off,
panic, panic.
I don't know if I've seen
so many shits,
but you're alive.
You know, let's say you have a coffee and then you die
because we are in this ultra panic mode
you don't think clearly, adrenaline is infused
you don't know if there is a problem or not
you saw the exception, we have the whole fox, that's why we have monitoring and logging
you die first
first question, if you don't know what it is, is it necessary?
I don't know, is it necessary to risk your whole life?
die and then pay taxes
die and then pay taxes, is it necessary?
it's not just that panic, fear, you get stuck
and then you don't think clearly
and then people, if they weren't conscious at the time
they do something stupid
they go and, I don't know, they make something up
or they go and, I don't know, they scale something
or they reboot, it's a classic
or they reboot and then they die in the logging
and then what?
it can come because of that, especially if you have a flat structure
quickly before that, the party called the boss
don't work, panic
you can't say that, it's very important to see the situation
to talk to your colleagues
make a smart conversation
maybe in the logging you just need to call the party back
and say, we'll fix it, we know what's going on
and I see that people always react
I have a slightly different view of it
unfortunately we got involved with alpinism
and some extreme sports
and you have to control your stress level
otherwise you'll always die because of it
if you work in an industry where survival is important
and it happens to you, you've already died somewhere before
an even bigger obstacle in these incidents
are the demands
if you don't talk about how it came to this incident
do we have a safety net?
do we have a safety net to overcome these problems in the future
with some human factors
or with a machine-programmed approach to whatever
maybe this exception happened because
integration tests that could test the whole product of the case
didn't cover it and we opened it up again
maybe we have a staging environment
maybe we have the latest version of the system
my point is to keep calm
you don't have to communicate
and then do it, I can see that
but you as a developer
whatever, I'm a woman
team management, I mean developing a team
how did you feel about on-call or manual requests
I don't know if it was some kind of code deploy
that happened in some strange hours
I was in a position with Andra
or his company and Marjano
and Marjano asked for an on-call
and all the talks that Andra had
we already had at that level
and the developer goes and asks for an on-call
to tell what is expected
apart from the on-call, it's also easier
we know that there are holidays
we just want to see if there are any problems
because we will sell something or whatever
what can you do, these are some possible failures
if it happens, we will do this
and then it all has to be documented
simulation also helps
one of the interesting problems is Cassandra
and their addition of disks
or if you have a tombstone or whatever
it's a thing that you can predict
if you have a lot of traffic, someone will be able to do it
and then there are engineers that will prepare the on-call
and if it happens, we will do this
and then on the same day, the person was paid
to look at it
this is my sub-question
how many handbooks did you work with
when you were working on Disaster Recovery Drill?
NDA!
Drill, yes!
I know that...
I'm not saying that the documentation that she mentioned exists
but it was like, look, today we will delete
an availability zone on AWS
which is our application
or a datacenter goes down
or we will delete a link, a database will come up
and it's like, the whole team knows what's going on
or they don't know
and you don't tell them
it's typical for VEA
that's why they have to know the board
we are not that extreme
I have a company where we practice
some monitoring Thursdays
and every Thursday we make money
and randomly we get together
and one hour on Thursday
we do some observability
slash monitoring
where we say, this is an exception
and randomly we pick a stack trace
we don't look for what is an error
or what is an exception
but where did it happen
did it restart the pod
did it run out of memory
we try to determine
how we will see when the next exception happens
and we practice that
and then we make an analysis
for example, for that particular service
we know that it scales up and down
we know that it's healthy
and we don't know how it restarted
Was it a random exception?
No, let's try it
It was a random exception
because the systems fail at random
and at the end
of that hour
there is a timebox
and we go, ok
in the center of the log I don't see
a URL or a path to the service
where it happened
and then a ticket is written on the back
and then it is corrected
and then in the back you can see
who is responsible for that
and this is what we call full over
because we poke all over the place
and we get a pattern
Also, the combination
of mixing team members
shows where you have silos
For example, you have a lot of knowledge
in some systems
and you forget to write it
It's good knowledge sharing
Especially when you don't have
documented things
For example, I had a cluster in Asia
and I forgot to write where it is
and then you force people
to figure out
what would happen
if there was a problem
and you improve the infrastructure
I see that it works well
and it's a good exercise
It's a good exercise
and you don't have to deal
with specific exceptions
I had a handbook
Disaster recovery
means
data center switch
They had data centers
they had their own equipment
Service
means people who weren't their own
that they had disks
because of compliance
They had two data centers in the same place
If it was in the cloud
it would mean two regions
It's more old school
There was a center switch
One of my commitments was
specific legacy services
that were feature complete
which is weird
They didn't have years of development
They had to modify
and change
Everyone knew the month
because they had to change
the software
so they supported it
and practiced
It was like that
with time
You have a company
that is 40 years old
and it's still going
It's a big
It was a switch
but there were expectations
from the engineering hierarchy
You haven't switched the service
for 6 months
and it happened
If you have real-time things
traditional financial industries
It was an event
Everyone knew
SVP and VPA
It's a company of 2000 engineers
I worked with them
I had it
It's a small probability
that you'll have it
I had it with bigger companies
in Switzerland
In Slovenia I saw it only on paper
With the same teams
that I worked in Slovenia
I managed to prepare
for the documentation
They never let me
turn off a button
It's interesting
that people
It's better
to deal with fear
It's better to
warn the church
It sounds like an extreme sport
but to turn off a button
shouldn't be extreme
But you said
everything is possible
The most classic legacy
is a problem
If you go in that era
before any cloud
All those problems
that you turned off
was a big risk
If you physically
don't turn it off
it won't work
If it would start
from the start
you would have
6 months of tests
to prepare
If you have an infrastructure
that is not up-to-date
I don't trust you
If you need to reboot
or turn it off
that's the problem
It's true that today
with cloud
or any other infrastructure
that is constantly lying
They are hiding you
You have other problems
that you can solve
But I have a feeling
that certain things are hidden
It's a lie
If you are an engineer
that is skilled
you can work on a deterministic
You don't have to
change everything
I'm talking from a perspective
If you are deploying
to a configuration
and the interface is turned off
and you can only get in the car
Do you know people like that?
We learned a lot
They are the second generation
Everything is from the second generation
It's different
When we talk about technical topics
it's always latest greatest
Everything that existed 2 years ago
didn't exist
It's good for the greenfield deployment
When you put something new
The problem is that
90% is about legacy
Something is already there
You can integrate it
You can upgrade it
It's understandable
that the systems are set
Hey, I just realized
that I have a bottle on my nose
Did you notice that too?
I have an empty one
I drink it all
My whiskey was the cleanest
It wasn't whiskey
I wanted to interrupt you
because we have a lot of interesting topics
Let's move to the last part
It's like when you get 2 grams of X-ops
It's not therapy
Let's move to something more positive
I'm interested
Wait, what do I have here
Suppliers, Wi-Fi, security
IPv6 is boring
WPC is boring
Flutter
Let's talk about it
You know what I feel like
It's the end of the year
so this episode will probably be in December
In Groovy we're trying
to create a community
because later
we give out the fake information
and we want to give it to people
not just to give it to us
I want to ask you
where have you been this year
at some meetups
What have you done for the community
Let's talk about it
What have we done for the community
We always talk about the community
I forgot where you were
I wrote that I have to ask
How many meetups were there this year
and how many BSides
I don't know how many
This year was a lot
What are meetups and BSides
What are meetups
Let's go back to the episode
The idea is that
there are meetups
where people who like it
or are interested in IT
cyber security
cyber
hash tag
let's say
who likes to hack
meet up
talk
hear something new
exchange experiences
maybe
make a capture the flag
and that's it
it's a crazy idea
Do you need a black hoodie
No
Do you need to have a laptop
We had a situation
where people
asked for a laptop
and they were successful
Are challenges part of it
Is it a foreign activity
or are they always there
Let's say
It's a franchise
It started in Australia
Is it Sektor or BSides
Sektor
Pedram started
There are more communities
I don't know
Almost everyone has their own
There are a few in the world
or in Europe
It's not necessary
to have a capture the flag
It turned out
that it's a loose
I won't say germification
but it's not just
a show
You need to have
small interactions
small competitions
There are many ways
to skin a cat
There is not only one solution
How do you solve a problem
It's great to see
and exchange experiences
When you learn something new
it's also a challenge
to prepare for it
It means that
you have a goal
and the concept is that
the winner has the privilege
to prepare the challenge
It's a privilege
It's a challenge
It turns out that
it's a challenge
that people don't have the knowledge
or the time
Sometimes it happens
that there is no CTF
or they use a CTF
from another competition
It depends
We also had a few sects
in the summer
when we were only drinking
Did you have any students
in the first year
Yes
We had someone
who gave a talk
about his android
It was great
because he didn't know
what he was doing
What about B-Sides
It's something new
The concept of B-Sides
is the easiest
to imagine
B-Sides are big events
or big conferences
that are usually
commercial
These are conferences
that are supported
by big vendors
and there is a lot of money
It's a C-level cadre
The more technical part
is that
around these big events
there are B-Sides
where the community
supports each other
The idea of B-Sides
is that it's community driven
It's besides the bigger event
One of the references
is that there were cassettes
and the cassettes were
magnetic tapes
We understand that
There were magnetic tapes
in a plastic packaging
and the tapes were A-Side and B-Side
You could turn the cassette
There were big hits on A-Side
and the rest were on B-Side
And in Ljubljana
there are no A-Sides, only B-Sides
Yes, and here in Ljubljana
when I was traveling
I thought that
we need this in Slovenia
so we made B-Sides
There was an A-Side event
and a bigger B-Side
and we realized that
we don't need A-Side events
I wanted to ask
if Slovenian security will come
The agency told you that they came to you, but you didn't tell them.
I think we haven't followed that yet.
I wouldn't have told that either.
I don't know, I think we haven't...
I've been to events where they were
undercover security services,
so all of that is happening in Tuin.
But no, not for us.
Not with the intention of attracting
security experts.
That's the big deal in Slovenia.
The biggest problem is that I don't know
if they have anything to offer.
Yes, if they do...
They can give you a very good challenge,
if they know how to compensate you.
If they know how to compensate you.
What do you think?
Is that a challenge?
No.
OK, OK.
You do that in Grodno, right?
Yes.
When they put you in those cryptos,
then you can't keep it.
Can we say that if people are interested
in security, real security,
come to Sektoke, come to B-Sites.
Yes.
Friends and family.
That's definitely a type of event
where you will have a lot of hands-on
people who are more technically
equipped in some hands-on areas
that are connected to that.
But we don't have any more questions
about that.
We don't.
You sold this year on two or three
tracks.
Last time you sold on AWS Meetup,
on Ruby Meetup,
on DevOpsDays Ljubljana.
On DevOpsDays Ljubljana.
Every year I sell on NTFL.
But this year I have too few students
on that select item.
What did you sell?
Maybe you can change the item.
Do you have the same?
No.
On AWS Meetup,
on Ruby Meetup,
on DevOpsDays,
it was almost the same.
It was evolving.
Last year I sold...
This year I could sell on NTFL.
on NTFL.
And then...
I have 10 of these.
I only focus on 3.
One of them is SQL injection.
And then still 10?
No, back.
I know it came back a bit.
Yeah, back.
I don't know how Slovenian news is this year.
But we had a whole bunch.
What I do next is
full impactful for them.
I have those memes.
I don't know if you remember.
And I also make them
fully plastic.
So it's very simple.
And in this show
I make it a bit practical for them.
And this organization
has this document.
I forgot the name.
It's a website document.
It's not for full control
of different standards.
It's not for full control of different standards.
For example,
Soc2.
And I'll tell them
if you can do anything with the app
and I'll mention it.
And I'll tell them.
And this is full of memes
and plastic ads.
Because in one hour
I have a spark of students
who see it's interesting
and remember it.
And remember it.
And then
I try to connect them
to Slovenian developer community
to wider events.
So I got this opportunity.
I'm an industry representative
so I have a little bit of it.
So yeah,
this is something
I'm really glad about.
Lani was really amazing.
Students were really happy.
Who did you mentor next?
I mentor people
who are not officially
I mentor people who are not officially
You mentor them but they don't know
that you mentor them.
No, no, no.
I think that from Andras' perspective
he's very susceptible to mentor the whole thing.
He has a big threshold
when he mentors someone by himself.
He has a big threshold when he mentors someone by himself.
There are two things.
One is coaching, which is a commercial thing.
Because for example,
we have a junior mentor
but we don't have anyone we can share
the job with.
And then I say,
hey, I can offer you this package
and general things
because if someone is really fresh
I can give him some knowledge that is not specific to the field.
And if I can teach this person
or
onboard him from the general things
so that you can specialize him on the things
you need.
For example,
for Slovenia, it's one thing.
It's a commercial offer.
I call it coaching.
I do it a little bit because I don't believe
that you can coach full-time.
There are some weird things.
The other thing is mentoring.
There is very little coaching.
Mentoring is like
mentoring is like
where I prepare them
and put them in
and then I try to help them.
It doesn't mean that I teach them how to program.
I try to direct them
differently.
If they have doubts
or questions that are not
in the getting started
page
or in the Slovenian space
I help them better.
Often
the stories of people
who come to me
are quite fascinating.
These people
are quite easy to take
under their wings.
I only get
a few times.
As much as I need help
I gladly help.
If someone I'm not sure about
I will mentor them.
For example, in Ljubljana
I have a Ljubljana city test.
I go on Saturday and get a Ljubljana city test on Friday.
It is a bit of a thrash.
It's hard for me to stay up
but it's a good feeling.
It's a good feeling.
You can see
how well someone prepared.
This creativity.
If I had to give you an over value
I wouldn't make it in time.
On Saturday at 6 a.m.
I don't care.
Most of the people
would change their careers.
Most of the people are working tomorrow.
It's funny when people ask me
how do you find new handcuffs.
It's good.
My mentors are distributed
in the industry.
If they have a problem
I know how to fix it.
People are grateful
if you help them.
It's about small things.
People think
They think
I tell people
where to buy books
It's not about that.
It's about
listening to people
learning about programming
if it's not your hobby
you do whatever you want
If you want to change
Then you have to focus
on your career
Then you have to
take part in conversations
and then I can help
if there is an option
If there are open spaces
that are fit for them
I always do it
so I don't get those commissions
because it's another trap
when people think they are innovators
just because you get
hiring fee
and then people don't understand
ok, ok
let's extend the question
shoot, shoot
no, no, my next question
was when people say
Andraj Zrihti is our developer
do you know any student?
we've already discussed
we've already talked about it
it's not that big
I still get it
I'm sure you know
who we need a student
not in front of us
you have to know
you have to be an expert
not in front of us
it's simple
I have people I can talk to
and I send them
but I'm looking for that fit
because it's not my thing
I'm not into that
someone is looking for a fit
to have a good experience
and that person
that I send
or that I know
is looking for a job
to have a good experience
and then I try to match that
and then a lot of times
there are inquiries
that I don't have to match
what do you mean by success rate?
what's that?
I don't know, I'm not tracking
because there's no API
but yes
most people you find
look, from those people
that have helped me
in the last 3 years
let's say there were about 12
because they have 4
that I know
two have changed their careers
I can't list people
that have changed
but they are building
in software development
and then
I just saw on LinkedIn
that they got a job
I'm not that
busy
I have kids
but I see
that
I don't draw it
I have to see
with those people
if you are
matching the job
then you are helping
I think I'm doing
a good job
I'm helping
out of those 12
there are 6
what's wrong with that?
that would be weird
but I have everything
nobody came to me
and said
those jobs are crap
even if you thought
I don't care
why are you doing this?
it's very simple
they don't have kids
no, not at all
ok, ok
they don't have kids
you have kids
and we heard that you are
flirting with sektoks
and b-sides
why are you doing this?
I don't know how many years
15 years ago in CyberPip
it's cool
no, I mean
why?
it's just
my passion
it's fun
it's fun to flirt
I mean
yes, in a way
you know
when those things grow up
and become a job
then it's fun
until we start
having fun
it's cool
I think the most important
understanding is that it's not
just a game
if you help people
the industry has a lot of potential
to grow
we can raise the level
so that we won't
be just a
agency
but we can
raise the level
and start a business
for me
when I was 18
15 years ago
I joined CyberPip
and I learned a lot
there
it's not like they taught me in Stalin
it was just a community
that helped me a lot
and now I have the privilege
that
I have enough time
and health
and I'm not very demanding
so I have a lot of energy
and I can give it back to the community
and I think that's the most fair
you can give back a lot of resources
yes, just a lot
whatever those resources are
yes, exactly
that's a good thing
you can give it back
because why
it's nice to organize events
when you see that people
like it
it's nice to make content
it's nice to help people
for me it's
the only fair thing
for me
is to give back to the community
sometimes it was with a lot of time
now with some time
you get some money
and you reinvest it in the community
if it wasn't for you
the previous generation
not in years, but in history
how we progressed
through the community
it would be a lot harder
I would do something else
it would be boring
yes, I would do something else
I ask myself
I learned a lot
how to give back
for me it's natural
and I look at the same faces
every year
and it's new
let's warm up
Oto a bit
Oto, why are you doing this?
let's start
you were also
quite active this year
the mission
service, three children
garden
and healthy
let's give a little more
and brush your teeth
and
why did you turn me away?
you started
double Andrasin
with the current
schedule
I have
I do pure development
and hardcore development
and I don't have
management
I don't have the team
so I don't have
to go to calls
I have some
but more limited
which means
I can do healthy
things that are
important to me
like gardening
so I have the capacity
to do it
it's not easy
to do it healthy
but when I think about it
we will do it
is it big?
no, no
listen
this is such
an opportunity
to do something extraordinary
and such opportunities
I don't know how
I like it
Oto manager
inspiring his team
ok
how many opportunities
will you get in Slovenia
3000-4000 developers
engineers
where did you get
this mindset? you create
opportunities
we created
an opportunity
and I think it's extraordinary
and I want to see
how it grows
it's exciting
and it's fun
my role changes
and all together
we have different
views
what is easy
and what is not
when you say
we are healthy
yes, but we delegate things
and it happens
anyway
it seems important
that if we have
an opportunity
to use it
and give something back
and I don't know
if we will destroy ourselves
with a nuclear weapon
from Vesolja
maybe YouTube will record
on some disk
then Vesolja will need
this signal
I see this platform
it's growing
the feedback is great
I see that we experiment
that we learn
that people believe in us
that they support us
I'm just interested
what will happen next
how will we grow
what will we do next
how will we get
the next generation of developers
all these things
are exciting
and
as I've seen
in different events
I've organized conferences
meetups, whatever
and
I see this as
an upgrade of all
these experiments
on a larger scale
more modern
and
evolutionary
this is the next step
this is important
and
I want everything
to work in such a way
to be resilient
as you said
if I get sick, David will go
to Val202
or we will have this
resiliency that everyone
is responsible
for the benefits that come
from this
this year
I gave a lecture
in Portugal
what are you waiting for?
is this it?
well
debate?
no, no
how did I find you?
you know what's funny?
when I'm in a position
where I have to speak
I will directly ask questions
we can have an episode
but I won't now
if technology is interesting
I was in a lecture
on Portuguese women
I said hello
we were together
in Portuguese
I was close to
Dragonhack
I was there as a judge
I hope we will have another
Dragonhack lecture
in December
that was very interesting
I also gave
some other things
I was at the Makeit conference
and at Openblend
we also started some things
this year
in the last part
I gave a lecture
for SkillUp mentor
shoutout
where I
with the thought
that I prepared this
program for skillup developers
for skillup developers
I was thinking
what is a talk
that I could do
that he can't
give
I have my own experience
so I had a talk
about
technical interviews
how you become
an engineer
as a developer
we focused
on that aspect
of technical interviews
we did
an event
there were 50 developers
we invited 2
we had a mock interview
we had
5 questions
after those 5 questions
we did an analysis
and then
first there was
a coding question
that was
incomprehensible, illogical, complicated
that had
no solution
so it was very
complicated
meaning that
for example, you pick a candidate
and then you put it in a
non-acceptable zone
to see how he will react
if he doesn't know the answer
what he will look for, what he will turn to, how he will start to think,
how he will look for help,
will he ask for help, so you can see his mindset.
We did that,
and it was very well prepared.
When we talked,
a lot of these things I do now,
because I have a little contact with what our audience is interested in,
to get feedback,
to understand if I am doing the right thing or not.
So that's a great thing,
that at these events,
people come and say,
hey, I listened to your theory,
that's a really good feeling,
when you see that you can help people,
that's a really good feeling.
Especially when you see someone who is very shy,
who tries to say what he is comfortable with.
That's really amazing.
We all understood that.
Maybe you can tell us about the sponsors?
We are through the library.
What do we have? Sponsors?
We can thank Humanfrog,
and 3FSO, because they are our supporters.
We all have a little more space.
We can also thank Patreon,
who supports us through the Patreon platform.
If an episode is prepared,
we put it on Patreon,
and if it is pre-released,
and it is a premium feature,
you can support us through Patreon,
and enable us to produce these products.
That's it.
You know what else we can do?
We can have a Discord,
and I will send you the link.
When it snows,
when it snows,
and when it snows,
it will be easier.
Will it snow this year?
We will film it this year,
because we can't do it in November.
Thank you for your attention.
Thank you both for this short interview.
Thank you, Andra.
Thank you, good luck.
Bye.