Hello, good day. In the second episode of Zagona, my name is Saravšina Gašpar, for those of you who don't know me yet.
Today I have two guests with me. First of all, Islam Musić, who has been teaching for almost 20 years and works as a professor at high school and high school.
He is also very active in our group, and above all, he is also a mentor to students, students and startups.
Yes, everything is for girls.
You also have your own program for young people, SkillUp Mentor, which we will talk a little more about later.
But one of the students or the success of this program is also Ilija, who joined us.
Ilija Tomić, hello to you too.
Hello.
You graduated from the Department of Computer Science at the University of Maribor last September.
And on the topic of full stack development of applications with two different approaches.
Yes, I also took the SkillUp project for writing my master's thesis.
That's right, because you joined the program as soon as you entered the studio.
And now, if I'm not mistaken, Glih was your first job, because you graduated in a good month.
So it's still honeymoon period, right?
Yes, that's right.
We will also talk about this a little later.
Today, I imagined this conversation in two parts.
First, we will touch a little on learning.
So where and how to start learning.
Then a little more about looking for first employees.
I also hope that you will tell us a little about what it is like to be a junior at the market.
Maybe we'll start with learning.
So, right at the beginning, with summer.
When can we start learning?
I'm interested in when ...
Maybe we'll start with Ilija.
When did you start learning and first met computers?
In high school, at Islam.
I started in the first or second year of high school.
I started with the initial programming.
I started with diagrams, basic things.
Then, step by step, I've been doing it for 14 years.
Did you have any interest in elementary school before?
Before, I didn't program anything.
I had an interest in computers, in technology.
I didn't program anything myself.
Islam, you also have children, a little older.
Did you teach them everything?
The two older girls are not so much for technology.
The younger ones, yes.
When did you start and how did you start?
My son will be 14 years old this year.
I think we are young.
We started, we showed him.
Also, what Ilija said at the beginning.
It is not necessary to have such a story.
It is also very dependent on yourself.
We have different experiences.
I'm talking from school.
For example, a student in the second grade,
when he first starts programming,
he breaks his head.
At the end of the third or fourth grade,
he becomes one of our better students.
I wouldn't be so sure now
what happens to the brain, synapses.
But something definitely happens at that moment.
It changes.
I don't have much pressure on my children.
Of course, if they want,
they have my full support.
But also those who listen.
It is not necessary to start with some top sport
when you are 8 years old.
It can be good enough later.
But as Ilija said,
interest is interesting.
That is the main thing.
If not, everything else will suffer.
We have quite a good experience in our company.
We started with a 5-year-old,
when he was 4 years old,
with some basic tasks,
such as coding,
when he has this programming logic
through games,
and Minecraft, for example.
But it seems to me that
we have a lot of experience
in our company.
We have a lot of experience
But it seems to me that
what we have prepared
is the difference
between having him
sit at the computer,
giving him a mouse,
giving him coordination,
getting to know the computer.
It seems to me that today
there are a lot of children
mostly on tablets,
on phones,
which are a bit more,
let's say,
a computer.
Some idea.
I don't know,
when I was in elementary school,
we didn't have,
I'm not that old yet,
but there were no tablets,
so the first experience
was with a computer,
with a mouse,
with a sniper,
and also with a console.
I don't know what that experience is like.
I think that what has changed
is that when there will be
a child on Minecraft,
the players will demand
a bit more processor power,
or whatever it is,
because mine was also on a tablet.
But again, maybe this
interest and interest,
and Minecraft,
if I take it as an example,
I also need to go there,
and I would say that
this coordination with the mouse
is very important.
Yes, that's true.
OK.
Let's move on to
the overall education
in the school system.
A short while ago,
we had a guest
from the Ministry of Digital Education
in our garden,
who also touched
on the importance of
digital literacy.
At the beginning of this month,
the Ministry of Education
also prepared a letter
requesting the introduction
of a mandatory subject,
computer science and computer science,
in all primary and secondary schools.
I would be interested,
maybe, Ilja,
if we start with you.
You went to a technical secondary school,
but maybe you made a mistake
in computer science and computer science
in the primary school.
What are your experiences
with these two subjects
in the primary school?
In the primary school,
we had 8th and 9th grade,
I think, in computer science.
The subject was once a week,
for one hour.
When we changed the mouse
at the end,
the teachers showed
an award,
I think,
but that was in the first 15 minutes,
then we had a break,
and we were students,
so I think we were most excited
about that subject,
when we saw the whole class
going to play games.
That was the start,
I think.
I would talk about it.
In the secondary school,
it is always more
about computers,
and through this
digital connection,
literacy is needed
and security
in the classroom,
so that the students know
which side is suspicious,
or a lot of confusing orders,
dressing up,
being aware
that there are a lot of perverts,
so basic education
is also needed in this direction,
even if it is not directly related
to computer science.
Islan, what do the students
bring with them
and if they could
bring more?
Now,
the most I want
them to bring is interest.
When we have a promotion,
we always say
that it can start from scratch,
that we don't need to wake them up.
Of course,
everyone is welcome,
but the most important thing is
interest, and maybe
what Ilja said,
I mean,
I teach computer science,
so that we don't play
games between classes,
so that we learn programming,
so that we don't
somehow break
the computer game.
For example, we have
the subject of learning games,
and we teach them to learn games,
but it is for,
on the other hand,
not as a player,
so what they could bring more
is perhaps
to see in advance
what they will do,
what the challenge of computer science
brings.
I think that it is important
for the students to know how to present
or not know how to present,
and you go with some illusion,
what do you think,
on the other hand, you go to a school
and maybe in the end you are
disappointed,
or maybe you change your mind,
or maybe it was a double battle,
because you went somewhere where you were happier,
and that was the goal.
Now you don't have to be a programmer,
or whatever,
but to believe in what you will do,
and what you will be satisfied with.
But maybe
that is
one of the biggest challenges
for all parents,
to direct their children,
when you go to school,
you try to explain to 14-year-olds
that they have to choose
what they would like to do
for the rest of their lives.
Let's say
that you already have
an advanced computer
at home,
and
what would
the world be like?
Is high school enough?
Is high school the beginning
for the advancement
in computer science?
Is high school
free, or
does the computer universe
choose better?
Yes,
that is a very good question.
Where would I recommend you?
My advice,
which I have been
noticing lately,
is to look at your
younger self, and look
at your subculture.
If he is more geeky,
don't put him in a computer school,
because he will suffer.
On the other hand,
if he already has his engine,
don't put him in a computer school,
because he will suffer.
And the same thing,
if someone,
I will generalize a bit,
is interested in philosophy,
psychology,
books,
maybe it is not a technical school,
because,
as I said, I have two older sisters,
when they decided,
and of course in primary school
it is fine,
but in primary school,
it doesn't matter
if you go to a high school,
a computer school,
a computer science school,
a cosmetic school,
a tourist school,
and I remember,
when I talked to my older sister,
at the end of the first year of high school,
she said exactly that,
that she is much happier now,
because she has a similar self,
and if she said at that time,
I want to have a license,
I will not have a license,
because she assessed it
on the basis of her balloon,
and that would be the beginning
for anyone.
Look where you fall,
you have to survive with time.
If someone chose
a high school at that time,
or an economic,
tourist school,
at the end of the first year of high school,
he still has enough time.
I think that secondary school
is not the final destination,
because if you did not choose it,
you are done.
I would say,
if someone says at the beginning
that he is interested in computer science,
he will be happier,
he will go to school more often,
because he will have a similar self there.
These are my conclusions
from all this learning.
It is very interesting
that this turned
into a character,
more than anything else,
because it is true,
at the end of those years,
this is what shapes them the most.
Ilja,
when you went to high school,
then you continued
and successfully completed
both the diploma studies
and then the master's degree.
Where did you see
this added value?
How did you build your knowledge
through all these stages?
If you ask
how it is in the service,
I think
these are the basics
that you expand.
Some basic principles,
soft skills,
you meet a lot of different people,
in fact,
even older professors,
and it is more
free, not like high school,
you have someone,
you can be there every day.
Professors require
homework, there it is simple
and you are really,
as Islam said,
when you want, you do it.
And then you also build
your knowledge
and learn to talk,
to approach professors,
which also helps in the service.
I will
really relate to that.
Now,
after a month,
with fresh experience,
you work in production.
Is there anything you would like
to bring with you before?
Is there anything
that surprised you
in the first service?
I think
nothing surprised me,
because the skill-up program,
which you mentioned at the beginning,
when we talked about it,
it simulated
production a bit,
so I got used to it.
Otherwise, what would you like?
Maybe to start a little earlier
and have more freedom
so that I don't have such pauses
and then start again.
If I felt
that I would be a little more consistent,
I would change that.
What about knowledge,
technology, syntax,
programming languages?
Did you miss anything?
Or was there
something too much?
Too much knowledge?
I don't think so.
But if I missed something,
I didn't pay attention.
The first month,
maybe a little more,
I don't know,
maybe in three months
they would give me a notebook
that I kept in my head.
What about those
who are a little older
and are tired of
formal education
and would like to learn
programming
or IT?
What is the world
like for them?
Where to start
if you want to know more about this area
and want to become a part of this industry?
If you are interested,
I think the first thing
is not to look at
whether you are 18 years old
and you want to come to this area
or you are too old.
I will not say the numbers
and say that this is old.
I want to say that
first you have to be interested,
then you have to make a plan
and thirdly,
you have to make a routine.
Today I have time
and today I started learning to program.
I didn't plan
where I would get this time
tomorrow, the day after,
in a week, in a month.
Something happens in my life.
Sometimes our brains
are not the biggest
friends.
When I say that I will work tomorrow,
my brain says that
you will work tomorrow.
Tomorrow you will be serious.
I think it is the same thing
with learning.
I think the third thing
is to make a routine
and say that this is my goal
and I want to get there
because of this and that.
Whether it is because of better work conditions
or because you want to be surrounded
by such people
and then prepare
when you will start.
Today I start, today I have time
but I have to realize that I will have time
tomorrow or in two days
and that this comes in a routine
and definitely at the beginning
I will say
like Donnie Kruger said
when you have a feeling that you are at the top
and then a new problem comes
where you say that you have no idea
and this happens all the time.
And also later
when you are experienced
I will say that this is a constant
but maybe I would say
to everyone that
the years are definitely not important
but you have to be interested
you have to set a goal
and a routine
so that you start every day
because otherwise
everything else will be wrong.
This program was not good,
this tutorial was not good,
this does not know how to explain well.
No, there will be something else
and I think that if you respect these three things
that success
simply cannot
not happen.
You are at such an
interesting intersection
of formal education
of the school on the one hand
and then this program SkillUp Mentor
where you focus more
especially on some skills.
Yes.
How does someone start?
Is it a theory?
Is it a specific
programming language?
Is it understanding?
How do we go from a transistor
to an e-mail?
That last one is definitely not.
I will say that technology is not important.
I think
last time you talked about it
I started with Turbo Pascal.
I don't know if it still exists
but I think technology is not so important.
But I noticed
that we are really different types of people.
For example, I myself fall into
what I
really don't care about.
I am like that.
If it is a function that does something to me
I put this data inside
I will get it out.
How it does it, I don't really care.
I will say
and through SkillUp and through formal education
I see that there are differences.
For example,
we have
a member of our community
SkillUp Mentor
she chooses books.
She started with Python The Hard Way.
For example, in my case
when I choose a book title
I would not choose The Hard Way.
Some people like to do it as a tutorial
which means that someone leads them.
Others say
I repeat but I don't learn anything.
There is a little trick
understanding comes with time.
Sometimes it is enough to do
3, 4, 5 tutorials
but again, I think
if you have a routine every day
when do you start
then when you come to the next tutorial
you will see that
like Karate Kid
who broke his car at the end of the video
that nothing is left of it.
Understanding comes with time.
I would say
prepare yourself.
If you don't have someone
at the beginning
to answer your questions
if you want to be
for example a developer
learn as soon as possible
how to learn by yourself
because you will not always have the opportunity
to ask someone
you will build a career
and there will be fewer and fewer interlocutors.
Whether it is a text
or you have
a text-based tutorial
or maybe
I like text-based tutorials
because I am interested in a very small thing
and I can't watch the whole video
to learn a lot of things
others would like to see
what they start
others choose to understand
what it is
so I think it is not so simple
to say exactly
how it would work
and then try
to see where
it suits you.
On the internet
there are a lot of
free code
programs
where you have
in Slovenia
smart ninjas
which are very good
in this ecosystem
so you can learn this way.
Do you have an estimate
how much time does someone need
to reach a certain level
in order to get a job?
Let's start from scratch.
In our skill-up
we don't learn
programming
we only give skills
because no one can come
or I would say
this is the beginning
but we also have
self-taught people
who come to us and we help them
to get a job
and there were self-taught people
who didn't want to come
to us
but this is a personal experience
so if I am careful
and I will do this
I will be able to speed up
but again, less talent
less support
it would be hard to estimate
how much time someone needs
but if I would say
on a finger
half a year, one year
I would say all these things
and what I mentioned before
self-skills, self-learning
all of this you learn on the shoulder
Maybe if I
relate to this
there is an idea
I go to school
I join and I get a job
and things
don't always go that way
what was the connection
between all of this?
Islam changed me
from the beginning
when I was a beginner
I did projects
for a year and a half
but I started
3-4 months break
a little bit of writing
a little bit of traveling
I took a month off
and then 6 months
so
then life came to me
and I don't know
when I started looking
different conversations
technical interviews, tasks
and then
you learn with that
on one interview you are better
more prepared
and so it goes
step by step
so you worked on
some other projects
outside of school
or in a group
a few years ago
I had my own project
and in the last year or two
I started
skill up
tasks, projects
When I took the time I had between classes, when I was an absolvent at the university, I started at Skilapo,
and when I graduated I had a bit more time, so I really took the time, set up a routine and then I finished.
What did the juniors expect from you during the conversations?
I think they said culture, that you are an open person, that you ask, that you know,
and that they are happy and that I like that, that I ask a lot.
They said the problem of juniors, that I don't ask a lot, so I go to assess how much I can do on a specific problem,
and then when I can't find a solution, I go to a partner or a senior and ask him.
I think they wanted me to know how to learn and to be open, to know how to ask.
Is there a difference between a student, a mentor or a writer?
I think there is a big difference between a student and a writer.
In Skilapo I always say that if your company allows you to be a writer,
because at the end of the day you build trust, you get to know someone better,
and I will say who will, because of course there will be some setbacks,
but if you can get in touch with someone you have already built a relationship with,
and if there is no other option, there is of course the remote option,
so that you can be sure that all of us, and I will say older people as well,
we always have this impostor syndrome, or this feeling that maybe you don't control it,
there are a lot of these myths, that a junior is looking for how to make time,
and a senior is also looking for the same thing,
and I am ready to say that it is ok if you ask, and that is what Ilya said,
but if we go back to formal education, there we somehow learned that asking is not the best,
because then the professor will say that I don't know, so I will be quiet,
and I will not ask anything, and then it is bad, for example,
in Skilapo we constantly ask, ask, ask, and ask even more.
Also, of course, there is a normal difference,
probably Ilya, if he comes to his mentor and asks him something,
he will have a lot of answers, in school there may be a completely different answer,
these are probably such differences,
so if this is definitely a mentor, I would get in touch with him,
if there is no other option, there is also the remote option,
I would say that it has already developed so much,
so we are already used to it, I don't think it represents so much.
And one more big shortcoming of our school system,
this is for sure, this is a frontal statement of knowledge,
that even if you want to do something in the field,
to some extent you are a new student,
and you learn new things, and that is the way the organization works.
Is there anything else that you think you could do better,
or learn in a better way?
I am very satisfied with our school system,
primarily because, as they always tell me, I have a bright future,
but I focus on things that work positively,
and I have a huge team, which I am very proud of,
and I am happy that they are my team,
and when I see how much energy and effort they put in,
and I also expect that the students who listen to this,
certainly have some professor,
maybe it was a teacher, I don't know,
of art, or math, elementary, high school,
who has changed me, I don't know,
in my life, or in the present moment.
So, when it comes to this school, I am positive,
especially because I see a lot of people inside,
who are working very hard.
Now, there are few things that could change,
but what is the goal?
If the goal is, as we said before,
to become a computer scientist,
to learn as much as possible, to communicate,
we don't follow these things in the beginning.
And if I go back to what you said about the two obligatory subjects,
I totally support this,
because we have to discover,
we are all teachers,
and we have to learn something,
on which I am not the most self-confident,
I will, of course, spend less attention,
and less time.
And the idea, this option,
to become a computer scientist,
would be, in theory, excellent,
in practice, unfortunately, a little less,
because, as you said, I will,
in the field of computer science,
I don't have a problem with green permanent things,
but if I don't feel self-confident enough,
to teach about it, and of course,
even if I teach, it won't be the same energy,
and I will say, young people won't learn the same way,
as we do in the database, or in other things,
which are close to me.
And because of this, I think they would need,
first of all, a frame.
If you don't trust anyone,
let's say, to accept obstacles,
and this is, I will say,
a frame in the sense that,
I will say, in advance,
or I will go back,
we have a lot of teachers,
and a lot of teachers who teach us in school,
but a teacher, a good teacher is not a bad teacher,
I think they would have to work on the entrance,
as they say, mostly on the doors,
when you enter, or in the organization of the company,
in the end, also in the school,
and they would have to work on this,
but now, in the coming years, it's even worse,
because the lack of a frame is huge,
and maybe someone came in, who would be a better engineer,
and maybe a worse teacher,
I don't know, if you give me a magic wand,
I don't know how I would solve this,
I don't want you to think that I'm criticizing,
it's a very responsible job,
but I would say to everyone who is listening,
or maybe you are older,
go to those teachers who are really cool,
go and tell them,
when the next generation comes,
And did COVID change anything,
and help with digital literacy?
Yes, the most.
I had a lecture at school,
and I said who digitized the school the most,
and I gave 1% equality, 1% school, and 98% COVID.
If it wasn't for COVID, it wouldn't be.
I think that COVID has helped a lot,
and if I go back to culture,
and what we are interested in,
I can tell you that we are not at the same level
of digitalization as we were,
we fell back to paper,
and we were purely digital,
but now that we are closer,
we see that we fell back to paper.
But that is purely human.
Maybe if we go back to the search for a job,
let's talk about the portfolio.
Did you have a portfolio,
a project,
how did you see that part,
as well as your representation
in this part of the market?
I didn't have a portfolio
as a split side,
I used LinkedIn and GitHub,
I wrote down all the projects I worked on,
I added descriptions,
and the tasks I received from companies
for conversations,
I added them to GitHub,
and I wrote them down nicely.
As far as the portfolio is concerned,
that's it.
Secondly, I wrote down what projects I worked on,
what I learned from them,
what difficulties I faced,
how I solved them.
Did you have a feeling
that people opened their GitHub
and saw that it was
a part of your portfolio?
I don't know yet,
but they said it was positive.
Everything was nicely presented,
and they also sent me a code,
they said it was a reliable code.
The comments,
depending on the participant,
and who is interested in going into the details,
it's good to have them,
even if they don't look at it.
I can't say
that it was positive,
but I can imagine
that this program,
SkillUp Mentor,
and your cooperation with companies,
and also if we refer to the portfolio,
is it something that comes from their side,
that would be right?
With SkillUp Mentor,
when you finish your formal education,
we are ready to join some people
who work in some services,
and in their opinion,
they would like to come to us
and look at the modern stack.
I connected with senior developers
from various companies,
and we prepared a project-based program,
we also have a community,
where we support mentors,
and we have a project in Figma,
where everything can be written in GitHub,
tasks that need to be done,
and we work with full-stack web developers.
At the beginning, we had a very strict technology,
but we held on,
and in the end we saw that everything was fluid,
we have a framework, we have Java,
we have .NET,
we are not that specific,
and I will say,
they also look at the campaign,
how to run these things,
how to estimate them,
and the goal is not to estimate them correctly,
the goal is to show that it is difficult,
and that they know how to split tasks into smaller tasks,
and when they have completed the task,
they have to deploy it.
We work on AWS from Amazon,
and they get a code review,
so the mentor goes through the code,
and decides to try to improve it,
I don't know if it would scale,
it wouldn't go through,
and we write down the possibilities for improvement,
we get a new project,
and we add a new technology,
which means that the old one maintains,
and the new technology expands,
and the mentor checks again,
if there was an improvement,
if there wasn't, where it would go.
We work remotely,
and we encourage them to ask,
so they know that it's not a problem to ask,
and that there is always someone ready to help.
And when they come to the end of our program,
for example Ilja,
then I talk to him,
what he wanted, what he wanted,
I also help with CV, how he prepared it,
what Ilja said,
I don't look at it as a tactic,
but I look at it as a step-back.
If you take a couple of hours,
and you prepare everything,
I don't think that if you choose between the two,
everyone would have everything prepared,
and I think that it would be logical to choose the one I would.
And we encourage them to prepare.
Then I would say,
I would like to mention,
that there are a lot of questions
about developers,
but in time,
maybe someone will come up with what you said before.
When I will conclude, I will say,
hey, I am here,
the business will grow,
but the topic will not be so open.
You need to have a lot of knowledge,
and I would like to say,
that the success stories,
when someone came to a door,
and they opened it,
not because they don't exist,
but because they are too exceptional.
And the projects where the mentors work,
are they standard,
how many projects can you finish,
or are they projects that are in production?
Yes, I would say,
that projects are a product.
They don't have to be in production,
but they are school projects.
And I think that everyone gets the same.
Because we tell them,
that they don't have to think,
that they don't have to be in production.
We also collaborate with other companies,
because they give us their own projects.
For example, we have a project with a stack.
We are not so powerful in their stack,
and we tell them,
that this is the company,
it has such and such a challenge,
and the company prepares everything for them.
We have 5 projects,
but it depends.
Ilja, I think you only made 2,
and we already agreed that it is not necessary,
that we keep it,
but it is already prepared to go to the service.
Or maybe we will make another project,
because we also had a self-employed person.
How did you choose the first service,
what criteria did you have?
Did you have any criteria for yourself?
Or was it just to be?
How did you choose it?
Good question.
First of all, I didn't want it to be
that technology,
when I was self-employed,
when I had already learned.
I worked in React,
but then I was more for React.
First it was some kind of an artist,
and even if it was a hybrid,
over time,
I got a job in Ljubljana.
I drove every day from Velenje in the first month.
It wasn't hard for me to get up in the morning,
every day, an hour and a half, 40.
I like to come to the shift,
because I like to ask,
and because of that,
it was often remote,
so it was possible to move forward.
That I have a mentor,
someone in the team,
or a few people I can turn to,
that it was important to me
to learn new things,
new technologies,
so that maybe in the evening,
on Nes, on Backend,
I would be interested in something.
I told Isla,
when I finished the project,
that I was interested,
and Isla said,
that such a good first job,
which offers support and mentorship,
and includes the environment,
which also shows you good engineering culture,
I think it's a good starting point for a long career.
What I notice is that
we often have problems
with juniors who have no experience
and don't understand what a good job is.
If I had an answer to that,
I would use it more,
because I know exactly what you're talking about.
But sometimes I'm a bit,
or I would say,
who am I to judge,
that the culture in which you are now,
is bad for you.
I try to talk to them,
and I also notice that
juniors stay in the industry for a long time,
and I would say,
maybe later,
maybe they are not fit for the industry,
but if I had an answer to that,
what would I say to someone,
but unfortunately I don't know how I would wake him up.
Maybe Ilija Sportrader,
maybe you can tell us more about
what do you see as a support
for juniors,
or what does it mean
for you to feel like you're not alone
and you have to know yourself.
First of all,
that juniors cooperate in all situations.
I didn't expect that.
When we talk about new functionalities,
when we divide tasks,
when we decide on time,
I've been there for a week,
and I've already been there,
when we were sorting out tasks,
deciding how much is required,
so that I'm included,
when you said I'm not included,
when we were sorting out onboarding projects,
a 20-year-old project,
they gave me what to do.
I got a task for the first week,
and I added a feature to the production.
That's the relationship.
When I had a question,
I always got an answer.
I'm happy if someone
sends me a picture,
because they come to me,
and they don't expect a senior to sit down
and show me everything.
I really like that culture.
I would definitely suggest
that all juniors
change regularly
and educate themselves,
because they see different systems,
different engineering cultures,
and they find it easier.
That was one of the biggest shocks
when I joined Recruiting.
You have people who wanted to work
on some projects,
and you think you won't find anyone
who would want that.
You have to think about
what someone wants,
what they are good at,
and then you can find your home.
I also saw the other side of it,
when someone stayed for 5, 7, 10 years
and then seriously threatened
the further development of their career
because they stayed in a company
and didn't have healthy practices,
testing,
and other basic things.
Maybe,
one part of it is that
the company wanted to show off
and make it work
in their system.
We also have companies
with different academies,
different courses,
summer schools.
You have a lot of experience
in the field of Islam.
Who is this for?
Is it only for people without formal education?
What are the gaps
that you want to fill?
I predict this.
I don't know exactly,
but it depends on the company.
I predict that every company
is looking for a white whale
to catch someone who is extremely talented
and will come to them.
I am very surprised,
because I think all these things
are very important.
I have a lot of experience in this field.
We realized that
the linear education
is not a serious project.
In the academy,
we have the same goal,
but we all have different beginnings.
Ilja came to us with a different beginning
when he did a lot of small projects.
The initial step was huge.
If we put him in a school
and taught him everything,
it would be either too long-term
or too demanding.
The classical school system
that they had in the academies
doesn't work in my opinion.
I predict that
someone who already has a lot of experience
will come to them.
They will want to work with them.
It will be a three-hour conversation.
I am sure that one day
a senior will tell them
how to do it.
I think that this is welcome
and we will be able to learn more.
They will tell us
and we will change something.
When we started two years ago,
I was very grateful.
I called you and asked you
what you think about this project.
You said that it is very welcome
and we would need it.
We would support that as well.
If I would have been told that it has nothing to do with me,
maybe I wouldn't have done it.
I think that now, after so much experience,
we definitely need that, and that young people,
and again, this is my balloon,
with whom I hang out,
I know that they will be excellent participants.
Someone who came in the afternoon, in the morning,
to educate himself, to contribute as much as possible
and with whom I would have started,
I think I don't need to explain more,
and there are not so few of them,
who know that, for example, when I was doing analysis,
when I started with this program,
when I asked the juniors when they came,
for example, what Ilja was talking about,
screwing some old projects in a cage for some business,
it kills their feeling, their morale,
to be able to contribute as soon as possible.
I think it's great that you are doing this,
that you can come in the first week,
or after the first two weeks,
and start producing things.
That is definitely a special feeling,
when you can do that.
What are your messages
in regards to this program?
Do you think that it would be...
What did it give you,
maybe additionally,
that you didn't have at school?
Do you think that because of a program like this,
you are now more employed?
First of all, knowledge, let's say.
I work in React.
I have some basics from other languages,
from other Java scripts,
I work less,
and then I learned Java script, TypeScript,
and then React,
that's one thing, not all technologies,
the other is soft skills,
to work with others,
I mean, on the project,
one is on another level,
and then you ask something,
you write it in Discord,
and then you get it.
I know that one of the first meetings
we had online,
I had a problem with a project for two weeks,
I had a problem with it,
and then I asked Clem,
he was working on Java,
and in two minutes, it was done.
If I had asked him before,
it would have been better.
When to ask, how much time do you need,
that's what I like the most.
Already in the first episode,
I also admit that soft skills
are the most important skills for an engineer,
maybe it's not so obvious,
but we really go back and forth
on soft skills,
that you are welcome,
that you know how to ask,
that you know how to communicate,
that you are a pleasant partner,
that was the most interesting outcome
for me from the first two episodes,
because in my field,
there is a lot of technical excellence,
experience, and what you have already done,
you have already worked on such a system,
and often those soft skills are important,
but they come as a second,
and the third is linear.
I think we go back to the fact
that this is an important part for a junior.
Soft skills are already soft skills,
but they are fundamental skills,
because without them it will be very difficult.
Our mentor, Clement Plazar,
definitely wasn't so successful,
if it wasn't for his soft skills,
his approach, how someone asks him,
how nicely he responds, helps him,
I am very grateful to him for that,
and how important it is for all the mentors
who are in the field,
that they take the time to explain,
because I can tell you that for a junior
it is really stressful.
It is really stressful for him to come
and ask him 100 questions,
and you give him that attention,
and with us, Clement is excellent,
and I think that for the juniors,
when they ask him how it all starts,
they have the most time in mentoring,
and that the right mentors choose them.
I think that those who are good developers
don't have to be very good mentors,
so I think they solve it well.
We are getting closer to one hour
of our conversation,
so we will wrap up in time,
but before we do that,
I would like to ask Ilija,
is there anything else you would like to say?
Do you have a message for all those
who are thinking about joining
the team of juniors,
or on the other hand, for mentors,
professors, and those who are looking
for a new role?
I think that we have come to the end
of soft skills.
One thing is technical knowledge,
and the other thing is that you need
that time to get used to it.
When I was looking for a job,
I got feedback that I liked it a lot
when they sent me an assignment,
and that I went through it,
and that I didn't ask about it again,
because the assignments were more open,
and that I didn't ask about it,
and that I could be more specific about it,
if the technology was okay,
if I could use those libraries,
and that seemed normal to me,
but after the interview,
I was asked about the parameters,
and that I had to be more specific.
So, yes, it's about the end.
You ask, and the more open you are,
the less fear you have to ask,
and to join.
I think that's the key,
that you are not afraid.
We all started somewhere,
Islam?
Yes, for the end,
I would like to thank everyone
who helped us at the beginning,
and all the children who supported us,
and joined us.
Thank you for the initial conversations,
and for the feedback,
and for building a very proud relationship,
so that when we get visitors,
we see that what we do contributes to them.
When it comes to the school,
I think that the most important thing
is the staff.
If the staff is focused,
then what is written in the programs,
I would put it in the second place,
and in the first place,
Thank you.
Thank you for this source,
and I hope that everyone heard it.
It is a wider social debate,
I think, about school in general.
That's it for the second episode of Zagora.
Thank you again for responding.
All those who listen to us,
or watch us on our well-known channels,
you can find us on ProPulsor,
where you can find the Zagora Podcast,
on YouTube,
and because we really try hard
to produce these podcasts,
you can also find us on Patreon,
where you can also support us,
or if you are our Patreon supporter,
you can get episodes,
so that you can support us.
We also want to open up
very relevant topics.
It is relevant that we got
the first sponsorship.
I would like to thank the 3FS and Human Frog
for the support,
so that we can create a community
that helps the entire Slovenian community.
That's it for this Saturday.
Thank you for taking the time.
Thank you to Otet and the team
for another great episode.
Listen and watch our show.