Hello, hello, Andrej. In the next episode of Ogrodje, we are in season 2, episode 15, and in the third episode of Zagora, where we will talk today about the work in progress,
and how to look for it. For those of you who do not know us yet, I am Sara Vašine Gašpar and today with me is Andrej Fodor.
We have known each other for quite some time, we met in 2020, and although at the beginning of the pandemic, the work is still on a larger scale.
First, if we start very quickly, who do you think you are? Let's introduce you a little. You will probably be alone, right?
Yes, I can. First of all, thank you for the invitation, I am a fan of Ogrodje, so it's great to be a guest. I hope I can say something smart today.
My name is Andrej, I've been running startups for 10 years, and I was one of the first. In 2018-2019, I started remote work, and now I help companies find individuals in the tech space.
On the contrary, I often help individuals I know, or from our tech community, to find interesting remote opportunities, because I think that with this we enable a lot of people who are locally positioned to come and play in the NBA instead of staying in your league.
Well said. When I was working on the plan for this episode, we really wanted to focus on the search for remote work. Then we asked our listeners, and I really felt the need to talk about remote work in general,
to compare it with other forms of work, and to touch on it a little. So maybe I would start with that. First, let's talk about how remote work works. We all know that remote work has experienced a very big increase, especially during the pandemic.
In the ZDA, from 6% of remote work, it jumped to 50% in 2020, and then this share began to decrease. But by and large, just under 40% of all global scientific workers are still working from home in 2024.
In short, the latest statistics from this year show that 98% of all workers want all the possibilities of remote work, while this opportunity offers only 16% of the company. Almost half are those who would be prepared to leave the service if we were able to remove remote work.
Workers from home or abroad are also very satisfied. About half are fully prepared to accept a lower salary just to be able to continue working from home. So let's first talk about that. How do you see, how did you experience these trends, also with the help of, of course, remote workers, and what could they be like as individuals and companies as well?
Yes, very good insight. I started to accept this trend around 2015, and it went up and up, until some smart companies started to use the opportunity of remote work as a way to attract interesting people.
They were able to draw out a local talent pool, and then they started to realize that this is a new opportunity to get a top position in the company.
In 2020, there was a complete black swan moment, where everything was put on the table, and there was a crazy amount of remote work. It was like we were giving a theme, and we all wanted to see more remote work, so we gave some rocket boosters, and it flew up.
Of course, this was also followed by the crash of 2021, when we were still working in a pandemic standard, we saw a lot of hiring and parties like there's no tomorrow.
Yes, I agree with what you're saying, because there were a lot of cut rounds, money was flying everywhere. Yes, I think that 2022 was a bit of a shock to the market, but in addition to that, 80% of the companies went back to on-site.
Yes, but there are still a lot of them. If we look at the global scale, it would be impossible to go to the current scale, and I think that over time we see that these trends are also maintained.
Some companies are trying to mitigate this with a hybrid mode of work, but because of what you just mentioned, 98% of people want to work, or at least have the opportunity to work remotely.
This doesn't mean that 98% of people want to work completely remotely, but they want to have one day or two days a week, maybe even five, to work from home.
Is there a difference between working remotely, working from home, and a hybrid system? Is there a big difference between working remotely and working from home?
Yes, working remotely means that you are not in the office, or you are not working on-site, but in the company, which means that you can also go to the co-working space.
You can also work on the beach, as a TikTok guru would say, if you are close to the screen and you can't see anything up there. But working from home means that you are working from home, and that is also working remotely.
What do people do? I think that both options are great, and it depends on what appeals to them. I know people who work remotely, and it is not possible for them to work from home.
On the other hand, we have a hybrid approach, which also has some advantages, but if we simplify it, it means that we work remotely two to three times a week, and then go to the office twice.
The ratio is different, I usually see it as 3-2, or 4-1, which means four from home and one day a week in the office. Some call it a mandatory Monday.
It is a more liberal approach, and I think that it applies to the structure of complete remote work, and they do it once a week, no matter what. Just to see if you are still alive. I see everything on the screen, but I don't get what I'm saying.
Should companies be organized differently, if they have a lot of employees who work from home, or remotely, or have a hybrid model of work?
Yes, I think that remote work from home has been a blessing during the pandemic. I know it sounds heavy, but I'll try to explain why.
Often, the structure of the company is the same as it is growing. When more than 20, 25, 30 people come together, they have to organize themselves, because communication doesn't work anymore.
They have to create a structure, and some people don't do that either, because they are lazy, they come to the table, and then suddenly there's a crash, where everything goes to shit, and no one knows how to talk to no one, and then the processes start.
Some companies don't do that, because they are lazy on-site, which means that you can just click on a change, and ask them again.
Remote companies have to do it on day one, otherwise they practically disappear, or it's impossible for them to work effectively. Many of these companies have proven that this is a good thing.
How do you work?
How do I work? I do a hybrid work from home and work remotely. My remote company is fully distributed, we all work in the same country.
Most of the communication is done via Async, which is synchronized, documented, or via communication channels such as Slack. I work three days a week from home, and two days in a dedicated co-working space.
So you stay in the co-working space.
That's right. This is a phase that's been going on for the last two or three months, where I've come to the point where I need a bit of socialization, especially between meetings and so on, so I've said to myself, okay, once or twice a week, no rules, but on average, I go to the co-working space, then I change, I go to a meeting,
I meet someone, either in the same field as me, or a friend, or someone else, and I strive for socialization, where maybe this negative aspect works from home, which people haven't seen before, and in this way I improve this social aspect.
What do you mean by that? Are there any other negative aspects of working from home or working remotely?
Yes, there are, of course. As a disclaimer, I would say that there are a lot more pluses than minuses.
But there are also minuses. Depending on the organization, for example, one of the negative aspects is that people are hard to get along with.
This happens from time to time, but this is again an anomaly of the company.
The second negative aspect is the lack of social aspect, because a specific company, for example a technical staff, does a lot on its own, i.e. individually, and there is a lack of socialization, and then some people forget about it in the afternoon or in the evening, and then it can happen that they feel a little lonely.
So this is a part that has a lack.
This person-to-person interaction with people in real life is very important.
I think it's very good how they solve this, that is, to organize a team meeting once every three months for a week, and then they meet in the evening, and this part is, for example, very important, very productive, and a lot of people say that this is a sweet spot.
Once every three months, you get your core team, with whom you work for five days in real life, brainstorm, debate, or plan, this part is perhaps a little better in real life than remote.
So yes, these three things, I would say, are among the most important.
Well, with us, the synthesis is once in a while like this, that every three months, not even for five days, but usually for two to three, we get it, usually it's for planning, brainstorming, i.e. daily, for some retro, and for a team meeting.
which is much more convenient with ten people in the room than with ten people on Zoom.
But, more than anything, when you change negative things, where can you change positive things.
And maybe as a personal experience, for me, working from home primarily means that I have a career.
I am from Ankara, and the perspective in Slovenia, if you are not in Ljubljana, is still a career,
but it is really an incredible environment in Ankara to live and raise children.
So, for me, it really means that I can involve my parents, that I can live with a grandmother who has dementia,
and if she needs anything, in a short time, I really have a career.
Recently, I also advanced in the leadership of a company.
The funny thing is that the whole team in London, which sits on the side of the founders,
and only I am here, 20 km away, was not convinced.
So, that seems to me to be such an advantage, when you have already made this difference,
your league versus the NBA.
If you were to share your experience, where else do you see the advantages of working from home?
I think that this is probably the biggest advantage I would make.
If we look at it on a global scale, people have certain desires or ambitions to do something.
Certain people do, certain people don't.
This is not so important, but it is important that people who want to do something,
their potential surrounds them.
In the past, it was also the case that you simply had to move somewhere,
to be able to do some things.
The industry still holds this, and this is the reality of the world.
In the tech space, this is not necessary.
In other words, it should not be necessary.
Looking at the demand, how much engineers are needed and increased in the market,
maybe a disclaimer, if GPT does not take over the market,
there is still a big shortage of engineers.
What I wanted to say is that once you have the opportunity to work for a top company,
you will be good at something.
It is not necessary to talk about top 3% or top 1%.
This is also nice, of course, for these people, the service,
and also for people who simply cannot find a job in the local environment.
For someone from Ljubljana, it may be easier to find a job.
For someone who comes from Slovenia, they have a very limited pool of employees,
and they have to move either to another place or somewhere else,
and it takes a lot of time.
Or it is not an opportunity for someone who is specifically targeted
and is very good at something.
And this is what prevents people from going back.
In addition, a side thing that is also important is the possibility of a higher salary,
if you work for this market.
This is of course also true.
The third thing is, maybe even before that,
I said this more in terms of a side salary,
it is nice, but the third is a huge increase in time.
People do not realize that there is a very simple statistic
that says that if you work every day for two hours to get to the office,
or one hour to the office and one hour back,
this is the equivalent of a 40-hour employee in one month.
That is, in four months, you survive one month of your employee in the commute.
And this is such a time drain, I have no other expression in Slovenian,
how much time is lost for this.
That is why the simple question is,
do you want the opportunity to work from home?
Yes, of course.
Because yes, some people like it,
but only a small percentage like it once a week to work.
Most of the time it is sitting in the car,
waiting either on the train or on the bus,
and waiting, waiting, waiting to get somewhere to work,
where you will probably have 15 minutes of interaction with someone,
and then go home.
You can also do this online through other channels.
Yes, this is also what we may be a little quick to notice,
what we start, especially in a hybrid setting,
what we start, who we are in the office.
If we come to the office to sit on Zoom,
you ask yourself again why and what for.
On the other hand, we all know that this human-to-human thing is really needed.
For some things you need people in the office.
Yes, especially brainstorming.
Let's not just talk about all the good things,
remote work is the best.
Brainstorming is by far better in person than online.
This is a fact.
I think we'll have to wait a long time for this to change,
so we can get closer to it.
But you don't plan every day.
You don't brainstorm every day in a new project or feature you build.
You do this maybe once a month,
for three months,
possibly once a week, but not more than that.
The rest of the interaction is very close to what you can do in person.
Because of that, in this example,
I see an opportunity to get more experience,
because you plan things.
The other part is the work itself.
You allow yourself to be a top fit for your position.
For me personally, it's quite stressful.
Maybe because I go in such an order,
and then everyone wants to greet me.
Of course.
It's logical.
I only go once in three months.
But above all, this instinct helps me.
For me personally, it feels like I'm organized at home,
I know when I do what I have to do,
because it's not a job.
But above all, I plan a good part of the day,
more than eight hours for the job.
So I have some space in my head.
On the other hand,
when you don't know how to work from home,
and you can't get into the hyper-focus at home,
and you go outside all the time,
maybe that's why you're not as effective at home.
That's where the stereotypes come from.
Working from home means you want to stay at home,
so you can get surgery, wash up, and so on.
But when you work from home non-stop,
you just can't operate like that.
At the end of the day, you're stuck at home,
and you have to show some results.
Do you also experience that?
Do you pay attention to your productivity,
whether you're at home or in the co-working space?
Good question.
I think we've entered an era of productivity porn,
where everyone is working non-stop,
but human brains don't work like that.
We all have a peak,
where we get to two or three hours a day.
The rest is still work,
less brain-intensive work.
How do I manage that?
First, I try to do the most important tasks in the morning.
Then, when I have low brain energy,
I do tasks that don't require a lot of mental load.
Of course, that also changes.
In the morning, when I fall asleep,
I do tasks like that.
It all depends on the person,
and on our nature.
But when I see that I'm not as productive,
I go to the office or co-working space.
It also depends on the person.
In my most productive environment,
it's the plane or the train.
I'm hyper-productive.
It's a funny thing,
because I'm ready to deal with other people like that.
I think it's normal, I'm a weirdo.
But that doesn't mean I'm going to fly every day.
I want to say that people have to find their own space,
and find the most productive ones.
I wanted to add something about productivity.
People from home, and the idea that people don't work.
It all depends on the organization.
How do you measure productivity?
One thing that I think Mouthworks is changing,
and it's very important,
and more organizations should do it,
when we talk about the creative or tech industries,
maybe not creative, but more intellectual industries,
we shouldn't measure the time we live,
what we do,
but the impact of what we do.
People often ask me,
how can you work remotely,
how do you know someone is working remotely?
I don't look if someone is online,
we don't have that either.
We have a rule,
that if someone is online,
I don't care if they work from 3am or 10am.
It doesn't mean they have to work from 3am.
It's up to them.
The question is, do I know who did what today?
Probably not.
But do I know who did their work in one week?
I definitely know that.
So, when it comes to remote work, we just have to start measuring things differently.
Not on a daily basis, but on a hourly basis.
Because presence doesn't mean work.
But, for example, I do this in the weekly part,
where we look at our goals, what we did and what we didn't do.
And very quickly we see that if this happens again,
then we have some difficulties.
Either we plan poorly, or no one fulfills their tasks.
At the beginning, you also touched on the technological boom,
which was a bit of a success in 2022.
150,000 people were released only in the ZDA, in the technological sector.
Meta, for example, released 11,000 people in October 2020,
which is about 13% of all those who participated in Meta.
This year, Amazon announced and also increased the number of employees by 18,000.
In Europe, it was a bit smaller.
We have different laws here.
And, in the end, maybe a bit more predictable business practices than in the ZDA.
But we came to about 92,000 employees who remained without a job.
Some countries were a bit more on the attack,
especially those that had more actors, such as SAP, Siemens, etc.
which are due to a decrease in expenses.
Even in Slovenia, we did not get rid of the release.
We also caught up with some businesses at that time,
which were on our market for quite some time.
However, these releases were not entirely evenly distributed.
Some sectors, such as e-commerce and social media,
which have experienced a lot of growth during the pandemic,
have also recorded a lot of release when growth slowed down.
On the other hand, there are companies for cyber security,
and of course we must not forget AI and machine learning.
In fact, after the questioning, the number of employees increased by 30%
among those professionals.
So, the releases were not equally distributed.
Perhaps, as a recruiter, a lot of recruiters were released.
There were also a lot of engineers,
and all of us who were involved in the work environment,
such as product QA and so on.
However, the increase in talent was a powerful factor in all of these.
Because, of course, when you release someone first,
when you want to hire more people, you hire more people.
So, if you can relate a little to this,
also from your field, when it comes to services.
How did you find out about it?
Did you notice any difference before 2022,
2022 and 2023, also in the questioning,
and in general, how did you feel about these trends?
Yes, interesting question.
I would go back a little more to 2020,
where we saw some April-May,
I think there was also a massive layoff,
because people were afraid of what was going to happen.
Then there was an abnormal influx, or growth.
In general, as you said, in social media and e-commerce,
the business did not record a 10% growth.
Some went as far as 3x, 4x, 10x.
Unusual numbers occurred in this space.
Today, I will talk about how Meta had massive layoffs,
and so did Amazon.
I would say that everything, and how it started,
end of tech, as we know it.
I would put it this way,
I have prepared a very interesting article on this topic,
people shouldn't look at how many businesses had massive layoffs,
people in the last 2-2.2, or 2-2.9, even more.
You will see that all those businesses had less employees,
than they have now.
The growth in 2.21 was such an anomaly,
and so much FOMO happened on the market,
that everyone went over the top.
Then the layoff came.
2.22 was the layoff.
We read about it.
It was around the second quarter,
it started, then there was a winter,
if it was summer for us,
but in recruiting it was winter.
In the whole American world,
because we work with American clients,
it was zero.
Now I would say that over time,
in the last few months,
2.23 started to stabilize,
and now it is growing again.
Slowly,
but so that,
when I talk to people in our space,
we all feel that it started to grow slowly again.
Because the layoff was really bad,
a lot of recruiters lost their jobs,
a lot of companies didn't want to hire,
they optimized their businesses,
those that were successful,
then they said,
ok, we are doing well for a while,
now we need people.
Let's put aside the whole AI tech space,
where there was a big boom,
and I think it is a new industry,
where there will be a lot of services,
and we will see how it will develop.
There is definitely a lot of interest in this field,
so here we see a huge growth,
people looking for experience working with AI.
Cyber security is also there,
and other more popular positions,
from PMs to back-end engineers, front-end engineers.
We are slowly seeing a growth.
I think we have already seen it with Bot.
From your words, I am really happy.
As they say,
for this crowd,
the Podcast of Grodno,
we all want the best.
I am in AI,
and I am doing a chat GPT-R,
after December,
and at the beginning of the summer.
It is really incredible,
how this chat GPT-R has affected all of us in this industry,
and our product zone is much bigger than it was in chat GPT-R.
It is really incredible.
You are on a spaceship with a rocket booster,
which is almost anomalous,
but the space is really growing,
and as you said,
it is becoming more popular.
I am going to a recreation with a colleague,
and I see a hairdresser,
who is telling me,
that this is a chat GPT-R.
Then we know,
that there is a lot of demand,
and a lot of things are going to happen.
Everything is great.
Maybe we can connect to chat GPT-R,
for the next question.
Let's talk a little bit,
about how to find a job in the future.
A chat GPT-R can help us here,
but maybe,
if we start at the beginning,
or at the beginning of this,
what are the differences,
between looking for a job on a local level,
and looking for a job in the future?
In theory, there are no differences.
In practice,
in my opinion,
I would say,
that there is a huge difference,
and this difference,
in the end,
is seen,
as a very important factor.
And this factor is,
if,
I will try to give an analogy,
which also applies to the job,
if a Slovenian job is looking for,
a DevOps engineer,
with 5 years of experience,
if I'm not mistaken.
In reality,
he catches his fish,
in some small fishery.
For example,
if he works locally.
If he works remotely,
he has an ocean in front of him.
And this is the difference.
Now, if you are looking for a job locally,
everyone catches a fish in a fishery.
Differently in the ocean.
Now, I won't scare anyone,
because this means,
that if you are competing,
for example,
on a job with 500 applicants,
and this is a very big reality,
is that someone,
who prepares properly,
and invests some energy,
and work in preparation,
has a good qualification,
will always be a top 5% candidate.
Let's start.
What are the first steps,
that must be taken,
when you finally realize,
that you want to work remotely.
There is a lot of conservativeness,
on the Slovenian market.
Not so much for the job,
as for the job for Tui,
and Tui's business,
and playing in the NBA.
You are so comfortable,
in the local league.
So, what are the first steps,
that must be taken?
Definitely,
if I start with an actionable point,
I would say,
that in the last couple of years,
we have been struggling a lot,
and there have been offers,
that came to us,
from a lot of experts,
who never looked for a job.
Now, they have reached the point,
where the company has dried up,
and no one has to apply for a job.
I have never applied for a job,
and here I would say,
that everyone should realize,
that this is not something,
where you click on LinkedIn,
easy to apply,
because, as I would say,
for a job at this level,
it doesn't work like that,
completely remote.
We have to prepare,
we have to update our CV,
we have to describe the things,
that we have done,
and be very hands-on.
We have to show,
what kind of impact,
we have added in the past,
and show how we match,
to some of these jobs.
I would say,
that if someone,
wants to get a good job,
but doesn't have a triple A resume,
or a background,
in the sense,
that works for Mera,
or X,
or some other,
fang-mang type of companies,
I would say,
that this is a part-time project.
Two hours a day,
or a couple of hours a week,
dedicated to,
applying for a job,
writing a good CV,
sending an email,
and potentially doing something extra,
to get an interview.
If we look at it globally,
the biggest challenge,
for the candidates,
that we work with,
is to say,
I applied for 10 jobs,
and no one called me back,
and I qualified.
You have to know,
that on the other side,
there is Sarah,
and you can't expect,
from someone else,
that they will get 500 quality jobs.
Our most important part,
is to figure out,
how we are going to get out,
of the noise,
that is created by the applicants.
That was my next question,
what can someone do,
to increase their opportunities,
for a job.
Or,
I think the first step,
in the first interview,
is to call someone,
and ask them to send you a positive message.
Not a generic,
rejection message.
That is a great question.
Some of the things,
that I will say,
might seem controversial,
but,
I will try to be transparent,
about what I would do,
and what some candidates do.
Most of the time,
they are very positive.
First of all,
as we said,
we are talking about,
our impact,
and the value,
that we added to the company,
not the responsibilities,
that we had.
I don't know,
if you are a devops engineer,
migrating structures,
saving thousands of dollars,
per month,
or,
launching a feature,
that had so many users,
etc.
If I may,
we are working in teams,
right?
Yes,
I would like you to know,
that you get your CV,
from the company,
and not from the team.
Yes,
I did that for my team,
and it is fair enough.
I know,
it is hard to quantify them,
but,
sometimes it works,
and sometimes it doesn't.
That is one thing,
but,
I think,
one of the most important things,
is to try,
to step it up.
For example,
there is a hot,
remote work company,
that has been building,
their brand,
since 2015.
They got 2,000 applications,
for an engineer,
I met the engineer,
he was underqualified,
but there was a difference,
in his application,
from the other 2,000 people.
He went extra mile.
He took the project,
and the CV,
that is a bit extreme,
he made it look like their app,
visually,
and that impressed a lot of people,
and that was the first interview.
But when he went extra mile,
and the recruiters said that,
and the people he talked to,
he used the app,
he was a user,
he reported some bugs,
that he had on his application,
and that added,
added some value,
they realized,
that someone put in the effort,
and showed interest,
that they really want to work here.
That doesn't mean,
that developers have to beg,
for someone to work here,
but just to show interest,
and energy,
to come to the call,
to ask a question,
what do you do,
to get interested,
and on the third day,
you will experience the next year,
two, five, something,
and you have no question,
where you will be,
what you will do,
to show interest,
that is huge,
and to show your skill.
Today, for some companies,
unfortunately,
the CV is not enough,
if someone writes,
one thing,
for example,
home tasks,
or live coding,
this part,
can be skipped,
if someone documents
their side projects,
on github,
this is,
sometimes,
a very positive signal,
that works well,
for companies,
and also for candidates,
to decide,
if they will move forward,
or not,
not a complete thing,
but an additional signal,
will save candidates,
and time,
because no one wants to
waste time,
in a conversation,
that does not lead anywhere,
and this is often
recruiting,
preparing fit,
but,
most of all,
correct me,
it pays off,
to choose 10 companies,
and prepare quality,
and really look,
and apply,
where you really want to work,
like in a numbers game.
If the question is meant,
to those people,
who are making a step up in their career,
and at the end of the day,
it's not just a paycheck,
that they are looking at,
I would say, absolutely, yes.
Apply to 10 companies,
and prepare,
maybe look at their app,
report if you find something,
or, I don't know,
add,
add a disclaimer,
that you are working on a project,
on a similar topic,
where you will,
I would say,
you will get a really good offer,
from one of those 10 companies,
which is often frustrating,
and where I see,
developers lose motivation,
to apply for 1, 2, 3 jobs,
they don't hear anything back,
until they get an auto-rejection mail,
and then it's like,
oh, maybe I'm not fit,
and it's some kind of imposter syndrome,
and all of a sudden,
I'll tell you this,
if we are talking about a remote work space,
for a really good company,
fast growing,
where you know there is a lot of competition,
and a lot of interest,
if you don't apply for such a company,
then in less than 10 applications,
there will be a service,
called LuckySide,
and,
I want to say,
it's worth taking time,
and dedicate yourself,
because every application,
1, 2, 5,
will result in you being
in the top 5% of applicants,
and you will most likely get,
if you are qualified,
a job on an interview,
and then they lie to you,
because it's their game,
but that part is the hardest,
and I see that most people fail,
because most of the technical staff,
has a lack,
and it's the biggest improvement,
to come to the first interview.
How did the motivational letter,
finally die?
That's a very interesting question,
I would say,
yes and no.
Now I will try to explain,
why yes and no.
In the way we see them today,
yes,
in the way
they can be done,
no.
Today, it's not a cover letter,
where you can write,
how to apply,
and why you should work here,
it's a motivational letter,
where you look at the app,
and maybe report 2 or 3 bugs,
find an improvement,
maybe you fixed something,
and show it on your report,
look at this,
I really like what you are doing,
and you should apply for this job.
That's a cover letter today.
And that's definitely,
one of those things,
that prevents you,
absolutely.
I think that,
if you apply to such a place,
and if someone sees this,
and if you are qualified,
I think there are very few possibilities,
of course there are,
but there are a lot of possibilities,
that you won't be invited to the interview.
Because a lot,
500-1000 people apply,
but they don't do anything.
You are one of maybe three,
who did something like that,
and that engagement is very valuable,
and it will buy you back,
a lot of times,
on the interview.
So, you are young,
you know what you want,
but it's pretty clear,
in what,
we are already in a previous episode,
the first part,
thinking about what we really want,
is also very important,
so that we don't
spread our network too much.
But,
where to find,
job vacancies,
are there any platforms,
where do we have that step in the profile,
first of all,
looking for those opportunities.
Remote, of course,
we click on remote,
is there anything else,
where else can we find jobs?
Yes, of course,
remote is just one of many platforms,
where we specifically work on matchmaking,
and we are a recruiter.
There are some outsourcing opportunities,
for example,
where you work more freelance projects,
like Toptail.
Now, if we look at some
job vacancies,
there are some
job boards,
where you pay to look,
and in the end,
LinkedIn is not a bad idea,
but what I would say is that
if there is an opportunity,
if you find a job on LinkedIn,
you can apply on LinkedIn,
but you can also apply via e-mail,
go to their website, find an e-mail,
and apply there.
If you apply a lot,
you will probably have a little more
influx of applications
on e-mail,
than on LinkedIn.
It depends.
I mean,
in my ATS,
it comes through the same bracket,
only the source is then
applied on your website.
Yes, it depends on the scale of the company.
Some have integration,
some don't,
and then there is a lot of noise on LinkedIn.
But I would say,
for example,
the job boards are
remote...
What did I forget?
Remote OK, yes.
Remote OK is one of those
where we work remotely.
But yes, there are a lot of services
on those portals.
For example,
if you want to work with
an Austrian market,
on an Austrian local portal,
I think it will work with
an Austrian market.
And then you log in,
and you look at where the voice is written in English,
and you apply to that voice.
But you should know,
for example,
that all the most popular opportunities
from LinkedIn,
Remote OK,
have the highest influx of applications.
There, as I said,
you will have to work a little harder,
sometimes even not.
I would also add
that social...
social media here,
Kliupo.se,
just any platform, whatever
someone uses, there are no rules here.
NX,
Facebook,
Slack,
finally Discord,
and I will let myself
invite all
listeners here,
so that we can also
join on Discord, we have Discord in Grodje,
I will also link at the bottom
of the video,
these are also great communities
for networking and joining services.
Crypto, for example,
a specific market,
was very huge on the topic
of Discord community,
plus, for example, some Telegram groups,
and you are already a member of that community,
and there I got
some interesting people
who were involved in projects,
for example, Contributor Codes,
and so on, so yes, I forgot
to mention, social media is also
one of the phenomena
that I manage in Slovenia,
and I also think that I manage
in a few countries,
for example, a Slovenian group,
Slovenian developers,
where there are a lot of services,
some interesting things,
and it's almost like an anomaly,
you rarely see it in such a large group,
a large number of residents.
So yes, prepare different channels,
then, as you said,
really see, aha,
this is something that I would really like to do,
and then devote
some energy and time to
apply for this model so that you will join.
It's like,
I don't know,
it's not a promotion,
but really, sometimes we really change
someone's life,
in the sense that we also helped
someone who lives
in Bosnia, in a village
that has two hours of driving
to Sarajevo, where, for example,
a tech hub
works for a company
in San Francisco,
paid $160,000,
which is really good for what it does,
and I couldn't have those opportunities.
And it's not just about paying,
it's about having the opportunity
to work on top-notch projects
that otherwise
I wouldn't have the opportunity to do.
And that's why
you pay to try,
because you really have the opportunity to work
with very smart people
and interesting people
who do the same thing, but are part of something else.
Yes, well,
as you said,
and now that you mentioned it,
maybe another big difference is
especially in some such companies,
the relations are also
a little different.
Working at an international level,
in an international team,
there must also be a slightly different rule,
because it seems to me that
this is a good school,
even if someone does not want
to work all their career in the future,
that it is an interesting
leap from a local,
and perhaps also from
some Slovenian culture
in some places.
I think it is certainly
an experience that you will not forget
or rich in some way because
you will work first with people
from different cultures,
you will learn different communication,
because you will have to respect some other standards.
The way we communicate
may be different from people
who sit in England,
in America, or in Latin America.
I often joke
when someone says
when an American
asks a Slovenian,
how do you think it's okay
if all Americans wear red flags,
what are they doing?
I think it's okay,
in fact, it's very good for them.
When we learn some of these
communications,
they work with different cultures,
so it's definitely a rich experience.
Plus, you can work with
very interesting people
who are good on their own front.
You gave me a very nice source,
and I'm looking forward to the next question.
Communication
and in general,
the first interview
is a video interview
on Zoom.
Do you have a specific advice
on how to
hack this standard format
of interviews?
I agree, I won't say
you have to do it in bed.
A little joke.
I think it's a very important part
because we have a lack
of in-person interactions.
One of the things you have to know
is that people are very active
in these interviews,
especially if they like the job.
I would recommend
all HR people
to be more relaxed
and not make it
like an interrogation room.
Unfortunately,
some companies don't always do that.
What I suggest to candidates
is
to
do a demo.
If they haven't done
any interview in three years,
it's a matter of practice.
In the end,
ask your partner
or colleague to do
a mock interview.
There are also platforms
where you can do a mock interview
and get valuable information.
They are very useful
when you're working.
Unfortunately,
in a limited setting
in a 2D format,
it can be a disadvantage
and won't help
your promotion.
On the other hand,
we have a lot of people.
As much as possible,
set up an interaction
with that person.
Because at the end of the day,
it has to be an interaction
on a high level,
because everyone knows
you're going to work with them.
If you don't have practice,
talk to someone
or do a mock interview.
I think I've done
around a thousand interviews
in the past three years.
In the first two or three minutes,
I can tell
who was in the first,
third or fifth interview.
How are the people
and how do they prepare?
Often, it doesn't serve
the people.
That's why I prefer
to talk to someone
before the interview.
That way,
you'll know how to respond.
If someone on the other side
of the interview
deserves you,
you might be a little nervous,
but you'll be able
to talk to them.
On the other hand,
I see that the candidate
might add
that you can sit anywhere
and decide
if you want to do
the interview at home.
You have to be careful
about the background,
about the equipment,
because that's also
something we assess
in the first interviews.
It's important to know
if the environment
you're in is suitable
for the interview.
You can really see
what's going on.
I personally don't mind
if someone has an interview
in a car,
because I know
that if they don't live in a car,
they probably won't work there.
You can see that
there's no proper equipment
all the time.
We didn't invest in a normal camera
or headphones
or microphone.
It's also
one of those things
that affects the
unconscious bias
and leaves an additional impression
on us
who do the interview.
I think that's a great source.
You said that people
are biased.
Your job, on the other hand,
is to try to eliminate
all the biases that may arise.
The fact that you don't have
a camera at home
and that's why
you're in the interview,
is definitely
HR bias.
I mean,
that doesn't correlate
with your quality of work,
but it will correlate
with the communication
or style of communication
that you have.
It's not necessary,
but it's a standard
in today's remote setting.
If you don't have a phone,
download an app,
change your phone
and say,
sorry, I don't have a camera,
but you have a phone,
it will show up.
If you're driving
from your on-site job
to your job in the office,
say, I'm sorry, but
unfortunately, I'm driving home,
and that's why I'm here.
A context will help.
The camera,
and our head of security,
have a video
identification
with pleasure.
We know
that the same person
who shows up on the first call
is also the same person
and we also record
our interviews,
so that we have
a record
with pleasure,
because
there's something
going on on both sides.
Yes, I agree,
it's an interesting thing.
I say, no panic,
you don't need the whole interview
including the video,
but
the first video
identification, even if
someone in the same Zoom room
comes over the phone,
because he doesn't have a camera.
Yes, of course.
You have to take it differently.
Why is the camera important?
Because you can see
who you're talking to on the other side.
It's a base.
Should we be 60 minutes on the call?
No, if it's a bad connection,
just wave twice
and that's it,
if it doesn't go differently.
So, this brings us
to the last question,
which will be
touched a little,
and if it concludes
for the rest of the search,
a lot of people
who are fake
or who are not
what they seem to be,
they have their profiles
on LinkedIn,
the whole portfolio is
made up,
you can see that
everything doesn't match,
and it's not
what it used to be.
On the other hand,
we also have fake businesses,
fake services,
so
can you give us
an idea of what we need to be aware of
and how we can
protect ourselves from this?
I would say that
it's easiest to protect yourself
from this with a healthy brain.
If someone offers you
a service for 10,000 dollars
per month
for 4 hours of work,
and it doesn't correlate
with your hourly rate,
and you'll have to pay
in advance for someone to offer you something,
then it's probably not
the right thing.
Nothing comes for free.
If it's too good to be true,
then it's probably not.
In the other context,
in today's era,
it's a very interesting thing
to understand
who is on the other side,
because sometimes people
change, we've already had
an experience with this,
and then we sort of turned it
around.
There were doubts
whether it was done by this person
or someone else.
Today, we've come to the era
where people have changed
and said,
ah, live coding,
which has its own specifics,
and people have to prepare for it,
because we don't code
in an environment where
these three people are watching.
Maybe friends,
but it's not the same setup.
So it's very biased,
so people prepare for it.
But even here,
we've moved to a place
where there's a chat GPT
and it helps us solve
certain things.
So it's a way of figuring out
how this part of the technical
evaluation is solved.
One of the very interesting
things I learned,
and maybe you can find a link
in the description,
is that it works like a review.
You talk in code.
No coding, but we talk,
and together we go through the code.
And here, it's hard to use
a chat GPT if you're on the spot
talking about something.
And that helps in some discussions
to see if something is being read
or used. But yeah, common sense.
Look if the picture looks the same,
or not.
If it's a different person,
I don't know.
But yeah, try to identify
and if someone sent you
something that looks too good
to be true for their level,
go back to the interview
and talk again, and see.
Because if it's someone
who's technical,
and works with it,
I'll get the feeling very quickly.
Is it really someone who did it,
and why did they decide to do it?
Or was it done by
some other person?
So, we've come to the end
of this episode of Zagora.
With you were
Saravšine Gašper
and Andrej Fodor.
Andrej, thank you very much.
I think we've covered
a lot of important questions.
And I hope
that we'll have more
opportunities to work together
as a result of this conversation.
We can't conclude
without mentioning
Human Frog and 3FSA.
Thank you
for the sponsorship
so that we can
have the awards.
And of course, our Patreons.
Without them,
our Discord
would be much longer.
And of course,
the awards teams
Otto Brgles, Andraž Straka,
Jan Dolar and Tomaš Zaman.
We're with you
and we're doing this
with joy.
With joy, right?
Thank you
and see you next time.