Welcome to a brand new episode of Ogrodje.
This time with a beautiful picture,
with beautiful guests,
with a beautiful sound,
in a pleasant ambience,
and with a new Elan,
with a new energy that we tried to choose
for this episode.
So, welcome to the new episode of Ogrodje.
This time with a beautiful picture,
with beautiful guests,
with a new energy that we tried to choose
for this episode.
In our Ogrodje we have now shot
I think about 22-23 episodes.
These are episodes that are somewhat
suitable especially for experienced experts,
for people who work in our industry,
people who do not work in our industry.
And among all these stories,
we listen to a lot of the audience,
we listen to our listeners and viewers.
And we started to ask ourselves
how we could make Ogrodje
even more accessible to the next generation
of developers,
beginners, juniors,
and people who try to enter this industry,
because they have already seen that it is interesting
intellectually and because it is also
very attractive.
And because we somehow tried in Ogrodje
to realize that it makes no sense
to simplify our debates with great experts
too much to bring certain people
closer to the beginners,
we decided to make a new series
of episodes that would be
very beginner-friendly.
This series of episodes will be called
Zagon and you will find them
in podcast platforms and also on YouTube.
They will be marked by themselves
and are thoughts for beginners
and also for those who would like
to become beginners.
Not to mention that we have
some experts who
talk about these things
in a very disconnected way.
We decided to invite them
as hosts of Zagon
Sara Vashini-Gašper.
Hi!
She joined us in one of the previous episodes
where we talked about talent.
It was a very well-prepared episode.
She also joined us as a co-host
in one of the episodes.
And now we will see how Sara
treats us.
I don't have any notes today
but we agreed on that.
I still don't understand
why I'm stealing this podcast for today.
But on the other hand,
I know he will be happy to talk
and not ask questions.
Greetings from my side.
For those who don't know yet,
I'm a tech recruiter
at the Slovenian and international markets.
I'm here today to protect the debate
on a fairly low level
and to provide all the information
that IT people need.
Not only those who want to program
but also those who would like
to decode some concepts.
I managed to invite Petar Kešet
in this episode.
I will start with my left.
Petar Kešet is a master engineer
and programmer.
He hacked supercomputers
in Australia in the 90s.
He is the leader of the Slovenian
national IT team at the Olympics
for 5 years.
He has been working at the Jožef Štefan Institute
for a long time.
He has a lot to do with video.
You know a lot about video.
You probably know everything
that can be done with video.
No, I haven't done a lot of things yet.
There is still a lot to do.
Petar is currently employed
as a lead data scientist
at the Http pool.
On my right is Dr. Mateu Špesek.
Those who go to FRI know him.
Those who don't know him
know him now.
He is a doctor and a lecturer at FRI.
He has his own laboratory
for computer graphics and multimedia.
I am a member of this laboratory.
You study and research
graphics and multimedia.
Your main focus is audio, music,
transcription, speech.
We have always been interested in audio.
We have dealt a lot with different types of audio.
From human singing to piano transcription
to data collection
from data
that is not studied
or recorded on such microphones.
In the 70s, when older guests
gather and sing human songs,
you can hear trumpets,
maybe a train or something else.
Especially what they do,
when they sing,
what type of singing it is.
These things connect us
with non-computer areas.
Today, I thought
that we will go a bit historical
and a bit current.
Nothing difficult.
We will try to explain
to the audience
what it means to be a programmer,
what is a day-to-day job in this industry,
what are the different profiles,
because I see that there is a lot of misunderstanding
about where to start.
If we start at the beginning
with some definitions,
if we first clarify
who is an IT person,
who is a programmer,
who is an engineer,
what are the differences between them.
You will start, Petar.
I would say that all these people
have something in common,
all these profiles.
This is a kind of
computational-analytical thinking.
It can be very synthetic.
An IT person is anyone
in the computational industry.
Programmers, I think,
should not be the first to explain
how they are represented in movies,
how a code is rolled,
etc.
What is an engineer?
What is the difference
between a programmer,
a developer, an engineer?
Are they all the same?
I have always seen it this way.
The difference between a developer and an engineer
is the definition I will use.
A developer is someone who uses
libraries, libraries that are already written,
and an engineer is someone
who works on those things
and goes deeper into it,
who has a deeper knowledge
of the computer itself,
if he knows it,
and creates it.
I can also say that
there are some differences.
An engineer is someone who uses
the libraries he receives
and creates something out of them.
He doesn't have a deep knowledge.
I think there is a similar analogy
with music.
You know how to play an instrument,
you know how to take notes,
and you can also write music.
An engineer is someone
you can trust to find a solution
to your problem,
even if you don't know
how to solve it.
But on the basis of all the previous
experiences and deep knowledge,
you somehow come up with a solution
that is satisfactory.
I see that there is a result
that I could use,
but more in the context of
being able to come up with a solution
that is relatively optimal in this context.
But what is the difference
between a senior developer
and a senior engineer?
We used to say that there is a difference
between an assistant and a student,
that the assistant has already googled
everything that has been googled.
Maybe in this context.
If we look at the polls on your group
on Facebook,
do we really know the difference
between a junior and a senior mid?
These are some signs that
they are not exactly the same.
For example, one of the reasons
is that they are on Google.
If we compare them with other companies,
they are completely unrelated.
I think that you are nothing more than
an engineer.
You don't care about the names,
titles and signs.
I haven't gone so far as to say
that you are a full challenger,
but depending on the organization...
If we are going to talk about
the fact that it was for beginners,
now that we have laid out the concepts,
titles are important in a way
because when you go to a meeting
and talk to other people,
these titles help you understand
where you are in the organization
and what your role is.
For certain titles, you know where you are.
If you are a senior product manager,
you probably have a bigger role
than a junior product manager.
Again, it depends on the industry,
size and so on.
It depends on the context,
the company itself,
how you fall into it.
But let's take a step back.
We are talking about people
who write code.
Engineers and developers
write code.
On the other hand,
there are also IT people.
I don't know.
I don't like all IT people.
Why?
In recent years,
technology has eaten up companies
and transformed them.
Some companies know this,
others don't.
They try to implement
some digital processes in the company.
These are different people
and you can't just say IT.
A lot of people hide this.
Even in large companies
that are not primarily technological oriented.
It can be the same person
who tries to implement processes
and digital transformation.
We've been talking about it a lot in the last two years.
It can be relatively dead on paper
because we don't have enough staff.
What is changing?
If we look back 20-30 years,
the problems are changing very quickly.
You can still study,
but you go to high school.
You are a supporter of IT equipment
and you can also be a supporter
of IT software equipment.
If you look at it from a different perspective,
yes, sometimes they hide,
but it seems to me
that they hide quite often
because we are so old
and we don't know much about digital writing.
But someone who is starting today
and is 15 years old
can focus either on IT equipment
or on digital writing.
Or not.
I would say that
my experience is different.
We often say,
when you have a guest
that you don't know much about.
Digital writing is a part of the IT world.
Over time,
you learn a little bit about everything.
You can specialize in something
or you can see better in something.
It is also typical
when it comes to maintaining equipment.
You need to know a lot about the software
because sometimes you need to download
some software to see
if it is working properly.
When do you decide?
I would say
that it is best to try new things.
Over time,
there is also a key moment.
You come into an environment
where you have to offer
a hardware challenge.
You like it and you deal with it.
I would not say
that it is better or worse than others.
I think that everything is fine.
I am also a hardware engineer.
I agree with that.
In this context,
it is not that you choose,
but experience chooses you.
There is a project
that is so specific that you can say
that you are a high-value expert
and there are 5 of us in Slovenia.
Then there is another project
and you lost the previous knowledge
and you have to change it.
That is why it is so much better in something else.
Every project is so challenging.
I think that is the frustration
that makes us engineers.
You are born an engineer.
You are always frustrated
and you want to solve things.
No one said that programming,
development of hardware,
development of hardware is a big gift.
It is black magic.
We do not understand how it works.
It is very complicated
and we are very frustrated,
and we do not want to experience it.
It is very esoteric.
I think that
you will see that
when you are recruiting.
When you are looking for talent,
when you are looking for people
with whom you want to work,
how do you recognize
if persistence is something
that can be achieved,
if you have to be highly motivated.
Can you learn that?
Can you learn to be persistent?
Can you learn how to pick apples
when you go to eat together?
Part of that is the environment.
If you are in an environment
where you can pick apples,
I think that everything comes
from personal motivation.
If you have knowledge,
no problem.
If you have enough motivation,
you will achieve it.
Everything comes from personal motivation
and that is a big challenge.
Maybe you are born as an engineer
and you have it implicitly in you
that you want to overcome that frustration.
It is similar to going to the gym
or fitness.
You decide that you will lose weight
because you have 50 kilos too much.
That is why you need a lot of motivation
and everything else comes with time.
Is your metabolism like that or not?
Those are things that affect you.
There are some coefficients in that path.
If you have motivation,
you can achieve anything.
It is the same for all potential
future programmers and juniors.
If you have a problem,
if you use one week instead of one hour,
it becomes easier for you.
Much better.
Most of my generation doesn't program anymore.
I was in the business
and I am back now.
I can program now.
I feel rewarded with it.
I really enjoy it.
You mentioned how to recognize
who is what.
You talk to a person about a problem
and then you see how he deals with it.
That is what it is about.
Do you have a person in your class
who talks about problems
or is it a special search
to find the answer to a complex question?
I can ask you one more question.
I hope we all agree.
It is about solving problems.
Difficult problems.
You will solve them difficultly.
There is a lot of work involved.
Do you ask questions?
There is a lot of trial and error.
Let's go back to music.
How do you start improvising in music?
That is a typical problem.
There are people who graduated from an academy
who are great musicians
and know how to create music.
The qualitative leap in the field
of improvising is one thing
that you have to try.
On the other hand,
everything you have done
in the past
always takes away the influence
of previous musicians.
You have already learned a lot
and now you are correcting it.
Every project has to be different.
If you don't do projects
that are too simple,
you have reached the optimum
and nothing has changed in your life.
You have to have another project like that.
Every project has to be so complex
that in the end you see that you grow from it.
Do you have to finish them?
Unfinished projects are an experience.
When you realize that you have a lot of unfinished projects,
you have to ask yourself why they are unfinished.
What does solving problems mean
in everyday life?
How do you solve them?
What kind of problems do you solve
as a programmer and how do you solve them?
What kind of problems do you get
and how do you solve them?
What does this fight look like every day?
Where do you get problems?
You have enough problems in your life.
If you start with some automation,
if you are preparing to do something repetitive,
you can get to it quickly.
I have a problem that I would like to solve
in a programmer way.
You can solve it on a blackboard.
It is great that you can solve it on a blackboard
and it is great that you can talk to other people
who are not necessarily seniors.
Sometimes you just have to put things out of yourself
in a way that you can easily explain
what you are solving.
Sometimes you have to ask yourself if you are not solving
something that is a part of the solution
that you don't know how to solve.
A lot of people come to me and say
that they have a problem with a framework.
You can tell them that their problem is a third one.
They are explaining a part of the solution.
You can always take that step back.
A blackboard is great because you can take that step
back in a physical form.
A while ago I got a question from a student
why do we have to program on paper?
Why do we have to write code on paper?
As far as I can see,
you just try to explain what the problem is
when you write something on paper
or on a blackboard.
Do I really understand what the problem is?
Is it clear to me what I have to do?
Do I need more information?
What is it that I don't know?
What is it that I know?
What are the things that I have to get rid of?
What are the limits?
I would like to start talking about drafts in the problem.
As I said, there are hundreds of problems.
A good way is to use tools.
For example, if you play video games,
today you have different tools,
studio for making plugins,
or if you create music,
you will try to change some settings,
or find some scripts.
Wherever you use a software,
you try to understand it,
then you try to break it,
or you try to prepare how it works,
or you try to automate it,
or you try to make an app for the phone,
or an app for VR,
and then you go back.
As an engineer, you try to find problems,
and you try to solve them yourself.
Or on YouTube.
If we talk about day-to-day,
usually companies look for programmers,
that's why people come to the company,
and usually, if they are big companies,
if they are juniors,
usually they are part of a team,
usually they are more experienced people,
who define some tasks,
and then it depends on the company.
If you work in a satellite company,
you will probably work on satellites.
As a data scientist,
what problems do you solve every day,
and how do you solve them?
I always deal with the problem
that I have too little data.
I always want to have more,
but I don't have to solve that problem.
There are problems that we solve,
and from somewhere,
our art begins.
We call it constraints.
If you want to write poetry,
it's easier to write prose,
because you don't have a structure,
but if you want to write poetry,
you need to have a structure,
and you have to, and so on.
The most interesting thing is that
in the end, prose can be more pronounced.
This part of my structure,
where I am limited,
means that I have too little data.
Let's start with that.
Let's try to take too little data,
and put it back together
on the basis of some models,
as it seems to us.
What are the processes
that generate too little data?
What is the most likely thing
to happen in the future?
Then we can make some business decisions.
Let's transfer some money from some accounts
to some other accounts.
OK, great.
This connection with non-problematic,
real life,
what is the result of such work?
Let's go back in history a bit.
I will ask you again.
Who were the first programmers?
How did they program?
How did it start?
I believe it didn't start on Windows 95.
What was the beginning like?
How did it start?
I first came across these personal computers.
No, they weren't personal.
They weren't computers.
They were Commodores and Spectrums.
In 1983-1984,
my colleagues started getting
Spectrums,
and then they started playing games.
I saw them a couple of times,
and they asked me at home,
if I was interested,
and I told them that I wasn't.
My mother was working on some statistics,
and they had a programming course.
My mother came home
with a basic script,
translated into Slovenian,
with 16 photocopies.
I started getting lessons,
and I saw that it was possible to program.
I could say something to a computer,
and it would do something for me.
I was fascinated by it.
When I went to a party with my family,
if I had a computer,
I would plug it into the TV,
and I would play a game.
That was my beginning.
It was a basic,
where you wrote 10,
print Peter, and 20 go to 10,
and then print Peter was printed
across the screen.
Those were the beginnings.
Then there was the 8th grade.
I think it was the 3rd or 4th grade.
We got our first teacher at school,
with a partner,
and that's how I met Pascal.
Then I was at Pascal for many years.
Partners are not the same as computers.
You should say that for younger listeners.
Partners are not partners,
in the context of cooperation.
What about you?
The first computer I got,
when I was younger,
was a 286.
It didn't even have a black and white screen.
It had an orange screen.
That was my first contact.
There were a lot of players,
and I played a lot of games.
That was my first experience.
Later on, I worked with Pascal.
Borland, Toru, Pascal...
There are a lot of people
who know what's going on.
I worked with them.
Before that, I worked a lot
on the Internet.
I worked on the first page
of Internet Explorer 4.
Then I started learning HTML,
from some monitors.
I spent my whole career
on the Internet.
The more the Internet developed,
the more I understood the platform.
I worked a lot with it.
At the beginning of my career,
I worked a lot with Flash.
Some of you may know it.
It was a tool
where you had a timeline
with a video editor,
and you could make animations.
You said, at this point,
the square will be here,
and when the time comes,
it will be here.
It was visual,
and you could make animations.
It was interesting,
because you could click,
and the editor opened,
and you could write code inside.
It surprised me.
When I came to high school,
I expected to work on something more modern,
so I started working with Pascal.
I had a pain in my back,
because I knew a bit about C,
so I could work with Pascal.
I learned algorithms in high school
with Borland Pascal.
I'm a bit younger,
but I'm obsessed with old computers,
so I collect old computers.
Old computers...
It's hard to explain,
maybe harder than drugs in your family.
Why do you collect old stuff?
I started with 386,
Windows 13,
then Windows 95 and 98.
I started programming in Logo.
It's a programming language
where you go through a two-dimensional envelope
and solve various things.
I think it was probably the best thing in the world
in terms of spatial representation.
First of all, it's phenomenally simple.
You can get a lot of web pages
that allow a web interpreter for Logo.
I recommend it.
I tried it on my children.
And it turns out that they love it.
They solve it and enjoy it.
Because the visual component
makes it easier for people.
Imagine a 5-year-old
solving a 90-degree cube.
You don't have to explain it to him.
He has the experience of trying to make a star or a square.
Why not go in the same direction?
Andrei Bitenc,
from ZRI,
who also had children in elementary school.
Then relatively quickly,
in middle school, there were web pages.
Back then, there were front pages.
Most people probably don't remember that anymore.
Then there were Dreamweavers,
a tool for working on the front page.
It wasn't one-sided anymore.
Maybe there were some other big corporations.
We also started with Android relatively quickly.
There were 1.2, 1.5, 1.6 versions.
We wrote tutorials with a colleague
on how to program.
There was also Eclipse,
which is no longer a favorite environment
for publishing.
Back then, there was everything.
Those were simple times
when you didn't have to install pip,
but you could install it on 150 packages
so that you could make Hello World.
Nice, simple times.
I started with Windows 98.
I'm not a programmer,
but that was the first Windows I used.
Back then, if you wanted to make something,
you got either a CD or a floppy disk.
I still remember floppy disks.
I know why a floppy disk is a safe icon.
You could also browse the Internet.
It was much harder because you had to connect
over the phone.
But if you wanted to get something on your computer,
you could install it.
What was the development like back then?
Who was doing what with some random applications?
Why were they able to package it that way?
What was the difference between
some random application
and a connected application?
The reason was very simple.
Back then, there was no Internet.
When it appeared,
you had to browse the Internet
and click on a modem on your phone.
That's why you could have all the applications
on your computer.
It was similar to what you have on your phone today.
If you had an Android phone
without a data link,
you could only use the games
or applications you have on your phone.
I think that the analogy
with the telephone applications
is quite good now.
Who was writing
those random applications?
How were the engineers divided?
What were they writing?
Probably because Windows 98
was a different kind of elementary school.
I wouldn't be able to say for sure.
Maybe the difference was that
the younger generation felt
through the gaming console.
The difference was that when you did it,
you wrote it down on a piece of paper
and sent it somewhere.
There was no room for the next update.
We would fix what we forgot
and we didn't do it well.
I think that the level of production
was higher because the price
of changing something like that
was higher than it is now.
We can publish an application
and move fast and break things.
We prepare the next week to fix something
and then we can fix everything.
It was especially difficult
because of the connectivity,
data transfer and media,
which were much slower and smaller.
People got used to one floppy disk,
1.44 megabytes.
It's a 16-bit picture from an iPhone
and you can save it in that context.
That floppy disk was very slow.
You could only have two floppy disks
because there was a whole operating system
on one floppy disk.
You could use it on the same floppy disk
and get something out of it.
For example, help files for Windows 95
could be used on a 30 megabyte floppy disk
if you really tried hard.
Otherwise, it was 150 megabytes.
It was so expensive
that we had to work harder
because of the applications we created.
We had to test them
because we felt like we were
doing it all over again.
Now we know what testing looks like.
The industry has some cycles
that are being repeated.
Let's talk about writing applications
and programming.
Was there a difference between
back-end and front-end software?
The biggest difference is probably
that we're going back to those times.
I hope I won't have to say too much.
We talked about Kadr in desktop applications.
I have AutoCAD in my head
for constructing scripts.
It was an app that worked
on a computer without any connection
to other computers.
You set it up as we talked
and drew a script on it.
You drew it with a plotter
or you pressed it or whatever.
The script was then used.
There were no physical changes
but there were media that were used.
Kadr then worked with networks.
Those terminals were called mainframes.
Those were those huge computers
with their own operating systems
that were attached.
When the computers started to connect
you had that connection
to the terminal.
What those terminals were like
is another story.
But the concept of a plotter
and then you connect to it
with your own computers
is still present today.
We still see it but we don't talk
about those mainframes.
I think those two softwares
still exist.
A lot of theories and statements
still come from those.
Terminals are like that,
servers are like that.
These things come from it.
Basically, this software is good
to solve a problem.
But it's not like those programs
or modern systems
where programs work together.
That's the thing.
What did a back-end engineer do?
What did a front-end engineer do?
Could there have been another engineer?
I would say one thing
that would be different
is that programs were smaller
than they are now.
Now you work with big teams.
I remember when we wrote
the first Windows desktop applications.
There was a program environment
very popular called Delphi.
The middle Pascal.
Pascal was given an add-on
for an object programming.
Then some graphic designers
started working on it.
Delphi was one of the most ingenious
programming tools at the time.
What was interesting
was that Delphi was written
by 3 or 4 programmers
in a big company called Borland.
That was a product
that the company probably lived off
for another 10 years.
The gentleman who invented Delphi
went on to work with Microsoft
and then wrote C Sharp
and TypeScript and so on.
Andres Heisberg.
What was interesting here
was that 4 people did it.
They probably split the work,
but most of them did everything.
Software was also typical at the time.
In Slovenia, there was a typical
software company called One Man Band
and this man did everything
from the calculations to the database
to the users and so on.
With all this software,
especially if it's bigger,
you have people who are architects
and their job is to take care
of where certain components are,
how they will grow,
how they will change.
Then the architects decide
how the application will be split.
Will we need a back-end developer
or a front-end developer
or will it be one person
who will do everything?
If we look at Wikipedia
and the big eggs in the programs
of the same region,
Windows 95, Windows 98,
they weren't that big a team.
At the end of that team,
there were a few people
who knew better or worse abilities
of others and managed to coordinate them.
Even if we look at the descriptions
of those people in the 30s,
they don't have all the beautiful
descriptions of samurais and everything
that we have now.
On the other hand,
we probably have 500 people
in the Microsoft team
who deal with the search bar
and a lot of things were put
more ad hoc than they are now.
On the other hand,
we will return to the fact
that some things are not as important
as others.
There is a stereotype
that front-end is easy,
back-end is hard,
but I don't think so,
because you can do it in any way.
Back-end was a real engineering.
I can try.
In this context,
the first thing is that
front-end is not for everyone.
I have a few colleagues
who are phenomenal back-enders,
maybe it's connected
to some other property,
maybe talent for art
or visual composition.
On the front-end,
if you break things,
they are broken in a way
that doesn't affect the whole structure.
But I still think that at some point,
people who have 30 years of experience
will see the difference
between what is more appealing
and what is more talented.
I wouldn't say that front-end is easier
or harder.
Everyone should combine.
I wouldn't say that back-end is harder,
because it can be at the end
very similar to front-end.
You don't have to imagine
big architectural systems
at every moment.
I wouldn't say that front-end
is harder or harder.
Maybe it's more appealing
to some people,
but not to others.
I've been working on front-end
for many years now.
In front-end,
things are very visual.
When you do something there,
you can see what you've done.
You can adjust your time very quickly.
You can't hide.
You can see the consequences.
When the functionality
of a product goes out,
it will be very fast.
You will be the one who will say
that you've done your job
and now it's over.
People don't see the back-end.
and sometimes it's even harder to adjust what you're doing in the back if it's not visible.
And some people enjoy the default system, as he said,
but the front end does not exist without the back end, and vice versa.
These things have to be connected, and if the back end doesn't work,
you can have a very nice make-up and nothing will work.
So we have to take these things into some kind of synergy.
Both things are tribal.
Especially in the last few years, I think that these specializations have created
that these things are more diverse.
I think that in the past we had a term called web developer,
and it meant that you did everything.
Today, perhaps, it's a bit more physical, but for beginners,
I think it's always good to understand the universe,
to understand what's in the back and what's in the front.
Because you won't be able to communicate with people
if you don't understand both sides.
Everything is in some basics.
But maybe it also stems from the fact that,
for example, if we take a typical software from 20 years ago,
you drive it to some public back end,
and in the front you have HTML, CSS and JavaScript.
We are already working in technology.
But it also stems from the fact that you are closer to the current technology.
You can be a very good public developer,
and in short, a very good JavaScript and HTML and CSS developer.
Yes, probably.
But I would also say that something is the same as your love,
your passion, something is the same as what you did
to get through that frustration and get to the end.
From the point of view of the back end,
what Otto wanted to say,
the conversation of a system engineer.
When everything works, we don't know why they pay you,
and when something doesn't work, you are still guilty.
Because it doesn't work, so we could.
Yes, the back end can be more tricky from that point of view.
But all in all, I remember from those times,
now we will change one programming language,
which will hurt a lot, PHP.
From those times when we wrote that part in PHP,
when we came to the first MWCs,
what was it, Symfony, PHP Cake, Zend, and so on.
Yes, we did something in CSS,
but we didn't deal with the design in that way.
On the other hand, we have in all categories,
we have to look at which ones will suit each other,
and we now have phenomenal designers
who are very focused in the technological aspect,
in the web, in the specifics of it.
We have designers who will work on leaflets and pamphlets
but they will never touch the web.
And if you compare both outputs,
one is very good for something,
and it's great as a designer for that package,
for that leaflet, for that CGP, in that way.
The other is phenomenal for implementing it on the website.
I think it's the same with programmers.
We are not all good for everything.
We can be good, quite good,
because of a project, let's say.
But we don't have to be great in the sense
that we will use our talent for everything.
I would like to add something.
As a beginner, it's not so...
It's not so...
I call myself a backend developer,
I call myself a frontend developer.
Your job...
It's better to try as much as you can at the beginning,
to play as much as you can.
We talked about frontend and backend.
You also have mobile,
you also have games,
you also have electronic programming.
Try as much as you can,
and you will hear,
oh, I can make an interface,
and it's great.
Maybe you can do it later.
We have already mentioned the web.
Before, we were talking about web applications.
How did the web change that?
And what exactly do you program in the browser?
Because web applications work differently
than if you are only in the browser.
The web has brought with it
such an interesting concept,
especially since it came from
the classical static split pages.
The first split pages were created by the server.
It was a static HTML,
and then it was tampered with,
and when something went wrong,
it went back to the server.
Then, at one point, we started working
with single-page dynamic applications.
And what has changed?
Back then, software was also written on the frontend.
And we started with very primitive tools,
such as jQuery and so on.
These were then huge repositories
of unmanageable spaghetti codes.
And what web development has brought with it,
is the fact that it was decoupled
from the browser,
from the business logic on the backend,
and from the user logic on the frontend.
And these two could communicate
in a nice and elegant way.
The second thing is that
in the frontend environment,
there was a problem.
The classical way of compiling applications
and learning functionality,
so that when something clicked,
something happened.
When it was stopped with jQuery
and the classic JavaScript tool,
they simply stopped together,
and then they were looking for better solutions
to solve these problems,
how to structure these frontend applications.
And the solutions that appeared,
and are still appearing,
were very beautiful.
And this way of thinking,
the frontend,
I think, works in its own way.
In many ways, the frontend is the one
that pulls the computer industry forward
with new ideas and concepts.
And then these concepts
settle on the backend.
Take V8 and make a runtime environment
for JavaScript,
and then you go to Node,
where you can write JavaScript
on the frontend and the backend.
Has this changed people's day-to-day jobs?
If I look at Twitter,
they started adding abstraction levels.
There was also a Mootool project.
A drag-and-drop operation
with 2,000 types of code.
At some point,
we created one type of code in jQuery,
and if we look back at jQuery now,
we say, what have I done?
I had such huge functions written
that something small happened.
These levels of abstraction
started to be added,
and how to integrate all of this
is problematic.
I work in the operating system,
and I always say that 99% of the questions
about this subject are answers from legacy.
Why do we call a terminal a terminal?
Why do we use an icon?
And so on.
We are so old now
that we know why this is so.
Some things are phenomenally illogical
for a beginner.
Sometimes you have the feeling
that you can turn everything off
and start writing anew.
It's stupid.
A bunch of stories show
that Johnny did something on Tuesday
and said, this is it.
Let's look at bash.
This thing is totally broken.
Before Microsoft said,
let's do a few more,
and all the names were shown
to be Japanese.
They have at least 15 characters.
But these levels of abstraction
maybe scare us a bit,
even us old people,
because there are so many of them.
You have a stack on the front end,
and a stack on the back end.
This is running in some
virtualization environments
that have their own stack.
In the past, we installed LAMP
in Apache.
We put it in the folder
and it worked.
And that was it.
Do you really have to know everything
to be able to do it?
No, but it's a huge advantage
for a beginner to be able
to do so many things.
Why can't you just install
150 lines to write Hello World?
In Pascal, we added a diskette
that ran the whole system
together with the text editor.
And that was it.
A lot of diskettes and editors
ran from the compiled program.
And that was it.
I think it's a huge advantage
for all of us in the industry.
On the other hand,
we have to ask ourselves
how many people,
with all their signs,
actually know these things.
Probably more or less.
Those who know
are already very close to retirement.
And this knowledge,
this transfer of knowledge,
we have to give a certain gift
and ask ourselves
if it's enough
if we learn everything now,
whether we are developers
and use this book,
and that book,
and another book,
do we want people to realize
that such books are capable
of self-development
and are capable of completing
this never-ending stack.
The last step of this
is the NoCode platform.
You don't even use
a mobile app anymore.
If we talk about NoCode
and serverless,
why companies
are adopting
serverless and NoCode tools
is exactly because of this.
Now you have to realize
that you don't care
about these things anymore.
The boss is happy,
the company is happy,
I'm crying, I hope.
Every level of abstraction
that we add
has a set of things
at the very beginning.
But the level of abstraction
that we add doesn't mean
that it automatically reduces
the complexity of the bottom.
It just removes it
or hides it a little.
Even if we were historically
like Peter said,
writing Go To,
or even Assemble,
it would be even more brutal.
Now we've made levels, levels, levels,
levels, levels, levels,
and now NoCode will
pull it down
year after year,
because you don't program anything anymore.
But Assemble still works.
You can still find a job
to work with Assemble.
And all these stacks are jobs.
I would add
that we are working
on these abstractions.
Sometimes we even find them.
A nice example is
Frontend,
where they are using
an architecture
called React,
State Management,
which is already called
Redux.
Redux is an abstraction
that was invented in another
programming language called Elm.
And then they saw it in Elm
and said,
maybe we could
use a similar concept
in JavaScript.
But it's a little difficult,
because JavaScript is
a different language,
and these things are not
one-to-one mapped.
This original Elm,
or something like that,
a rare company
implemented a complete Redux
that was presented
from Elm
in JavaScript.
Again, I can't imagine
why something is needed,
and they said,
we won't do that.
But then it turns out
that when you start
assembling together,
more complex things
come together than
Lego bricks.
And here is the problem
that we have
so many abstractions
in the computer.
We would like
to express ourselves
on a higher
abstract level.
I wouldn't like to
do everything myself,
but since we used abstractions
that were poorly translated
into another programming language,
we need to know
what's going on down there.
It's not easy.
Let's get back to
why you need to program on paper.
Because it increases
your internal buffer.
Why do you need to understand
or burn a couple of LEDs
in an assembly on a development board?
Why do you need to know
how UART works?
There are a lot of things
that may seem banal,
but on the other hand,
it gives us the depth
where we can understand
or develop things more easily.
A typical example
when we did the first Android apps.
You need a state machine
for messaging,
or if we look at what happens
when you turn off the application
and then turn it on,
there are a lot of states
in the modern frameworks.
One colleague,
who is a great Flutter programmer
from Alpha,
has as much experience as Flutter,
but not as much
as the people
who write their stories.
They have more experience
than the programming language
in the city.
One time,
when we were talking,
he said,
why would you write an app
if you couldn't write an app?
One guy came and said,
we know how to do it in C,
for Android.
You see,
this level,
maybe 10 years of difference
between us,
gives me something very familiar
and state-of-the-art
in my perception
of what is Flutter capable of.
Understanding how these state machines
interact with each other.
If you don't want to
hit anything,
you get into trouble
where you reach your optimum
and you say,
I did this,
and I'll do it again.
You quickly get to the point
where you start
implicitly learning these things.
Which is great,
because there is
a hidden dark web,
hidden in the projects.
We are already talking a lot.
We are getting close
to the end,
so I will stop
and ask specifically.
Today, someone who is going
on this path,
where does it start?
In which programming language?
Is it mobile development?
Is it splat development?
Will it be you?
Where does it start?
Probably Python,
and JavaScript.
I think that today
most of the computational paths
start with Python.
I think it's both
a great language for learning.
Where does it start?
On the one hand,
you find a problem
that you would like to solve.
On the other hand,
I don't know,
these complex portals with
some kind of requirements.
I think that you can
learn a lot from them.
The question is
whether
these requirements
are presented
in the right way.
If they are presented in the right way,
then
the complexity
gradually decreases.
Sometimes you start
solving two tasks,
and the third one is like that.
In the last year,
my expectations
have increased.
The same with Python.
I solved two or three tasks,
but the fourth one
seemed too easy for me.
I really took a lot of time
to figure out
what programming is for.
Where do you start?
At the faculty?
At the university program,
we start with Java and C.
we start with Java and Python.
It's always a debate
whether I need to know C or not.
Java has references,
which is basically pointer to pointer.
If you know what a pointer is,
I wouldn't say for a beginner
to start with C.
I can say that
you can start with C.
Come for free.
What can the faculty give you?
It can't give you all the knowledge
we have available
on mobile devices and computers.
There are people
who can ask you in a very
stupid way,
I don't need to be an expert,
I don't need to know what to google,
I don't need to know which tutorial
to find on the internet.
There are people who will
give you all the knowledge.
Free has the beauty
of making a relatively open
room for other faculties.
You can come to any laboratory
and ask for a cup of coffee.
You don't have to worry
that it's someone
who has a doctorate
and isn't a doctorate
or is a professor.
You can come to any of them
and say that you have a problem
and they help you solve it.
Then you get people
who will welcome you
and say that they have solved
a very complex problem.
If I may ask you,
why do I go to free
rather than to math
or physics?
After all, I see people
who come from different
Norwegian faculties
in programming.
That's a good question.
From this point of view,
two students from all
Norwegian technical faculties
could be relatively the same.
The difference is
in the applicability.
Probably in math and physics
students deal with different
problems than we do.
We will go to the application
for a specific field
and specific problems.
The theoretical part
will probably be more powerful
there.
I am on a relatively high level
and you can find people
everywhere
where you can come to them
and say that you have a problem
or they will help you
solve it.
That's the beauty of FACS.
Nowadays, when we realized
that everyone can work
online and watch lectures,
personal contact is the only
thing the faculty can give you
if you don't need all the knowledge.
I don't need to do as good
a lecture as someone on Coursera
who did one lecture in three months.
What we can give you is
that you come to me, we work
together on some problems,
we work together on complex tasks
and I can help you and guide you.
That's the only added value
of FACS.
You have all the other things
on the internet.
You can sit down and discuss
all the knowledge through YouTube
or through FACS.
Most of us are mortals
and we need someone who has
been through a lot
to help us along the way.
That's why.
Jesus, you are so well-founded.
When are you going to sign up?
No, you sold well.
I am also a high school teacher
for those who have to go to high school.
You can tell them the same.
The thing is
that most people
who work in this industry
really have a passion
for technology.
They like to talk about it.
They like to help.
Most of the people
will want to help you.
Don't be afraid to ask.
I know it's hard to ask.
I know that sometimes
it's natural to ask.
people will help you
in a special way.
The world is so connected
that you really have
a lot of communities
for everything.
Maybe it's English
and you learn English smartly.
But you also have a community
in Slovenia.
You have a Python meetup,
an ARM meetup,
a JavaScript meetup.
You have events
with people who already know it.
That's a great way
to do it.
When it comes to technology,
try as many
different things as you can.
Then say
I will learn one thing well,
whatever it is,
to go through
one language from start to finish.
Whether it's Java
or C++.
Finish the book
so you can learn
some things.
When you switch languages,
you have to learn
the difference
or the specifics.
A lot of
basic algorithms
are transferable.
A lot of knowledge is transferable.
When we talk about abstractions,
a lot of abstractions are transferable.
You have to go through
the book
from start to finish.
I would recommend
a lot of side projects.
A lot of side projects.
What are side projects?
We can ask the guests.
If you can,
you can ask the last question.
No, I think
in 15 minutes
the last one
will be over.
Great,
thank you for doing this.
What would you like, Peter,
for a junior to bring with him
when he joins your team?
What would he or she
already know?
What can they learn?
My team is very specific
because we work on data science.
Data science
is a national
endeavor.
It's a medical space.
Data science is like the next big thing, and everyone wanted to be a data scientist,
but that's not true.
In order to be a good data scientist, you need to be very good at programming,
you need to be very good at math, especially in statistics,
you often get a certificate in mathematics, you don't have to, right?
Well, I think there was a third one, but I don't remember.
There was a third one.
Blackmagic will do it.
And now people are introducing themselves,
I know how to write in those Pandas, Python notebooks, some graphs,
and now I will be a data scientist.
So, I think that in my field, people can use music, but they don't.
I think people can use statistics and probability,
and I think that's a very valuable thing,
and I think that's another thing you would want to program.
It has the capacity, and the desire to solve problems.
So, maybe I, if I have to answer,
who would I like to have in my team?
I have 30 years of experience.
On the other hand, we have some young people,
and it's fascinating how they have the right approach,
it's interesting, it's okay to solve this problem,
but what else can I do?
Mateo, at the beginning we didn't say that you are not only a teacher,
but you also work a lot with companies,
so you probably have a look at what Fax gives to someone,
and what Fax doesn't prepare people who join.
Yes, because of that, who would I like to have in my team?
Highly motivated people.
That's it, primarily.
Everything else, we will get to that, no problem,
we will get to that, you will know, you will have a certain level.
And I think, because of cooperation with the economy,
I would say that what Fax gives you,
is that sometimes you have to believe that we know why it's good,
that you know the jigsaw,
even if you don't know at the moment why it's good.
But if you come to Peter in five years,
you would think that these are simple problems,
that you can solve them.
Depending on the specific frame,
or orientation in a specific direction or topic,
people need motivation.
When people come motivated,
yes, everyone has a little more or less listening,
and of course we all want the most listening,
but if people don't have motivation,
then they usually don't give you a fax,
and they usually know that in the quality of the projects,
the way of cooperation, freelancing or employment.
Then this is somehow taken away in other aspects.
Rarely, a person would say that he doesn't need a fax,
because it's good.
Because these are the people who made a fax for Zravan,
who did it, because it wasn't hard for them.
Some of you had tears,
some of you were my classmates,
when I was a graduate,
and I can say that these are phenomenal people,
who would say that you don't need a fax.
But sometimes you have to go through a very difficult topic,
which is very challenging for you,
because your partner,
who went through a similar topic in three years,
says that if he was able to go through it,
then he would be able to finish the project.
I can also say that we had some topics
that were shared with me.
Why would I need it?
For example, we had a lecture
on computer technology,
which was taught by Professor Sretkar.
I said that your older colleagues
will tell you that it's physics 2,
but if you look at computers,
what is different from physics?
Then you start to put electrons
into infinite potential holes.
Sometimes 10 to the minus 34.
We didn't even know what it had to do
with our forces on the slope.
That's physics, of course.
You know it from high school.
But 10-15 years later,
we're working on a scheme
of automatic elucidation of organic bonds.
Basically, we're trying to automate
the understanding of spectra,
on different spectra,
which have their own flaws,
which are maybe a bit blurred,
which are not all visible.
We're trying to use all this knowledge
from this subject to understand
what they're trying to explain
to us through some tables
that have been calculated in the last 100 years.
In the meantime, you have to have
a bit of faith that your boss,
or whoever he is, knows
that there's a good reason
why this moment doesn't seem
so important to you.
Because in five years,
this probability and statistics
will be very important
for your understanding
of our problems on our farm.
No, that's too long.
No, no, it's cool.
I always have an answer.
The most valuable part,
the most valuable employee,
the most valuable colleague
with whom I work,
and we can all talk about this
in technology later,
but what does it mean
that he has it?
If someone,
you said motivated,
means that he will find
this energy,
that he will learn
what he doesn't know yet,
that if he,
if we go to the very beginning
of our conversation,
that if he comes to the problem
that he will grind,
that he will learn,
that he will research,
that he will look,
that he will grow,
that he will shoot,
whatever.
That desire,
it can be overcome,
but that's what you need
in the end.
If you want,
you have different teams,
but for me,
the most important thing
is motivation.
You can try this
through CV,
through references,
through experience,
through 5 projects,
whatever,
but I always looked for
this interest,
this desire.
Such people will learn.
You can't buy it.
From this recruiting,
when you get
the first game server I made
when I was 12 years old,
I put it in the room
and there were a million users
when I was 12 years old.
This real
motivation.
At the same time,
this real motivation.
It probably takes a long time.
Maybe it looks like
someone who comes to FACS
without actually
trying.
Again, it's about motivation.
Everything else comes with time.
But the motivation
and loyalty,
that you are there.
These are two components
of a person
that are the most important.
Because of this,
this person will be able
to finish the project
because he will be there
or he doesn't have the motivation
for a long time or
for three years.
You have to be satisfied
in a way that
you set yourself
some goals.
Some ambitious goals.
You sometimes say
I will become the best
back-end developer.
It's better to say
I will do this project
and you do it.
You get some satisfaction from it
and you do the next project.
It's much better
if you set yourself
a long-term
and unrealistic goal
and then you push it.
It's better to cut
the path to some side projects
and then you get
the feedback loop
that you did something good
and you develop it
habitually.
Habitually.
That was
a really great
summary of what
I'm learning.
Mata, I would like to ask
one more summary
for people
who come to this industry.
I would really
rely on what he said.
A big part
of the IT industry
is
this.
Maybe this is also
a part of engineering.
How to
solve
a problem
in a way
that
every problem
is a whole
that can be
disassembled and tested
and something starts again.
These parts
are
equally
big.
You can do one or two a day.
My experience
and what I remember
from my colleagues
30 years ago
when we learned to program
and more.
Even now, I think
it's true.
You imagine something
that is too complex,
and then you don't know
where to start.
We start short
and see that
what we put together
doesn't come.
How to build
like a cake.
First a layer of
dough, then a cream,
then a little more dough.
I agree with both.
In the end,
we all know
XKCD as a funny
video game that comes out
three times a week.
There is a good picture
of what is the most effective.
800 hours of lectures,
400 hours of homework,
or one weekend of playing with a ball.
Maybe it's so hard
to play
that the kids
won't know what a ball is.
They don't need to know.
Just try it.
When you were a kid,
you used to disassemble a computer.
You were crazy about it,
but you wanted to know
what's inside.
Just the motivation
is all you need.
I have nothing more to add.
Great, isn't it?
I don't know.
I can only say
thank you a lot.
No, you can thank yourself.
I would just say
to share this episode
with your colleagues
who may be trying
in this direction.
Give us feedback
to see how far we are from the truth.
You decide.
Thank you,
Petr, and thank you,
Mateo, for taking the time.
I hope it wasn't too short.
Thank you, Oto, for letting me
host this podcast.
I hope it wasn't too short, either.
It wasn't.
I hope you enjoyed it.
Maybe I'll say it one more time.
Share, like,
get as many people
as possible.
Watch us
and listen to us.
If you need anything,
you can always contact us.
We'll put the links below.
Thank you for hosting.
Thank you, Sarah.
Thank you, good luck.