Hello, Erik, to a new episode of Ogrodje, especially about fairy tales.
These are our episodes that are short and effective and have a common theme.
I greet you once again in Ogrodje.
This episode is conceived as an episode where we will launch the Slovenia AI meetup,
where you will also be teaching today.
A few weeks ago, I followed your product SpyDelta on the Slovenian Developer Group.
I saw that you decided to work in the public sector.
That's right.
What's better than working in the public sector?
Introduce yourself and tell us who you are and what you do.
My name is Erik, I'm an electronics engineer.
I've been programming professionally for the last few years.
I've been working on SpyDelta for the last four months.
You've been developing it for four months?
That's right.
It's been a pleasure.
The title of your today's lecture, as well as your post, is
Product for Competitive Analysis.
Competitive Analysis.
Yes, Competitive Analysis is a Slovenian translation.
You published a link to ProductHunt.
It's a website where you list your products,
where people give rankings and look for the most innovative products.
I went to take a look at it, I saw some comments below,
and I said, OK, I have to try it.
Then I forgot about it, like everyone else.
Then we agreed that we would have this today's lecture.
I wrote to you and said, Erik, give me some demo access to try it out.
And you said, it's not even a UI.
It's just an email.
Your product at this stage, when we're talking now,
looks like you're going to the website,
you write your email in there,
and then you write a split page
in which you would like to do a competitive analysis of the news.
That's right.
Those are two inputs, and then you wait.
In a few minutes you get an email report.
I printed it out here.
It's a very impressive analysis of competition.
I don't have to say exactly what I put in there,
but it's a company I work for.
It's a Fortune 100 company.
I put it in there and it said,
the price went up in July,
the products were launched,
the products were sold,
they found some connections in the menu,
they saw I was a stockholder, they were very happy.
I was really surprised, like, wow, something is really happening here.
It's a one-pager, an A4 sheet,
and I was very surprised.
We started recording this conversation the day before,
I went to try it again, and it didn't work.
So I decided to go for the free tier.
For me, it's just one domain.
In the future, I plan to integrate Stripe with paid customers,
a kind of freemium model,
so I can monitor more different domains,
more different components.
Before we move on to the solution,
can you tell us how you came up with this problem?
Is it your personal experience, or is it something you're interested in?
With the previous company,
I tried a few existing tools,
and I realized they were either enterprise-grade,
like RCS, which I learned to use,
or technologically not optimal.
For example, they make screenshots and then try them on.
Then I thought, I can make a better product with AI in two weeks,
and send me only the useful stuff by e-mail.
For example, if you have a heavy video,
the product that's on the bottom of the screenshot
will send you an e-mail with a different frame on the video.
Oh, okay, okay.
It wasn't optimal.
When you published the blog post I mentioned,
a sketch was drawn.
I redrew it, so we have an architecture overview.
But tell us more about the components that make up this system.
I'm treating it like it's not a full secret,
but I'm interested if you can tell us
what the main components of this system are.
I published a sketch of the entire business stack,
both technically and for e-mail hosting.
I described the entire cost of this project.
For e-mail hosting, I used Zoho,
which is a platform for five users.
I wanted to show that you can start with $10 a month,
and you can already have a live project.
We have Cloudflare,
I think you used JavaScript Worker for e-mail hosting.
I'm not sure about that.
Yes, I used Cloudflare for back-end,
for sign-ups, and for landing pages.
Then I used the Hetzner server,
for e-mail scrapping and analysis.
Back-end is on Hetzner.
I saw that it's an instance,
it costs $5 or something like that.
Hetzner is what you can afford.
Then, in this flow,
the core AI logic is divided into
data collection,
and then translation of the results.
Am I interpreting this correctly?
Yes.
LLM is used on larger workflows.
How does it work?
First, the website is scrapped,
multiple times, you have different snapshots,
and then it looks at what has changed in the last month.
Then it looks at the markdown diff,
and then uses LLM for insight extraction.
M-section, on the front-end,
goes from the top of the page to the bottom of the page.
It's not as useful,
because the company launched a new feature,
or a new product, or the pricing changed.
One aspect of this is insight extraction
from the diff on the webpage.
Do you also look at the front-end right now?
I saw in your sketches that you also go to the web archive.
Yes.
I use this a lot.
If you sign up,
you will first look at the archive,
to get a summary of what it looked like a year ago.
You will directly get a report
on what has changed in the last 12 months
on the website.
You will look at the landing page,
what it used to look like,
and what it looks like now.
You will look at the links,
which links used to be from the landing page,
and which ones are now.
Based on this, you will decide
which sites you want to cover,
which know how to have business insight.
What you just described,
all the requirements,
is this expressed through a programmed flow?
Is this a prompt?
Or is it a combination?
It's a combination.
Because it seems to me that it's a complex logic.
Yes, it is.
First, you will try to get a landing page from 12 months ago,
then you will look at the changes,
for example, which are the new sites,
or pages, or deleted pages.
Then you will use LLM,
so that it will decide
which are the sites you want to look at.
You will look at them,
you will summarize them,
and then at the end you will do a summarization,
so that you will get a simple report
in an A4 format,
10 bullet points,
but the most important things that have changed.
Excellent.
When you send an email,
I saw that in the email footer,
it also connects to,
how do you say,
a prompt that was used to generate an email.
Yes, a full prompt.
Yes, a full prompt,
and you click on it,
and then it will write to you,
what was the prompt with which the email was sent,
that you see it done.
That seemed like a very technical detail to me,
but it was like,
oh wow, ok,
that was definitely processed.
This is now the prompt engineering,
how to make the best system prompt,
so that you get the email only from the user,
and now,
do I have the best system prompt or not?
Maybe someone will write a better one,
and then maybe they will say,
hey, maybe I should use this,
or I should use this,
to get a better report at the end.
Plus, add some additional information
that you can see.
With this summarization step,
now again,
I will say again,
I know it's hard for you to imagine,
if you listen to us visually,
as a podcast,
then I will put a link to it below,
so that people can see this sketch.
It's a bit dramatic,
if possible.
But,
this last step,
summarization,
you have it written there,
that you have 4GPT-4O,
and,
what is it,
what did you write?
Gemini.
Gemini, yeah.
So,
do you try both at the same time,
or do they complement each other,
or what's the difference?
It depends on the workflow.
So,
only for summarization,
I use one,
but for example,
if you have a summarization
from one side,
then I use another,
because maybe you don't need
such good logic.
Now,
in fact,
in the last iteration,
I use one,
maybe something better,
maybe not,
for the final summarization.
But,
if you only get,
after I scrape a page,
I only get two states,
in which this page goes,
then I can also use 4O,
or 4O mini.
OK.
And,
what did you use now?
So,
there's LangChain,
and LamaIndex,
which are some frameworks
that make the flow easier,
right?
Do you use any of those,
or is it even better?
No,
not really.
For my specific use case,
it wasn't that relevant,
so I didn't use any of those.
None of those, OK.
Then it's completely simple for me.
I'm sorry,
I have a bigger question.
No,
here,
there's another component,
which is also in the name,
it's called BrowserUse.
It's a component,
which was developed
by a Slovenian-Swiss combo,
from which you also,
on Y Combinator,
made,
I think,
$17 million in investments.
So, Gregor,
if you're listening,
I hope you're listening,
OK,
we're also listening.
So,
I see that you also use
this BrowserUse.
Now,
I'd like you to tell us,
in your own words,
what is this BrowserUse,
because I see that it's always
more important for products
like yours.
So, please,
tell us what BrowserUse is.
It's a tool,
a platform,
which helps you
create a web agent.
And it's specifically used
as a fallback option,
how to get,
how to get from a domain,
how to get to
which are open,
so to speak,
open positions.
Jobs that are currently
being offered.
First of all,
I'm just trying,
if there's a domain
slash careers,
if it's already there,
but sometimes they have
open positions,
for example,
on About Us.
So,
first of all,
I'm trying,
if there's something like that,
if not,
then I use BrowserUse
to, in fact,
autonomously navigate
on the back side,
to try to find
where,
where is that list
that has open jobs.
Which, in fact,
is a good indicator,
for some kind of
business insight.
For example,
if there was an open position
for six months,
and now it's closed,
that might mean something.
Or if they put
a new position out there
for a specific engineer,
a role,
it might mean
that they're now
focusing on
some other vertical,
for example.
Excellent insight,
OK.
And this BrowserUse,
now I know Playwright,
and I know Selenium.
Selenium initially has
some kind of
standard,
and everything works
with which
you automate
the browser.
Primarily intended
for testing,
but it's also very useful
for scraping, right?
Yes.
Playwright is also
some kind of
modern version of that.
Does this BrowserUse
then use
something from that,
or does it
open a new
browser,
and then
manipulates it
as a user?
If I'm not mistaken,
it uses Playwright,
under it, yes.
So, basically,
the browser is
fed in the back,
right?
Yes.
Then you have
LLM, or
Large Vision Model,
used then
for autonomous
navigation,
depending on
the device
you're using.
So, basically,
it automatically
uses a picture,
or a video,
to navigate
where it is,
so it doesn't
have to go
to a small
park,
or a house,
right?
You have two
modes,
I mean,
you have two modes.
It's much more
accurate if you
use,
depending on
what you're doing,
a screenshot of
a page.
Before that,
it used
JavaScript Execution
to create
bounding boxes
around inputs,
and then,
on the basis of
that,
it used
Large Vision
Model to
determine
what I'm
clicking,
or how to
do it,
what I'm not
clicking on
the front page,
so I can
finish the
task I
gave it.
But that
means that
you have
a Persep
instance,
or you're
using it
hosted,
or what
is the
flow?
Persep is the
right instance.
It's powerful.
It's an
open-source
project,
so you
can do it
yourself.
Do you
move it to
a container?
No,
it's direct.
Ah,
OK,
OK.
Damn,
that was
a lot
of challenges
for me,
from
scraping,
to
different
cloud flares,
protection,
and
V0,
as you can
see,
it's an
automated
browser,
and it blocks
you.
The solution
here is
that you
use an
undetected
Chrome browser,
which,
in fact,
covers all
the automated
signals.
So,
yeah,
you can
combine the
two,
and then
you can
scrape
most of
the pages.
And
if
we were
to
say that
BrowserJuice
is a
visual
model,
so that
it can
visualize
the page
in a
similar way
as the
user sees
it,
and if
we were
to
say that
BrowserJuice
is a
visual
model,
so that
it can
visualize
the page
in a
similar way
as the
user sees
it,
and
if we
were to
say that
BrowserJuice
is a
visual
model,
so that
it can
visualize
the page
in a
similar way
as the
user sees
it,
and
if we
were to
say that
BrowserJuice
is a
visual
model,
so that
it can
visualize
the page
in a
similar way
as the
user sees
it,
and
if we
were to
say that
BrowserJuice
is a
visual
model,
so that
it can
visualize
the page
in a
similar way
as the
user sees
it,
and
if we
were to
say that
BrowserJuice
is a
visual
model,
so that
it can
visualize
the page
in a
similar way
as the
user sees
it,
and
if we
were to
say that
BrowserJuice
is a
visual
model,
so that
the
user sees
the page
in a
similar way
as the
user sees
it,
and
if we
were to
say that
BrowserJuice
is a
visual
model,
so that
the
user sees
the page
in a
similar way
as the
user sees
it,
and
if we
were to
say that
BrowserJuice
is a
visual
model,
so that
the
user sees
the page
in a
similar way
as the
user sees
it,
and
if we
were to
say that
BrowserJuice
is a
visual
model,
so that
the
user sees
page
in a
similar way
as the
user sees
it,
and
if we
were to
say that
BrowserJuice
is a
visual
model,
so that
the
user sees
page
in a
similar way
as the
user sees
it,
and
if we
were to
say that
BrowserJuice
is a
visual
model,
so that
the
user sees
page in
a
similar way
as the
user sees
it,
and
if we
were to
say that
BrowserJuice
is a
visual
model,
so that
the
user sees
page in
a
similar
way as
the
user sees
it,
and
if we
were to
say that
BrowserJuice
is a
visual
model,
so that
the
user sees
page in
a similar
way as
the
user sees
it,
and
if we
were to
say that
BrowserJuice
is a
visual
model,
so that
the
user sees
page in
a similar
way as
the
user sees
it,
and
if we
were to
say that
BrowserJuice
is a
visual
model,
so that
the
user sees
page in
a similar
way as
the
user sees
it,
and
if we
were to
say that
BrowserJuice
is a
visual
model,
so that
the
user sees
page in
a similar
way as
the
user sees
it,
and
if we
were to
say that
BrowserJuice
is a
visual
model,
so that
the
user sees
page in
a similar
way as
the
user sees
it,
and
if we
were to
say that
BrowserJuice
is a
visual
model,
so that
the
user sees
page in
a similar
way as
the
user sees
it,
and
if we
were to
say that
BrowserJuice
is a
visual
model,
so that
the
user sees
page in
a similar
way as
the
user sees
it,
and
if we
were to
say that
BrowserJuice
is a
visual
model,
so that
the
user sees
page in
a similar
way as
the
user sees
it,
and
if we
were to
say that
BrowserJuice
is a
visual
model,
so that
the
user sees
page in
a similar
way as
the
user sees
it,
and
if we
were to
say that
BrowserJuice
is a
visual
model,
so that
the
user sees
page in
a similar
way as
the
user sees
it,
and
if we
were to
say that
BrowserJuice
is a
visual
model,
so that
the
user sees
page in
a similar
way as
the
user sees
it,
and
if we
were to
say that
BrowserJuice
is a
visual
model,
so that
the
user sees
page in
a similar
way as
the
user sees
it,
and
if we
were to
say that
BrowserJuice
is a
visual
model,
so that
the
user sees
page in
a similar
way as
the
user sees
it, and
if we
were to
say that
BrowserJuice
is a
visual
model,
so that
the
user sees
page in
a similar
way as
the
user sees
it, and
if we
were to
say that
BrowserJuice
is a
visual
model,
so that
the
user sees
page in
a similar
way as
the
user sees
it, and
if we
were to
say that
BrowserJuice
is a
visual
model,
so that
the
user sees
page in
a similar
way as
the
user sees
it, and
and Google Ads, and a lot of other businesses are just looking at that.
So it seems to you that if you add even more data to that data collection,
you will get even more interesting and more data,
and probably also more frequent reports, and so on.
That's right, and then at the beginning you have that big enterprise company,
that somehow wants to take over everything.
Now you used the term vibe-coding there.
What are you laughing at?
Where is that connection for the audience who doesn't know that term yet?
To describe who is a vibe-coder and what does a vibe-coder do?
At least it works.
It's a prompt.
Well, I'm sorry to say that.
Yes, actually, vibe-coding means that you use AI for programming.
Now there are a lot of tools out there.
Cursor, Windsurf is one of them, and both of them have really exploded in popularity.
And yes, it's true that even non-programmers can program something.
That's the concept.
Although, soon they will realize that they will have to program everything,
and that knowledge is very useful,
but even for someone who already knows that, it takes a lot of time.
But is it because you write a combination of prompt,
and then that classic correction for prompt,
or is it always just with prompt interactions with code?
Most of the time, it's just a prompt.
You write something, then you look if it's correct,
and if it's not, you put it in a decline.
You learn those codes, and then you write what you want.
But, you know, do you still need to know what you generated?
We're still there.
I mean, you have a very wide engineering background,
you worked on visual systems and stuff.
I imagine that you understand what you generated before,
and you will merge it inside.
I always ask myself, is it still important?
You need to know more.
Probably, in a few years, it won't be anymore.
When I was a programmer, I was a product manager,
I wrote requirements.
We'll see.
But for now, we're not there yet.
The models are not there yet.
I think this is a good starting point
for today's Slovenian AI meetup.
Well, Eric, let's wrap up this conversation.
Once again, I would encourage you
to check out the SPI Delta product.
The link is in the description.
It's a slide that destroys architecture.
Thank you for your attention,
and I'll see you next time.
Thank you.