Let's start with the new episode of Grodje.
Today I have in front of me and in front of the microphone Benjamin Džuburja from Zebra BI.
It's a Slovenian business that deals with the development of business intelligence products.
Benjamin will be going to the Congress Square after this podcast,
where he will have three lectures at Slovenia AI meetup.
He will be talking about agents.
You will be running, I will give you 20 minutes to explain what you are doing and what is so interesting about your work.
Benjamin, welcome.
Thank you.
Tell me what Zebra BI is all about.
Zebra BI is a company that started with the development of SAS solutions for business intelligence.
We developed a plugin for Microsoft Excel, where you can visualize your data.
When you click on it, you get a chart.
It was great.
It followed a standard of how good it is to present the data,
so that the stakeholders that you present insights to,
can quickly understand what you are doing,
and can quickly decide on the basis of these visualizations.
I saw this product in Excel a while ago,
when I was working on Dell EPS.
I was fascinated by what people were doing with Excel.
When I saw this plugin, I was like, wow.
This plugin doesn't just create a pie chart,
but it has terms that I don't understand at all.
Is it a special tool or not?
It is a very specific tool, a very advanced tool.
We experienced this boom with Power BI,
when Microsoft introduced Power BI in 2014-2015.
We were one of the first to look into it.
We saw the potential in this tool,
and the BI field started to develop.
We then rewritten our visualization in Power BI.
It started as a relatively simple visualization,
with two different plugins,
which we then developed more and more.
Now it is a fully interactive visualization,
in which you can directly prepare various calculations,
add new items directly via QA.
It is very responsive.
The main point is to visualize these insights as best as possible.
We achieved success together with Power BI on KPP.
If you want to use this tool in Excel or Power BI,
do you have to prepare your data in such a way that it works?
It is very complicated.
It is a good question.
It is a very good question,
because in the current or previous versions of products,
a specific form of data is needed so that you can use it well.
We have also taught our partners how to prepare their data.
This is a very interesting topic,
because it becomes very interesting with AI technology,
because you can also send this bottleneck to an AI agent.
If you go to the product page of Zebra,
you can see that it is Zebra for Office,
and you can use this widget in PowerPoint or Excel.
Then there is the second segment, Power BI,
where you can use it as a storage.
Now you have opened the third vertical.
I assume you work the most on this vertical,
where you call Zebra AI.
This is a visual tool.
I got a look at the slides you will have today,
and I scrolled inside,
and then I was inside the YouTube demo of your Zebra AI product.
In the demo, you probably choose data from some Excel,
and drag and drop it into the UI of Zebra AI,
and boom, boom, boom, boom, I see charts,
second, third, sales, up, and everything.
Additionally, I have the input, so I can print,
and it's really, wow, a quantum leap visually.
I don't know if these are synthetic data or real data,
but it seems to me that you really feel
a real leap with this technology.
How do you feel about it?
It must be very exciting for you.
It's very exciting,
and the idea of automating the whole process
from the very beginning,
but we couldn't really realize it.
You can achieve this with a large number of codes,
algorithms, some settings,
how the tool behaves in certain situations,
but it was a lot of effort,
and also the classic data science approaches,
which can, for example,
from the raw data you get,
somehow prepare,
for example, make a table,
an individual table,
what does a table mean,
so that you can make decisions on the basis of it.
They were very soft,
and difficult to adapt to the domain of data
for which we are specialized,
such as sales, finance, and business data.
And then, when it came out,
that was November 2022,
it was already impressive,
and we saw some potential in it,
and then at the beginning of the next year,
when we saw these concepts of tools and agents,
we realized that this is a breakthrough,
and we got an idea
of how we could build a system
that would be quite flexible,
it wouldn't need a single set of code
to cover all the cases,
but would somehow understand the data
and make certain decisions.
And then we started developing Zebra AI,
we made a proof of concept,
we were all shocked,
and then we decided to develop it further,
and then I,
I was alone at the time,
I started to develop it further,
and then we expanded the team.
Let's go a bit deeper,
tell me what is BI,
business intelligence,
how does it work,
and how does it relate to business intelligence?
Business intelligence is a field
that deals with a lot of issues,
it is primarily business analysts,
they deal with the analysis of business data,
primarily internal data of a company,
how it operates, etc.,
and they also analyze
SQL, ETL,
which is used as a tool
to transform and clean data
from the beginning,
then they go on to model,
understand data,
connect it, search it,
prepare insights,
build visualizations,
dashboards, etc.,
prepare messages for stakeholders,
and then add recommendations.
All of this together
is called business intelligence.
It is not enough to know only SQL,
you also need to know
business aspects,
processes,
the importance of data,
because you need to know
if it is correct or not.
Yes, you definitely need to know the field well,
but also, depending on how far you go
with the last step,
some recommendations for management,
and to some extent you need to know
the importance of the results.
The fact that companies want to
prepare data,
means that there is a lot of work
for BI or tools,
which, if they are good,
will help you prepare the data,
they will also help you
prepare high-level data.
It is always more important
that these segments are healthy,
and that the data is up-to-date.
Yes.
It is often not like that.
It is always the same.
Especially in smaller or medium-sized companies,
they don't have a team of people
who would deal with it,
and this is the segment
that is the most interesting for us.
From a certain perspective,
these are the people who are looking for solutions.
They see this technology, AI,
and they see a change in it.
Wow, this will solve this situation.
Maybe I won't need to employ someone from BI,
but I can skip some steps with this smart tool,
and I will get some insights that will help me
I hope people understand what BI is.
Let's talk about these agents.
Can you tell us
what exactly these agents mean
in the context of AI?
What are these agents?
For me, agents are,
as far as I remember,
reinforcement learning,
where we have agents
who communicate with the environment
and then get feedback from the environment
and work in return.
In this case,
we have LLMs,
which we can use
as a core for brainwashing the agent,
and they have access to the environment,
which is an additional tool.
A typical example is
writing and extracting code
on the basis of data.
An agent can write a piece of code
to answer a user's question,
get results,
and then decide
whether he did the right thing
or whether he will try again
or decide to go back to the user.
In this sense,
this is the definition of an agent.
We can imagine this as
the brains of a robot,
a large language model,
which can interact with the world
through some processes, mechanisms, and tooling.
It has a perception of the world,
it has the ability to interact with the world,
and then it probably also learns,
or is it a matter of conversation?
It can also be counter-learned.
Everything is definitely learned from this context.
With these interactions,
you can learn new things.
There are also different architectures
where you can learn new things.
For example, you can learn about cancer,
or you can learn online
about the effects of cancer.
I don't know,
I don't think this is a need for an agent.
It's more of an interaction with the environment
and some kind of autonomy.
Often people associate agents with autonomy.
It flows in a loop.
An agent can also be imagined
as a workflow in the final implementation.
You will do this and that,
you will have some loops,
you can suspend or move.
Can you give us an example
of what an agent or process looks like
in your Zebra AI?
Let me give you an example.
That's a great question.
If I can.
I will think about how to put it.
We use agents in all the phases
that I mentioned,
for example,
in the last version.
An agent tries to determine
how clean the data is,
how it meets the requirements
that we have,
so that the remainder works as it should.
It is also able to clean them in a loop,
improve them,
and then move on to the next step,
which is semantic modeling.
This is primarily about understanding the data well.
If you have a SQL database on Input,
you want to understand
what certain columns represent,
what values are present there,
and what these values mean
for certain combinations,
for certain processes,
for analysis, etc.
This is where a lot can be done.
You can create graphs,
networks,
where you define relationships,
dependencies, etc.
The next step is explorative analysis,
where we have five agents
who decide on the basis of some guidelines
and tools
what to look for in the data,
where you can do an extensive search
of a specific column of data
and look for patterns,
outliers,
various curiosities,
and then move them forward.
The next phase is visualization
of these interesting results.
We have integrated with the agents,
we have shown them
an interface with our visualizations
so that they can show the data,
the results, and build a dashboard.
The agent decides
which dimensions will be shown,
which filters will be applied.
Do you have to limit it somehow?
Yes, definitely.
You limit it with these tools
and with checking its output.
You require the output to be
precisely structured,
like JSON,
and then you also check
what is shown in the data.
Then you can sparse it
and build a dashboard.
The last step is summarization,
a classic LLM use case,
where you can try to
recommend something interesting
to look at in the future,
so that your attention is focused
on some insights.
Great!
My experience was there.
In Grodno,
it's not just an enterprise company,
but we have an Excel table
with these finances,
and I dragged it into my Excel table.
The first step was
when I found out
that the data was like this,
and I received 3 or 4 warnings
that the data was not OK
and that it could be delayed.
It could be delayed with analysis
or import, but it warned me
that I wouldn't be able to do it
until I clicked Next.
But today,
as you said before,
you helped to shape the data
so that it could be analyzed better.
Today, this problem is being solved
in a very concrete way.
I was surprised that the data
was not in the right shape,
but it managed to make a few charts
and to see that we are ready.
I have to say that what you say
works legitimately and I hope
that you will improve it.
It was very fascinating
when I saw the widgets
that were the same as in Power BI,
and how you reuse it.
Today, I have a chat input
and I can ask him some questions.
I like the fact that today
he understands the data.
You get a feeling
that he knows what kind of data
he has, what he can say
and what he cannot say.
Do you also deal with this?
This is the last big goal, right?
Yes, this is the consequence
of iterating on these agents
all the time, trying to improve them.
This is the whole workflow
that I described earlier.
We are trying to achieve
this effect,
so that the system really understands
what it is doing.
Thanks to the agents,
it somehow saves us,
and we hope that it will improve.
I have already asked this question
before, but I don't know
if I can correct myself.
This is a good question.
Do you use chat GPT,
source models, combination models,
Gemini?
Is this a relevant question?
Are these models so good
that they are all pretty much the same?
Is this a meaningful question?
To a certain extent, yes.
For a specific agent,
you need more capable models
that give more detailed answers
and results.
The rest of the pipeline
depends on the results.
Here we have a combination
of enclosed sources.
We have already experimented
with open source.
At the time, there was no DeepSeek R1.
There were no on-par results
with closed source models.
This is definitely something
that we are still preparing for.
When open source models
are on par,
this leads to additional things,
such as a security database.
Are there any models
for large language models
that specialize in finance?
Is this a niche?
Is it possible to pay someone
to do this or to distill it
just for the financial industry
or for visualization?
You can pay to distill,
but you can't pay to take
smaller and more specialized models.
For example, for finance,
you can pay $70 billion to LLM
to make a Chai GPT
in O3 with reasoning
and a billion other parameters.
The tasks that these agents solve
require a lot of reasoning
and this specialized model
is what gives us good results
and is better for larger models
all at once.
So the reasoning process
improves the one-shot approach?
Yes.
Where do you talk to yourself
until you're confident it's the right answer?
Is that a mantra?
Yes, it's a way of thinking,
it's a time to think about the task.
Some tasks are not specifically coding tasks,
but they are tasks where you look at the structure of the dataset
and mark which columns are which,
what do you think,
how are you going to model those columns,
and not mark the properties of those columns.
So, in fact, for such purposes,
they are much better in our experiments,
especially the larger models.
You're making a lot of water,
I'm going to make a little commercial.
In Grodno, maybe because of the well-known Patreons,
thank you,
and maybe also because of the companies
VisionEch, Kaldi, HumanFrog and Koforki,
who give us storage.
Thank you for being with us.
Now we have the last five minutes.
I'm more interested in the existence now,
let's say that a few years ago there was a boom
with OpenAI and 4GPT,
and you did a lot of leaps,
and then LAMA, and so on.
Are we now entering a period
when this ecosystem,
I won't say standardizes,
but are we at a point where these tasks are interchangeable,
and are already forming some standards?
Now specifically,
in the last few weeks,
I've noticed that this MCP has become
a de facto standard for doing some extensions.
At the end of the month,
I realized that MCP is Model Context Protocol,
and the idea is that through a client
that runs your LLM model,
or an agent, for example,
using a standard protocol,
you can call tools or capabilities
that can be on a server,
which means that you can have a weather tool,
and it will tell you what the weather is like,
and the model will call that tool
and tell you the weather.
It's a classic example.
You can send an email,
and the tool will send you an email.
Have you ever played with this?
Maybe you can say something about it,
because I see that it's becoming a very hot topic,
and a next phase of integration of models.
Yes, yes.
My sister came to me,
and I check it every day.
I was at MCP last week.
Yes, I think it's definitely great
that this access to various tools is being standardized.
At the moment, it seems to me that everyone,
I think this is an introduction to Antropica,
OpenAI still has its own way of using these tools,
if you use their LLMs,
they somehow expose you
in their best way how to use these tools.
This seems to me also because of the way they are taught.
In what format is it best to use this?
So I think it would be great
if this standard would be used in the future
for some new models,
and it would be so effective,
and all models would know how to use it well.
But at the moment, we're not there yet.
I was talking about the spec of this MCP,
the basics are for JSON RPC,
so you have to use, let's say,
capabilities or tools,
make a request, where do you have the tools,
and then also methods,
face recognition, arguments,
and he knows that.
What's interesting is that it enables streaming,
so if he gets a request,
he can answer it like that,
or he can answer it later,
what are the new capabilities,
and it also has a way
to send it back as a notification.
So it's a very interesting way of integration,
it will definitely be possible to do with these parts,
so I see that it's very...
I see that it's still a bit in the middle,
but it's definitely a direction
that I see will be very interesting to think about.
Maybe the last question,
and then I'll let you go.
What do you think...
Will we need more of these analysts in the future,
or do we just need more large language models,
or a better process,
or what do you think?
Do you think that...
Because we also have the same question
with programmers now,
because of all those wipe codings,
and that tooling,
people think,
oh, we don't need programmers anymore.
Do you think that people will also start
using these tools?
I don't know,
but I hope so.
Definitely,
I think it's very similar,
what programmers are experiencing,
and I think the answer is also very similar,
because in BI,
you can also use writing some codes,
some queries,
to get...
It's hard to say,
but I think,
now I think,
that for some of these lighter tasks,
an agent is already able to do a lot,
and it's almost...
I don't know,
those solutions,
like Devin,
or those automatic programmers,
who would do anything,
are already impressive.
They can do a lot of other tasks,
but they also get stuck,
and they always make more mistakes,
or make some inoptimal things,
and they need to be corrected all the time.
So, I think that,
first of all,
it will take a long time,
that we will also,
for some, not so senior people,
that we won't need them anymore,
but especially for those seniors,
who will be supervising AI,
I think,
it will take some time,
and also in BI,
I think we will need analysts
for such a long time,
because, for example,
in BI, I think,
the adoption of AI
is a bit slower,
because it's a field
that deals with sensitive data,
and people are afraid of AI,
they don't understand it as much,
as maybe programmers do.
Great.
Benjamin, thank you for your time,
and good luck with your sales.
Thank you.