Dear listeners, dear listeners, welcome to the 4th season of episode 2 in Grodno.
Today we will have an extra super fine.
Why am I talking so enthusiastically?
First of all, because all millenials and zoomers have a bad focus.
So stay tuned to this episode of all the first N minutes.
Let's talk about N, of course.
Today we will talk a little about hardware, a little about it.
David Zobavnik from DVSoft is with us, and his title is...
Help me, David.
Head of Embedded Software Development.
Or the head of integrated connection in something deep.
What do you think?
I think it's either integrated or integrated.
It depends on where you ask for a fax in Slovenia.
Ok, the best.
Now, what would we do without Tomaž?
So today we have Tomaž here to massage David,
so we can talk about hardware together.
I'm actually the biggest noob here,
because I don't have a company that makes hardware.
I still have a lot of customers in Amazon.
So, every good episode or content,
whether it's a podcast or YouTube,
starts with a good hook.
So David, we're interested in,
besides fresh hardware,
what does DVSoft have,
even if it's not Porsche.
How many do you have?
So I'm asking you,
do you know any engineers who put something on themselves,
and then Porsche it for you?
I mean, yeah.
Those people who make hardware don't Porsche,
at least not Porsche.
Yeah, so in my opinion,
the way I know those engineers,
it's the same for us,
because we were told that we're engineers,
and then there's that extra money,
where we put some graphics,
cards that have been expensive lately,
and then maybe those who are a bit more financially literate,
like ETFs,
that have a low budget,
or low expenses.
Okay, okay.
Porsche is a waste of money.
But if you have a Porsche,
I'm just wondering,
where do you put your hardware?
I think it's BMW.
BMW?
Or did you photoshop it,
for the marketing sake?
Yeah, and this car, for example,
has been redesigned,
and it's been done so that
we can put it on display,
and now we're able to measure everything
in this car.
So, for example,
it has a few hundred sensors,
and we can measure everything.
Okay.
What is all of this?
I mean, temperature,
shaking,
brightness,
sleep,
speed,
flow,
position,
then acceleration,
then, let's say,
what's the temperature,
I don't know,
how the engine is working,
or if something is strangely shaking,
or maybe the engine is a bit broken,
and now it's fixed as it should be.
But I don't know,
also, for example,
in the automotive industry,
if I'm specific,
if it's a bit big,
you also get data through CAN,
so you also have,
let's say,
a thousand parameters
that you get from their ECUs,
and so on.
What is the pleasure
in engineering
that you do with CAN?
Or, no,
I'll put it differently.
From 1 to 10,
what is your experience?
With CAN?
Yes.
Okay, what is it?
Yes, let me first explain
what CAN is.
Okay, yes.
It's a protocol
that actually works
on an electrical level.
You get a specific signal,
and then you decode it into bytes,
and then you extract
some information from it.
Now, as I enjoy it,
from 1 to 10,
I have to admit
that I'm like two at the moment.
Maybe not specifically now,
or in the last few weeks,
we think about it,
but we have CAN FD,
which is perhaps
a slightly newer protocol
that is able to send
a little more data from it.
But, no,
I personally don't like it,
and I also feel that
with time,
there will always be less CAN,
because, I don't know,
the automotive industry
is also,
which is modern,
ethernet.
So, that's,
in addition to everything else,
I would also say
that in the automotive industry,
ethernet is becoming
more and more popular.
Is that CAN encrypted?
No, only by itself, no.
If I turn the knob
in the car,
and switch to CAN bus,
what can I do?
You can choose
where the stream is,
but then you have to know
what kind of data it represents.
But I would say
that according to my information,
a lot of it is not
specifically encoded.
You have to know
what kind of information
it is,
which all developers
hide,
but if you know
where to get it,
which is a lot of secrecy,
then you can
practically get
that information.
Ok, and you can
even go further with it?
You can.
Ok.
And how do you work
with that,
if everyone is so stupidly
hiding it?
Isn't that
a common bus
that everyone would hold?
I don't know,
some kind of USB in the car,
so that everyone has
a common language
over CAN bus?
Isn't that so?
I think it is.
That's how it is.
Those who use
the software,
they receive
some data,
and then everyone,
every Amazon user,
has to know
where to get
that information.
That's why
the information
you find
is hidden.
Ah, ok,
so you need
some kind of
ground truth.
Yes, yes.
Ok.
When we were
talking about
measuring,
and let's go
in that direction,
you said
that you
measure,
and I'm interested
in this,
I mean,
where in the software
is the core business,
the measurement systems,
right?
I always
wonder
where is the
beginning?
Who is
the source
of truth
for things,
in general?
I don't know.
We measure,
I don't know,
distances.
Ok, a meter
is today,
I think,
an establishment
of how precise
a meter is,
that it is
a mathematical thing,
right?
But who gives
us our
right second,
which is
perfect?
Who are these
authorities?
I would say
so,
I think
some physicist
said
that everything
is relative.
Now,
for example,
we have
our own
devices,
which we
have to measure
somewhere,
and we,
for example,
use a
calibrator,
which is
a big
device,
also expensive,
which is
calibrated with
a better
calibrator,
and so on.
Ok.
Which is,
yes,
at the end,
the last
source of truth,
you have
some physical
definitions,
and probably
some facts,
because we know
that they are
so and so
precise.
Ok.
For example,
I don't know,
for GPS hours,
we know
that they are
so and so
precise.
So there is
a source
of truth,
and it's
good enough
for your
needs.
And then
you have
verification,
certificates,
and knowledge
of the
provider,
and then
you believe
that what
you use
is really
so and so
precise.
Ok.
And do
I have to
verify it
independently
or?
Yes,
I think
it's
good enough
within those
parameters,
and so on.
Ok.
Very interesting.
For example,
when I first
started,
well,
I think
we all know
this,
but when
I first
heard that
this is
one of the
more successful
Slovenian
businesses
in this
field,
I thought
ok,
what do
I, as a
layman,
need to
do?
And then
I thought
ok,
at home
we all
have,
for example,
ok,
now that we
are more
technically
advanced,
you have
a shovel,
and you
have a
multimeter,
and a
thermometer,
and that's
where it
ends.
So,
tell us
a little
bit about
your
business,
and
what
is it
like?
Ok,
so,
I am
also
often
asked
what
I do
as a
member,
and if
I can't
discuss
enough,
I say
I do
it as
a voltmeter.
But,
maybe,
what is
special about
us?
We
all
have
sensors,
and
if you
have an
Eiffel
Tower,
which is
400 meters
tall,
we
know
the
dimensions
of
things.
That's
one thing.
Another
thing is
that,
which is
very
important
in our
industry,
is that
you
can
measure
things
from
a distance
of
100 nanoseconds
or
with our
measurements.
What
do we
measure?
Let me
say that
we are
really
committed
to
doing
it
in a
way that
if you
have
a structure
or a
device
and
you
don't
know
how
much
time
it
takes
to
measure
it
you
can
measure
it
in a
way
that
you
can
measure
it
in a
way
that
you
can
measure
it
in
a
way
that
you
can
measure
it
in
a
way
that
you
can
measure
it
in
a
way
that
you
can
measure
it
in
a
way
that
you
can
measure
it
in
a
way
that
you
can
measure
it
in
a
way
that
you
can
measure
it
in
a
way
that
you
can
measure
it
in
a
way
that
you
can
measure
it
in
a
way
that
you
can
measure
it
in
a
way
that
you
can
measure
it
in
a
way
that
you
can
measure
it
in
a
way
that
you
can
measure
it
in
a
way
that
you
can
measure
it
in
a
way
that
you
just
have to
measure
it
in
a
way
that
you
can
measure
it
in
a
way
that
you
can
measure
it
in
a
way
that
you
just
have to
measure
it
in
a
way
that
you
can
measure
it
in
a
way
that
does
not
make
sense
in
a
way
that
you
can
measure
it
in
a
way
that
does
not
make
sense
in
a
way
that
you
can
measure
it
in
a
way
that
does
not
make
sense
in
a
way
that
you
can
measure
it
in
a
way
that
does
not
make
sense
in
a
way
that
does
not
make
sense
in
a
way
that
does
not
make
sense
in
a
way
that
does
not
make
sense
in
a
way
that
does
not
make
sense
in
a
way
that
does
not
make
sense
in
a
way
that
does
make
sense
in
a
way
that
does
not
make
sense
in
a
way
that
does
make
sense
in
a
way
that
does
not
make
sense
in
a
way
that
does
not
make
sense
in
a
way
that
does
make
sense
in
a
way
that
does
make
sense
in
a
way
that
does
make
sense
in
a
way
that
does
make
sense
in
a
way
that
does
make
sense
in
a
way
that
does
make
sense
in
a
way
that
makes
sense
in
a
way
that
does
make
a
problem
in
a
different
way
and
a
different
way
like
maybe
a
step
slower
than
we
would
like
different
way
than
we
would
like
different
way
than
we
would
like
different
way
than
we
would
like
different
way
than
we
would
like
different
way
than
we
would
like
different
way
than
we
would
like
different
way
than
we
would
like
different
way
than
we
would
like
different
way
than
we
would
like
different
way
than
we
would
like
different
way
than
we
would
like
different
way
than
we
would
like
different
way
than
we
would
like
different
way
than
we
would
like
different
way
than
we
would
like
different
way
than
we
would
like
different
way
than
we
would
like
different
way
than
we
would
like
different
way
than
we
would
like
different
way
than
we
would
like
different
way
than
we
would
like
different
way
than
we
would
like
different
way
than
we
would
like
different
way
than
we
would
like
different
way
than
we
would
like
different
way
than
we
would
like
different
way
than
we
would
like
different
way
than
we
would
like
different
way
than
we
would
like
different
way
than
we
would
like
different
way
than
we
would
like
different
way
than
we
would
like
different
way
than
we
would
like
different
way
than
we
would
like
different
way
than
we
would
like
different
way
than
we
would
like
different
way
than
we
would
like
different
way
than
we
would
like
different
way
than
we
would
like
different
way
than
we
would
like
different
way
than
we
would
like
different
way
than
we
would
like
different
way
than
we
would
like
different
way
than
we
would
like
different
way
than
These devices were specially designed for this purpose.
First of all, they were used to store data.
Then, I would say, they were used to be used as full-time relays.
Then, this device was used to send data via USB to some computer.
I would say that this is the core software of Laufa 9 Soft X.
This is the application of Laufa on Windows.
This is where we started.
Then, as I mentioned earlier, the next step is to make the ARM processors more powerful.
Here, we are using the Sitaro AM57, which has an ARM processor on top, A15.
It has two cores.
On top of that, Linux is running normally.
These are profiles that have changed a bit.
People are working on different profiles.
There is a microcontroller.
FPGA was used for electrotechnics.
So, they had to know how to connect.
Here is the ARM processor.
Then, you have Linux.
It is very easy for people to get to know Linux.
Then, there are more programmers, or those who came from the free sphere, for example.
This is object programming.
I would say that architecture is more complicated.
This is what our parties are using.
Then, there is the third model, or combination, that I just mentioned.
You can have a big box, which has eight buttons.
On the bottom, there is one more layer, which is a computer.
It is made on our side.
It is slightly adjusted, so it can withstand higher and lower temperatures.
It is a typical computer.
It is a computer that can handle 80 degrees.
I would say that there are more critical use cases.
Is it better if it is made more complicated, or does it not matter?
In the sense that it does one function, and it does it well.
The more it is made, the more complex it is.
That is why there is a greater possibility of error.
Does this play a role?
Yes, I would definitely agree with that.
Our mission is to make life more complicated.
We are working on multifunctional devices, which do a lot of things in a short time.
This is where programmers take the hard path and say, we will try to do everything.
I agree.
I will say that this is a bit of a debate, because we will spend a lot of time here.
In real-time, you want to be more predictable.
What do you mean by real-time?
One millisecond?
I think the definition of real-time is that something happens to you in response to the current time.
It can also be one minute.
I think that 95% of applications in the world, if they have real-time,
one millisecond is enough.
Why is one millisecond enough?
Because you have mechanical systems that do not have to be fast.
If something is very fast, it is not as if it were physically moving.
OK.
Let's go, because we can talk a bit more about hardware.
In short, let's go step by step.
I come from the side, and I am the problem for which you do not have solutions on the market.
How does it all start?
And how do we get to the point where you say, OK, this will take 300 hours,
and so on, and then you deliver it to me.
What happens in the middle?
I think you have to be the owner of a factory or something.
Let's say I am.
That is why I wanted to say, forget something that is too small.
Or something like that, yes.
The thing is, when you have a bigger company,
there are some schedules of what you would like to have.
First of all, our sellers around the world are looking for these schedules,
and we will make the first check to see how many things we can deliver.
It is not often that you deliver, but it makes sense to work with them.
It is often the case that you deliver 80-90% of the points,
and 10-20% still needs to be done.
And then you contact our project office,
and the project office writes down what they would like to have,
and offers suggestions on how to deal with our existing solutions.
And the remaining 10%, which is still not enough,
they sit down together with the product managers,
and then we have the product owners,
we have a team of product managers who take care of the products
within their streams,
and then we talk together,
and we analyze whether this could be done or not,
and, for example, how much would it cost to do it.
We make an assessment,
then we look at the schedule,
and then we choose a priority,
which is important to us.
Sometimes it is not just the money, but also the strategy.
For example, when we first started working for NASA,
we didn't have that much money,
and it was a very prestigious project from the point of view we came from.
But maybe, when the company left,
they suggested where they would like to go,
and it is a very good opportunity to join together and make this product.
And then it is up to the decision-makers to go and work on this product.
Then we have the summer plans,
we have the quarterly plans,
for example, for one year we make a plan of what we want to do,
and then for the fourth year,
we look at the project and decide
that this project is a top priority,
and we start working on it.
For example, we divide it into teams,
the hardware team has to do this and that,
the software team has to do this and that,
and the engineers inside the team have to assess
how much work there is to be done.
This is where Igor Kostanđer comes in,
who is a big fan of all the developers.
And then we write the stories and assess how much work there is to be done,
and then it is done.
For example, you think that a successful company like DvSoft
doesn't have internal failures,
but I hope that DvSoft will also face failures.
Tell us more about this.
Tell us, if you can,
about a failure that was also expensive,
and you say, ok, we are done with this.
It is very interesting,
because if someone asked me a year ago,
I would say something else.
Ok.
It is so fresh.
So fresh, yes.
And now we only had one failure,
which was a problem in itself,
and which affected all parties.
We have synchronous and asynchronous measurements.
Synchronous measurements are when something comes from a distance,
for example at 20 kHz,
and then you have asynchronous data,
which you get in a few seconds,
and then you have a healthy timestamp.
And it turns out,
we did a big architectural improvement,
and it turned out that if you do these asynchronous measurements,
and if you do them for a long time,
you can corrupt the data.
And this is a kind of special scenario that can happen to us.
And this is, for example,
a website, or a kind of scenario,
for example,
that rents an office,
where you can spend a few million per day,
make measurements,
everything looks fine,
and then they want to look at the data,
and it turns out,
and this is how it was,
that if you quickly took the data,
everything looked fine,
and then you did the measurements,
and it turned out that it could be corrupted.
And this happened to us last week.
What I would say is that it is a matter of luck or misfortune,
to be able to correct it in such a way,
that those who corrupted the data,
I would say,
95% of them would be able to solve it,
fortunately.
But I said,
it happened to us once,
that the actual thing affected all parties,
and that it was the worst thing.
If you can't measure it,
then it's not good,
because if you measure it,
then it's not good.
Who is Kregan, for example?
Who is Slijš?
Well, you know,
usually,
I would say,
in my opinion,
not only in the engineering world,
you try this,
non-blame culture.
Okay.
So, usually,
you make a report,
you get the results,
and then you try,
and finally,
you correct it,
because it won't repeat itself.
So, I would say,
here,
you learn a lot,
especially with a name,
so that it would stand out.
Yes,
I didn't ask for a name,
so that it would be similar.
What is the reason for that?
We created it first,
didn't we?
Yes.
It was a software bug.
The tests weren't found,
because you can work on it for a long time,
for example,
I don't know,
for a few days,
so that you can see the bug.
Okay,
now,
software developer,
in my opinion,
not software,
I don't have to have it.
Where do you store the data?
What database do you use?
That's it.
Yes,
that's interesting,
I think,
we've come so far,
I would say,
industrially specific,
that,
I would say,
when you work with cameras,
it's almost like,
these are really the data
that you want
to be displayed
anywhere.
Okay.
And again,
here,
it's not like
I would store them in a database,
because I will give,
I don't know,
one example again,
our fastest production
is always there,
somewhere around 15 million
data per second,
per channel.
How many channels?
Yes,
for example,
I can make 8 channels,
I can have them,
I don't know,
10, 20, 30,
I can make them.
Okay.
And in practice,
here you can't use all,
you can't use the database,
and again,
you store it locally,
and then maybe
when you analyze the data,
or you compress them a little bit,
then you get
the data
that you want
to be displayed
in the database.
Okay.
So,
you compress the data,
and then maybe
you can write it down.
But, for example,
I will say that
our core business
is not about
storing data,
but I will say
that we have
a startup,
or I will say
a spin-off,
which deals
with more modern
methods,
which are then
stored
in the database.
So,
it's pretty much
raw data.
Yes,
on a disk.
On a disk,
and then...
A disk,
or a translator?
On a disk.
So,
I would say
that Avender
is spinning,
as well.
You mean
spinning disks?
Yes.
You mean spinning disks?
Okay.
A lot of data,
right?
Yes.
Yes,
exactly.
You see,
I would say
that
SQLite,
or some
lightweight
engine,
but...
How many
seconds,
did you say?
15 MBs per channel.
I think
Okay,
that's pretty
high numbers.
But that's
an extreme example.
Yes.
But,
despite
typical,
let's say
100 MBs
per second,
that's typical.
Yes,
that's a pretty
nice number.
For example,
I don't know if
you remember,
but the automobile
industry
is very
reliant on
data.
So,
at night,
this camera
would be sent.
So,
you have
a computer,
which would
send a software
to a computer,
which is
basically a
Windows machine,
and you store
it there.
It could be
a computer
or a laptop
somewhere
in the middle.
And you have
an internal
way of...
I mean,
I'm assuming
that,
regardless of
the type of
measurement,
whether it's
length-wise
or temperature-wise,
whatever,
it's all
standardized.
Is it
externally
standardized,
or is it
internal?
You said
that you'll
sort the data
in a way
that's best
for you.
We have
our own format
which is
optimized
so that
it can be
saved as
soon as
possible,
and so
that later
when I
store the
data,
it can
be used
in a way
that's
best
for me.
So,
we have
our own
format
which is
optimized
so that
later
when I
store the
data,
it can
be used
as soon
as possible,
and so
that later
when I
store the
data,
it can
be used
as soon
as possible,
and so
that later
when I
store the
data,
it can
be used
as soon
as possible,
and so
that later
when
I
store the
data,
it can
be used
as soon
as
possible,
and
so that
later
when I
store the
data,
it
can be
used
as soon
as
possible,
and
so that
later
when
I
store the
data,
it
can
be used
as soon
as
possible,
and
so that
later
when
I
store the
data,
it
can be
used
as soon
as
possible,
and
so that
later
when
I
store the
data,
it
can be
used
as soon
as
possible,
and
so that
later
when
I
store the
data,
it
can be
used
as soon
as
possible,
and
so that
later
when
I
store the
data,
it
can be
used
as soon
as
possible,
and
so that
later
when
I
store the
data,
it
can be
used
as soon
as
possible,
and
so that
later
when
I
store the
data,
it
can be
used
as soon
as
possible,
and
so that
later
when
I
store the
data,
it
can be
used
as soon
as
possible,
and
so that
later
when
I
store the
data,
it
can be
used
as
soon
possible,
and
so that
later
when
I
store the
data,
it
can be
used
as soon
as
possible,
and
so that
later
when
I
store the
data,
it
can be
used
as soon
as
possible,
and
so that
later
when
I
store the
data,
it
can be
used
as soon
as
possible,
and
so that
later
when
I
store the
data,
it
can be
used
as soon
as
possible,
and
so that
later
when
I
store the
data,
it
can be
used
as soon
as
possible,
and
so that
later
when
I
store the
data,
it
can be
used
as soon
as
possible,
and
so that
later
when
I
store the
data,
it
can be
used
as soon
as
possible,
and
so that
later
when
I
store the
data,
it
can be
used
as soon
as
possible,
and
so that
later
when
I
store the
data,
it
can
be
used
as soon
as
possible,
and
so that
later
when
I
store the
data,
it
can be
used
as soon
as
possible,
and
so that
later
when
I
store the
data,
it
can be
used
as
soon
possible,
and
so that
later
when
I
store the
data,
it
can be
used
as soon
as
possible,
and
so that
later
when
I
store the
data,
it
can be
used
as soon
as
possible,
and
so that
later
when
I
store the
data,
it
can be
used
as soon
as
possible,
and
so that
later
when
I
store the
data,
it
can be
used
as soon
as
possible,
and
so that
later
when
I
store the
data,
it
can be
used
as soon
as
possible,
and
so that
later
when
I
store the
data,
it
can be
used
as soon
as
possible,
and
so that
later
when
I
store
the
data,
it
can be
used
as soon
as
possible,
and
so that
later
when
I
store the
data,
it
can be
used
as soon
as
possible,
and
so that
later
when
I
store the
data,
it
can be
used
as soon
as
possible,
and
so that
later
when
I
store the
data,
it
can be
used
as soon
as
possible,
and
so that
later
when
I
store the
data,
it
can be
used
as
soon
possible,
and
so that
later
when
I
store the
data,
it
can be
used
as soon
as
possible,
and
so that
later
when
I
store the
data,
it
can be
used
as soon
as
possible,
and
so that
later
when
I
store the
data,
it
can be
used
as soon
as
possible,
and
so that
later
when
I
store the
data,
it
can be
used
as soon
as
possible,
and
so that
later
when
I
store the
data,
it
can be
used
as soon
as
possible,
and
so that
later
when
I
store the
data,
it
can be
used
as soon
as
possible,
and
so that
later
when
I
store the
data,
it
can be
used
as soon
as
possible,
and
so that
later
when
I
store the
data,
it
can be
used
as soon
as
possible,
and
so that
later
when
I
store the
data,
it
can be
used
as soon
as
possible,
and
so that
later
when
I
store the
data,
it
can be
used
as soon
as
possible,
and
so that
later
when
I
store the
data,
it
can be
used
as
soon
possible,
and
so that
later
when
I
store the
data,
it
can be
used
as soon
as
possible,
and
so that
later
when
I
store the
data,
it
can be
used
as soon
as
possible,
and
so that
later
when
I
store the
data,
it
can be
used
as soon
as
possible,
and
so that
later
when
I
store the
data,
it
can be
used
as soon
as
possible,
and
so that
and we were like, what's going on, let's make it clear.
At first we thought it was some kind of a contact,
because it's a BGA, which means that it's going from the bottom,
that it's some kind of a stick slab,
and when it's heated, the current expands
just enough for the stick to reach the stick and start working.
But what was the catch, or what was the catch,
that we chose the wrong value of the current resistance,
and when the board was heating up,
the current went out of the tolerance,
so that the current fell into the right tolerance of the chip,
which then started to send 100 MHz frequencies from itself.
That's the fun part, when you're lucky and it works.
Yes, exactly.
That's the best part.
It's a good learning.
But before that, do you have,
do you have an internal library,
I would say, of those components,
which you can reuse over and over,
so that you know how it works,
so that it's just a copy-paste.
Of course.
One thing is the fact that you have these libraries,
from which resistance you use capacitors,
and it's all updated,
but I will say,
we also work on our components in a modular way,
so that you can also use them differently.
This will be an example.
We had one generation of some components,
and then you have the motherboard,
and then you have the amplifiers,
and now we can use the same amplifiers,
but in a new generation.
We also try to reuse all these things as much as possible,
and so that we drive development,
and so that these things are checked as much as possible,
because, as I mentioned earlier,
you really need a lot of time to check all these things,
so that the work is really bearable.
So it's worth investing in having,
let's say, similar components,
common components and so on.
And, in fact, going even further,
you also want to have these partners,
who, for example, support these things.
In our case, it's Eltech.
We have been cooperating with them for 15 years,
and we will continue to cooperate with them,
because here, I will say,
this trust is very important,
and you know that if you don't have it,
it's completely different,
if you don't have one key choice.
It is very important to trust the whole variety,
so that you can trust.
I will say that it is probably very easy for you,
because you have such a wide range,
but also a name,
that it is possible for you to work against it somehow.
Yes, that's right.
I mean, you have to work hard,
but you also have to help a lot,
and you make sure that it is good enough.
We will have something,
as I said before,
we also have some ether cables,
and you also need power.
That's why I will say,
high voltage power,
and you can have it fast.
And, for example, with these cables,
I don't know,
for almost a year,
we thought that we got a good provider,
who knew how to put the cables together.
It's all too simple,
data, data,
and then you have your power,
and it turns out that it's a complex thing.
But yes, you try,
and together we have a solution.
The best.
That's a great segue,
I also want to thank our partners,
our supporters,
Humum, Frog, Kaldi, Visionect,
TR Kufr,
Kufr gives us money for our videos,
and of course our patrons,
who chose us and support us.
So that was Mini EPP.
Now I will continue
with a high-quality question.
The best.
Let's go.
You mentioned calibration before,
I will go back a bit,
but I am interested,
when you put this device somewhere,
it's been a little over a year,
I don't know, 15 years,
you have these devices,
I suppose that these devices
have to be measured again,
calibrated,
and then the parties do it locally,
how does it look like?
That's right,
they have to be calibrated once a year,
or they have to be measured first,
and then calibrated,
if I can put it that way.
We have our own calibration laboratories,
we also have,
around the world,
for example in America,
in Asia,
we have our own,
so we have a few of our
certified laboratories,
where the parties can
buy calibration equipment,
and then calibrate themselves,
even though it's not an official calibration,
but it's,
I don't have the papers,
but it's just as valuable
in terms of functionality.
You can measure your instruments
yourself.
We are a bit special here,
we make it possible for the parties
to calibrate themselves.
So you are an international company,
so on different continents
you have these laboratories,
you have sales, marketing,
what else do you have?
The majority of our development
is in Slovenia,
we have a majority in Trbovlja,
and also HQ,
we also have a small one in Maribor,
and in Ljubljana,
and around the world,
we have these development departments,
for example one company
we bought in the Danube,
which specializes in
some turbines and measurements.
Then around the world,
we have a large
company,
and mostly it's local support,
it's sales,
it's calibration equipment,
there are also
business developers,
who specialize in
some type of measurements.
And if there is a bigger country,
like the US,
they have their own application engineers,
or programmers,
who can automate
and build applications on top of us.
I think that in the US
we have
around 60-700 employees,
so you can have such a large team.
What does the marketing look like?
Do you go everywhere?
I think it's always different,
we go to these conferences,
CubeCon,
and I think
that in electronics,
and in the industry,
it's always a bit different.
I have another question for you,
if you go to these conferences,
who is your competitor?
Who do you look at so little,
and you don't really care
what you say,
but you laugh about it.
I go to these conferences a lot,
but I would say that
a lot of what our side finds,
is that you get to know the people
in the industry.
I don't know,
our sellers are good,
they have the best tools,
I don't know,
for a product,
or a website,
they have been selling for 20-30 years,
and then they have some contacts,
and they get to know each other.
Or champagne.
They get to know the website,
and if they get to know each other,
they get to know the product,
and then they can do a demo,
and then again,
they get to know each other.
Now, who is our main competitor?
I would say that the two biggest companies
are HBK,
Hottinger and Brilliant Care,
and National Instruments.
I would say,
that,
to be honest,
with HBK,
we all work together
in a venture company,
where we decided
to have an open-source
protocol,
and SDK,
where we all work together,
which is called OpenDAQ,
so we all work together.
I would also say,
that more competitors
are helping us,
because I think that we are
watching these works,
they are being broadcast all the time,
and I would say,
that our competitors,
I think,
that we have the best products,
but there is one,
which has been changed,
it is a Chinese company,
and I don't know their names,
but I would say,
that locally,
we are losing,
because they are a bit protectionist,
so if they don't choose us,
then it is their business,
but I would also say,
that Chinese companies,
as far as I can see,
are more responsive to the market,
they are more innovative,
they change faster,
and so,
if you ask me,
who would be the biggest competitor
in 10-20 years,
I would say,
Chinese company,
because HBK is more
like a German company,
and I would say,
that they bought a warehouse,
similar to our instrument,
and I think,
that here they optimize
the short-term gain,
and maybe they fell asleep
with the technology itself.
And you have,
you have all the production
in Slovenia,
and here,
what we produce,
and what we do in the house,
is that we cut the aluminum hair,
then we have the laying
of the components,
the connection,
the L-technique,
which we also have in the warehouses,
and then we have the production,
when it is all screwed together.
Now we will move
to a new category,
intimacy with Tomas,
and we will ask you, David,
how do you come to this job,
where did you start,
and with this mix of simplicity
and goodwill, I guess,
to enjoy where you start,
how does young David find
the path,
which he follows,
to get to where he is today?
It is a very interesting story.
I have always been
a programmer,
and I also had,
let's say, logical instincts,
and I was a bit weird,
I also had a lot of equations,
Now you are among yourself,
a bit so weird.
But then I said,
I will not go to the computer,
because it is all programmed,
a bit boring,
I will go to the L-technique,
then I liked automatics,
because it was so interesting,
but I didn't like the connection either.
I mean, I found this automatics
quite interesting,
I had it programmed a bit,
it was great,
but then again,
what was in it for me?
I wanted to be a programmer,
but not just a programmer,
I wanted to solve some engineering problems
on a larger scale.
And then I was a bit on the side,
and it was a miracle,
when I was working with a student
for VESOL PICASIC,
the Slovenian VESOL agency,
when I was working with them,
and also with DVSoft,
when they were working with us,
and I said to myself,
ok, I can work in transport,
ok, a bit strange,
but if they are working with us,
something will work out.
Then I went to an interview,
I met DVSoft's chief forester,
Juret, and I found it quite interesting,
what they were doing,
it was the first impression,
I was like,
ok, let's try,
if it doesn't work,
you can change it in half a year.
So I started working,
I was a software developer,
I was in automation,
I was also a bit in real-time,
and I thought,
first of all,
let's make some fixes,
but then I thought,
we can also work in real-time,
so we came up with the idea
to make some fixes
that work on the real-time
e-tracket protocol,
and I made one fix,
and then there was a cool team,
and I think I was
the most formal leader
of that team,
and that's how
the company started,
when I started,
we were like 5-6 programmers,
15 people,
Jure was a programmer,
and the current director was a programmer,
and then we were growing,
and we could organize ourselves a bit differently,
and there were already
a lot of things to develop,
and then I got my own team,
and then I started with that,
ok, two teams,
because sometimes I don't program
more than 50% of the time,
but I program 20% of the time,
and then maybe 10% of the time,
and then I started,
and I became a programmer,
I became an organizer,
and then I think
at some point I decided,
ok, now I have to decide
if I'm going to become a programmer,
and then I dedicate myself to a team,
and then maybe I'll be an architect,
or I'll try
to be in that
big picture organization,
because it will be interesting for me,
and it's also true that
I change a bit every now and then,
and if I'm already in the same service,
it's good that I change a bit,
I don't know if you've noticed,
every 5 years it changes,
and I'm enjoying the process,
I'm trying to optimize the process,
or that I have an influence
on the fact that things are
getting better and better,
and then occasionally,
as a leader,
you have a little more power
to change it,
so I said, ok,
I'll go into this leadership,
and I'll try to help,
and then, I think,
3-4 years ago,
I somehow became a leader,
and then another colleague
also became a leader.
Are you pissed off
against your hierarchy?
Have you described yourself as pissed off?
No, I don't think so.
Can I say something about that?
Now, when they give me
one-on-one talks,
and summer talks,
and feedback,
they tell me,
in the company,
that we are, I don't know,
it's a bit of a cliché,
as you said, we have a flat structure,
but for us,
everyone can do anything,
we have an open map,
I also believe in transparency,
and I think,
this advantage, for me as a leader,
is that I was a software developer
before,
and somehow, I know,
how much you wanted to be a software developer,
how much you wanted peace,
how much you wanted to deal with a drama,
how much you wanted some
reasonable conditions,
so that, for example,
not every day, another task
flies in.
So, in general, I think
I know how to make people happy,
and also, I don't know,
if someone doesn't agree with me,
that's the best thing for me,
to hear another opinion,
so we can talk, I don't know.
What also helps,
and I can say for myself,
is the high-end kitchen,
the food is top.
Every time I was there,
I ate there, and...
For Sava, Viljama liked it as well.
They are not interested in me,
except if David gives me
other information.
Because you have two refrigerators,
public and private, right?
Right, right.
May I?
No, no, you can continue.
What, where do you cut corners
on projects, if any?
Because I think...
I don't know where.
Every project has some constraints.
If you don't know the other one,
you always partner with someone else.
Okay, first of all,
we're talking about bigger numbers,
there's always a ceiling.
Where do you say, okay,
let's focus more,
let's put this aside.
You have to think through
what the corner is.
In this job, you have to be
very pragmatic,
you have to think through
what is really worth.
You have to be careful not to get stuck
and not to invest too much energy.
The reality is that
if you want to have
an ideal product,
you would bankrupt it.
The corner is...
The beginning is very good,
because it's your final goal.
Then, I would say,
architecturally,
you look at how you can
achieve this goal
with as little energy
as possible,
but at the same time,
it's all a matter of persistence.
We're not a startup,
you can do something
and in a month
you'll be able to
break all the code.
It's an engineering experience.
Those who were senior developers
know, okay,
this is good enough,
and maybe this is the right thing to do.
Give me a specific example.
I don't know,
is it a weaker version
of some chips you choose,
or less engineering hours,
or is it reusability?
Give me a specific idea.
For example,
I don't know,
something like that.
A chip that has a lot of tolerance,
let's give it less tolerance.
With components,
you have some specifications,
then you look for components
that are within those specifications.
You don't want to take
the best and most expensive component,
because in the end,
the product will be so expensive.
You look at what you want to achieve,
and then you look for
what is possible for you.
But it's not about
cutting corners,
it's just about optimization.
It's a good business practice.
Exactly.
I don't know,
let's say,
let's say it's a product,
let's try to send it
to the first page,
which is still imperfect,
so you get feedback first,
and then you see what's missing.
I don't know,
it's a bit of an agile theory,
test early, test often.
You don't want
a product to be packed,
and then someone else does it,
and then you go out and see
what they're doing.
Then you try to do something
that's good enough
for the page to say,
OK, that's good,
that's good,
and then you decide
that there's a sequence
where you can support it,
and then send it to a page,
and then you support it in software,
and then you calibrate it,
and then, let's say,
once it's missing,
then it's time to visually
look at all the links in the program.
And then you decide
whether to send it all out,
or not.
You have to know the price
for a specific page.
That's not important.
It's more important that you can
test it a month in advance,
even if the picture isn't healthy.
Tomas, you're doing well,
but where do you cut corners?
On the router?
Huh?
Nowhere.
You haven't reached a financial peak.
No, because we're turning
into an investor's day,
so I don't know where to start.
No, we're practically
at our level,
because we're a startup,
and we're working on it
with two and a half people,
and we're practically
a fi-chip.
For those of you who don't know,
a fi-chip converts
network data
from electricity
into bits,
and we're a fi-chip.
It took a lot of time,
because the best
are considered by
Marvel,
but a gigabit Marvel chip
is $15 for a nobody
like me,
who starts from scratch
and almost orders a mouse.
It's $15,
and if you look around,
you see that Max Linear
bought the IP from Intel,
so Intel's fi-chips,
which have been in production for 20 years,
are like $0.80
versus $15.
But watch this,
what's worse
is that they have
better specifications
and more features
for $0.80 versus $15 from Marvel.
But Marvel has
this reputation,
so they're nothing better or worse
than Intel.
Branding.
And they all know each other.
I mean, I don't think
we need to compare with Ubisoft.
Not even close.
Not even 10-15 years.
But, you know,
because we're a nobody,
you see,
we have a frame that's not
as good as the one we have now,
and it's only 30%.
I don't know,
the price of a board is $60,
but the frame is higher.
For us, it's like this.
For example,
if you're measuring
why someone would take
a very thin resistor,
which is important
for measuring,
if you can calibrate it
and compensate it,
then you can,
for example,
make it darker.
Or similar,
you have these blocks
that are less thin.
In the end,
for the user,
the clock will be very thin,
because you will adjust it.
Or in electrotechnics,
we have this classic software
debouncing of buttons.
If you have a button,
if you press it,
if it doesn't have a capacitor,
it will blink a little,
and then in the software
you see how many times
the button has been pressed.
In the software,
the first time the button is pressed,
it's pressed every millisecond,
and there's one button.
Also, if you're measuring
the temperature at home,
and you're interested in 0.5°C,
then you need to measure
10,000 times per second
at 0.001°C.
I wouldn't be willing
to invest $100,000 for that.
It's important to be able to
measure through your ass,
how many times you can press a button.
Now I have a little spotlight
in front of the listeners
from your team.
Why DvSoft?
Not as a supplier,
but why would I,
as a partner,
invest in you,
instead of competitors?
That's a good question.
As I said before,
I personally believe
that our products are the best,
and that we have a big advantage
when it comes to both
hardware and software.
Let's go back to the example
that I like the most,
Apple.
If you work on both hardware and software,
you have more options
in your hands,
and you can optimize more things.
I don't know how the hardware
behaves, but if you have software,
you have a lot of options
to optimize it.
For example,
what we are better at
than our competitors,
is that a user
takes our hardware and
measures it.
It can be done very quickly.
For example, we just measured something,
and then again, when you
press a button,
you can see
the results.
It's very fast.
to do tests for cars.
I don't know, for example,
with competition you can
use it for a day or two, right?
For us, for example, for the same rites,
we used, I don't know, two hours
to be able to record all these things.
Because it's not software, I will say,
really, when we work together with partners,
I will say that it is,
in my opinion, the most user-friendly
of all softwares.
Then I will say,
a few more bonbons,
that we have easy resolution,
that we are more precise,
and that we are more precisely
synchronized as a competitor.
But I would say that,
yes, this whole thing,
one more big thing,
that with us you can really
measure everything,
and you have, I will say,
you also have, when you get data,
not only can you visualize
in thousands of ways,
but then you also have the opportunity
and then in the analysis
and you can decode
and analyze how the engine works,
you can, I don't know,
give FFT, because, for example,
with the competition it is so that
you have specialized programs
where you can, for example,
do only one of these things,
then you can export the data
to another program and do it there.
So, I will say,
we have the most user-friendly
software.
It's a bit weird, as you thought.
Otherwise, compared to others,
it pays extra for one more program.
Yes, yes, yes.
It is also the case that,
as you said, they are specialized
for one of these measures,
and you can get
from those sensors that we talked about,
you can get touch, you can get
some kind of camera, everything,
you can do a lot of things.
Now, these things,
which are also tricky,
because they are all over the world,
behind the Chinese firewall,
in the USA,
in Canada, which is also in the USA,
now, in the end,
they made it, right?
And now AlphaGornic Software made it,
and there are spaces there,
and it's been there for 10 years.
And how do you update it?
Does someone come with a USB key?
I mean, does it hurt a lot?
Yes, it really hurts.
Pleasant?
I mean,
as I told you,
in our industry,
there are also those
parties that are very careful
where they have those measures
that they do.
I mean, there have always been,
but there will always be this security problem.
And yes, it can happen
that these measures are made
entirely in some hall or building,
where there is no internet,
no wire,
and in fact,
no one has access to it.
I can tell you an anecdote
when I was a junior developer,
and I was on one side,
and I took the key,
and I said, OK, let's update it,
and I gave it to the computer,
and then, the whole panic,
they took the key from me,
and I didn't have the key in my hand anymore,
and I didn't give it back.
So it's very,
I'll say, yes, it's hard to update.
It's like, I'll say,
maybe it's a little different,
that on one side, where I'll say,
measures are being made,
a lot of decisions are made,
let's set an example,
that these measures are being made,
our scenario is being made,
I also know if there are any problems,
I know where the problems are,
I'll set an example.
And again, it depends.
There are also some,
I don't know,
and you, you don't even know
how to update it,
it's their thing,
we don't talk to you about it.
Interesting.
When we're talking about updates,
what do they do at the end of the cycle?
For example,
why does the machine work for 8 years,
and then stop?
Why doesn't the machine have to do something?
All the chips are,
let's say, silica,
and the plastic components
don't rot, I'd say.
Why can't this device
fly for 30 years?
You know what causes
aging of the electrical components,
which is death.
Heat?
Really, yes.
The more you make it,
the older the components get,
and over time,
their characteristics get worse.
It's always, over time,
worse,
and the lifespan of the components
is reduced.
So, I'd say,
in the end,
the lifespan is long.
As I mentioned earlier,
we have a 7-year warranty,
and it can only grow to,
I don't know, 15 years.
I don't want to
optimize it,
and say,
we want to make a 7-year warranty,
so we can do it for 8 years.
If I stop now,
then the other party,
who has a 17-year warranty,
will send me condensers.
I'd say the same.
Even if they have a 15-year warranty,
and it's not working,
they can still send me a series,
and if it works, I'll try to fix it.
The law.
Let's see,
if there's anything else.
What else do you do,
since you're not in the service?
Sorry, when are you not in the service?
I'm not in the service.
I'd say,
last year, my main hobby
is singing, if I'm honest.
I don't know,
I had so many other hobbies,
from, I don't know,
playing chess.
I played chess before.
I used to play swing,
but now I have less time.
I used to travel a lot.
That's still going on.
I'd say,
now that I have a small child,
the state of these worlds
is becoming more relaxed.
I might have a service,
an interesting trip.
I'd be like that boss,
who sends me around the world.
I don't need to be there,
I just need to be there.
That's great.
I'd say,
it's great that developers
have a website,
where you can
go to any website.
It's different
when you see your instruments
and software.
I don't know,
when you go to a shooting range
or a race track,
it's a different feeling.
Tell me,
are you shocked
when you see
this?
One thing that surprised me,
and it came out of nowhere,
is that I'm going to talk
about Vesovian genes.
A year ago, I found out
that they have these caves
with the first pictures in France.
You have pictures there,
and I don't know
if 100 people a year can visit
these caves.
You need permission to see it,
to protect yourself.
I was also surprised
by the environment
with our instruments.
For example,
I was also surprised
and I'm interested
in my next trip
to Disneyland.
They're already testing
some of our products.
They invited me to come
and see what their
back-end Disneyland looks like.
Free Disneyland.
I can hear that.
Are we going to have
hardware fairs in Slovenia
in the near future?
Because that means
we're going to spend
a lot of time at home.
I don't know.
I think we'll get more
when they have a bigger kitchen.
They have months of work.
Let's talk about months.
I think we're also
sponsors of the city of Slovenia.
We also include events
if we don't know
where the seeds are in the world.
And we also include them.
I also introduced
an instrument
that can be transported.
That's the difference
between the software industry
and the proper industry.
What?
Are we doing pick-ups?
We're doing pick-ups.
I have a question.
I have a suggestion.
You might say,
why didn't you ask me?
I studied that
you could ask
and you could answer.
But maybe we didn't.
I often get questions
about ADC transformers.
It's more interesting
because it's an interesting project.
Go ahead.
Plan B.
ADC is...
No, I know.
Isn't it a band?
Also.
ADC is a band?
ADC.
ACDC.
Oh my God.
No, it's not quantization.
Say something else.
Maybe one of my experiences.
A few years ago,
maybe it's also a part
of the Fellers' group,
we sold
to Nikola's company.
These are some cars.
They were making these engines
and they were making
what's it called?
Self-driving?
I think so.
I don't know what
the differentiation was.
We sold them some equipment
in bigger packages.
Then they put
the equipment together
in a more innovative way.
For example,
in Phoenix,
they made a test space
to test their engine.
Then they started the tests.
When they put it together,
nothing worked.
Again, it's an expensive thing.
I don't know how much it costs.
I think it's more than
$100,000 per day.
There was a panic.
Why doesn't it work?
I didn't work on it consciously.
Then they said,
OK, I made some of them,
then I said, David,
maybe you should go and see
what they think and solve this problem.
Then I said, OK, we'll buy a car.
We went together
and covered the whole space.
Then we put it together.
When I got it,
I still didn't know
if it would really work or not.
Fortunately, it worked.
Then we came to Phoenix.
Fortunately, we were young,
so it was only 40 degrees.
It was dry air.
I think it was so hot.
We came there
and somehow managed
to convince our local CS
to take care
of the main project manager.
The project manager
also looked very enthusiastic
that I wouldn't be able to do anything.
Even when we got there,
it was like this.
One screwdriver and 300 engineers
jumping around it.
Each one was screwing a small part.
We were there.
I was working there.
Every 3-4 hours
we had a time slot
of 5 minutes
in the creator's cabin
to try to debug
what he was doing.
The first thing
was that they connected
everything together.
Then they asked me
to do 2-3 things in the same combination.
Then I was working
in the same garage.
We were programming a bit.
It was quite interesting.
It was late at night.
We were programming.
We were testing
how it works.
We had 5 minutes to test
what works and what doesn't.
Then we repeated the cycle.
We were lucky
that we were also connected
to Slovenia.
I would say that those time zones
are very useful.
When Slovenians
finish their work,
they can start
the next day.
That combination worked well.
We were working
for 4-5 days a day.
It was interesting
because there were
Bosch engineers.
I think they were
from Chbk.
Everyone was flying around.
There was panic.
I don't know if you know
how it works.
You have to test
everything to see
how well it works.
It was also interesting
to see the results
and what they measured.
I think they were nervous
because of the panic.
We solved
the problem in 4-5 days.
In the end,
the project manager
was really satisfied.
He was surprised
and said
that we will start
with a project manager.
The manager
was a wonderful guy.
He said that he will
fix it in half a year.
We solved it in 5 days.
In the end,
everything worked out.
Maybe it was a walk around.
But in the end,
everything worked out.
It was a success story.
It was interesting.
It was an extreme challenge,
but it was interesting.
Do you know what was the problem?
They turned it off,
but they didn't turn it back on.
I had an idea
to make only 32.
They put together 45
and I constantly changed it.
But in the end,
it was in half a year.
I have one last question.
Are you ready?
Very important.
What is a grenadier march?
This will surprise me.
I will be very nervous.
I can tell you.
I will give you a correct answer.
Then I can tell you my opinion.
A grenadier march
is when you have
potatoes,
which is really good.
Then you have pasta.
I have a lot of pasta.
A grenadier march is
when you put it together
and you are worried
that the pasta is overcooked.
I found it.
Tomas thought it was a good kitchen.
It is.
I have to try it.
It is a speciality.
With a grenadier march
we end this episode.
Thank you all for listening.
Thank you David.
Thank you Tomas.
Thank you to our supporters.
See you next time.
Take care.
Bye.