In the next episode
Greetings, this is the third season, fourth season, fourth season, fourth, four, four.
Not four, three?
No, four, four.
Four, four.
Four, three?
No, four, three.
Ok, four, three.
All by one error.
Yes, all by one error.
Again, a slightly different episode.
This is a joke that we had in our hands,
where we are making some kind of connection.
Podcasts with beer makers,
and a podcast in the garden.
And then we said that this is a square versus a full square.
The idea is that, on the other hand,
lovers of technology and the law
have joined forces with beer makers,
and we, technology,
drink in the middle.
Now, one story with beer.
We decided last, I think, second season
to make a podcast with alcohol.
It's a no-go.
We have very poor experience,
so we decided to do it again.
Before we give you a talk,
to introduce yourself,
you have to tell us what you drank today.
What did I drink?
First, a disclaimer that the Minister of Health warns
that we should not drink alcohol.
Just one glass.
Oh, yeah.
You know what's inside.
Cheers to the Minister of Health.
I can tell you later,
that this disclaimer is really important.
It was a declaration of alcohol users.
Yes, I don't know if it's still a declaration,
but yes, especially for me.
I think we also have it as a podcast.
If you say that the garden is a hobby,
and then podcasting is a hobby,
I think you have to declare it as a hobby.
I don't think so.
But let's go back.
What we have here in the garden
is a former workbench.
It was a daily printer for work.
Now it's a tectonic brewery.
They also have their own brewery,
Tectonics.
Then they have beer,
which they brew here,
which they call open league,
which are smaller series,
or test series.
Today we have something ultra-special,
simply a black IPA,
black IPA,
which has 6.3 volumes of alcohol.
The photo was brought to us
by the owner of the brewery.
And that's it.
Nothing special.
I wanted to take goats and sheep,
but they said they didn't have
enough beer for that many people.
So I was like, okay,
give us something to drink.
So that's it.
Are we recording now?
How do you two start?
First of all,
long live Žiga.
And long live Andraža.
Yes, long live Andraža.
We are Petar and Žiga,
two goats,
because I'm Petar,
and he's a goat.
We're doing a podcast,
P na Kvadrat,
where Andraž talks about
our technological favorite topics
and law,
law and technology,
and, of course, beer.
Because we handle alcohol,
not the podcast.
So that's what we do.
And as a colleague from FACS,
I'm an advisor to Žiga,
and CryptoSveto.
What do you do, Žiga?
I'm a kind of an operations lead
at Block Analytica,
and we work on various solutions
for the field of financial
investment,
so deep in the financial world.
That's it.
So,
is it a pure
kind of law?
Is it a sub-category?
Is it very narrowly
directed?
Yes, I think
the law is very divided.
If you start from the very beginning,
very technically,
theoretically,
there are probably a few areas,
economic, civil, legal, and so on.
Then you have the majority,
and I don't know how you
divide it in the office,
but you also have the industry,
where you cover more areas.
So you can say,
for example, that you deal
with pharmaceuticals,
then everything from IP
to international agreements,
to health regulation,
and so on.
That's how I would say.
It's something you probably
have to learn by yourself,
but it's not something
that the faculty gives you.
No, no.
It's the same as for us.
I mean, through practice and work.
Front-end, back-end,
DevOps, SRE,
and so on.
Whether you do CRM,
streaming,
various fun scientific videos,
or other problems.
That's it.
Software, hardware,
no very informatica.
No very informatica, yes.
We are electronics.
Anyway, let's first say hello.
Welcome,
let's say,
to the creation of a joint podcast.
Let's say hello.
A quick greeting.
I hope the mic is working.
Good stuff.
How is it?
Fantastic.
I must admit,
I'm not a big fan of black pears,
because they are too sweet.
But black apples are great,
because you have a dark soul,
but at the same time
it's very tasty,
because it's an apple.
It's more ethical.
Yes, this is great.
Not too bitter,
good for the body.
Shall we start?
Let's start.
Everyone in the city,
when they see
that we are starting a podcast,
they say,
why are you doing this?
I don't know,
how did you start it,
for a long time,
or did you feel
the need
to share
with others?
I'm a classic man of fair podcast,
you feel like a man who needs it.
Your opinion is the most important thing in the world.
It started
when we went to Pyr,
near Tektonik.
I was a teacher there,
but I didn't take it seriously,
because I drank too much,
then I suffered,
and then I thought
about Tektonik.
I don't know,
when we were at Pyr,
it wasn't just a debate
about home, work, etc.
We talked about legal and technological issues,
and we thought
it would be fun to do a podcast.
That was the start.
Then we started
to progress,
and now
relatively well.
It's been a month and a half or two,
because we are both awake.
And now
you have
a community
of colleagues
who are in the same field,
enthusiasts who follow you.
I would say yes.
What I really like
about this podcast format is
that you don't have to
look for feedback.
If people don't come,
they comment.
For example, what you do,
you have Discord,
which is great,
because you have more debate
and more personality.
But yes,
I think we have some good listeners,
everyone who gets feedback.
Of course, the feedback
was via e-mail,
or also on the street,
or business-wise.
Like, hey, Zančevi is a good podcast.
Yes, it's more like that.
E-mail is pretty rare.
I don't know how many people
want to record with him.
No, not you.
But that's more for
after podcast.
No, but I want to say
that he is alive,
I don't know what his colleagues
are doing, if I'm not mistaken.
He told me, hey,
I listen to it very well,
and it's interesting to listen
to my lawyers,
and IT people.
You get what you have,
those two extremes.
It's like a cross between them.
Yes, it's interesting
when someone you don't expect
says, hey, it's a good podcast.
And you listen to it.
Our story is
very similar.
At some point,
in the coworking,
one of our
voice actors
had a coffee,
and then the first episode
came out.
And we put it out.
With what purpose?
And then we talked about it.
But is it like that
in the legal circles?
Where are the lawyers?
At the meet-ups.
Was it like
the first shift
and you had to change
which side you had the most problems with?
How does it look like?
At the meet-ups,
there are different events,
and those variants,
for example, the 19th school
in April.
The older you are,
the more fun it is to see your colleagues from FACS.
Those events,
I don't know,
different conferences,
those are the closest
to a meet-up.
And you have more of a crypto meet-up.
Yes, I was
coming from the point of view
that podcast is a good way
to translate
serendipity
in English.
It's a bit random,
but you get into it
and realize that maybe someone
will come to me with the same interests.
Maybe I will meet someone
and he will teach me something
and I will learn something from him.
It's similar to a meet-up,
but there is too much
one-way communication.
When it comes to meet-ups,
there are not that many.
I don't know,
conferences are more like
very professional events.
I think that in the developer world,
there is a lot of it.
You can show your solutions.
Yes, we are more like middle schoolers.
All of my colleagues
from FACS
are more or less the same age as me,
but I think that there is always
someone higher up on the podium.
There can't be a meet-up.
There are a lot of things
that can't be shared.
And now we are going to show
how we solved it.
Yes, we are very confident about it.
Does it help
to be transparent?
It depends
on the context.
For example,
transparency.
Most of the meetings
are publicly announced.
It's a legal debate
whether to publish
all the meetings
publicly.
I think that
it's not a problem for the society.
It's not digitalized.
For example,
when people talk about AI,
where do you first scan
all the data?
So that it can be shared.
Transparency
would help
the society
to understand
how the sausage is made.
What's going on behind the scenes?
Why do some things
last as long as others?
That's my biggest criticism.
Why does it last so long?
Because you have some hands.
For example,
you have 30 days to answer
a question.
If you haven't answered
in 30 days,
you can answer in 45 days.
It's logical
to give people time
to prepare.
Is this time
used up?
Do we have a buffer
to take this time?
Are we so busy
that the government
thinks that they are
taking their time?
Is there so much backlog
that they can't
share everything?
That's my question.
It depends on the court.
Some have so much backlog
that they don't follow it.
I think that the court
has a lot of backlog.
Some courts have to solve
the backlog.
That's one aspect.
The other aspect is
the rules.
You have 30 days
to answer a question.
If they put you in jail
on 100 pages,
you'll get a fine.
But most things
are simple.
You can answer
in advance.
But the organization
and the court
work in triage.
You don't have to do it first.
I like that.
It's the same for me.
I think that people
go to the court
or to the health center
and ask to open the file
and see the backlog.
You work in triage anyway.
If you're in jail and you don't do 5 things,
what will you do first?
We have the advantage
that there is
mostly a digital background.
There is very little
physical image in a paper
or in a magazine.
That's why we don't know how to write.
I agree.
People always carry it in a suitcase.
Yes, in a suitcase.
It's physical,
but it's written communication.
I don't know how many of you
have the experience.
Theoretically,
it's possible
to insert an electronic decision.
It's so difficult
that it's easy to print and insert.
It wouldn't be a UX designer
to check it
because of the simplicity.
You don't have to click
for every file you upload.
Then you have a ruler
that tells you that every application
has to be a selected file.
Then you have this application
that tells you the date,
click, sign,
and so on.
I uploaded a vlog for 5 hours
and I had to insert
at least 200 files.
In such situations,
I print and insert.
It's easier for me.
Is it a web interface?
Yes, it is.
Why didn't you decide
to offer it?
It would be nice if I offered it.
In general,
if there was
a digitization
of the legal system,
would it help
or solve
something?
Would it speed up
the process?
I can tell you
that recently
I was at an event
where there was
a meeting
in which 10 pages
of the meeting
could be submitted
to the court.
The court had to copy
the meeting.
I uploaded it physically,
but then I ordered a USB key
that I brought to the court
in ODT format.
I already clicked
so that it wouldn't be you.
It was very nice.
If there was an electronic system
in which 10 pages could be printed
by hand,
it would be helpful.
Now we solved it.
I'm glad
that the whole country
is talking about digitalization
and AI.
You can have data first.
If you don't have
digitalized data,
what does AI help you with?
I will pull it out of my pants.
I will hallucinate
when I see this room
from 10 years ago.
We will talk about these topics
on the podcast.
I like the gaming geeky topics
the most.
I'm happy to hear
that you are involved.
I learn things from him.
I don't understand this world.
He does.
I'm interested in
crypto
and how it can be
regulated.
And then
it comes into the game.
In the sense of
working on the side of regulation
or protecting
the end users.
What are
the biggest legal challenges?
I think it's everything.
Maybe it's interesting
that America is going in a different direction.
With Trump.
My personal opinion is
that it can be very good or very bad.
We will see in the next
mandates.
In Europe, we went
to regulate everything
with stable coins
and so on.
I think
there are more things
that can be done legally.
You can be on the side of regulators
or companies that
allow you to
break through
the mess of regulations.
Plus, to not run into
something else.
You have some financial regulation
depending on the decision you make.
I've been in this since 2017
and at that time
there were a lot of things
that were not clear.
I don't think
that more or less
work has been done.
Do you think we are moving
to a better direction?
I mean, if you
manage the work
in the same way,
is it changing to a better direction?
Yes, I would say so.
Because
you have a clearer picture
of what is possible and what is not.
At that time, we were just doing something new.
It was similar to this and similar to that.
You could see the evil.
You relied on
things that were similar.
I don't know,
you approached regulators,
you approached other industries
and nobody could tell you anything.
Now you have a framework
that you can stick to.
Now you have to make an assessment yourself.
Does it fall apart?
Are you regulated?
It seems to me that
crypto is so specific that
there are still
a lot of things that are not regulated.
Although they have already been regulated a lot.
There are still
European NFTs.
It is regulated.
Meme coins.
The whole decentralized finance system
is also very dependent.
So, yes.
As you mentioned
EU versus Europe.
I would say that
in Europe,
we are going to regulate everything.
We are going to set some laws
for all areas.
And then
some
breakthrough in Europe
with technological fairs
or some
knowledge.
Some start-ups would create
a lot of things.
It seems to me that
this regulation is pushing us
to start outside of Europe.
How do you see this?
Is it too deep
for a start?
No, it is not too deep for a start.
I also ask myself
these questions.
If we go straight to MICO,
the regulation for cryptocurrencies,
in defense of regulation,
for example,
is better.
If you are a member of a state,
and you are in the
Crypto Asset Service Provider,
then you know
that it will be the same in the whole EU.
Similarly,
for financial instruments,
you sell shares or whatever.
If you are licensed in one state,
you can also passport
to another state.
Which is great,
because you have a bigger market
and you can do it easily.
Of course, it is difficult
if the regulation is too fast
without...
I would say that it is not too fast
for crypto, but for example
for AI-Activ,
which is potentially
enchanted.
With AI-Activ,
it is still a risk-based system.
What we want and what we don't.
For example, it is already limited
that AI will not be able
to make a decision.
Thank God!
In the US, there are garbage-in-garbage-out
problems,
which were used
to determine what is the maximum penalty.
Ten years ago,
some EU systems
were taking more penalties.
Why? Because the data was like that.
I don't know.
I am not interested in it.
There is still a dilemma
whether the EU is a unicorn or not.
Yes, in the US it is.
It is a different
side of the debate.
What does it mean for the economy
as a whole?
I would say that the average quality of life
in the EU is still much higher than in the US.
Will unicorns solve it or not?
But yes, I agree.
Maybe it is because
most people
with
better
and higher
income
are less connected
to the EU.
Maybe.
Yes, maybe.
I don't know.
I think it is a bit difficult
because the biggest
technology
like Spotify,
Skype, etc.
We have SAP,
and the exception
is ASML.
It is a huge capitalization.
I think we are like that.
In Europe and the US we have two different approaches.
They are like
risk on, leverage,
we employ thousands of people
and even if they disappear in a day, it is OK.
In Europe we are like
ten people a year,
then ten more,
then a bank loan.
I think we should
regulate
more in Europe,
more risk on
in the US.
How to change it?
We could be a bit
behind.
But
how can you be behind
if you don't have capital,
if you don't have a data system?
and then, of course, those who are more inclined to go to America,
those who are not, maybe, well, let's give Europe a credit.
They have a lot of
don't ask for permission,
ask for forgiveness,
which is also indicated by the AI,
they have parsed the whole internet.
Yes, yes.
And what about that?
It would be ironic for me
if this OpenAI
criticized DeepSeek
that they violated their copyright
and I thought, oh, really?
But
I, for example,
GDPR,
which is a public organization in the field of personal data,
they criticize it a lot,
but a lot of developers, I know,
who criticized it, I would like this project to be
based on personal data, okay, I agree,
but the logic is
privacy by design, that you start
with a privacy mindset.
But when I look at what's going on in America,
I see that, for example,
a phone number, God forbid,
you give it to any company,
because you're just robocalling
in the dark,
while in Europe,
I mean, GDPR, and then you have
European Electronic Communications Code,
IECC, which conducts this robocalling,
and I think,
well, maybe I wouldn't be in this dystopian world
if I lived in America.
So, yes, it's a trade-off,
but, for example,
I don't know about GDPR,
but there was an article
that said, for example,
that a long time ago,
Target,
this pharmaceutical company,
was so happy
that they were expecting
something like
prenatal vitamins,
where they said that
their daughter was buying
things that indicated
that she was probably pregnant.
I've never heard anything like that.
Is it still a problem
that when you say something,
you get a response like that?
Well, I don't know,
they could have said
that all certain things
in Europe
are too complicated,
and then, actually,
they could have said
that it's an IT thing,
and that it makes no sense
to re-engineer it.
I don't know,
the Cookie Directive,
I mean, what have we achieved
with it?
In a way, it works
like job security.
All those who sold something,
now got it back.
We need this feature,
so everyone can sell it back.
It's a fucking annoyance.
Yes, and also,
with the Cookie Directive,
I don't know how much
they've spent on it,
but it's a different story.
For the Cookie Directive,
I don't know,
I don't see the point anymore.
The best thing is when it's
optimized for the phone,
and then you try to watch it.
But, for example,
one thing,
we mentioned scraping,
which is a different view
for public data.
You have the Open Data Directive,
which, according to the law,
means that information is public,
because public entities
store certain data,
in machine readable formats.
The logic is that
what the state has collected
from some useful information,
which may have commercial purposes,
everyone can access it.
Then there's regulation,
which means that it's possible
that someone will get
all the data from a bus driver,
and someone will develop a solution
to optimize it.
So, I don't know.
In the US, there's also
something terrible with public data.
We're not that far behind
in terms of digitalization.
And, for example,
what you mentioned,
the passporting of financial data
works much better in Europe
than in the US.
All those providers,
crypto exchanges, payment providers,
have to go state-by-state
and get licensed
before you can get married.
In fact, the barrier to entry
in the US for some services,
which are regulated
at the state level, is very, very low.
And it's better here in Europe.
So, I think
we've probably reached some breakthrough.
You can go to the whole market
very quickly.
In some areas, we're a bit
too predictable.
Maybe we should
limit it to the end,
because Terminator will come out differently.
Will it be that fast or not?
That's the question.
I think it's hallucinating even more.
In my opinion,
if you get to know
how things work in the US,
I often think
that everything is very liberal.
The Big Eagle flies around
and says,
they didn't hire me.
Why not?
I'm the only one in that state.
They didn't pay for that state
out of all those papers
to hire only me.
If you're from Nevada,
you'll work in California,
and then in Nevada,
there are only
Las Vegas developers.
That's it.
I don't work there.
I don't drink alcohol
in the US.
Most people tell us
to buy whiskey from Germany.
I've been to
the Cannabis Business Conference
in Slovenia,
where I met
people from Canada and the US.
Marijuana is fully legal there,
but not on a federal level.
Their biggest challenge
is to switch
from one US state to another.
Especially if the US
doesn't agree.
It's a federal shipping
and on a federal level
it's still legal.
Their interaction
between the US and the US
is very confusing.
The EU still has its problems,
but it has to follow
its own rules.
You can't have
a local police
and an interstate police
on a different level,
while they can arrest you
or arrest you
in a different way.
For us, Europeans,
it's very confusing.
I'm interested in
if you can go from Croatia
to Portugal without
checking your passport
and roaming.
Data roaming is a great thing.
I'd say we know
what happened in the past.
I think many young people
are convinced
that everything is worth it.
There was nothing
better than everything.
If you go to England,
they'll tell you
that one megabyte is 10 euros.
Please,
just open the data
and you'll see
that it's 300 euros.
What has the EU
done for us?
Nothing.
Maybe that's it.
There are too few
of these things.
We've decided
on one thing
with the EU,
and we've made it
a common denominator
that everything is better.
Not that everything is bad,
but when I started
with IT,
it looked like
we really can't
make any progress in Europe.
It's easier to open a company
in Delaware in America
and start something there.
Sometimes,
I think everything is
a general world.
Maybe we shouldn't
be afraid of the EU regulations.
I think many of these things
are media-driven.
You open a website
or a magazine
and they show you
a list of regulations
and you're like,
wow,
what is this?
If you're a layman,
you think
there's a lot of this,
but I think
a lot of companies
fall out of this,
including IT.
In some episodes,
a lot of companies
are very regulated,
but very few are not.
We have a bunch
of irrelevant things
that I could probably
cut out,
but there are also a lot of things
that don't fall under.
They are placed in the media,
various
subcontracting agencies,
legal agencies,
and maybe
you just need to go
to the world to explain
what you need and what you don't.
Don't be afraid of this, be afraid of that.
Sometimes you will be afraid
if you don't know
what's going on.
I mean, sometimes
it turns out that
for certain things
it's better
to pay a fine
when you weren't
prepared enough,
or too little,
or you didn't give
everything you had,
or you said
that it's not as easy
as it sounds.
I would say
that it's not that hard
to regulate.
If we look at IT,
a start-up,
four colleagues
working on a company,
they are all changed.
What you put on paper,
you will have to deal with
for a long time,
and it can be more difficult
than with regulation.
In my experience,
it's more difficult
with regulation
than with everything else.
Especially if you have a lot of money,
because sometimes you say
that you gave this,
but you didn't give that.
I compare a start-up
to a band.
When a band is formed,
it's very fast.
Who wrote the lyrics,
who did the arrangement,
who did the music.
With a start-up,
it's the same logic.
You can change it
on Friday,
on Saturday,
on Sunday,
on Monday,
when you are a friend,
when you are not a friend.
That's good wisdom.
That's the best.
When you mentioned
regulation,
it's one of two things.
One interesting thing
that will probably
affect everyone,
at least someone who is
self-employed,
because they sell
their equipment
in a critical
infrastructure.
That's why
they can be
regulated
in accordance with that.
Everyone who is outsourced.
There are a lot of them.
There is also Doro,
which is an arrangement
for the financial sector.
I've already heard
that they started
sending it to SP
and SP programmers.
Most of them are SP.
They are outsourced
and they have to...
These are strict conditions,
like the right of audit,
so they can check everything.
On one hand, it's logical,
because if a bank
has an outsourced SP,
they don't have to
check all the sensitive data.
There are a lot of financial institutions,
unfortunately.
They provide a cloud
with two-factor access.
Yes, absolutely.
But I don't know.
You are a security expert.
No, no.
Once we were in a beer,
there was a debate
that those who
operate as a company
should come here
as someone who is alone.
Because the cost
for them is not too high.
And then again,
the question is
will only the big players
survive?
Or will the small ones
start working in some shops
or in some firms?
I don't know,
but the question is
with the SPs,
who will start thinking
about joining the DOO?
Then you can go in that direction.
If you have a few colleagues
in a shop,
then you can start a firm
and sell your equipment that way.
I was thinking in that direction.
With every regulation,
what's the point?
For example,
for critical infrastructures,
I would...
If we give an absurd example,
if someone works
as an outsourcer
or a developer,
I would be happy
to have a security protocol.
Because I know so much
about IT security developers
that everyone thinks differently.
And to have a developer
with security,
I don't know,
it's impossible.
Yes, it's true,
but I would say
that all these things
are getting worse.
Also,
20 years ago,
when we were still
working on Balkan-related things,
someone said
let's hire him
to work on critical infrastructures.
I think we gave it a chance.
It's better,
but still,
it's likely
that it won't happen.
I've already said
that someone
on their personal computer
is probably storing data
that would be classified
for trust or something like that.
Yes, or user access control.
In some companies,
everyone has access
to everything,
and when someone new comes,
he has everything on video.
It seems to me
that when you work in IT,
you look at these
various controls
on various security standards,
and then you download it,
and you're like,
these are really stupid controls
that tell you the password
must be greater than 12 digits.
Thank God that we have
these regulations,
because it's the minimum standard.
It's impressive
how many people,
a year or two ago,
we had some written debates
where we were two-factor
about what we already had.
It wasn't such an important system,
but we were like,
why are we still using two-factor systems?
I mean, you already log into every bank
with two-factor systems.
In my opinion,
Slovenia contributed a lot
to the fact that security
and two-factor authentication
were used.
I wouldn't say banks,
I would say scammers
and this kind of crime
contributed to the fact
that so many people
suffered that it became
such a serious problem
that banks wanted
to improve their users.
It could be an indie band.
Scammers.
I still think that
we will never solve
social engineering.
When you hack
a person
and he gives you all the access
because he thinks
he can give you something bad,
that's the worst thing.
It's pure human psychology,
how to
actually...
You don't have to think
how to hack.
It's just about
what kind of attitude
you will have towards the person,
that you will gain someone's trust
or in a smart way
so that the feedback
on the other side will be better.
So, in times
like
long, long time ago
when those companies
had those doors,
like today,
sometimes it was just
because you had
a bad day
and you wished
a good day,
you went over the fence.
Or just because
you know exactly
where you are going
and you don't need help,
they told you
it's a psychological trap.
And I don't know
if we will ever solve it.
Because today
I think
a lot of people have a problem
because they don't know
how to talk to AI.
They already know that.
Yes, that's a big problem.
How to talk to AI.
I don't know.
There are a lot of people
who don't have it.
Because I already know
that it's such a specific problem
that they don't have it inside.
Just give me a chat.
I don't know.
I understand why it's happening
because there are a lot of people
but when I know that it's a specific problem
there is no chance
that the answer will be given.
From our point of view
is it better than getting
an index on the other side?
Yes.
We had a lot of experiences
when we called someone
and we were friends.
More and more companies in Slovenia
have AI chatbots.
I recently had a very interesting
experience with emails.
I wanted to check where
they sent me a package
that they didn't send me.
And just with the number of the package
the email gave me all the data.
And I was like
as much as possible
I could have my neighbor
or someone else get it from the email.
I was talking to the bot
on the other side of the phone
and I was like
ok, interesting.
He recognized everything I said.
So I was like
ok, we definitely made
a jump here.
But the security
bothered me a bit.
The problem is
with the package.
When we were in the IT department
someone sent me a chatbot
on the GPT platform.
The problem was
that developers said
that they have limited data
that they can send.
They can't just send it
without someone getting
the price of the product.
That was a real dilemma.
If that chatbot
gives you the price of a product
you can buy it
but the price will be different.
That's problematic.
And if you have a company
and they give you a fake price
you can't do anything.
I understand that developers
can't just jump
but they will go to the company
and you will tell them
that this laptop costs 200 euros
and he offers it for 200 euros.
I want it for 200 euros.
So, yeah.
Oh, so they sent you a contract.
You can always say that.
Yeah, yeah.
I think it's okay to say that.
There have been cases
where the market inspector
told them off.
A couple of companies
already had problems
with the pricing
so they bought it
but the market inspector
didn't do anything.
It's an interesting balance.
I think there are also
certain problems
with very small
releases.
For example,
this car model
costs 12,000 euros
and they have 3 cars like that
and the rest are for additional equipment.
It's a lot of money
in a way.
Our market inspector does not fuck around.
I mean, he knows how to be more active
and also to sell more.
I think that
there have been enough
cases where
it was necessary to
make a decision.
Yeah, and that's probably
the difference between the USA and Europe.
For example, in Slovenia
not only because of
the time limits
but also because of
private enforcement.
For example, in Slovenia
we rely on law enforcement
because in that way
I can sue them.
But for me it would be difficult
because I don't know how much time
I would need for that.
Unless I'm a lawyer
I would worry a lot.
And maybe
in the USA
the regulatory bodies
are doing something.
At the moment, no.
It's more like
I'm going to sue.
There is also a difference
because in the USA there are
financial damages
that are not in Europe.
It's not only the value
but also the damages.
If you have a loss
or a loss of income
in the USA
there are also punitive damages.
Millions and millions.
In Slovenia, even less.
The first association was
the competition clauses
that have defined
contributions.
The competition clause
with a big contribution
that in Europe
doesn't drink water.
Yes.
The competition clause
and the punishment
if you break it.
You all know
there is always more.
At the end of the day,
it's a punishment
if someone
washes the windows.
The competition clause
it's hard to get a lot of knowledge.
No.
The developer is
doing something
that doesn't have
a lot of knowledge.
You said before
that you could
go to court
because you know
that the overhead is not that big.
I don't know
because I do other things.
But then I thought
that the programmers
ask us
what is the fear
that you will go to court.
What about you?
I mean, I can write
that I will go to court.
How do you look at it?
I write
but I don't say that I don't.
Although there is a lot of language in Slovenian
which is very
American, native, rich
and I don't know
of course, but OK.
For the court
I am also
I've heard that there are already some cases on the court that seem to have been written down.
I think they will be closed soon.
Because, for example, in a case you have to structure the requirements of the part,
when the plaintiff does not pay so much and so much.
Aha, there was a prompt.
Yes, there was a prompt.
And there is a very rigid rule of how it can be composed.
Or, well, this one has to pay, that one is even simpler.
But when you have a case for a more complex case,
there we are also in the office, double-checking, triple-checking with colleagues,
and he drinks water for you.
Because it is a very formal logic and for that AI for now, no fucking way.
But yes, I don't know.
I'm just worried there, because, you know,
everyone can be a little connected to it, but how to fuck them up, right?
So I will always need AI for the diagnosis of my medical condition.
Sure.
Okay, we will apologize for this problem.
Well, actually, I also heard from a medical colleague
that with a very well-described prompt,
or what he understood from the patient,
he got a very good answer,
in which direction to think ahead, or what could be.
That's right.
So maybe in that direction, some analysis,
or in that direction that, I don't know,
you will assign a stream of medical records, or a case,
and he will, you know, pull out a digest and say,
this is where this came from, or be aware of that.
I don't know. Think about it.
Yes, I think it is very similar to developers.
If you know the whole topic, then somehow the field, the area,
on which you then send 4GPT or whatever AI model to work,
it is a great combination.
If you are a pure layman, and you put something in it,
and the result goes a little in one direction,
you don't know, you don't know how to logically combine it,
or check the result.
By itself, this is very weak.
So maybe this entry level,
for an entry level person,
this is a bit of a weak barrier,
plus competition.
It seems to me that,
maybe we are in a situation where, I don't know,
if I didn't teach my child right now,
the question is,
would I teach them software development?
Yes, maybe a little more, I don't know.
In my opinion, the main problem,
for us juniors, for us preparers,
this will be the biggest problem.
Because when I work,
if there was a spiritual task at the time,
where there was this x-structure,
then there is this x-structure,
and if it is quite simple,
you just can't deal with it,
because it does some other things,
then you give it to a junior,
and then you sit down for 2 days,
it goes in the right direction,
it doesn't go in the right direction,
it's like that for 3 minutes,
and then it just writes like that.
I think that this entry level position
will be in the software,
and there will be even more of this gap.
I said the same thing,
how can you be a senior developer,
if you are not a junior?
For us writers,
when I started 10 years ago,
as a preparer,
most of the changes we made,
and this is normal,
because for a lot of changes,
if you write anything in front of a notary,
then you have to register in Slovenian,
most of the examples,
I don't know, a group of Germans,
and they don't speak English,
and then you have to translate.
Google Translate already existed,
and it was relatively good,
and if you compare it now,
it was really good.
But we are still very satisfied,
we are very, very satisfied,
yesterday at 9 o'clock,
we published it,
tomorrow at 12 o'clock,
we sign it,
100 pages,
I don't know how many people
translated it,
in all the writers,
in Slovenia,
they did it like that.
Now it's less people,
AI, Google Translate,
you still have to check it,
and yes,
it's more fun,
and I see that
more people are using
AI tools,
so it can be more fun stuff.
But yes, absolutely,
to know what to ask,
is very important.
I also use some GPT models
for legal research,
but I know exactly what to ask,
and I know exactly,
because sometimes,
I don't know,
I don't know what to say.
But I think
it's possible to
draw a prompt,
to put clear enough
names, what to answer,
I mean,
to train yourself.
I already tried
to give the whole text of the law,
because I couldn't find the link,
I don't know why,
I gave the text of the law in Word,
uploaded it,
and I saw the text of the law,
and I thought,
if it's not in this text,
then it's not in the law.
I mean,
I used it a lot
for Visual Basic programs,
to write it in Word,
it's great for these things,
but it's a low-level
programming,
you can't find it online,
but instead of looking for it,
I write it down and it works.
For these things,
as I know, you said,
for these simple things, it's great,
but if it's more, you need to know
and understand all these things.
That's it.
When you looked at
Open Source licensing
for these
large language models,
what does it mean?
Is it really
Open Source,
where you can see
how the model was learned,
or
are things a bit
distorted?
I didn't look into it.
You did.
I would like
to say
that you lived here.
It's very common for me,
in public debates,
open source
solutions,
or Open Source software,
in the beginning,
no matter how you
translate it,
it means that
the code is public,
everyone can check it,
and most of the licenses
come with a lot of freedom.
You can take it,
distribute it, modify it,
if you deserve
your annual income
to exceed 1 million euros,
you can ask us explicitly
for a license.
But that's not the case
in Open Source software,
or the licenses that
these organizations recognize as open source.
We have the classic MIT,
that's huge.
When you look
and talk about
open source models,
there are some models
that you have to pull down,
that are some kind of a burden,
maybe an explanation
of how the circus learned it.
But there are some skills
inside.
It's very interesting
to look at the scraps,
licenses,
and all those solutions.
And then there's the hint,
if you're an average Joe in Slovenia,
or a physical person,
it's not a problem.
But there are those
that you can use,
but if you're a direct competitor,
then no.
How are we going to do it?
You can't distill it.
You can't take
the information from that model
and re-license it
with something else.
I think it's harder
to clean open.
It's very good marketing,
but then there's the problem
that people think
that if you take it all together,
you can't take it all
with you.
It's like taking
a different terminology.
Basically, it's like this.
If Lama or Meta
have a license,
they have the right to
release it as it is.
But it's hard to call it open,
even though I know that
certain open source licenses
have some limitations.
You have a lot of things
when you do technical due diligence,
to see if it's open source
so that you can see
what it's really worth
and what value it gives you.
You have to prepare it all night
and decide if you can
take it out or not.
I'm not sure about that,
but it's interesting.
Marketing.
How did you look at those licenses?
Is it interesting to you?
We, the programmers,
click on them.
Like EULA.
You scroll down
and press accept.
I've already written about EULA.
It's a company
where we also put
half of the distilling inside.
It's interesting to me
how enforceable it is.
You also have
intellectual property.
You have copyrights,
copyrights, patents,
and database rights,
which a lot of people don't know.
If you scrape those
on the internet,
if you don't break the copyright,
you'll break their database rights.
If you put a database together,
it's like
in Bollywood,
SQL base or whatever,
it's a database right,
and you can't...
It has a value,
a phone number.
I would say,
I took only one part out of it.
Did you break it,
or do you say
that when you put it all together,
you break it because
someone made a catalog?
Most of the time,
we talk about the whole thing,
but there's also
public data,
phone numbers,
but you structured it,
and that's why it has a value.
For example,
you have a website
with a list of
car accidents.
We'll talk about that later.
If I made a decision
to break the database,
and then do something else,
you want to say
that it's not OK.
It's not OK,
plus there's another difference
when it comes to the interactivity
of the database,
and that's Terms of Use
on the website.
If you make a website
for Terms of Use,
it's convenient,
and it probably says
that you can't break it.
But for distillation,
I was thinking about
how technical the problem is.
The first time I heard
about this concept,
I was like,
you can't make a better model
on the basis of that.
But technically,
it was done with DeepSea.
I think it's more about
price-performance.
You don't need all of that,
and maybe it's a bit weak,
but in the end,
it doesn't cost half a billion dollars
to learn it,
and it's not that shady,
but it's still a good price
when you invest in it.
That's how I understood it.
No, no, no,
I just agreed that
you can't do that,
and I was like,
I don't know how,
but it's a part of it.
That's an additional question
about how many lawyers
you have,
and where you can
look at something
to see if it's technically
correct or similar,
or if you're not
on the same page,
and that's it.
Yes.
You always need to know
the actual situation.
No one can explain it to you,
you just have to look at it.
If you just look at the situation
and say, yes, it looks great,
the actual situation is something else.
So, the cooperation
with the technical staff
is always necessary.
You can't just
go to your office
and write it down and say,
that's it.
This is the beginning
of the isopressure.
Everything is on paper.
Yes.
How practical
is the question,
because I've been
to companies
where everything
went well
with the contract,
but it didn't reflect the actual situation.
Or did it reflect
the actual situation of the moment
when the contract was shown,
and they said, yes,
let's fix it and move on.
The auditing period
starts the next Monday,
and then you come back
and you have to wait
and then you come back.
But, yes, it's according to the standard.
But, also according to the standard,
our sponsors are on paper.
Ah, yes.
So, we're on paper now.
So, now Andras
is pleasantly hinting
that we should thank
our sponsors,
Human Frog, V-Nect, Kaldi,
and Kufr for the space
they give us for the recordings.
And, of course, Patreon,
who have already created
this episode.
Reptenica.
If we try in Grodje,
we can do it in Reptenica.
No, in Grodje, they only support themselves.
Ah, yes.
Makes sense.
It's complicated.
People are like, how many times
have you had this in Grodje?
And I'm like, no, it's a framework,
it's logical.
I interrupted you on purpose.
Amata is watching,
because she doesn't know the question.
We were like, she's not interested,
he is.
No, I think it's a good point.
I don't know, what worries me the most
are the people
of the legal part of their job.
It's always...
For me, it's like...
I'm always like...
I work for a client,
and I work for a client.
And it's a job,
when you work for 15 years,
and you have a lot of risks,
and you have a lot of agreements,
and I have some patterns of those agreements,
that I worked with the legal team,
and I took other agreements,
and I was like, why does it say
that there must be access to the toilet?
And I was like, maybe I won't give it.
Or, for example, in a war,
maybe I won't call it,
I won't give it either.
And those things,
then you try to make some patterns,
but everything you said,
I have good manuals,
so we never argue,
and those agreements are never challenged.
But what worries me the most
is always like, hey,
now we have this hobby project,
and it's some kind of Buddhist app.
What is the minimum standard
if I make an application
and someone else uses it
with my colleagues and my family?
And that's something
that I'm like,
do I have to have a password?
Do I have to have GDPR?
Do I have to collect data?
That's one thing
that I'm like,
okay, what is the minimum standard?
And I hope that I'm like,
or I copied it,
because I'm a programmer.
Or plain text.
I think that's the top one
from the shooting range
for me.
You're probably going to take
an American one,
and you're going to ride that wave
as long as you don't get caught.
Yeah, I do a lot of things
for the Americans,
but a lot of my colleagues
are more German engineers,
so they're like,
what do I have to do?
What is the worst thing
that can happen to you
in this job?
And then you say, okay,
that's a thousand euros of damage.
It's hard to imagine
all the possible examples.
Not a thousand euros of damage,
but a life.
A life that's in danger.
Okay, let's not go there.
I'm just doing a side job.
I started automatics and robotics.
Terms of use is fine,
but you need to know
that you're not being scraped
or robbed.
Do I need to write
who's behind it?
Am I an SP or DOO?
Do I need to write
that I'm a DOO?
It's probably written in...
I don't know if it's translated
or not.
I don't think you can see
a DOO for an SP.
I don't know if the registrar
writes you who's behind it.
No, but if
you need to
go to an organ
or a court,
they can ask the registrar.
You can hear it until
you destroy the door.
It depends on what
you're doing.
As you said,
you're making personal data.
Do you share personal data?
What can you safely
store? Do you have a printer?
No, I don't have a printer.
That's the context.
It's not a mail problem.
It's a mail problem.
I don't know
what the website does.
I don't know, let's say
the website allows you to track
all the batches of kombucha you're making
at home. Or let's say
you're making beer at home.
You can go to the fermenter
and get a mail when you're done.
No, that's already...
That's already a whole stack.
That's already a lot of data.
So, you're just
making beer and that's it.
No, because
at the conference
I had with
an information assistant, she said
personal data is
very different from the context.
But you can identify the employer.
For example,
a few years ago,
IP,
when they were more dynamic,
more popular,
but also dynamic,
you could identify
who had that IP at that moment.
So, yes,
data privacy,
yes, that's a whole list.
About registration,
there must be some...
Privacy policy.
By the way, I really agree.
Our information service, Slovenian,
is one of the most friendly
regulators in Slovenia.
It also has a lot of resources
on the website.
Guidelines.
Guidelines are also very friendly
for questions.
Because it varies from regulator to regulator.
For my work,
the best regulators
are the ones that are like
OK, let's find out
if we did a bad job
with the law, we'll be punished.
And most of them, thank God, are like that.
Also, maybe...
A good idea for a project,
to write a wizard.
That's the best.
You just don't know the template.
Something that is very different from the context
to program a wizard.
Typical IT.
I like that a lot.
Maybe because it's so different from the context,
it's good to have
a constant process.
Whatever you add to the website,
oh, we need to change the Terms of Use,
we need to change the Privacy Policy,
we need to screw up something else.
You have to periodically
save something
and
that the legal compliance
part is done.
That's where you sold your job security.
We don't need someone
who will constantly work on that.
The worst thing that Europe
hasn't done is to make a draft
of something for them.
I mean,
if I sit in a vlog
of a private person and say
I'm not a lawyer anymore, I'm fucked.
Now, if I have to say...
If I have to give advice,
I'll do it minimally
so that there won't be...
I tried, but...
You have to build it.
I understand.
So that no one finds you.
There are also people
who look for problems
and will say,
there isn't any,
now I'll look for it.
It's not like in Slovenia
when the neighbor will call you,
or the competitor will call you.
I don't know how many competitors
there are on the market for Apple
compared to Kombucha,
but you never know.
Maybe, I don't know,
maybe you just need to measure
and that's it.
Then there's
the other extreme.
Let's say
that this app
works for you,
and you're there,
now you have
an incoming student
who hacks this app.
Does that mean he has black hoodies
and...
He hacks it,
and everyone gets emails.
He's so friendly
that he can say,
Andraž, I saw this,
you're so reliable.
What are you going to do about it?
I think that's
pretty late.
The information system
because you always have
these white hat hackers
to good people.
The problem is how to deal with it.
I know that
there are a lot of hackers.
When I was younger,
they were
just a healthy expression
for the use of cracker.
It was like a difference
if you're a hacker or a cracker.
Then, because of the pirate games,
they just used cracker
and there was a bit too much racial slur
for white people.
There was also the script kiddies.
Those who just copy
what they see on the internet
and then they copy it.
They don't know how it works
and then they do all the magic.
It's a good thing
because all IT people,
developers, security experts,
they want a proof of concept.
Not just that you found
a vulnerability,
you want to get inside.
That's not OK.
If they call you and say,
I think that's it,
it would be great
if they would just call you
and say, sorry, there's a bug.
It's really hard
because until you try it,
you're not sure if it's a bug or not.
But technically,
it can affect
good in the IT network.
That's why it's good.
If someone is more professional
in pen testing,
You either have to agree to it, or you look for companies that have publicly announced bug bounty programs or agree to it.
You are a bit more on the safe side.
No, it's not like that. Larry Farrie, for example, always puts himself in the role of personal relations, if it's a state-owned company or public enterprise, because he doesn't know how to protect our health and information security.
You know, if someone pays you too little for help, and then you tell him about it, they will go medieval on your ass.
It's a bit of a managed relationship.
Maybe that's one scenario, that you are the villain.
But I would say that there are a lot of people who believe in good things.
They want to demonstrate, to say that they have the ability to do so.
On the other hand, I can take it as a defense, and say that I did it.
I just showed it, I didn't do anything wrong, I didn't steal anything from him.
But on the other hand, in the logs you can see that there is some evidence that he was there.
I would say that you should try to communicate with different bodies, such as C-Cert, etc.
But they don't make a full disclosure with the website, or with your personal website, like you do.
I found some reliable photos in the health homes, and then I asked for C-Cert as a mediator.
It wasn't just...
Esquiline Jackson.
Esquiline Jackson, I just said in the title, it's the same.
And I saw that Esquiline Jackson, I didn't touch that table or anything, and I sent C-Cert.
It was weird that the developer wrote in the logs that he developed it,
and then I went to Google and found all the other health homes with the same reliability.
And then it lasted for quite a few years.
But what about the conclusion?
They sent it, but it lasted for a long time.
And I didn't disclose it until it was removed.
It's not reasonable, but it's a responsible disclosure.
That if you find a reliability, you don't disclose it to anyone before it can be removed.
Technically, I did it with the intention of discovering that reliability,
but I didn't have much data on it.
I only knew that it was technically reliable, but I didn't write any data.
And you can see that if you give an anonymous statement,
it means that it's not a scam and you don't make a specific mistake,
because you know that it's reliable, but you don't know anything about the system.
Yes, but it's interesting for a new student.
Yes, that's why you don't do it.
No, I remember that in our FAQs, when we had the electronic index relatively fresh,
I think it was obvious to us that there was a mistake.
You logged in with your e-mail address and password,
and it wasn't just a basic HTML page,
where your e-mail address was inside,
and you changed it.
Yes, and I could see everything from another student.
I think they fixed it, but you can think,
yes, that's also true.
What is the responsibility of the one who did it?
Not the one who did it, but the one who founded the Cambucha site,
which could have done it in such an unreasonable way.
That's what we talked about today.
Don't we have some kind of law
that you can't park your car anywhere,
and if something happens to your car,
it's your fault?
It's not a law,
but I think it's probably interpreted that way.
I don't know if it's the most correct interpretation.
You know,
I said this in one of my FAQs,
the fact that someone has a locked Wi-Fi,
doesn't mean that you can get close to it.
If there's a locked door,
it doesn't mean that you can go inside and steal it.
But it's a different FAQ.
Yes, but I think that the Italians and Germans
had...
I mean,
they were at the public places,
right?
The point was open,
but now,
such an offer is a crime
for any nonsense that could happen.
Yes, and that's why
in Italy and Germany
you always have a page
with all the necessary information.
On the other hand,
you remember the podcast,
don't you?
I don't remember which episode,
but yes,
it's very important
to look through the prism
of civil responsibility.
I mean,
what kind of responsibility is there
and then look at the cause,
the damage,
and all that.
If it's a very small damage,
it's a big problem,
then you have to
look at it case-by-case
and simply check
all the actions.
It's completely dependent.
A company could develop it
and then release it.
Now, when I look at
technical problems,
I don't know, SQL injection,
I'll say, I don't know what it is,
it's a big damage, small damage,
small damage,
and then look through it.
Then comes the damage
responsibility.
Now, how the company will act
from the inside,
they may then look for the culprits,
but again, it's a bit of a work law,
a bit of a civil damage.
It will be decided what kind of damage
is there.
Yes, that would be
prepared at the court.
It's just a rule of thumb.
For example, SQL injection,
it's a very old technique,
but it's well-known.
I don't know how much more
it's well-known.
It's still present
in the top 10.
You didn't read
the input.
But maybe, for example,
it would be right
to mention
the rule of thumb.
The company, the developer,
on the other hand,
did it,
and then it was transferred.
Then, of course,
an IT security expert
said, look, this is bad.
No one would do that.
No one would
put out a fire
with gasoline.
I don't know, I'm joking,
but it would be a court action
because there was responsibility
and it's very difficult.
I mean, it's the same with
response errors.
You always look at the standard,
what is expected of the respondent,
and so on.
If you are a respondent,
which is a free call,
do you have that responsibility?
Yes.
It's a very bizarre thing
that we have,
because there are people
from Great Britain
in Slovenia,
so you either
don't have it,
or you can
take it
from the intermediary
just in case.
It's really interesting.
Yes, for the respondent,
I mean, notaries don't do it,
but the respondent has the right
to make a call for insurance,
and then...
I was looking for that
and we were looking for that,
and they called us for insurance,
and it was like,
OK, what is that, why do you need it?
Like building a bridge.
It's a very different development.
I mean,
it depends on what you do,
but I think
it's still very difficult
to express my responsibility.
I mean, OK, we had that,
but as far as I understand,
the programming process,
you know,
a lot of times it's like,
it doesn't work.
I mean, is there really
someone who screwed up,
or is it the hardware,
or some other factors?
I think a lot of those,
I don't know,
probably in other industries
it's very similar.
I mean,
a team,
like a company with a reputation,
but they also develop
some juniors
and students
that they have there,
because it's a sub-private sector
that develops it,
and those people
don't know anything different.
They don't have those kilometers,
and they come from certain mistakes.
And now someone has to answer for that.
What was that example
when this security company
froze the whole Windows cube?
Crowdstrike.
That was a complex mistake.
The problem is,
we don't have a judicial inquiry.
I'm an electrician.
Telecommunications.
I could screw an antenna,
but I can't work with microwaves.
So I'm programming some complicated hardware.
Technically, it's not my expertise.
But Crowdstrike,
especially in development,
has an extra step,
and I think it will stay that way,
even on a daily basis.
It will start differently.
QC, right?
You need to test it.
Yes.
But you,
you come to it through mistakes.
It also happened to me,
as I mentioned yesterday,
in the weather forecast,
that you have a few bad weather forecasts,
and then you think,
OK, I made a mistake here,
if I don't fix it,
I'll be fined, etc.
Yes, I mean,
the IT forecast I work with
is also a matter of experience,
knowledge, and process.
My colleague worked with city forecasts,
and the more you do them,
the more city things you see,
you know what's good to include,
and so on.
With the IT forecast,
it's good to know the source code,
who it belongs to,
what are the disadvantages,
what are the advantages,
and so on.
Or the maintenance forecast,
SLA, and so on.
You mentioned it earlier.
The forecast I have
in the Slovenian version
says that the right
for the code I produce
is brought by the company,
paid for by the account.
That's what it says in the forecast.
With larger corporations in Slovenia,
I always get the right one.
When they say,
no, that can't happen,
we pay for it, and it's brought to us,
and so on.
That's the kind of thing
I need.
That's the most typical change I get.
Yes, that's true.
On the other hand,
there are a lot of things
that you simply
don't think about,
in the sense that
you have a developer
on the other side,
and you have the right code,
and so on.
What about the admin access,
and who has it?
If you are connected to the developer,
and you have admin access,
and you can also host,
and if you don't pay for it,
it can be very difficult.
Two or three years before
your page is solved,
and you don't have anything.
It's good to think about
these things in practice.
Our listeners
like to hear war stories.
Do you have a name,
an IT name,
that would be interesting,
or
a Slovenian name,
or something that
receives the respect?
I didn't say this earlier,
but there was a similar case,
where our side,
I don't know if it was
Lisanjan Kulijan,
said it very well,
that it's good in all IT development
situations,
because of the client,
and it's also good
because we still get
a lot of headaches,
and now it's solved.
Yes, it's impossible,
but how can you not feel it?
Because you signed it.
It was for a development project
with a page that cost
over a million,
and it was for an online shop.
I didn't know what a million and a half
would cost, because there was
nothing special.
I agree,
but I think that the developers
are very smart,
our side is one of the top developers,
and they are all smart,
especially in terms of
the economy,
because it's going to be crypto-based,
and on the blockchain,
and they paid a lot for it,
but then our side
didn't want to pay at the end,
because the page wasn't worth it,
and then we started to stop
everything,
and they paid for it,
but instead,
they hosted the source code.
All of this was done by the developers.
They pulled the plug,
our side couldn't
generate income,
because they didn't work on the website
for sales, and then they tried
to put it together
with some old databases.
It was a horror story,
when you want to help a page,
but you're like,
hey, how can you help me?
I'll call him in two years,
and he'll sign it,
but he won't sign it.
And then,
let's sit down
and talk a little,
if you find
some mediation,
and you come together.
Absolutely,
mediation is a great thing,
but the problem is that
a lot of pages
are full of ego,
in the business,
and he won't even
bring me a call.
And if Slovenia is small,
2 million people,
you'll probably be able
to get along,
maybe you'll find a colleague.
What's your horror story?
When you said that
the biggest horror for me
is when someone says,
hey, we signed this,
that's it.
It also happened that
we signed this,
and I said,
it's over,
and he said, no,
we'll move on.
And it also happened
that on the other side,
they said,
ok, you want it a little different,
I added things in,
and we went to a more meaningful
meeting.
I have a lot of horror stories,
but you'll find out
how it goes.
If you work as a reporter,
you have hundreds of pages,
it's different than if you're
an in-house reporter.
Yes, the pages are more
scanty.
You can't reduce anything,
we worked hard on it.
But yes, you don't know what it is.
There's still brownie,
but you don't know what it is.
I mean, yes,
thank God,
I have a lot of luck,
I work for a big newspaper,
you can have a fair page,
and you can't pay for it.
And you can't change it,
because we can,
maybe we got it,
but no,
it's a piece of work,
which is fine,
but it's good to be honest,
it's a joke,
I'm just saying.
Well,
we already drank a lot,
so now it's time
for the second round.
For the second round,
we said it's after,
because we'll record
something else,
just beer.
So,
what was your final thought?
Did you like it?
Yes, yes.
Now it's a topic.
Yes, after midnight.
That's the setup.
No, I liked it a lot,
but it's nice to have
a different perspective on things,
because, you know,
we have two lawyers,
and as a guest,
we also have lawyers.
Where can we find you?
On every podcast platform.
I'm a bit of a CEO genius,
so it's hard.
Maybe it's easiest to find me
on one name.
Yes, because we have P2 Podcast,
and we have 2.0.
It will change once.
Yes, once.
But I have Apple Podcast,
Spotify.
On YouTube,
if you type P2,
it will find you.
What did I miss on YouTube?
Google Podcast, Kino,
I don't know.
And LinkedIn, Facebook?
Yes.
And which pubs?
Whichever.
Is there a chance
that you are more present
than recently?
Not recently.
Recently, I've been writing
under Messenger,
but in Ljubljana,
one of the best pubs
is Sir William's.
It's an institution.
Plus 10.
Tectonics, too.
I like Tectonics,
because it experiments.
Leibach.
More than that, yes.
But you drink too much alcohol
every year.
That's it.
You can still find us
on classic channels.
Like and subscribe.
Thanks to
Caldio, Human Frog,
Vision Ecto,
Sponsorship,
our Patreons,
and in the back,
Jan and Oto,
who are waiting
for you to come
to their pub.
Drusga Piva.
That's it.
Bye.