We're very sorry for the delay.
We're very sorry.
We always accept criticism
to forget to introduce our guests
in the garden.
We don't have any guests.
I can try to make an intro.
And today,
I'm going to introduce
our guests.
And I'm going to introduce
And today, in a new episode in Grodno,
in the fourth season,
I think we've seen each other
in the fourth season.
Rockets and fish.
I'm a rocket, he's a fish.
And today, in Grodno, you're called
Andraž Sraka,
Loki,
Andraž Brodol,
Brodnik Brodol.
What about me?
And the host Otto Bergles.
Is that okay?
We're not
in the same boat.
We're in the same boat.
We're a flat structure.
Otto is the boss.
I feel naively responsible
for taking so long.
We're all the same.
Dr. Nipi and Otto Kril.
Now you're alone in the garden.
We have to figure out
what to do.
We've invested so much time and energy
that now I feel naively
that we have to push it forward.
Well, push me.
The title of this episode
is Rockets and Fish.
I hope that during this episode
we'll discover a different,
better terminology
and we'll get a title out of it.
That's the title of the documentary.
As I said,
this is the first episode
of the fourth season in Grodno.
Who would have thought
that we'd make it this far?
The agenda for today is
to bring together
the topics
that are close to us
and that we'll talk about.
We'll see
how far we'll get.
You've already
interrupted me.
Yes.
Who would have thought
that we'd make it to the fourth season?
I mean, who?
If you had said
that we'd record
this speech
and three years later
we'd be here.
That's good.
No, Nikol,
my thinking was...
You know,
I'm not sure
what it'll be like for me.
There's always a direction
we want to go.
Are we close to that direction?
How many years has it been?
Three?
It's the fourth season.
We have so many major releases
on the app.
That's the name, right?
I don't know.
Last time I had an update
on the Grodno.ca page
and I went there
to change the header text
to Grodno.
I think this mission
is kind of balancing
what we want to be
and what we want to become.
I think it's becoming clearer
what's yes and what's no.
We're slowly preparing
what we want to be.
Yes.
Last year,
I thought we had to come up
with a new strategy
for Grodno.
Now that we've seen
that there's a new law,
I feel like
we won't be able
to position ourselves
as a media.
Everything is primary.
PICASI says
that Grodno is a technological community
of people
who want to connect
and create
those personalities.
We want to be a community
of seniors,
of the younger generation,
and we want to
talk about the things
that are important to us.
I think we're united.
You can correct me if I'm wrong.
It's all about the question
and the discourse.
Are we
managing
this mission?
If we look at it
like this,
last year,
if I'm not mistaken,
last year
we made
17 episodes,
16 plus one,
something like that.
That's a lot.
During the year
not all of them were 90 minutes long.
Some of them were
even shorter.
We made
17 episodes,
some of them were special
only for Patreon.
Those were some kind of
content production.
We also went to
various conferences
and meetups.
We also hung out with people
or supported conferences
and events.
We retweeted
and posted on LinkedIn
when something happened.
We tried to
bring people
to these events.
We tried to bring
the online community
and the offline community closer.
I think we managed to do that.
During the last event
at the end of the year
some people
who organized the conference
came to us and promised
to do something interesting this year.
I think
we positioned ourselves well.
Why is that good?
I think
the market
that we have
with these people is relatively small.
I think it's good that we are close
to the people for whom
these events are organized.
I'm going to
interrupt you.
I would like to ask
the same question.
How does it look like
last season?
How do you see
where we started and where we are now?
We supported
a student group
and moderated
a round table.
I think that
when I talk to people
my peers
who are senior people
I think that
it's good
to listen to them.
I have a lot of time
to listen to them,
but I don't like the idea.
I think it's good
to have an icon
or a northern star
in the group.
Even if they don't follow you.
Even if they are not
regular listeners,
I think
they can consume it.
We have
ultra-fans who are super happy.
We have people who are really happy
to cover a specific topic.
For example,
I work more in the field of ESRI,
DevOps, systems.
They are like, oh my god,
we are really happy
when it comes to these topics.
I think that for someone
who likes this industry
it's really valuable.
I also watch it
quite often.
I don't know how meaningful
it is for us to be in this live stream,
but it will be really fun
to watch it in 10 years.
I'm really happy.
I know it's cringy,
but it's such a cool production.
We can honestly talk about
some things.
It's purely anthropological.
What we do,
what we are doing,
I think it's really good.
It's quite unique.
It's not filtered.
I don't know.
A few times
we were reminded
that we are at the beginning
and we have a slow start,
but we are engineers.
When I come in the morning,
I have a coffee,
I open a pool request to review,
but I'm an engineer.
If I were a DJ
or a professional,
I would deal with public performances.
I would be full of energy
and all-American.
Why aren't you?
I am what I am.
I think that
authenticity is
the most valuable thing.
I realized that
if we talk
to people
who do these things,
who have done these things,
who live for these things,
it's easier to connect
and organically add some personality.
If you have someone
who talks about topics
that are not close to us,
you lack the journalist's
point of view,
the journalist's experience.
I don't want to say it in a bad way,
but I think it's not interesting.
I mean,
I don't want to try
to get out of the water
because you fail.
Maybe we can practice
and do something
to be more conversational.
If you want to do interviews
one-on-one,
then you can practice.
Andraž, what do you think
about last season in Grozny?
What energy?
That's a question
that really makes me sad.
It's been half a day in five
since the last interviews.
Half a day in five.
No, to be honest,
I think that...
I honestly didn't think
that I would drive him to sleep.
Shock.
Partly because
we let go of
the inner tension.
I would keep that
somewhere.
On the A channel?
No, sometime during the recording.
People come to us, right?
Yes, they do.
No, joke.
We actually
got to the point
that the fourth season,
as Otto said,
we did a lot of things
that you
probably didn't
even imagine
at the time.
It was like,
why would I
have my own Discord,
why would I have
that interaction with people?
It made sense.
Why would I
want to be on YouTube?
It makes sense,
whether you want it or not.
I think that
we talked about it
at the beginning,
when we were recording here,
that the last season
was very on the road.
A lot of things,
because he was jumping around
in Grodno,
so...
I made a mistake
about that.
Couch?
Yes, couch.
We made some
organizational changes
for the fourth season,
so that we have
two-week
retros and planning.
We're not a startup anymore.
Now we need a corporate,
and some meetings.
We talked about
what works
and what doesn't.
One thing that we
noticed is that
we went to a lot of events,
and we were present.
It's a logistical
and demanding task.
You have to transport people,
then you're in a group,
and so on.
It's stressful
to record events,
if you're in that environment.
I think it's very important
to emphasize that
it's not our job.
It's not something
that we do for free.
It's our free time.
It's our hobby.
I wanted to say
that we did a lot of events,
and the episodes
that were recorded
on the conference
will have a different dynamic
than if they were recorded
in a couch.
Maybe this year
we'll have a bigger couch,
and less conferences.
But it's a good thing
that we did
a mini-series of Bites
between the last episodes.
We did the shorter episodes,
I think it's like
half an hour long,
three episodes.
It's very interesting,
because it's something
that we did easily at the conference.
You can bring your friend
and talk about
one topic at a time.
The feedback was also
very interesting,
people liked the format.
I won't say
that we won't do anything
at the conference this year,
but maybe in a different format
we'll find a balance
of pleasure.
As you said,
we're both startups.
A very important thing
that we can't forget
is that we do it
freely,
we finance ourselves
with Patreon,
with our supporters,
and the cash goes to production,
equipment and expenses.
We need to realize
that we're people
who want to do it,
who take time for it,
who don't work with others
because of that.
When you try to lead
such a synergy,
you have to respect it.
We also come to the question
why don't you have girls,
why don't you have Asana,
why don't you have a ticketing manager?
When I get another girl
for this job,
I see that it's more
organized.
We're all Slavs.
Programmers.
To some extent,
it's nice to connect a hobby
and a job,
so it's a bit like
my ex-manager.
But I don't know
if you'd look for a ticketing system
for the city of Grodno.
I mean, it's there now.
I don't know,
I think there are
about 90 people
in Grodno now.
And that
simplicity means
that we have a new service,
a new website, a new project.
It means that people
can invest their time
in this project.
And maybe it doesn't work
like we have a big team
and users.
If people rotate,
we got new
support.
I hope that
Oliver, who will help
in PR,
that we'll get
new audiences,
that we'll be able to
improve
all the topics
by individuals
and organizations that prepare us
and support us to improve communication.
And I hope that
we'll get
what we're trying to do.
That's it.
What else did we learn
from last season?
Maybe that
it's very important
to work for ourselves
and that it's cool for us
to work with people who are close to us.
Because then we can work
for others.
Anything else?
If I don't have more...
No, I'm just happy that
I don't have to watch Mišalka anymore.
And that this technique
is only for January 15th.
It's a law.
I'm very happy that someone else
started writing LinkedIn posts.
I can't tell you how much
it means to me.
And that it's well written.
That it's better written.
I hope we'll improve it.
Don't be sad anymore.
Let's move on.
Let's move on to the future.
You didn't tell us
where are the 10 topics
that we talked about today.
The idea is that we'll
talk about rockets and fish.
I wrote here
ccc.de
It's Chaos Communication Congress.
It's a conference
that takes place every year
in Frankfurt.
No, it's Hamburg.
No, no, no.
It was in Hamburg and then
moved to Berlin.
Then it was in Hamburg again.
There were some events in Leipzig.
But mainly in Hamburg.
I'm a big fan of this conference.
Oto, why haven't you been there yet?
I have a problem.
Wait, wait, wait.
First of all, I'm afraid.
I hear that it's the best
and you don't have to
be a researcher or a hacker.
If you haven't been there,
you'll lose all credibility.
I've already confirmed that.
But this conference is
for Christmas and New Year holidays.
What do I mean?
25th, 26th, 27th...
From 27th to 30th.
It's December.
Yes.
It's a small date.
That's the biggest problem.
If you have three kids
and you tell your wife
sorry, babe,
for the New Year holidays.
That's a bit risky.
Everyone will be older.
I know you have to prepare
for everyone to have it.
But tell us about the date.
It's very interesting.
So, yes.
It was on the 38th
when
this event took place.
What is it about?
It's easiest to describe
a well-known DEF CON.
Yes.
I would say
it's a European DEF CON.
Besides that,
security hacking is...
I won't say it's not,
but it's so bad.
Hacking is
art,
biohacking,
everything you can
include here.
In the broadest sense.
In the broadest sense
possible.
People
who deal
with technology
in a different way,
for technology,
let's say
from physical
hardware hacking
to food hacking,
to the level
of metaphysical,
philosophical,
legal,
civil society,
where we go,
are the laws in the right places.
The idea
of this congress is
four days
of
lectures
by
employees
who are prepared,
go through a meeting
and then return.
I think this year
there were about
190 lectures.
I think you gather
between seven halls
and
a group
of
self-organized assemblies
where the employees
or some groups
go and
meet.
So,
I don't know,
I think there were
14,000 people
at the meeting.
The maximum capacity
of the Hamburg
congress center
is
something like
four days.
This year
I was
pleasantly surprised
that there were
a lot of Slovenes
after a long time.
I think there were
35 Slovenes
when I counted
or when I managed
to gather
a lot of students
and a lot of people
who were first.
It is commendable
that this conference
or congress is in this spirit.
We are doing it
on a fairly free level
and what is being financed
is to cover the expenses
of the event,
the venue,
I don't know,
the 50 giga optics
in the congress center and so on.
Is it hard to get a ticket?
I mean, it is hard.
Let's say
that this year
it was relatively easy,
but last year
there were a lot of people
so it is easier
to get a ticket
if you join a group
or if you meet people
who are there
to get a ticket.
If you work in an open source project
you know that there will be
a group of people there.
Tickets are valid
and you can join
and you know that you will be there.
It is easier to get a ticket
if you know that you will help
and that you are a part
of their angel system.
This year I saw that
a few Slovenes
also helped.
For example,
security hacking
means modifying
technologies
in their own name.
You can say modifying
but you can also say
searching.
This is important
because if you say
hacking to someone
they don't think what we think.
Full hacking means
that people
don't think what we think.
Give us an example.
What was interesting for you?
Last year
I didn't go
to lectures that much.
Wait.
You go up for 4 days
and you don't go to lectures?
You know that
things happen at lectures.
Ok.
You know, you hang out
with people
and most of those lectures
I would say 99%
are quality
recorded
with transcripts
and simultaneously
translated.
Of course, it's great to see it live, but those things that happen when you hang out with these people after the show,
you ask them, you join them, they have some kind of event that hasn't been recorded yet.
Those things have some added value, why it made sense to be there.
Or if you are part of an open source community, when something is being done there, to be a part of it in the end.
Now, this show, I don't know, what was interesting, I don't know how well-known it was two years ago,
this big affair in Poland with these trains.
Yes, you make a recap.
Yes, the Poles bought some trains.
No, there is a vendor.
In Poland, right?
In Poland, there are more vendors that deliver trains.
Do they deliver or service?
No, they deliver.
No, no, they deliver.
And then there is this thing where you have to take the trains for repair or, I don't know,
summer service, as far as the cars are concerned, they are not summer anymore, I don't know,
but it takes a lot of time.
And what started to happen is that these trains,
you make a recap, we want this train, and then you buy the train as a manufacturer,
but in the beginning you want it to be serviced independently of the manufacturer.
So you can go to any vendor and then you tell the manufacturer,
we want to have it written down how to service this train, and it has to be as usual.
But if you buy a car, it is not prescribed that you have to go to the repair service,
really, no guarantees.
This was a gift that these services are still in operation,
because this is an operational service, they have a certificate that they know how to service these trains.
Well, let's make it simpler, let's imagine it for a car.
And this gives the developers inside Geofencing or other mechanisms
that an independent servicer or another servicer,
these are not independent, like someone who screws cars,
but like a big factory that repairs trains, or maybe repairs trains itself,
couldn't fix them because of these screws.
Actually, in the firmware, the train vendor made a lock-in,
which is in connection with the fact that others won't know how to fix it,
like we do, which means that these specific services
were then asked by the developer for help,
and this was calculated successfully by the developer,
and yes, on a certain schedule,
because, of course, the vendor also applied for a schedule for maintenance,
this vendor failed, and when these trains needed repair,
it turned out that a lot of things went to waste,
and those who prepared the schedule, or the municipality, or whatever it was,
had such a problem that they were literally eaten by hackers.
So they were actually eaten, and it wasn't even the fans themselves.
No, no, no, they were eaten, and it's a funny thing,
how they were eaten, as if Google would say,
hey, let's get rid of a lot of hackers in Poland,
and then someone fell out, let's go,
and the fans were so far away,
okay, we'll solve this,
and they were very professional in solving these problems,
and reverse engineering, and they found a bunch of vendor lock-ins,
I don't know how it's done, I don't know,
like you said, Andraž, geo-fencing,
that when you're at a certain point, the train stops,
or when it stops for a long time, you can't start it again,
and similar problems,
and these problems, they presented it two years ago,
made a disclosure that it's happening,
but in January or December, it was a different story,
when the thing has actually surpassed the state level,
that it's now being solved at the courts,
where the court line is now,
that the vendor is now a hacker,
and that it was a modification of the firmware,
and you have these funny photos,
like snapshots of a certain code,
which is actually their own code,
or inside, and you know,
that's what the hackers wrote,
and it's actually from the original firmware.
And they say it's because the manufacturer is trying to say,
that for all their trains,
it's a free upgrade.
Now they want to cover up these problems.
To destroy the train.
That's right.
And now it's a problem,
which is developing in Poland,
and a lot of these members,
these hackers,
these penetration developers,
who came to these conclusions,
are actually getting civil lawsuits.
A documentary was made,
that was one of the things,
which was among the most discussed,
and it's also interesting.
It's made, it's online.
Only one question,
I have one question,
while we're talking.
You're a security researcher,
how did they come to these codes,
to be able to investigate them?
Can you tell us?
Do you have that insight?
Because what I'm saying,
how did they come to these codes?
They dumped the hardware,
the firmware,
and then the firmware made a debugger,
and they tried to reverse engineer it,
to see how it works,
and they successfully combined it,
to make sure that there's no geofencing,
that there are coordinates,
that there are parameters,
and that's it.
You know what I'm interested in?
I don't want to hijack the whole thing,
but among all the millions of people,
who are invested in this infrastructure,
and programming,
is it hard to get to these dumps?
No, these are PLCs.
You need a physical one,
I understand that we're all freaks here,
but we're also electrotechnicians.
You have the hardware,
it's a bit more complex,
but it has PLCs.
Programmer logic computer.
Or controller.
In PLCs there are ROMs,
ROMs are security PLCs,
and ROMs have standards,
and that's very well defined.
You have C++ extensions,
but that's not why the hardware
has so many standard things.
The controller is a security PLC,
so it doesn't press anything,
or locks on trains.
Those are additional standards.
In the end, it's a computer.
If you take B as a PLC,
it's an ARM or slow Windows,
where the system runs on isolated cores.
It's a software.
You dump the images,
and you can put them in ADO or WD Compiling.
You can't program everything,
so it's easier to reverse engineer.
Because you have standard things,
that are not on the PLC.
Because the ports are clearly defined.
No, you don't compile a binary and put it up.
You write it in a language,
like Ladder or Structure Text.
Those are the two languages.
You write something.
It has C++ extensions,
but you can't audit it inside the company.
You have to understand,
that the trains are not programmed
by someone who made them for free.
It's done by machines,
and it's more structured for the sake
that it's more maintainable.
It's not like, let's write a code,
and the compressor will run on the train.
You write a hex,
and you decompile it.
Then you look at it.
The registers are on the physical relays.
When you change a bit in the virtual memory,
it can mean that on the PLC
you opened the physical relay.
These are more complex systems.
I'm curious,
are they encrypted?
No, it's not encrypted.
It's encrypted in the sense that...
Do you have physical access?
It's not like there's a USB port,
where you can see where you have to stop
to get to the train.
But it's not obfuscated.
The safety, the traffic lights...
You can imagine that in a traffic light,
you can't have two green lights on.
Obviously.
In the PLC, it's solved.
But in a safety,
when the safety controller sees
that something went wrong,
it will go into error state.
In a traffic light,
you can't increase the speed.
No, but it's just a premonition.
I thought that this is
a software-defined train
that goes here and there.
When you go left, you go right.
I wanted you to give us a background
so that people have a feeling
of what we're talking about.
You have a lot to do with wireless.
Did you go more into wireless hacking?
Yes, I did.
Is 5G a topic you're interested in?
No, I mean...
AI, was AI a topic?
This year,
I think that from the inside,
besides the fact that there are
different networks,
wireless networks,
where people get access to the Internet
and the internet,
there is a project called GSM.
There is a phone network
where you can get an extension
and you can log in or log out.
This year, it was very retro
and they installed the ISDN network.
They were the first ones
to install the ISDN technology.
BBS, Klicalce, etc.
Very retro.
Yes, very retro.
You can start something
with this technology.
It was all very well documented.
If you didn't participate at the time,
or you were a viewer,
now you can have the opportunity
to see a lot of these things.
There was a lot of talk
about open source projects.
It was an interesting topic.
I don't know.
One of the lectures
was about how to solve a satellite
that has lost control
and is circling in orbit.
A student at a faculty
said how he managed
to reprogram the firmware
so that it can no longer
flash the firmware.
What was the communication
with the dead satellite?
The satellite was not dead,
but it was returning certain data
to the server.
It didn't return certain data
because part of the firmware was deleted.
The entire firmware and all the registries
were on the same stack.
Part of it was deleted
and they had the feeling
that they had lost control over it.
But you could still access it.
It was his doctoral thesis.
He took the time to reverse-engineer
certain things.
It was one of the oldest satellites
that a German university shot down.
It was a soft shell,
like a cube in orbit.
He successfully activated
the camera that the satellite had.
The firmware did not support it
and they never tried it.
They never worked with it.
Part of it was written off
so that it was a deep picture.
It was such a good find
How old was it?
Was it a 10-year-old satellite?
No, it was a school satellite.
It was a 10-year-old or 8-year-old in orbit.
When you launch a rocket,
you have different dimensions of the satellite.
Typically, they are cubic or circular.
Circular ones are stable,
but a lot of them crash.
They are school satellites.
There are also other things on the CCC.
People hack devices for communication,
or biohacking,
or cooking,
or how to make apple cider.
I once talked to a person
who did a doctorate on pear cider in France.
You have a lot of things.
One more question.
We sold you.
When you started talking,
you said that all the important things
are recorded,
but you also said that it is very important
what happens on sidewalks.
Do you like whiskey?
I also taste whiskey.
No, I like the whiskey on the balcony.
All the whiskey is here.
Only the CCC has whiskey licks.
When people bring their whiskey,
you turn it around and lick it.
It's a coincidence.
I wanted to ask you.
We have a lot of listeners
who don't go to conferences.
We were at a conference last year.
How do you start talking
to people who are teachers?
Like when we talked about satellite hacking.
How do you set up communication?
We have a lot of introverts
who come to us.
It's great.
You go to the Slovenian Kubernetes Meet,
and you talk to me.
You go to Whiskey Licks,
you drink something,
and then you start talking.
Give us something more specific.
What is the best icebreaker to talk to?
I listen to conversations in the garden,
and then you come to a person and say hi.
That's it.
Why do you ask that?
Not necessarily.
People often ask me
what I do for a living.
I don't know how I advance in this industry.
But if you want to...
You have to get out of your comfort zone.
You don't rush into the topic.
I think the beginning
is a small event.
You have a small event at home.
You have to record everything,
you have to stream,
you have a Discord,
and everything is online.
You try a small event.
At the beginning,
you are just a listener.
Then you start networking.
You join a group,
maybe invite people,
but also ask some questions.
You introduce yourself.
I'm new here, I don't know you.
I don't know much.
When you are a senior,
what do you do to get a better job?
What do you have to do?
Definitely sell.
Is it hard to make your flow stop?
No.
Maybe it won't be
at the main hall,
but you will come to a smaller hall.
Even if your flow doesn't stop
at the main part of the program,
it's still a self-assembly event.
You have a hall,
where you talk to people.
I will demonstrate that.
It's like football.
You play football.
You start regional.
If you want to be in the Premier League,
Slovenian organizers
always look for a teacher.
It's not like people contact you
and tell you how much they want you.
It's the opposite.
You want to organize an event,
you find a local teacher,
and then you look for another one.
You don't need to have a phone
or a map,
but you need to motivate people
to come.
You start regional,
and then you connect.
If you want to go to CCC as a visitor,
there will always be 5 people
in the Discord group.
You tell them how many times you've been there,
and they tell you that you've been there 10 times.
We've been there 18 times.
18 times?
One question related to that.
Do you have to be an expert to do that?
No.
I think a lot of people have that problem.
Do you have people who are self-confident?
No.
Do you have to be a technologist
to do that?
No, because you have impostor syndrome
and you have no idea.
You have meetups.
You have a 5-year organized meetup.
If you have that standard
that it has to be more and more,
you'll be the only one at the meetup
who knows,
because they have meetups from beginner
to intermediate to advanced.
I would say that at the beginning
it's more important that you do that meetup.
People are like,
if I go to a meetup,
I don't go there because of the meetup.
If I'm interested in implementation,
I go to the meetup to see what's going on
and I don't have to do a meetup
because I'll have a written skin.
When you're a senior,
you're doing nothing,
and if you do a meetup,
it's very unlikely that you'll be able to do
exactly what you want.
I think that general,
beginner and intermediate meetups
are the most important.
I don't look at the meetup
because I've been watching it for 10 years.
To put it simply,
maybe CCC is not the place
where you want to start.
Football?
It's great that we have you.
Maybe at the beginning of the year
or the beginning of the first season,
if you need some ideas for this year,
maybe try a talk until the end of the year
at one of the local meetups.
Go to Sonya Odobja and try to submit something.
If you don't know where to submit,
DM me.
DM Andraža directly, we'll exchange.
Is that why you're so busy?
No, I'm the only one who cancels.
I cancel you.
Let's continue.
Let's go to another topic.
One of the most random topics
is that last year
Python overtook JavaScript
on GitHub
as the most popular language
in the world.
It's the most used language
according to their metrics.
What's your comment on that?
Are you crying, JavaScript?
Are you crying, Python?
Both of you are crying.
I don't know if the world has changed
because this metric has changed.
You're both in organizations
where Go is the main stack.
I have a feeling
that since AI is still Python
I don't know why
AI and Python are so different.
Landscape is like that.
Or are there other tools
that Python is ahead of?
As far as I'm concerned,
you can learn everything.
JavaScript, Python, Django.
If you're a senior,
you need to know everything.
At the end of the day,
it's all about coding.
I don't know.
I think the hype is due to data science and AI,
that Python has grown a bit,
and I think there is a movement
that people just want to do things,
and if you want to make a fast SaaS,
you need a system like Ruby on Rails or Django,
or Elixir, just so you can run in 3 days
a bunch of models and render something.
Python can make a job done, that's it.
That's what I've noticed.
The question was why Python in AI,
and engineering, data science, AI in the world,
why is that?
Users start giving these tools at random,
and when you see that the implementation
of those libraries is always using some C,
C++, Rasta, something more exotic,
and Python is said to be a very nice
and ergonomic wrapper on top of that.
They are building a wrapper,
but they are trying to learn the language.
Yes, it's good enough,
it's good enough,
there will always be problems,
because it's a bit like
a European type of engineering,
diversity, right?
Well, at the end of the day,
you have to know everything.
I know the scales.
We left that for later,
but it was a milestone for me,
when I wrote it down.
OK, we've covered that point quickly,
so let's move on.
One of the bigger topics that
everyone is talking about,
and that are relevant,
is the job market.
For all three of us,
last year we replaced
our core pages,
and we were all in the process
of looking for
other customers, I would say.
I'm just curious,
what did you see
in the job market
in the summer of last year,
and what do you see as trends for the future?
I won't jump directly
into that focus.
Last year I noticed,
and I see this year as well,
that there is a big increase
in what we call
ghost jobs.
Ghost job is a term
that is now used
to describe some phenomena,
which I will describe,
and then you can ask me
about it.
Organizations constantly
announce that
they have an open job
available for all possible
living positions.
These jobs are
freshly announced,
and they are constantly
being announced.
When you sign up for
this job ad,
you either don't get
any response,
or you see that
10,000 people have
signed up for the job interview,
or you see that a copy
has been uploaded again,
or it also happens
that organizations
have this job interview
process now,
I don't know exactly why,
but they have 7-8 steps,
which I think
has almost doubled
compared to some
previous years,
and today this process
of job interviews has become
completely different.
Then I also notice
that until
the interviews
are almost repeated,
and then when you go through
all these processes,
you end up being left out.
They don't give you offers,
or whatever,
or they say,
thank you,
now we have given you
our base,
and that's it.
This is something
I was very careful about,
when they say,
yes, you are very interesting,
or we will give you an offer,
and you focus on
one person,
and then you prepare yourself
for the interview,
you go through everything together,
but in the end,
you don't get the job.
This is something
I was careful about,
and I don't have to comment
on Slovenia,
because they have already
started doing this.
So, yes,
you have the term
GoJobs,
and you don't have
these symptoms.
I think that
these things are still relevant,
and I don't know,
the quota on the stock market
is somehow increasing,
and they are still
investing in the staff,
and so on.
The question is,
are they really increasing
the staff,
or are these jobs,
what I saw in Ljubljana,
was it really
a trend,
where,
as you said,
you didn't get any
feedback,
or was it
an automated way,
where a bot
went through your CV,
and if it found
enough keywords,
then maybe you had
someone who said,
yes, I'm interested,
but I was very surprised
that it was so hard
to get to the first initial screening.
So, you get a person
on a call, and you
talk to someone,
and there was a lot of
replying,
a lot of replying
to positions
where you didn't
really have a say.
But I understand,
it looks like
it's...
It's a phenomenon
that we have,
that people are looking for
security staff,
and so on,
but then you realize
that you can't
hire someone
on a daily basis.
And now,
I would say that
a lot of good people
are on the market today.
I don't know,
in our field,
it's a normal,
average period,
two to three years,
when you work with a client,
or you're employed
So, a lot of people
are still looking for
new opportunities,
and it's interesting
how this
doesn't happen today.
I think,
first of all,
for Landscape,
I had a lot of trouble
deciding between
hiring
and recruiting.
People would say,
Andraž, we have these problems,
and you get a job,
and then you're like,
ok, we're going to stop this project.
And then people are like,
no, we're going to close the company,
and we're going to get a job.
That's a problem I have.
I, on the other hand,
from the industry,
think it's really weird.
It's one of those things.
Talking about jobs,
first of all,
you have the staff,
and then you have all the resources
to go through this process.
And then, even if you don't
need to actively look,
you still have these positions open,
so you have a fresh pipeline
of people,
which you can technically hide.
And if you're a company
that's going to grow,
it's really nice to have
this pipeline of people
that I mentor,
and it's one thing.
But if you have this,
when you're hiding people,
you have a team
that deals with
some potential
new staff,
which means you have
a lot of hours,
and you have a fixed schedule,
so you're busy,
you have people to work with,
you're filling out a notepad.
You also have some engineers
that have to deal with it.
It's a collateral damage.
It's one hour for one technical screening,
but you're filling this tunnel,
and then you're starting to
dilute the time in this funnel,
and you're literally diluting it.
And then at some point,
when you're like,
hey, we want to grow,
you're just clearing this funnel.
I've seen this,
but you know,
that's one thing.
The other thing,
which I think a lot of companies do,
is full stack engineering,
and then what happens?
When I send my mentors,
I tell them,
hey, you're a junior for us,
you've done everything,
you've done this system,
and they've done that system,
but these are private people,
and we won't take you
because you know too little.
And that's one thing.
And then there's one answer,
hey, you know too little.
The other thing,
if you're a senior,
you're actually
pulling them through the interviews,
so they're really poisoned.
And then at the end,
you say, hey,
I want this,
and you say, hey,
that's too expensive.
And then you have this exhaustion
and you think,
this person will take this offer,
and you'll exhaust him.
But something good
probably isn't the only thing
for which you...
No, but you're
8, 10, 14,
and if you want to prepare...
And then the engineer says,
you have to ask in the second interview
what the response fee is.
That's our industry,
you can't write hours for a meeting
and travel expenses,
so maybe somewhere else in the technical world.
And then you have this.
And again, it's the same trick.
You have people who are
permanently employed
and those people,
if they're idling you,
aren't utilized.
And then you look,
if you get a good job,
because you're still in the market,
opening up some sectors
with a good price-performance ratio,
and then you have to
take a risk.
Watch out, there are people watching.
Yeah.
You know, people ask me,
Andraž, we're looking for this
profile for OBS,
and I say, look,
I know all the people I know,
they're on vacation,
and they're like, we're not interested.
Because they know
the best price-performance ratio
is zero, so it's a discount.
But they'll still come to me,
and I'll get the job.
And so,
I get the same experience
and the same questions.
One of the things I tell people
is that until you have
a document,
it's an offer,
you haven't really changed.
Because I see people
going, yeah, I'm the first step,
then the second, then the third,
maybe you try to
talk to two or three companies,
and then
you try to get offers
from different companies.
Don't try to stick to one company
on the first try.
I know that
it's not the best time,
and there aren't a lot of offers,
but try to take a risk
and talk to bigger companies.
And when you're in an interview,
and they ask you if you talk to other companies,
it's a bit like...
It's a dance.
I won't give you a football example,
but I'll tell you that
it's a bit like dating.
If you're dating someone
who's in Maribor,
and he says,
let's go on a date in Maribor,
you go to Maribor,
you go to another date in Maribor,
and you say, if you come to Ljubljana,
I don't know if I'm in Ljubljana now,
and I don't have a problem
going on a date twice or three times.
But if we don't change our date,
they'll look at it in a different way.
I mean,
in our industry,
you typically
don't go on a date
and don't count on a date.
That's obvious to us.
But you say,
what's the cost of a new business?
But if it's a date,
it's a date,
and it's the same
with interviews,
with domestic tasks.
I always tell people,
domestic tasks are bullshit,
and in this process,
they're doing engineering
at the same time
as you're doing it.
The engineer will be on the car
for six hours,
and the domestic task for six hours.
It's a symmetrical relationship.
The job market,
if we draw a line on this topic,
is still broken.
In my opinion, it's even more broken
than it used to be.
People use to say
that the job market is broken.
Yes, we can't find
too few engineers.
In the end,
seven steps out of the picture,
or eight, and we kick the river.
After 20 years of experience.
Crazy.
If you don't have a job,
you don't have a junior position.
I'll ask people
some more questions.
Blendor from Maribor,
shout out.
He wrote to us,
he would like to hear more about
programming in robotics.
Thank you, greetings from Maribor.
What is robotics?
Programming in robotics.
He is completely interested in
programming in robotics.
Apart from the fact that
you programmed for Yaskawa,
I don't think you have
any experience in robotics.
No.
This is our job.
We can discover things that interest us.
That's why I said
he should come.
The thing with robotics is
that they are great.
But to have three-axis
robots, as people imagined,
with a lot of cars,
it's not a big deal.
What do you mean?
It's not a big deal?
When you are in the industry,
you are working on a product.
You are optimizing
the most meaningful,
complex solution for the application.
Meaning,
if you have a milk cart in a dairy,
you won't have a robot
that moves in three axes
to pour milk for you.
If you could do it technically,
it would be terrible to maintain.
But it would look good.
It would look good, yes.
I haven't worked on projects with three-axis robots.
They looked good.
They looked fine.
For example, if you want to fill something
from one container to another,
you need a three-axis robot that pulls it out
and moves it inside.
Two engines, three engines.
Two engines, one line,
and then the thing moves.
Ok, I'll put it this way.
In robotics, we will get
someone who deals
with industrial design,
and we will talk about that.
I'm more interested,
when you started this project
and with the robots,
did you have any knowledge
about how to fly,
or how to fly?
Is it like you give a tutorial
and watch YouTube?
How do you come to the level
that you can fly?
Is it something you have to be a part of
a bigger organization to come to the level
that you can fly?
A lot of metadating.
Robots are like networking.
Proper networking.
Not industrial,
but for some big companies.
You have a company
that comes and says,
we will make a line
and we will do something.
We will have three-axis robots,
or packing milk.
And then you call the vendors,
who are really good at
welding round things.
ABB, if you watched
a video from Tesla,
when a drone flies
those are not Tesla robots,
those are ABB robots.
They assemble cars
and weld doors.
And then you say,
we have cash here,
our process is like this.
And then you exchange with the producer
and their integration teams
and they prepare everything.
And it's like networking.
You say, we have this application,
you don't talk to the press,
but you buy social equipment,
you implement it,
and it works.
Because it's made to work.
If you can't make a car in half an hour,
it's completely lost.
It's not hacking.
It's a kind of career
that is predictable,
but on the other hand,
it's not a big market,
because when you do it once,
it works.
I think it's a bit of an overstatement.
Wait, wait.
No, no, wait.
Let's get to the second part.
What does it look like in Germany?
And in Slovenia,
it looks like this.
We have a robot here,
it has 15,000 hours.
And we bought it at a high price.
Is it needed?
Yes, it's needed.
The Germans will take it out
because it's expensive
and has a high error rate.
And the robot that wasn't made
is this Slovenian system.
In the sense that we have
a big network system here,
and we're going to design it.
And then you flick it,
and it scans,
and everything works.
You described it as software developing.
Wait for it to finish.
Wait for that goal.
And now you have something like that.
But the good thing is that
we find ourselves in the same situation.
I'm not an automaton.
I studied communication,
but I'm an automaton.
When you work in a company
that knows robotics,
you're not allowed to do that.
There are some competitive clauses
in those companies,
and you're not allowed
to do other things.
Why would you touch a robot
that's out of date,
that's 40 years old?
I think that's suffering.
I've solved a lot of those projects
that were totally broken.
But also
tooling...
I mean,
if I want to put
milk in a pot,
I'll buy
a German-made robot.
I'll probably buy
a few brands that are the most popular,
so I'll have some SDKs,
and I'll prepare everything.
SDKs?
No, you buy a robot,
and you get a controller.
I don't know.
You get a Siemens S-series controller,
and you pay 15 euros
for a license for the controller.
And then you have
the CAM development,
where you have
a simulator
of how the hand moves,
and for your application...
It's visual, right?
It's visual, yes.
You program it,
and you'll probably also
change the hardware,
because you have to change the pins,
and if you buy it...
You hack it at home,
and you were probably smart
and bought a 3-axis robot
to make something
that would be much simpler.
I ask people,
what is robotics?
Because in your machine
there's a robot,
a 3-deficient robot.
Can you imagine a 3-axis robot
that you grab like this?
Yes, I can.
And that's also robotics.
I wish there was a market for that.
So, in the beginning...
That's why in the educational system
you don't have robotics,
but you have automatics.
Because when you hit a button,
it's like they're doing
some boring things
for typical people,
and they're not humanoid robots.
But they're made to
do very efficient things,
to make a general
humanoid robot,
like Tesla does.
If you're a computer scientist,
we're very used to
general purpose languages.
It's great that general purpose
can do anything.
In the physical world,
if you have an electric motor,
and you don't use it,
you'll fail anyway.
And you don't want
that thing to be productive.
KPI in the industry
is a bit lower
than in software development.
If you download it on Friday,
it won't work.
If BMW doesn't do it on Friday,
the whole line will be like this.
If they don't do it for 10 minutes,
there will be a problem.
Are people like the first experience
with automatic robotics?
With microcontrollers,
Raspberry Pi,
will everyone get a feeling
of what it's all about?
If you want to play with
automatic robotics,
I recommend the following.
Buy a microcontroller,
CX series, CX300,
from Beko,
and their IDE,
and how it's compiled,
you can also find it
in Visual Studio.
Visual Studio,
it's for 100, you don't need
a license,
and FrontCosta,
that microcontroller will cost
500 euros.
It's industry-grade,
and you'll have
that expectation.
It's what it is.
They've also made it
so that
when you open valves,
you close valves.
It's industry-grade,
and it's very accessible.
You take TwinCat,
you take Beko,
and microcontroller.
If you call Beko in Slovenia,
and tell them
that you're a programmer,
and that you'd like to play,
they'll give it to you for 100,
and they'll say,
I'll give it back in a month.
If you do it all at once,
then they'll have new ones.
He'll give it to you,
you'll look at it,
and he expects you to work on it.
Anyway, you'll buy it.
Tell me,
will it be your new hobby?
You have a house,
and you have a bunch of robots
inside to assemble a car.
I'm lucky that we put a house
in Milan.
I don't have any automation
in my house.
For example, if I have a glass,
I press it, and it goes up and down.
If you're really cool...
I don't have anything else.
No Knix,
no automation, no sensors,
nothing. If I have it on my phone,
I know it's washed and cleaned,
I have it, but...
If you're really cool,
instead of eating end-consumer...
or products for home automatization.
You are like an industrialist inside.
Because you will do better, but it won't be that easy.
Blender, I hope you answered it.
No, wait.
And we hope that the next episode
which will be very hardware,
it won't be in robotics,
but it will be very interesting.
It's already in the pipeline
and we have already agreed to film it.
At this point, I would like to thank our supporters.
I would like to thank Humanfrog,
which supports us on this mission.
I would like to thank Kaldi,
I would like to thank our new supporters,
who joined us for this season.
I would like to thank Visionact,
and I would like to thank Kufr,
which offered us 3TB of storage for our episodes.
I would also like to thank everyone
who supports us via Patreon.
We are now on 8K resolution.
No.
And everyone who supports us on Patreon,
one of the perks is that you can get
Hey, did you bring the merch?
Yes.
I brought it by car.
Andraž will confirm the presence of the merch in the building.
So, thank you to everyone who supports us.
These are cool companies and they help us
to achieve our goals.
Now, looking at the time,
I think we still have two topics to discuss.
Shoot.
Right away.
Don't lose the conversation.
I thought it was about robotics.
No, no.
That was a good one.
We have two more questions.
One was from Robert Sedovšek.
How to connect your domain knowledge
with a hobby that has no direct connection
with technology and build a business out of it?
This was written by the guest of the wrong podcast
Miha Rekar's Parallel Passion.
It's a Slovenian podcast.
Miha has been doing it for some time.
It's more about what you do
besides being an expert in technology.
The main question is how to connect
your domain knowledge with a hobby
and how to do something with it.
I thought about it a lot and studied it.
Learn marketing and sales.
No, really.
If you think about it,
you know something about technology
and you're interested in something.
For example, about software.
You say, we're going to make an app for software.
It's simple.
You know about software or a hobby
and you know about technology.
But what you really don't know
is marketing and sales.
If you know these two,
the most typical thing in the world
which is product development,
is to do it in Excel
and learn marketing and sales.
That's how you'll see if it's interesting.
In the end,
when I look at everything,
it's all about business.
Neither your hobby nor your technical implementation
is important.
You need to get those two skills up
so that you can launch it.
It's hard to hear,
especially if you're good at technology.
You need to lower the technological level
so that it's not as important
as marketing,
entrepreneurship,
validation of ideas,
especially if you're at the beginning.
These are very different skill sets
and different metrics
when it comes to software development.
You need to trust.
Look at our Tomas.
He was like,
I didn't like the end consumer
from the optics operator.
I hacked it and now I'm making my own router.
You need to trust.
You need to know these things.
You can't be prejudiced.
You need to simply...
In the long run,
marketing and sales are geniuses.
That's it.
You drive it.
You're lucky that it's all the same for you.
No, I think you said it.
But I don't know if it's...
It's a missing link
if you go into a business.
I understand the question
where you find the connection
with your hobbies.
But that's really...
I know what you want to hear.
In the end,
it's the hard work
that's not really your hobby.
In life,
when you're down and scared,
you can always move on.
That's your northern star.
So marketing and sales.
But there are certain things
that you'll never be good at.
That's why you outsource.
Yes, but...
You can only learn certain things
to a certain extent.
Maybe you're the type of person
that will never do certain things.
Or for certain things,
you can invest a lot of time
and it doesn't make sense
if you can't do it.
I strive for it,
and I'll tell you my answer.
First of all, you're a partner
who knows good marketing and sales.
But you need to know
that the technical part
is a minor part of the product.
That's the thing.
You need to find a partner
or a team
to come together
when you're doing it alone.
I have a great team.
I mean,
let's go back to the beginning.
Let's say,
if only one person
was doing this podcast,
how far would you go?
That's what I'm striving for.
Maybe I...
Well...
In the first place,
I see that...
One thing is OK.
Let's talk about it.
We'll get into it
in due time.
We'll invite people together,
choose a topic,
look for speakers,
talk about it.
Then we'll patch it.
Then we need to
edit it,
make it deliverable.
And then
you need to make your product
reach people.
And if you failed
to make it work,
to have an excellent product
but you didn't give it to people,
you failed.
Maybe you need to think
about how to develop it
and how to make it
reach the people
who need it.
How far will I go?
One of the good
early moments
with Ugrodje was
when I went to meetups
and asked people
what Ugrodje is,
why we do it.
They said it's interesting.
Then they picked up the phone
and wrote Ugrodje in front of me.
Ugrodje doesn't exist on YouTube.
I realized
that our product,
if it's the best on the market,
will miss the last step
to reach the people it's meant for.
And you're not here.
Try to figure out
who you're working with,
give them feedback,
and ask
how you'll get money
from them in the end.
I think it's important
what your goal is.
Are we building a job
or are we sharing ideas?
Or are we sharing something?
It can be two very different things.
I think it's very important
that
what you started
when you started
or whatever you started doing,
it's a path.
You're learning on this path.
Maybe it's not exactly
for a bricklayer,
maybe it would be
for a gardener.
You have to be
objective
when you look at your ideas.
You have to be prepared
in front of criticism
and correct that direction.
To find what you're meant for.
If you're going into business,
you're going to pivot
in a different direction.
If it's not
your hobby anymore,
you'll probably turn your business
aside and say,
that's not what I want to do.
There are a lot of books about it.
I think you'll need
to find them quickly.
In the end, it's up to you
how you're going to do it.
It's convenient.
On the other hand,
it's not so bad to get some seed money.
When people give you money,
they torture you
and it's going to
suck.
One comment is
that as soon as
you find people
who see the same problems
in the same space,
you're going to solve
them with a product.
As soon as you find that feedback,
you're going to see who you're working for.
I think that's a lie.
Whether it's a business
or a hobby,
you need a partner to help you.
As soon as you find
a group of people
on a subreddit
or a club,
whatever,
you're done.
Tomas already said that
I think that we gave
some sources.
Mark, I think we addressed it well.
Let's open one.
Let's do it quickly.
Let's just ask.
Are you going to do a lot in the cloud?
No,
we're going to do it in the cloud.
We received
one more question
from one of our
members.
His nickname is
fighter slash random user
1, 2, 3, 4.
Sniper16.
I'm interested
in AI and Jobs.
How will it affect
juniors
who have been employed for a year
and those who are not yet?
Maybe this is also
a question we had
before.
How do you see
using
the latest AI tooling?
How do you see
day-to-day Jobs
changing because of it?
If you can give
an insight
on how it affects
juniors.
You started
using it more.
Is it easy to use it?
I started
in the last
two or three years
using AI
more.
I have two
use cases.
The last
two B-Sides events
wouldn't have happened
without AI.
We lost
Katja, who used to
run PR and
marketing.
She became
busy and
no one could generate
text.
ChetGDP was good enough
to make
this trivial.
This is
one such use case.
I imagine
that in
the agency
AI
reduces
certain tasks.
It can
overwhelm
a certain person.
It is still
a problem to write
a good prompt.
Maybe there are more
gifts in engineering
and how to get something
done.
What do you use
specifically?
We know that the agency
generates the text.
In the last year
I was in a process
where a
SaaS product is being developed
which is more like
a no-code compilation of
Lego bricks.
I have to use this product
as well.
There is a group of
JSON objects.
I help
a lot of things
with jq
when I make transformations.
It is very
simple to say
this is my object
or JSON object.
I want it to look
like a command
or jq
filtering
or tasks.
I use it
on a daily basis.
Recently
I learned a lot
because
in a way
you learn jq syntax
in an experienced way.
This was
a good use case
in my case
where the task
was maximized.
I don't program
and I didn't
need an AI
to write a boilerplate
or to prepare a code.
But when I need
to make a transformation
it is easy to use.
If you generate
jq expressions
you just take
the input,
look at the output
and try
to understand
what the output is.
It depends.
Sometimes it is good
if you know you will need
to change something
and then you can
do it yourself.
It is good to start
with a very simple JSON object
with 10.000 classes
and a nested JSON
for 9.
Debugging is a bit
hard to understand
for 9.
But yes, it is
a very...
I would say
that jq is one example.
I would say that
anyone can snipe
some codes and say
I need this code to behave
a bit differently
and you can get
a very good score
that you can already use.
Recently I tried
a network configuration
and it is written
in the configuration
of vendor A
and it transforms
into vendor B
and for a lot of things
it was a very good approach.
I won't say that I hope
the same will happen
on direct production
on the vendor B box.
But you can get
and it is used
in some way.
Have you tried different models?
Do you pay for them?
Yes, currently I use OpenAI the most.
I have tried
others as well
but somehow
everything that is payable
is OpenAI more
focused than anything else.
Ok.
I write 90%
of the code for AI.
But it is very different
than what people imagine.
It doesn't mean that you say
I have this problem,
write me this.
Or you use
something integrated in the editor.
And I already have a code
or a pivot
and then I make micro-changes.
I say, change
this so that I literally know
if this does this
and then it flows out
and then everything
that is written to me
goes through the editing process
and then I say, this is fine
or I make some changes.
But I don't type
the code as I would
if I wrote a function.
Very little.
I say, this is a bash
I don't know what a bash is
write me a bash function
For example, the word bash
and shell
you make very fast syntactic changes
because it is a very rigid language
you will forget the sequence
and it won't do anything.
It is not what it auto-generates
a hundred times more.
It works very poorly
on github actions
it doesn't work very well.
I do it manually
but everything else is written to me.
But these are micro-questions
I get the result in the editing process
and then I iterate it.
I don't have to type
the syntax of the language
anymore
and also my prompts
are already synthesized
or postulated.
I don't write in human language
with this AI.
I say seven words
and it understands.
We already have a relationship
whatever that means.
I use it a lot
in an office setting
private
and also
in a business setting.
I get all the transactions
which are not my personal
or business transactions
but a food marketer.
I connect it
and then I engineer the prompt
so that it pulls
400 transactions per year
and then I group them
these are categories
that it helps me.
I say, try to do it yourself
and if you don't like it
solve it one by one
and I will only write categories for you.
It's easier for me
to access them in Excel or Sheets.
And then I go to work
and that's how I do it.
Do you use OpenAI or GPT
or do you use LAMO
and Selfhost
or do you use different vendors?
I used LAMO
quite often
because I was more interested
in their implementation
of guardrails
and how to
create an escape.
Obviously.
Yeah, ok.
It's very good
for work
it's not
strictly trivial
but I felt
that it was
quite slow
and it's a fast laptop
and I think
that
if
it was just on the fly
it's good enough
but it's definitely
as slow as
a paid service
where you upload
a prompt and you get
a relatively fast response.
Now I will go back
to the question
how did it affect you as a junior?
Terrible.
Why?
It's so hard now
It's so depressing.
It's like
you have a mentor
and you encourage him
and you tell him
that you are doing well
and that you are learning
for example
if you are older
and you have to pay the rent
you tell him
that he can find
a job
and that he will be the first
in a month
to work on low-hanging fruit
which is a mechanic
which is not
a system design
for a normal engineer
and that it's a bit of a pain
and that's the problem now.
Those tasks are getting harder
and if I need a shot
or something that is not
very architectural
which is ideal for a beginner
then it's not a big deal.
And now
my productivity
has increased a lot
and I don't say it like that
it's a part of the job
For example, I was
No, but I don't know
I am 2x faster
If I was, in the past
it was a shell check
and you forgot something
and now it's done
it works
and you can test it
but it's very fast
and it's a huge
problem
which I hope the industry
will realize that the gap
has widened a bit
On the other hand,
you have a body
which is indestructible
and you can chat with it
I ask myself
how do I poison it
it answers me
like it's fresh
when I'm not thinking
and then
how do we solve
problems we need to change
both seniors and juniors
if you say, I don't know
what you told me
write it down
the psychologist will calm you down
he will ask you
don't ask him
for deterministic results
I have this problem
write me a syntax code
and when you ask him
how do I get rid of it
you can hurt them
if you ask procedurally
what do I do
or I don't know
how do I recommend it to my superiors
he can give you
a very simple answer
I know it's a bit creepy
but it helps me a lot
I do a lot of tests
which are complex
and then I have a rubber duck
and then I challenge myself
I think
that you will
for all the new people
coming to the industry
who are at the very beginning
or for example
those who are not registered
it's
an opportunity
it will be their new reality
I am more afraid
that all those who
in the last 10 years
in this industry
and now
they didn't manage
to grow up
and it will
present a problem
I think
I don't know if
they will take
their services
but they will be able
to show something more
they will need
country to...
I don't want to sound like an ex-developer, but if this automatic will be lost in the blink of an eye,
then you need fewer people to do these things.
You know, this is where it all comes down to.
Not that we have changed things more effectively,
but now we have added additional tasks to them.
Because they will perform better anyway,
because they have the right tooling,
Andral can now do a lot more tasks,
he doesn't have to write code anymore,
it's less of a problem,
he talks to himself, the code is written.
Let's give him more things to do.
So I don't know if this is a parallel,
that there will be fewer people now.
I think that a certain number of people will be lost.
AI will also need to be directed to some extent,
it will need to be programmed,
it will need to write good prompts,
it will need to check if things are going in the right direction.
Maybe it will be a part of knowing that AI is a blood,
that it will dedicate roles to people who specialize in that direction.
So I wouldn't say that it's a black scenario.
The biggest problem we probably have,
because we've been in the industry for a long time,
and in a way we're used to it.
You know what I find really interesting?
If you look at last season,
we had people who had a lack of sleep,
or had gray hair,
and everyone told you,
lack of sleep, lack of sleep,
lack of sleep in networking,
lack of sleep in system engineering,
everyone argues that people lack sleep,
that people fall asleep a lot.
This tooling,
it gives you some answers,
and you're more productive.
But how reliable is that code,
how safe is that code?
If Andraž generates 10 times more code,
the whole software development life cycle is different.
You will still need sleep.
You will be more effective,
you are more effective in determining those tasks
that are time consuming,
that will go away now,
but you will still need to be successful,
you will need critical distance,
you will need to have some knowledge,
some skills.
Or a better model.
Look, it's very simple.
What is it to be a liar?
A journalist who writes a bad article,
or an editor of ten journalists
who writes bad articles?
I'm a journalist who worked on bad articles,
I'm not an editor who evaluates through AI
if the output is OK or not.
But I'm still responsible, aren't I?
That's right, dear juniors.
Everything will be fine.
That's true,
what's the variant of stop, precedent, panic?
No, but look,
if we say, hey, you didn't fall asleep,
or people who go on interviews tell me,
hey, you didn't know that.
Your mentor is relentless.
And at will, too,
at three in the morning,
you let him talk to you.
It's not just that.
In practice, you can ask him
even more stupid questions.
When you do an interview,
you think, if he asks me that,
I'll really know that I don't know.
In practice, you can ask him that.
And the probability that he will answer
a statistical question for a junior
is really good.
In the case of legacy systems,
which are not Greenfield projects,
which are complex,
you won't miss the chance
to magically solve AI.
And we've had that in history a hundred times.
From graphic programming to...
You just forget that in history
we haven't learned anything yet.
Yes, yes.
With this conversation,
I realized that most of my time
has passed today.
What do you mean?
In the beginning, you said you were a host.
Now, ladies and gentlemen,
it's time for a beer.
It's time for a beer
in the Gospodar's exhibition.
We won't say more.
Let's bring this ship down.
Let's thank the people
and give them a beer.
Thank you for being
our listeners in Grodno today.
Thank you for supporting us.
Thank you for hanging out
with us in our Discord.
I hope to see you
at some of the events.
Thank you for your support.
Anything else you want to add?
Thank you, Jan, for recording us.
Thank you, Jan, for taking the time
to be here with the other two teams.
Thank you all for your help
and see you soon.
Bye-bye!